<html>
<head>
<meta name="lawparseroptions">
<title>Greenwich Hospital Act 1990 (c.&#160;13)</title>
<url>http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts1990/Ukpga_19900013_en_1.htm</url>
<year>1990</year>
<chapter_number>13</chapter_number>
<preamble>An Act to enable the Royal Hospital School to admit both girls and boys and, in either case, regardless of any seafaring family connection; and for purposes connected therewith.</preamble>
<date>29th June 1990</date>
<words_of_enactment>Be it enacted  by the Queen's most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows</words_of_enactment>
<isbn>10 541390 9</isbn>
</meta>
</head>
<body>
<table width="95%" cellpadding="2">

<tr valign="top">
<td width="20%">
<a name="mdiv1"></a><br>
<font size="2">Power of Royal Hospital School to admit girls and boys regardless of any seafaring family connection.</font>
<br>
</td>
<td>
<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<b>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<b>1.</b></b>&#151;(1)&nbsp;It shall be lawful for any child to be admitted to the Royal Hospital School regardless of sex and of whether the child has any seafaring family connection; and funds of Greenwich Hospital may be expended accordingly.<br><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;(2)&nbsp;Subsection (1) above is without prejudice to the power to make regulations under section 20 of the  [<a>1865 c.&#160;89</a>.] Greenwich Hospital Act 1865 restricting the descriptions of children who may from time to time be admitted to the school.</td>
</tr>
<tr valign="top">
<td width="20%">
<a name="mdiv2"></a><br>
<font size="2">Short title and citation.</font>
<br>
</td>
<td>
<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<b>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<b>2.</b></b>&#151;(1)&nbsp;This Act may be cited as the Greenwich Hospital Act 1990.<br><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;(2)&nbsp;This Act and the Greenwich Hospital Acts 1865 to 1967 may be cited together as the Greenwich Hospital Acts 1865 to 1990.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="10%">&nbsp;</td>
</tr>
</body></html>