<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1319.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1319.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1319.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1319.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1319.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1319.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1319.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1319.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1319.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100367" speakername="Lord Lester of Herne Hill" colon=":" colnum="1319"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0001.htm#07012689000023">
	<p pid="a.1319.3/1">My Lords, I beg to move that this Bill be now read a second time.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/2">The serious social evil which the Bill seeks to combat and remedy is the forcing of children and young adults to marry against their will. It gives rise to gross abuses of human rights especially affecting children and young people of either sex within our British Asian communities and elsewhere. It involves inhuman and degrading treatment and punishment of those who resist coercion, even their murder. It is a form of domestic violence and there is a direct link between forced marriages and honour killings, as was noted in the important debate on honour killings initiated by my noble friend Lord Russell-Johnston on <phrase class="date" code="2005-12-15">15 December 2005</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/3">Forced marriage is, of course, an oxymoron. It is condemned across and within all communities, including their more religious and traditional sections. It is a form of sexual enslavement, sometimes amounting to domestic slavery. Dowry is often paid and women are bought and sold in the process of being forced into a so-called marriage. As we mark the bicentenary of the abolition of the slave trade, we should surely take effective measures to tackle this gross abuse.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/4">I am indebted to the Southall Black Sisters and many other dedicated NGOs with practical experience of the actual problems on the ground for their invaluable advice and support.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/5">It is essential that the Bill is not misused or misrepresented politically as a way of demonising British Asians or resisting much-needed reform. As the noble Baroness, Lady Scotland of Asthal, emphasised last March, on the first anniversary of the Forced Marriage Unit:</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/6" class="indent">&quot;Forced marriage affects children, teenagers and adults from all races and religions, including Christians, Hindus, Jews, Muslims and Sikhs. And it is not solely an issue facing Asian communities&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/7">We are very sorry that the noble Baroness's bereavement prevents her from taking part in this debate and convey our sympathy to her and her family. But we are delighted that the noble Baroness, Lady Ashton of Upholland, has ministerial responsibility for the Government's response.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/8">The Bill adopts what the Government have described, in the context of human trafficking, as a,</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/9" class="indent">&quot;victim centred human rights approach&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/10">It empowers women and children, enhancing the protection given by existing law. It would help the overstretched, under-resourced Forced Marriage Unit, working with other agencies and NGOs, to develop and implement training, to develop victim support networks, and to secure compliance with the unit's admirable forced marriage guidelines.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/11">There is support from British Asian groups, such as Karma Nirvana and the British Muslim Parliament, as well as the Kurdistan Refugee Women's Organisation; from women's groups, including the Middle East Centre for Women's Rights, Rights of Women and Women's Aid, as well as child protection organisations such as the NSPCC, the Children's Commissioner, and both Liberty and JUSTICE. Liberty's briefing paper explains how the Bill gives effect to the UK's international human rights obligations. The Bill is also supported by senior specialist members of the police service, such as Commander Stephen Allen, whom it would assist to combat this form of serious abuse.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/12">I am grateful to the Members of this House who served on the working party on forced marriage in 2000 and who will take part in this debate: the noble Lord, Lord Dholakia, the noble Baroness, Lady Uddin, the noble Lord, Lord Ahmed, of Rotherham, and the noble and learned Baroness, Lady Butler-Sloss, who has visited Kashmir to obtain direct knowledge of the problem, and other experienced and expert noble Lords. Several noble Lords who cannot take part have written expressing support, including the noble Baronesses, Lady Prashar, of Runnymede, Lady Flather, Lady Verma, Lady Young of Hornsey and Lady Whitaker.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/13">I am also grateful to four family law practitioners: Henry Setright QC, Teertha Gupta, Anne-Marie Hutchinson and James Turner QC, who have advised in designing the Bill, drawing on their practical experience. They welcome the way in which the Bill would promote access to justice in county courts as well as in the High Court, making legal aid more readily available and enabling properly interested third parties to apply for injunctive relief on behalf of potential victims who are unable or unwilling to take such action themselves against members of their families. It is essential that the burden of seeking protection should not rest only with victims, who are deterred from seeking help for fear of triggering the criminal justice process against family members. The diversity sub-committee of the Family Justice Council has expressed its strong support, and I wish there were time to explain to the House the marvellous work that it has done.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/14">It is more than 30 years since I warned that,</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/15" class="indent">&quot;it would be entirely misguided for public authorities to tolerate the exploitation of children or the maltreatment of wives and daughters because such practices were condoned by a particular national, religious or cultural group ... cultural tolerance must not be a cloak for oppression and injustice within the immigrant communities themselves&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/16">Regrettably, the warning was not heeded.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/17">We hope that the Bill will pass speedily into law and that it will be the springboard for effective educational and administrative measures and for leadership and public education within, as well as outside, minority communities. Ram Mohan Roy, the great Bengali social reformer, made common cause two centuries ago with British Benthamites in abolishing the practice of sati. Mahatma Gandhi acted similarly in securing the 1929 Act on Hindu child marriages during the British Raj. Today, the abolition of forced marriages and associated evils will be effective only if there is clear and bold leadership from within minority communities, making common cause with mainstream leaders, irrespective of religious, ethnic or cultural identity, or political party. Reform has to come from within, backed by well-designed and well-executed legislative, administrative and educational measures.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/18">The violence and cruelty involved in forcing children and young adults into so-called marriages is powerfully described by a remarkably brave survivor, Jasvinder Sanghera, in her book <I>Shame</I>, published this week. On Tuesday, I was privileged to take part in the book's launch in Derby, where she was born, and to meet other survivors of the most terrible ordeals, who told me that the Bill would have been of vital help to them. Jasvinder is present at this debate. Her experience painfully illustrates the pressing need for effective legislative and other measures.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/19">Jasvinder was born into a Sikh family in Derby, one of seven sisters, all coerced into marrying Sikh men living in the Punjab. She alone escaped by running away and being treated as dead by her parents and siblings for bringing shame on them in the eyes of their close-knit community. Jasvinder describes her struggle to survive the brutality of family and community coercion, her escape aged barely 16 into poverty and destitution, one sister's suicide to escape being sent back to a brutal husband, and her work on behalf of women affected by honour-based violence, where the suicide rate among Asian women in Britain is three times the national average. Those who stand up to family oppression may receive real threats to kill. If they run away, they have to live in hiding. Hers is a vivid, honest and deeply moving narrative of despair, courage and hope.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/20">As Jasvinder notes, our public authorities,</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/21" class="indent">&quot;can be in a fog of ignorance, and misplaced cultural and religious sensitivity. To put it bluntly, a blind eye was turned to the problem in the name of cultural diversity ... and for those brave and desperate enough to escape, they are dead in the eyes of their parents and their community ... the women brave enough to stand up for themselves, and escape from families who bully, abuse and imprison them face disownment, immense sadness and loss&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/22">Mr Justice Munby, a family judge with particular experience, has written to me in support of the Bill. He drew attention to a recent judgment in which he noted that,</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/23" class="indent">&quot;a distressing feature of such cases is that too often the marriage is consummated by force&mdash;by rape. In one case ... it appeared that the 'wife' had been repeatedly raped in the most degrading circumstances until she conceived&mdash;the 'husband's' motives apparently being to ensure that he would gain admission to this country without official challenge if accompanied by a pregnant wife&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/24">The time is over-ripe for effective measures now to be enacted giving enhanced legal protection. Law is not a panacea, but a well-designed law can influence anti-social attitudes and behaviour derived from cultural practices, condemned by all religious faiths but embedded in traditions of community, family honour and identity.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/25">Last summer, the Government decided against making forced marriage a crime. The Southall Black Sisters was among many well-informed organisations opposing such an extension of the criminal law. It argued that a new criminal offence would add little to the existing body of law on murder, kidnapping and offences against the person; that police intervention would be counter-productive; and that it would be difficult to obtain sufficient evidence to satisfy the criminal burden of proof beyond reasonable doubt.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/26">At the most recent Labour Party conference, the Home Secretary announced that the Government intended to return to the problem of tackling forced marriage, but there was nothing in the Queen's Speech to give effect to his statement of intent. It was because the clear and present danger to vulnerable children and young adults at risk&mdash;mainly, but not only, girls and women&mdash;requires an urgent legislative response that I decided to introduce this Bill in the hope that it will win the support of British Asians and that, with government support, it will soon become law.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/27">The Bill is concerned with what happens in this country, but it should also assist in tackling abuse overseas and could serve as a model for similar legislation elsewhere. That is important because the problem is international. No other country has used civil law to give protection and legal remedies to victims in this way. If the Bill is duly enacted, it may encourage the introduction of similar legislation in South Asia and elsewhere.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/28">Following public-interest litigation in the Supreme Court of India seeking stricter enforcement of the rather useless law against child marriages, a compensatory mechanism and rehabilitation for victims and preventive measures, last month, India's Parliament passed an Act on the prevention and prohibition of child marriages. It deals with child marriage, but the Minister for Women and Child Development, Renuka Chaudhary, hopes that it will give protection to,</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/29" class="indent">&quot;tens of thousands of children forced into marriage every year&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/30">The women's commissioner for India, who is actively involved in forced marriage prevention, is taking a great interest in our Bill. Shruti Pandey, an Indian advocate expert in this area, who is present at this debate, believes that if the Bill becomes law, it may influence India's lawmakers in giving enhanced civil protection. The same may be true of Pakistan and Bangladesh.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/31">The Bill is carefully tailored to prevent and deter forced marriage, and to provide practical remedies. It goes further than existing legislation, notably the Protection from Harassment Act 1997 and the Family Law Act 1996. We have placed an Explanatory Memorandum in the Printed Paper Office summarising the Bill's contents. It applies only to England and Wales because of the need to respect the terms of the Scottish and Northern Ireland devolution settlements, but, if enacted in England and Wales, it will no doubt result in similar legislation in those countries.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/32">No provision in existing legislation states that forced marriage is unlawful and a civil wrong. That provision is contained in Clause 1. The Bill covers deception for the purpose of causing another person to enter into a marriage or purported marriage without that person's free and full consent. That is essential and is not covered by existing legislation. Cases of forced marriage frequently involve removal of the victim to another country, on the pretext of taking a family holiday or similar deceptive conduct. Clause 1(1)(b) deals with that form of abuse.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/33">Clauses 2 and 3 apply to the aiding and abetting and the inducing of unlawful acts. That is essential in the context of forced marriages because wider family members are frequently involved. There is rarely a single perpetrator where family or community &quot;honour&quot; is regarded as requiring the victim to enter into a marriage with a partner acceptable to them. I hasten to say that that situation is entirely different from the practice of voluntary arranged marriages. The Bill protects both adults and children. Clause 4(2) goes further than existing legislation by enabling an application for an injunction to be made not only by the victim or potential victim but also by her or his litigation friend or any other concerned person who has the court's permission, which is obviously essential to get access to justice.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/34">Family judges, notably Mr Justice Munby and Mr Justice Singer, have been creative and innovative in their use of the High Court's inherent jurisdiction to fashion remedies for victims. They have relied on their jurisdiction over minors, or have treated potential victims as &quot;potentially incapacitated adults&quot;. But there are clear limits to the remedies they can give, and it is important for their work to be recognised and extended in the Bill, giving jurisdiction to the local and accessible county courts. Clause 7 makes it clear that the Bill does not detract from existing remedies available in the exercise of the High Court's inherent jurisdiction.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/35">Clause 4(4) provides that interim relief may be granted to secure the safety of the person who is or may be the victim of the conduct in question until the first hearing. That is another important advance on the Protection from Harassment Act.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/36">The primary remedy is preventive orders for injunctions under Clause 4. But the Bill, like the recent Act in India, also provides for compensation under Clause 5 for anxiety, distress, injury to feelings, or other detriment caused by unlawful conduct. Clause 5(3) makes it clear that no award of damages may be made unless the court is satisfied that it is appropriate and necessary as an effective remedy in the particular circumstances of the case. To ensure that the law is not abused, we have included a standard of objective reasonableness in Clause 10(2) in determining whether conduct breaches Clauses 1, 2 or 3.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/37">We have received several suggestions for the Bill's improvement&mdash;clearly it can be improved&mdash;but that is for a later stage. I thank the Attorney-General for meeting with the noble Baroness, Lady Butler-Sloss, and me to discuss the Bill's legal effect. We hope that the Bill will be supported from all sides of the House and that the Government will recognise the need to enact this measure urgently as a matter of high parliamentary priority so that it may become law by the end of this year. We have waited too long, and too many vulnerable children and young adults have been grossly abused for us to delay further. I commend the Bill to the House.</p>
	<p pid="a.1319.3/38">Moved, That the Bill be now read a second time.&mdash;(<I>Lord Lester of Herne Hill</I>.)</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1324.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1324.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1324.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100652" speakername="Baroness Uddin" colon=":" colnum="1324"  time="011:24:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0001.htm#07012689000051">
	<p pid="a.1324.0/1">My Lords, I begin by expressing my gratitude to the noble Lord, Lord Lester, for introducing the Bill. I would like it noted at this point that it was the then Home Secretary, Jack Straw, and Mike O'Brien who first instigated the original working group to examine forced marriages, following a debate in the Commons in 1999 on human rights of women. I express my thanks to them and pay tribute to the work of Southall Black Sisters, Imkaan and East London Asian Family Counselling Service, among others. I appreciate all the comments that the noble Lord, Lord Lester, has so eloquently made about those who survive forced marriages and I pay tribute to Jasvinder Sanghera, who is present.</p>
	<p pid="a.1324.0/2">I also take this opportunity to thank all those organisations that have worked in this arena for a long time, supporting the victims of forced marriages, often with very few resources. Our debate has been enriched by so many contributions and briefings from so many organisations, but it would be remiss of me not to mention the NSPCC, the Equal Opportunities Commission, Liberty and particularly Khatun Sapnara, who is a part-time judge. I am grateful for their contributions.</p>
	<p pid="a.1324.0/3">Like the noble Lord, Lord Lester, and other noble Lords who will take part in the debate, I condemn this shameful practice. I am deeply committed to rooting out this harmful act of violence. Forced marriage is a fundamental abuse of human rights. It contravenes thousands of universally accepted standards. Any legislation that makes this unlawful, any measure which supports the victims and provides practical and valuable redress has to be given full consideration. I thank the noble Lord, Lord Lester, for detailing the many points that the Bill needs to consider. I shall not refer to all the clauses that he detailed, as I leave that to the many other noble Lords who have decided to take part in this important debate. My contribution will refer to some general points and highlight further considerations that perhaps need to be made at a later stage to ensure the effectiveness of the Bill as it stands and the likely impact on the victims. Together I hope we can reach a satisfactory way of supporting those who suffer or face the indignity of a forced marriage.</p>
	<p pid="a.1324.0/4">My noble friend Lord Ahmed and I come to this discussion having spent the best part of 14 months, in 1999 and 2000, in countrywide consultation, research and conversation. We covered as much ground and as many stakeholders as was evident at the time. The report, <I>A Choice by Right</I>, which we put together, recognised that the definition of &quot;force&quot; is that defined by the victims themselves, which I hope noble Lords will accept. That is very positive and unique. The report recognised that we had been letting down the victims of forced marriages over a number of years. It recommended numerous remedies to prevent the practice and to support the victims, including educating the communities from which significant numbers of victims come.</p>
	<p pid="a.1324.0/5">I note the caution to which the noble Lord, Lord Lester, referred about ensuring that a small section of the community is not criminalised by the acts of a few as a result of the Bill. I believe that we have produced a good framework from which we can begin to address the forced marriage issue.</p>
	<p pid="a.1324.0/6">As well as sending out clear condemnation that forced marriage is unlawful and will not be excused as a cultural practice, we produced numerous recommendations which argued strongly for forced marriage to be dealt with within the existing legislative framework of domestic violence, child protection, abduction and kidnapping. I would still like noble Lords to come back to that in due course.</p>
	<p pid="a.1324.0/7">In addition to getting the forced marriage unit established in the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, we called on the Government to commit resources and work across various departments to support women's organisations, produce educational materials to raise awareness and utilise all means available within the local authority statutory framework to provide protection for potential victims. I am therefore pleased to see this position being reiterated today by the EOC and Imkaan, an organisation representing about 30 or 40 refuges, particularly Asian ones. If properly consulted upon and well resourced, the proposed Bill may be able to provide stronger protection to people affected by forced marriage and send a clear message to all communities that forcing someone into marriage is unacceptable.</p>
	<p pid="a.1324.0/8">However, there is also a concern that the few available appropriate services must be supported to help those at risk. We hope that this debate will help not only to raise the profile of the issue, but force the Government to examine where some of the difficulties have been in supporting some of the agencies campaigning for the eradication of forced marriage. Perhaps the Government have not taken that great responsibility so seriously to date. Here we are, asking for similar assistance and raising the same kind of issues six years later.</p>
	<p pid="a.1324.0/9">I commend some of the work undertaken by Ministers thus far, but hope that the Government will accept that they must work to ensure wider consultation with a variety of women's organisations which have not come to their doors to date. This is an important opportunity for us to hear the voices of women's organisations that are not necessarily used to the parliamentary system, and who therefore may not have been able to get their voices or opinions across. I hope that the opportunity to progress the Bill will also give rise to further consultation.</p>
	<p pid="a.1324.0/10">I am being pressed by my noble friends to keep within the six-minute speaking time, but forgive me for pressing my points a little while longer. I support the Bill in principle, but am concerned that it should not be regarded as a panacea: a convenient but empty tool by which well meaning but practically ill-informed individuals and agencies can feel that a shallow victory has been secured, while women affected by this are kept out of the loop, not receiving the services and provisions they desire and rightly deserve.</p>
	<p pid="a.1324.0/11">The creation of a civil remedy must go hand in hand with a broad infrastructure to support its implementation. The Government, wider society, individual communities and the voluntary sector must come together to tackle the practice of forced marriage, as well as ensuring that any new legislation is accompanied by mandatory obligation for training for all professionals involved in the process, including the judiciary, social workers, police officers and so on. In this context, I would like some assurance from the Minister about the genuine concerns raised by members, particularly of Imkaan and SBS, about the resources and financial commitment of the Government. Does she accept that the current trend of reduction and closures of specialised units has put our commitment to the victims of violence and forced marriage under threat? How do the Government intend to address this? I also ask the Minister whether, in considering this Bill, she can say if existing legislation can be amended to incorporate the measures of support and protection desired and stated in this Bill. If so, would she ensure that the consultation process which will need to take place gives this matter further deliberation and includes, as I suggested earlier, a wider number of groups?</p>
	<p pid="a.1324.0/12">I fear that a solitary Act may be a symbolic outlawing of forced marriage&mdash;a good thing&mdash;but, without sufficient practical and mainstream support such as economic emancipation and opportunities for education and training for women from specific minority communities, it will not be able to eradicate forced marriage. Despite many misgivings, I give this Bill a cautious welcome on the basis that we shall ensure further consultations, widening participation of the numbers of women's organisations, and make some co-ordinated efforts within the mainstream legislative framework to address this barbaric practice.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1326.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1326.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1328.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1328.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1329.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1329.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1329.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100530" speakername="Baroness Rendell of Babergh" colon=":" colnum="1329"  time="011:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0002.htm#07012689000077">
	<p pid="a.1329.0/1">My Lords, I too congratulate the noble Lord, Lord Lester, on introducing the Bill. Forced marriage is primarily an issue of violence against women, as is female genital mutilation, and the motivation for its continuance is, in many respects, the same as for that other abuse. It is another way of controlling a woman's conduct and her sexuality.</p>
	<p pid="a.1329.0/2">To counter that, we are told that males are also coerced into marriage, but the Forced Marriage Unit's figures show that of the 300 cases brought to it annually, only 15 per cent of men are victims while 85 per cent are women. Forced marriage is an abuse of women's human rights. It is not a Romeo and Juliet situation, romantic and poetical, but one in which parents assert their perceived right over a daughter, body and soul, and obey a tradition in which there is no place for happiness or marital accord.</p>
	<p pid="a.1329.0/3">The Forced Marriage Unit stresses that a clear distinction must be made between a forced marriage and an arranged marriage. In arranged marriages the families of both bride and groom choose the marriage partner but the final choice remains with the couple. So well and good, but it should not be forgotten that many, if not all, forced marriages begin as arranged marriages but change in character when one of the couple, usually the prospective bride, objects to the arrangement.</p>
	<p pid="a.1329.0/4">A major difficulty here is something which all civilised societies must regard as desirable. I refer to the love and respect which young women of Asian origin have for their parents, a regard far in excess of what we generally see in relations between daughters and parents in white communities. This civilised and honourable attitude makes resisting parental control immeasurably more difficult for young Asians; fear of causing mothers and fathers pain may lead them into marriage situations which have tragic consequences. Refusal can result in the kind of family solidarity which leads to so-called honour killings in horrific circumstances, of which we hear all too often.</p>
	<p pid="a.1329.0/5">I support the Bill of the noble Lord, Lord Lester, because I believe that we have need of a law to protect the vulnerable and also that, at present, the criminal offences and protective measures on the statute books are inadequate. But there are great difficulties, not least instanced by that love and respect, which I have mentioned, and which the great majority of these&mdash;often very young&mdash;girls feel towards their parents. One can easily see how making forced marriage a criminal offence could result in breakdown within the family; and that this, which a non-Asian woman might take quite lightly, may be a tragic outcome of defiance for those whose fate we are discussing. Many such parents, like those of another ethnic minority and country of origin determined on the mutilation of their daughters, are following an age-old tradition and are otherwise law-abiding and good citizens. They are not criminals but often of high moral character; and those intending to force a daughter into marriage against her will are more likely to be deterred from taking such a step when they know they would be acting against the law.</p>
	<p pid="a.1329.0/6">It is a matter of concern that there seems no way around the fact that the majority of victims of forced marriage are young women who have come here, or whose parents or grandparents have come here, from the Asian sub-continent. Whatever may have happened in the past, we are not going to find a 16 year-old white girl coerced into marriage with a boy she has never met. And herein lies an obstacle, not perhaps insurmountable, but very serious. We have heard a great deal in the past fortnight of racism underlying the surface of our society, more of it than perhaps most of us realised. We have heard of disgraceful taunts levelled at innocent people from those who are either vicious or ignorant and whose behaviour is unacceptable. The more enlightened of us will not forget that forms of forced marriage existed here in historical times. Literature and social history have countless instances and it is only wise legislation which finally put an end to it.</p>
	<p pid="a.1329.0/7">As the Bill proceeds along its course, it is important for all who support its recommendations to understand how sensitive a matter it is and what careful handling it needs. There are, apparently, all too many members of the public out there who look constantly for reasons to vilify and condemn black and Asian people&mdash;even now, after all these years of immigration and integration. It is important to do nothing to encourage those who call everyone with a brown skin and black hair a &quot;Paki&quot; and are ever on the watch for a chance to abuse those whose customs strike them as bizarre or outlandish.</p>
	<p pid="a.1329.0/8">If the Bill is to become law, as I hope it will, its measures must be implemented. Parallels with female genital mutilation have been pointed out in the several reports on forced marriage, and it should be remembered that the Prohibition of Female Circumcision Act, later superseded by the Female Genital Mutilation Act, has been in existence for almost 23 years without a single prosecution having been brought.</p>
	<p pid="a.1329.0/9">It is important to remember that in many instances young women have been deceived into believing they are travelling from the United Kingdom to India or Pakistan, their ancestral home, for a holiday or a visit to relations when, in fact, they are being taken to meet a future husband whom they will be coerced into marrying while there. This is a very close parallel with the provision in the Female Genital Mutilation Act 2003 which forbids the taking of a child or young girl out of the United Kingdom to an African country for the purpose of mutilation. As I have said, the Bill, when it becomes law, must not be permitted to lie moribund on the statute book, a fate which threatens the Female Genital Mutilation Act. Many have defended FGM on the grounds that we should not interfere with age-old traditional practices, the same or similar arguments should not be allowed to prevail here.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1331.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1331.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1333.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1333.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1335.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1335.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1337.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1337.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1338.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1338.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1338.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1338.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1339.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1339.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1340.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1340.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1341.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1341.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1342.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1342.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1342.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100791" speakername="Baroness Murphy" colon=":" colnum="1342"  time="012:38:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0004.htm#07012689000136">
	<p pid="a.1342.0/1">My Lords, the noble Baroness, Lady Rendell of Babergh, has already mentioned Romeo and Juliet. I remind the House that Juliet pleads with her mother not to force her to marry Paris, the choice of her father, Capulet. She says:</p>
	<p pid="a.1342.0/2">&quot;Is there no pity sitting in the clouds,That sees into the bottom of my grief?O, sweet my mother, cast me not away!Delay this marriage for a month, a week;Or, if you do not, make the bridal bedIn that dim monument where Tybalt lies&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1342.0/3">In other words, &quot;I'd rather die than marry that man&quot;. How does her father respond?</p>
	<p pid="a.1342.0/4" class="indent">&quot;Look to't, think on't, I do not use to jest.</p>
	<p pid="a.1342.0/5">Thursday is near; lay hand on heart, advise:An you be mine, I'll give you to my friend;An you be not, hang, beg, starve, die in the streets,For, by my soul, I'll ne'er acknowledge thee,Nor what is mine shall never do thee good&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1342.0/6">So Capulet's attitude to his daughter is precisely that of those few who see nothing wrong in marrying their children for what they see as the greater good of their community&mdash;erroneously, as we have heard from every speaker today. Forced marriage is not, as we have heard, a characteristic of any religious group. It is worth reminding ourselves that it was pretty much accepted here&mdash;if despised&mdash;until the 19th century, especially in aristocratic circles where property and the inheritance of it formed the basis of a marriage contract. I have recently been reading with horror the story of the poor 15 year-old Lady Jane Grey, forced, in the 16th century, into marrying the youth Guildford Dudley, who was equally reluctant, it seems; a marriage to promote the tragic ambitions of their families.</p>
	<p pid="a.1342.0/7">Forced marriages are the consequence of medieval feudalism, paternal supremacy and the desperate desire to maintain one's culture in the face of threats to it posed by there being insufficient local marriage partners of the desired restricted kind for one's offspring. It is of course the evil end of a wide spectrum of behaviours and attitudes that place some young women in despairing situations, where their education and exposure to wider influences in the UK&mdash;by no means would we necessarily say superior influences, but certainly different from that of the communities from which they came&mdash;bring them into profound conflict with their parents, and that conflict produces a profound sense of guilt and failure about their obligations.</p>
	<p pid="a.1342.0/8">At St George's, University of London, where I chair the council, 40 per cent of our medical students are Muslim, largely from the south Asian community. We see every day the challenge that some young British Asian women feel when faced with the freedoms and the need to adopt the assertive, confident social interaction we demand of a doctor in the UK. A conventional medical education can pose serious challenges for some parents of our young women students.</p>
	<p pid="a.1342.0/9">There will be many people who say that has nothing to do with forced marriages, but it does. It is the extreme and totally unacceptable end of a spectrum of cultural attitudes about women and children's rights and proper place in the family group. The noble Lord, Lord Ahmed, has bravely outlined some of the issues that face communities today. As we have heard from the noble Lord, Lord Lester, suicides among young Asian women are three times higher than among their white counterparts, particularly in very young age groups. The victims are often wives who cannot have children, or who produce only daughters, but another group that is at risk are those living in families where there is intergenerational conflict and a clash of ideas.</p>
	<p pid="a.1342.0/10">The Government have explained their reluctance to introduce a specific criminal law against forced marriages. Although I was not at first entirely convinced by them, having seen the responses on the Home Office website, I understand how difficult that would be, with prevention, investigation and prosecution occurring across international boundaries, as well as the dangers of driving the practice even further underground than it already is.</p>
	<p pid="a.1342.0/11">The noble Lord's Bill today, though, is one way that we can make some major progress. Like many others here, I suspect, I have received emails from groups who feel that it would drive the practice further underground and would not be helpful, but I have observed that they have no satisfactory alternative apart from doing more of what we are already doing. That does not seem to have been enough. The journalist Camilla Cavendish asked in the <I>Times</I> on <phrase class="date" code="2007-08-31">31 August</phrase> last year,</p>
	<p pid="a.1342.0/12" class="indent">&quot;When so many women are being forced into marriage, why are there not more howls of protest? Where have all the feminists gone?&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.1342.0/13">Why are we not saying more about the plight of these women who have been treated not as individuals but as possessions?</p>
	<p pid="a.1342.0/14">I hope the Muslim Council of Britain, which was concerned that a criminal law would be yet,</p>
	<p pid="a.1342.0/15" class="indent">&quot;another way to stigmatise our communities&quot;,</p>
	<p pid="a.1342.0/16">will give its support to the Bill, recognising that a small minority of its community are seriously jeopardising the reputation of Islam. It has declared that it regards men and women as equal partners in marriage. It would be even more encouraging if it gave practical support to those communities to stamp out this abusive and detestable practice. I would like to see it use its influence and financial muscle to support the charities working in this area, and to support the Bill.</p>
	<p pid="a.1342.0/17">The cultural questions are complex, but the feminist cause is clear. Every woman should be able to say no to an unwanted marriage. I give my full support to this Bill.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1344.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1344.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1344.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100936" speakername="Baroness Butler-Sloss" colon=":" colnum="1344"  time="012:44:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0004.htm#07012689000144">
	<p pid="a.1344.0/1">My Lords, I declare an interest. As a former judge, I tried cases that contained elements of forced marriage.</p>
	<p pid="a.1344.0/2">I strongly support the Bill. I pay tribute to the speeches of the noble Lords, Lord Lester and Lord Carlile, with which I entirely agree, as I agree with all the other speeches that have so far been given in this House. I am aware that the Bill is strongly supported by the NSPCC, the diversity sub-committee of the Family Justice Council&mdash;the council is chaired by the President of the Family Division, while the sub-committee is chaired by a British Bangladeshi barrister&mdash;and the Family Law Bar Association and its diversity sub-committee, as well as several High Court judges.</p>
	<p pid="a.1344.0/3">I think it is important to remember&mdash;it has already been said several times, but I believe it is worth saying again&mdash;that an arranged marriage is a well-known and well-respected way among many communities to safeguard the future of their children and help them to make sensible permanent relationships, so long as it is genuinely consensual. But to require a young person to marry without his&mdash;and there are young men in this position as well as young women&mdash;or her consent is not only unacceptable, but, as the right reverend Prelate said earlier, is contrary to the beliefs of the major religions of the world, such as Islam or Sikhism. It is also an obvious violation of a person's human rights.</p>
	<p pid="a.1344.0/4">In 2004 I went, at the request of the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, to Muzaffarabad, the capital of Jammu and Kashmir, to talk mainly about international child abduction, but also about forced marriages. I met some of the leaders of the communities in Mirpur, from where come a large number of British-born or resident members of the Pakistan community in England. They are actually Kashmiri, not Pakistani. There is, I understand, a practice of marrying within the wider family&mdash;to marry one's cousin&mdash;and I was told firmly by the leaders from Mirpur that they were concerned at the number of young people from the United Kingdom who were married to their cousins in Mirpur. They felt that this was often not a consensual arrangement, but they felt unable to take any steps to discourage it. They said that this was an English problem.</p>
	<p pid="a.1344.0/5">We may ask: is there really a problem that needs to be dealt with? Today in your Lordships' House we have heard many speeches to show that there is. It is a problem right across the world; the community leaders from Mirpur were right to say that it is also here in England. We must tackle it. It is not a problem only of the Muslim community, as has been said, and it may occur among Sikhs or Kurds. We heard at the meeting last week about the Kurdish community, where this happens from time to time. It can happen among Christians, Hindus or Jews. It happens, no doubt, within the Arab communities, but we do not usually hear about it.</p>
	<p pid="a.1344.0/6">I would say in parenthesis that landowning families in the 18th and 19th centuries in England married their daughters in order to consolidate their land. The noble Baroness, Lady Murphy, told us about the sad position of Juliet. The major problems arise from families originating from the Indian subcontinent, but it is important to remember that they are certainly not confined to them.</p>
	<p pid="a.1344.0/7">This issue is a major concern of the NSPCC, and I declare another interest as I am president of another of its appeals, which is just about completed. The NSPCC is involved because forced marriages affect children and young people under 18, as well as adults. The NSPCC has given me an example of a 15 year-old girl, about to take her GCSEs, who wanted to become a doctor. Her sister was married at 16, and her parents were planning to take her to marry the man chosen for her, who lived in the Indian subcontinent, and whom she had never met. They had already booked the flight. How was she to deal with this situation? The parents would not listen to her, and would disown her if she refused.</p>
	<p pid="a.1344.0/8">The NSPCC has an Asian child protection helpline, and 10 per cent of the calls in 2004-05 were about forced marriages. Childline, which is now amalgamated with the NSPCC, had 82 calls last year from children about arranged and forced marriages. The main complaint was that parents did not listen to them. The family judges of the High Court deal with cases of children who are abducted by a parent for the purpose of marriage. Forced marriages affect mainly girls and young women, but they affect young men also.</p>
	<p pid="a.1344.0/9">One way in which we hear about forced marriages is in cases of honour killings, where a member or members of a family may punish another member for refusing to marry the proposed partner or for choosing to marry someone else. They are often reported in the press. I remember being in Birmingham on one occasion as a judge when the judge who was there with me had a case in the Crown Court of a father who knifed his elder daughter because she refused to marry the man he chose for her and then knifed the younger daughter because she went to the aid of her sister. The tragic thing was that the father did not know that he was doing wrong. And that was in Birmingham, not a remote part of some distant place.</p>
	<p pid="a.1344.0/10">There are sad cases told in the family courts by those bringing nullity petitions to end marriages to which they did not consent. Some High Court judges have engaged in a creative use of their inherent jurisdiction to enable them to help these girls. There is a worrying element of domestic violence in some cases, as noble Lords will have already heard. Domestic violence in the family has, as we all know too well, a serious, adverse and long-term effect on the children in the family, and children of these marriages as well as others. I understand that an average of about 300 girls a year go to the police and seek protection from their family who require them to marry. That is a dramatic and tragic step for a girl to take. She is likely to be barred from the family thereafter and live in isolation from the community in which she has been brought up. I pay tribute to the Southall Black Sisters for taking on and looking after so many of the girls who come though their hands.</p>
	<p pid="a.1344.0/11">Another question is whether legislation directed at preventing forced marriages will do any good or will it only demonise or stigmatise a community and be ineffective? I was unhappy about the previous proposed legislation which would have created criminal offences. As we have heard, it had little support from NGOs and other organisations which remain extremely concerned about the plight of many young people in this country. But a civil remedy does not have the same coercive force. It is accessible in the county court and it would be relatively easy to make an application to a family judge.</p>
	<p pid="a.1344.0/12">The Bill would give a message that could be understood by those communities or individuals who consider they have the right to choose the spouse for their child. Speaking as a former judge, I have to say that one of the attractive features of the communities from the Asian subcontinent is their recognition and acceptance of the rule of law. They are generally law-abiding people and are accustomed to using the courts in family and other disputes. The possibility of litigation if the Bill was law might give the family a breathing space and an opportunity for reflection. Our family judges are experienced in defusing a fraught situation and persuading a settlement. It would be far better to have an injunction or the threat of proceedings and then a family discussion than a trial on attempted murder in the Crown Court. There is also the chance of keeping the family together rather than a tragic and permanent family rift.</p>
	<p pid="a.1344.0/13">The Bill provides several remedies, of which the most important is the granting of an injunction, with a power of arrest if the injunction is not obeyed. This is a strong remedy which has been effectively used in domestic violence legislation. Very helpfully, the Bill provides that when a girl is locked in her bedroom at home, for example&mdash;I know of such cases&mdash;another member of the family or a friend may help her obtain relief by making the application on her behalf if, and only if, the judge gives specific permission. So there will be no unsuitable people making applications about which the girl does not know or to which she does not consent.</p>
	<p pid="a.1344.0/14">The Bill makes provision for granting injunctions against other members of the family who take part in the threats or intimidation to force the marriage on the unwilling young person. It also includes forcing a marriage by deceit as well as by intimidation. It provides the interim relief to secure the safety of the young person, pending the hearing before the court.</p>
	<p pid="a.1344.0/15">In the view of NGOs, including those from the ethnic minorities, the legislation would not demonise any community and would be very effective both in its use and as a preventive measure. It might be said that to change culture is a slow business and would it do any good as it would take so long. My answer is that one has to start somewhere. There are examples of changing culture in other areas of legislation such as public disapproval of drink-driving in the past 10 years, increased disapproval of smoking and a relatively recent understanding and awareness of the evil of domestic violence. The Bill would be a trigger to move people forward.</p>
	<p pid="a.1344.0/16">Does the Protection from Harassment Act 1997 provide protection so that the Bill would be an unnecessary addition to the statute book? With one voice the Family Law Bar Association, the diversity sub-committee of the Family Justice Council and, in particular, Mr Justice Munby from the High Court Family Division advise that it does not give adequate protection. One act of forcing a child or young person to marry would not, I believe, come within the definition of harassment. The county court does not at present have the powers it would have if the Bill were passed. The 1997 Act is also somewhat cumbersome. The Bill is short, to the point and&mdash;unusually, perhaps&mdash;easy to understand.</p>
	<p pid="a.1344.0/17">Perhaps even more importantly, from time to time legislation appropriately fulfils a declaratory or denunciatory role expressing the view of society that certain behaviour not only is unacceptable but requires to be identified as such. An example would be the Prohibition of Female Circumcision Act 1985, and I suggest that forced marriages come within this category.</p>
	<p pid="a.1344.0/18">I very much hope that the Bill will have a strong preventive element and that leaders in the communities will recognise the law and spread the message that to force a daughter or son to marry someone they do not agree to marry is wrong and is against the law as it is against the principles of the major religions.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1347.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1347.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1347.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100172" speakername="Lord Desai" colon=":" colnum="1347"  time="012:57:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0004.htm#07012689000162">
	<p pid="a.1347.0/1">My Lords, it is a privilege to follow the noble and learned Baroness, Lady Butler-Sloss. I have nothing very technical or legal to say, but first I welcome the Bill and thank the noble Lord, Lord Lester, for introducing it.</p>
	<p pid="a.1347.0/2">It is always said that the law is not really a solution to a problem and that instead we have to change the culture. I remember that when I was a young man in America in the early 1960s, a lot of civil rights Bills were being opposed because people said that legislation about black equality would never be enough and what was really needed was a change of heart. At that time, if one had waited for a change of heart in the American South, there would never have had been any progress whatever. So I strongly believe that in the solution to something like this, the law is always a good first step&mdash;perhaps not sufficient, but definitely more than necessary. In the absence of law, there is no incentive to change behaviour.</p>
	<p pid="a.1347.0/3">It is always said that all religions are against all evil. I have heard that before and have never been convinced. All religions, at one level of generality, are for peace and they have all been used as excuses for war. However, I do not want to get diverted into a diatribe. In Pakistan, India and Bangladesh, among Muslims, Hindus and Sikhs, whatever the religion may say, we know that very bad things happen to women. They are forced into marriage and raped in marriage. In India, you hear rumours such as, &quot;Oh, she was cooking and suddenly the kerosene stove flared up and she burnt herself down&quot;. That is a case of dowry murder. Even if a religion allows such things, we should not allow them here. If a religion does not allow them, that is all well and good, but even if it does, that is no reason to condone such things.</p>
	<p pid="a.1347.0/4">People often say, &quot;That is our culture and we do not want our culture to be interfered with by law&quot;. First, culture is not homogeneous, even back in the south Asian subcontinent. I know for a fact that among Hindus&mdash;let me stick to a safe pitch and talk about Hindus&mdash;there is a tremendous difference in attitudes to forced marriage across castes. Some would never contemplate it. I come from a group where even arranged marriages are frowned on and people want to make their own choices, but there are communities where forced marriages exist. What is much worse is that, often, groups have come from the subcontinent to this country and the culture that they believe in has been frozen in aspic from the time they were there in the 1940s and 1950s. Back in south Asia, the culture has progressed and the position of women has improved, but some people here feel, &quot;We must preserve our culture as we thought it was in the 1940s&quot;. What we call &quot;culture clash&quot; is often generated by the refusal of the immigrant community to advance, not just with the culture here, but with that back in their place of origin. Cultural arguments should be examined with great caution and not be conceded at all.</p>
	<p pid="a.1347.0/5">What is happening is immigration. As many noble Lords have pointed out, one reason for forced marriage is to allow someone from the subcontinent to obtain entrance to this country. Usually, it is a man who wants to come here, although the noble Lord, Lord Ahmed, pointed out that to save the family honour some women are brought over like that. When they grant visas to decide entry to this country, Her Majesty's Government should try to have a separate interview with the bride to see whether she is being used as an excuse for coming here. The interview should include people who can facilitate conversation, not only interpreters but socially-skilled people who could reassure the woman that if she tells the truth she will not be victimised. That would go a long way to discourage this practice. At the bottom, all such matters of culture boil down to matters of money. If we can prevent the advantage of a British passport being earned through forced marriage and statutory rape, it would be much better for us.</p>
	<p pid="a.1347.0/6">I have said enough to provoke other noble Lords. My time is up so I shall sit down.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1349.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1349.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1351.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1351.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1353.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1353.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1353.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1353.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1353.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1353.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1353.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100173" speakername="Lord Dholakia" colon=":" colnum="1353"  time="013:20:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0005.htm#07012689000185">
	<p pid="a.1353.2/1">All noble Lords. I thank my noble friend Lord Lester of Herne Hill for introducing this private Member's Bill, which is a relevant and nuanced solution to a multilayered problem that must be tackled with sensitivity and grace. Forced marriage, in which a victim is pressed into marriage against their will, is a growing problem in this country. This practice can lead to huge stresses on tightly knit communities, and to young students being removed from schools and virtually confined to their homes. It can be used as a tool for immigration violations and, at its worst, has led to honour killings. At least a third of recorded cases affect children aged 17 or under, and, as a signatory to the United Nations Convention on the Rights of the Child, the UK Government have an obligation to ensure that children's rights are fully protected. Furthermore, the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe has urged the national Parliaments of member states to,</p>
	<p pid="a.1353.2/2" class="indent">&quot;adapt their domestic legislation so as to make it easier for forced and child marriages to be prevented, detected and annulled and to bring to justice the perpetrators of such marriages, as well as those who aided and abetted the contracting of such a marriage&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1353.2/3">This proposed solution is welcome and timely, and has been prepared by an expert in this field, as has been pointed out. My noble friend Lord Lester has a remarkable record in dealing with human rights issues, having campaigned for 30 years to make the European Convention on Human Rights directly enforceable in British courts, and having introduced two private Member's Bills that became models for the Human Rights Act 1998. He is an expert in this field, and there can be no better person to put forward this legislation.</p>
	<p pid="a.1353.2/4">I begin my remarks on the Bill by highlighting the words of a young woman&mdash;a victim of forced marriage:</p>
	<p pid="a.1353.2/5" class="indent">&quot;A person knows when they are being forced into a marriage against their will&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1353.2/6">That must be the starting point. Thankfully, the Bill understands that sentiment implicitly. It does not attempt to patronise any community or to attempt to speak for the diverse groups of people for whom forced marriage is a problem. The above quotation makes it clear that the Bill distinctly understands the differences between forced marriage and arranged marriage. Arranged marriage should involve active and open dialogue and the consent of all parties, and is a successful practice today in many such communities. It is also worth pointing out that it was actively pursued by the English in Victorian times. By making this distinction clear, we can all be sure that the Bill does not discriminate against specific communities and will lead to prejudice in the future.</p>
	<p pid="a.1353.2/7">Rather, the Bill has made use of a process of consultation to provide proactive solutions to an issue that the Government have been working on since 1999, when the Home Office set up a working group, in which I was directly involved, to investigate the issue. This work was done with the best of intentions, but it did not result in any concrete achievements, except to prove without a doubt the scope of the problem. The Government instructed Foreign and Commonwealth offices to be more proactive in providing support to those seeking help in forced marriages, but that is not enough. Such an approach is not comprehensive, as FCO locations are few and far between and may not be easy to access. Most importantly, such an approach relies on the victim seeking out an office of the UK Government, rather than the UK Government seeking out ways to help the victim. Legislation is what is needed because, with it, women will for the first time ever be able to know that this practice is illegal. They will be able say to the perpetrators that it is unequivocally wrong, and will be able use the law as a basis for action.</p>
	<p pid="a.1353.2/8">The reason why many years of work resulted in no new legislation hinged on the criminality of forced marriage. There was no consensus on making forced marriage a crime in its own right. It was considered too costly and too complex to introduce, given that existing laws provided a workable form of protection. Most importantly, however, it was considered an unwieldy solution that might drive the problem further underground, prevent reconciliation, isolate the victim and unfairly stigmatise certain communities.</p>
	<p pid="a.1353.2/9">We are dealing with a problem in which fewer than one in 10 cases is reported, which means that the 300 cases reported by the Home Office and Foreign office are simply the tip of the iceberg. We must accept that the problem is far more deeply rooted, and that some cases never come to light. In the diverse communities in which forced marriages take place, it is often the parents or close family members who force a victim into marriage. There is a strong chance that the victims of forced marriages would be unwilling to report their own parents, or other family members, if the punishment included jail or a criminal record. However, by not pursuing other forms of legislation, victims may be less aware of their avenues for redress, and communities may be less aware that such actions are wrong in today's society.</p>
	<p pid="a.1353.2/10">Multiculturalism must never blunt the fundamental point at the heart of the debate; that it is a person's right to choose whom he or she wants to marry. It is a tragedy that a victim of forced marriage may have to use charges of rape, kidnapping, domestic abuse or torture as a way of dealing with a forced marriage. If she has not yet been subjected to such depravity, but is in fear of it, where does that leave her? It leaves her in a state of confusion, wondering what her rights are.</p>
	<p pid="a.1353.2/11">One of the key recommendations from the wide consultation process in which I was involved was that,</p>
	<p pid="a.1353.2/12" class="indent">&quot;Resources should be used to support a holistic approach that addresses the causes, supports the victims and works with communities to eliminate the problem&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1353.2/13">Thankfully, we have such an approach in the Bill, and I sincerely hope that, now there is a solution in sight, the Government will take the necessary steps. We must be aware that change is always frightening, and that changing people's mindset is difficult. There are always transitional problems for immigrants into new communities, and forced marriage is one such problem. However, this legislation is not about racial profiling or insensitivity, because across south Asia, forced marriages are in the minority, and there, as in any culture, those who abuse the trust of their families are not respected. It may eventually iron itself out in the United Kingdom as second, third and fourth generations of families are born here, but it is our role to spur on this process by smoothing the way for its acceptance and to increase awareness. For this, we need legislation.</p>
	<p pid="a.1353.2/14">We will be looking after the welfare and future of the young generations of British people, we will be making this an issue among first and second generation British people, and we will be fulfilling our role as leaders in the global community by setting an example that countries that face forced marriages within their borders may want to follow.</p>
	<p pid="a.1353.2/15">A law is necessary because the law is an unequivocal statement of public policy, whereas the current patchwork of laws that can be used to challenge forced marriages does not present any unequivocal statement against the act. By using an existing and ill defined set of laws to tackle the issue, we are putting the burden of proof on to the victim&mdash;a victim who may be reluctant to come forward anyway&mdash;and we will allow the issue to continue to be swept under the carpet.</p>
	<p pid="a.1353.2/16">Most people are law-abiding citizens and most look to their community for support. This legislation will allow people to point out an obvious wrongdoing and to pursue an avenue of complaint where prison is not the end result. By making the issue a civil one, the Bill elegantly gives direct redress to victims without any of the drawbacks suggested by the research on the implementation of criminal legislation. The remedies in the Bill focus on the protection of the victim and the prevention of the forced marriage rather than the punishment of a crime. The Bill is proactive and preventive rather than reactionary. A civil remedy to this problem will help to change people's behaviour because it will allow victims to come forward in pursuit of compensation, mediation and reconciliation&mdash;the cornerstones that have been requested by the victims themselves.</p>
	<p pid="a.1353.2/17">The Bill has the support of my party. I believe that all communities, particularly the black and ethnic minority community, owe a debt of gratitude to the noble Lord, Lord Lester of Herne Hill, whose record on rights and liberty is second to none. He has been right before and he is right today. Let us not dither in the task before us.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1356.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1356.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1356.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100016" speakername="Baroness Anelay of St Johns" colon=":" colnum="1356"  time="013:31:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0006.htm#07012689000197">
	<p pid="a.1356.0/1">My Lords, Her Majesty's Opposition support this Bill. It is right in both principle and practice to try to prevent forced marriages taking place&mdash;they can and they do destroy lives. It is surely better to prevent a forced marriage taking place rather than to leave a person in the invidious position of trying to make an application for nullity after the event of the marriage taking place.</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/2">This Bill does make some advances through the civil rather than the criminal law. It should not be seen as a eureka answer to the problem, although it is a worthwhile piece in the jigsaw. The aim of the Bill is laudable, but it needs to be more than window-dressing. We have seen enough of that from the Government over the past 10 years.</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/3">I am grateful to the noble Lord, Lord Lester of Herne Hill, for meeting me last week to discuss his Bill in detail. I am certainly convinced that he is making a worthwhile addition to the measures that are currently available to victims of forced marriage and those who are at risk of being victims in the future. As always, this House will wish to scrutinise the Bill's provisions very carefully at Committee. We will need to consider how effective it will be and how accessible it will be to those who should benefit from it. In particular, we will have to consider what protections it adds that are not adequately covered by existing legislation.</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/4">Noble Lords have today been at one in condemning the practice of forced marriage. Noble Lords, such as my noble friends Lord Taylor of Holbeach and Lord Sheikh, who made a particularly powerful speech, were right to draw the attention of the House to the differences between arranged and forced marriages. It is absolutely vital that we do so.</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/5">I was interested to read the guidelines on this matter that were issued for the police by ACPO, the Foreign and Commonwealth Office and the Home Office. They are sensible and sensitive&mdash;not words I often use in the same sentence as the Home Office these days. The guidelines state:</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/6" class="indent">&quot;The tradition of arranged marriages has operated successfully within many communities and many countries for a very long time. A clear distinction must be made between a forced marriage and an arranged marriage. In arranged marriages the families of both spouses take a leading role in arranging the marriage but the choice whether to accept the arrangement remains with the individuals. In forced marriage at least one party does not consent to the marriage and some element of duress is involved&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/7">It is right to stress now, and to continue to do so in our examination of the Bill, the difference between arranged and forced marriages and ensure that we do not by mistake or oversight bring arranged marriages within the scope of any measures that are intended to prevent forced marriage. That would not be the right thing for Parliament to attempt to do. But I believe that it is right for Parliament to take an active role deterring in the imposition of forced marriage. The right reverend Prelate the Bishop of Manchester was right today, as he so often is on these matters, to remind us that legislation should not be our first or only recourse in changing human behaviour. There are other and much better methods, which have to be complementary and, if possible, preferred routes.</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/8">There are times when I agree with the Minister, Lady Scotland, who has the policy responsibility in this area&mdash;we all regret that, for a very good reason, she is not able to be here today. In her press statement on <phrase class="date" code="2007-06-07">7 June</phrase> last year, she said:</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/9" class="indent">&quot;Forced marriage is an abuse of human rights and a form of domestic violence which cannot be justified on religious or cultural grounds&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/10">She was right to draw attention to the fact that forced marriage is more than domestic violence. It is violence to the right of the individual to make their own life choices. No doubt when the noble Baroness, Lady Ashton of Upholland, replies to the debate, she will tell the House of the various schemes that the Government have launched in recent years to give aid to those who are the victims of forced marriage. I do not criticise those schemes&mdash;far from it. They are important, but I ask whether they are enough.</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/11">Noble Lords will be aware that the Government have changed their position regarding legislation. They had promised a criminal offence as requested by police, but then backed off. In September 2005, the Home Office put out a press release about its plans to hold a three-month consultation on whether to create a specific criminal offence of forcing someone to marry. The police had already told the Government that there should be a new criminal offence. They believed that it would make prosecutions easier and send a clear message that intimidating young people into marriages that they do not want is unacceptable in the UK. In the Government's consultation document, <I>Forced Marriage: A Wrong Not a Right</I>, Ministers accepted that the arguments against creating a new criminal offence outweighed those for it. Despite that, the Government said that they would go ahead and create a criminal offence. Indeed, the noble Baroness, Lady Scotland, said that a new offence would act as a preventive measure and &quot;say to people this is wrong&quot;. She told reporters in central London:</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/12" class="indent">&quot;It's like a clarion call that this is not legal, you are not going to get away with it&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/13">The Government subsequently changed their mind, and I think that it is important that we hear from them why they did. There may be very good reasons for the Government changing their course on this occasion, but we need to hear them.</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/14">Noble Lords who have spoken today have pointed out some of the dangers that may follow from criminalising forced marriage. My noble friend Lord Sheikh set out how a criminal offence in particular could be counterproductive in its effects. I note that there have been concerns in the past that, if there were a criminal offence, young people might not report their parents for fear of criminalising them. Have the Government carried out any further research on that matter? If the concern remains about introducing a criminal offence, surely it should not interfere with having a civil offence. I do not think that the proposal of the noble Lord, Lord Lester of Herne Hill, should fall foul of the same arguments; I think that he has found his way round that difficulty.</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/15">What work has been done over the past two years to make better use of existing civil remedies and the family courts, and with what success? I would be grateful if the Minister could give us information on that. I am aware that there is a range of criminal offences that can cover some of the aspects of the abuse involved in a forced marriage: rape, false imprisonment, kidnap, and assault. However, that can usually follow on only after the event of the marriage and after the damage has been done. The Bill of the noble Lord, Lord Lester of Herne Hill, has the enormous advantage of trying to prevent the abuse in the first place.</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/16">As noble Lords from around the House have so correctly pointed out, this a highly sensitive issue, but one that must be addressed, in a sensitive way but strongly and with determination. As my noble friend Lord Sheikh said, it is a global problem. It is not just about one ethnic or religious community. It is not a south-east Asian issue per se. It affects communities across a wide range of countries, including Pakistan, Bangladesh, India, Syria, Sri Lanka, the USA, Holland, Somalia, Lebanon, Hong Kong, Turkey and Bosnia&mdash;we could go on.</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/17">I look forward to the opportunity to examine the detail of the Bill closely in Committee. In relation to Clause 2, there is one improvement that I hope the noble Lord, Lord Lester, may consider, and I have already given him notice of it in advance. I listened very carefully to the speech of the noble Lord, Lord Plant of Highfield, because he highlighted the fact that Clause 2 could provide some element of controversy and I hope that we can find a way of overcoming that; I am sure that there are practical ways in which we can address it. I am concerned that the drafting of Clause 2 may not go wide enough to protect those who need to be protected. It covers people who threaten, &quot;If you don't help me, I will damage you&quot;, or offer a benefit to the person that is being threatened or coerced. I am concerned to assist in circumstances where someone says, &quot;If you don't help me, I will not necessarily damage you, but I will damage your mother-in-law's or father-in-law's business. I will cause damage to another person who is of great importance to you&quot;. We need to ensure that Clause 2 provides all the protection that it needs to, without bringing too much within it.</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/18">I note that when the Government published their consultation in 2005, the estimated cost of creating a criminal offence was around &pound;420,000 in the first year of implementation and &pound;220,000 in subsequent years. Can the noble Lord, Lord Lester of Herne Hill, say what he considers might be the costs of implementing the Bill? If not, perhaps he may assist us in Committee.</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/19">Clause 5 makes it possible for the victim of a forced marriage to make a civil claim for damages in the last resort. We will have to consider in Committee whether daughters and sons would wish to do that by imposing extra financial burdens on their parents by suing them for payment. We need to explore that legitimate area.</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/20">Last month, the Women's National Commission, ably chaired by the Minister's noble friend Lady Prosser, published its report from the Muslim Women's Network, <I>She Who Disputes&mdash;Muslim women shape the debate</I>. It makes for arresting reading. A respondent from Bradford made the following plea:</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/21" class="indent">&quot;By minimising our problems on domestic violence and forced marriage it will not disappear. It has to be addressed. Women would rather die in their silence&mdash;we need confident women; we don't need shattered, battered women&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1356.0/22">I agree with her with all my heart. In the final analysis, that is why my party supports the Bill&mdash;I certainly do&mdash;and I hope that the Government will support it.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1359.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1359.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1361.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1361.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1361.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1361.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1361.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100024" speakername="Baroness Ashton of Upholland" colon=":" colnum="1361"  time="013:43:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0006.htm#07012689000228">
	<p pid="a.1361.1/1">My Lords, my information is that it has not been cut. We shall have to reconcile that. Whether or not the noble Lord and I agree, it is clear that a fantastic job is being done, which is important. Perhaps we will unite in our desire to see that my words are right and that the noble Lord's words on this occasion, however good the information from my office may be, are not.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/2">I endorse what the noble Lord, Lord Carlile, said about the fantastic work of officials in the very difficult circumstances that he described. I also endorse what he said about women controlling their own lives. That fundamentally underpins all we are discussing in the debate.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/3">The right reverend Prelate raised a key issue about whether young victims want to use the law, and particularly the criminal law, in relation to their families. I know that the Forced Marriage Unit, in looking even at the civil law, is concerned that most of the victims with whom it deals want to find a way back to their families; they want to try to change the nature of their relationship with their families and be supported in so doing. We have to consider the remedies in that context. The knowledge of the way in which young people respond to the work that it does is very important.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/4">A central defining feature is consent. I agree with the right reverend Prelate that this is not about legislation alone. That is another theme that has come through the debate. By itself, legislation can achieve some things but not others.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/5">My noble friend Lady Rendell spoke of the distinction between arranged and forced marriages. I agree that sensitivity is extremely important in looking at all these issues.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/6">The Forced Marriage Unit is very concerned that it is much more difficult for young men to come forward to ask for help. It is now considering different ways to improve the services available to men, to enable the unit to reach out to them and to enable them to come forward more easily. I look forward to seeing how the unit does that.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/7">The noble Lord, Lord Sheikh, said that every world religion condemns forced marriages, which, of course, is correct. He spoke of the issue of force and said that force is not just about physical force. We need to be aware of the role of financial assistance that families give to their young people and ensure that we do not mix up things when we consider the legislation. We also need to consider resources and the best use of resources in everything we do.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/8">The noble Baroness, Lady Falkner, talked about attitude and cultural practices. It reminded me of something that came up later: not long ago, women were the property of their husbands in this country and children automatically belonged to their fathers. We seek a combination of the law, education and empowerment, and recognise the critical importance of the duty of non-discrimination in upholding human rights.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/9">The noble Baroness, Lady D'Souza, continued the theme of being unable to avert our eyes from human rights issues. We recognise our responsibilities under the convention on the elimination of discrimination against women. We are working hard in a number of ways to live up to those responsibilities.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/10">I have written on my notes the word &quot;passionate&quot; about my noble friend Lord Ahmed. He spoke again about the incredible work going on. I pay tribute to my noble friend's work. He spoke of being pro-active, and I recognise how important it is that we work with the communities. He was also concerned that the issue is not picked up as one that could be turned against some of our communities. It is important that we work together. I endorse everything he said in that context.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/11">The noble Lord, Lord Taylor of Holbeach, focused on issues of arranged marriages and forced marriages. I agree with everything he said. He asked specifically about extra-territorial jurisdiction. The consultation on the criminal offence highlighted the difficulties of the lack of extra-territorial jurisdiction and gathering evidence on marriages overseas. The overwhelming majority felt that families might take advantage of this, taking their children overseas to circumvent laws in the UK. That is an interesting and important issue. The noble Lord also spoke of Scotland and Northern Ireland. As the noble Lord, Lord Lester, said at the beginning, it will be interesting to see what happens with this Bill and what colleagues in Scotland and Northern Ireland decide to do. I am sure that there will be dialogue on that for the precise reasons the noble Lord mentioned.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/12">The noble Baroness, Lady Greengross, talked about being caught between conflicting and irreconcilable values, with someone saying, &quot;I am sorry that I am not what you wanted&quot;. That is an important part of this issue. The Forced Marriage Unit works with families to show them that these young women are precisely what they want, and to recognise and respect the contribution that these children and young people can make.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/13">My noble friend Lady Turner talked about some misogynist attitudes which must be challenged. The noble Baroness, Lady Murphy, spoke of the experience beginning with &quot;Romeo and Juliet&quot;, which demonstrates how long this has been an issue in all societies, and how much it takes to deal with it effectively.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/14">The noble and learned Baroness, Lady Butler-Sloss, has spent a huge amount of time supporting the noble Lord, Lord Lester, on this Bill, and has enormous experience in her role as President of the Family Division. She spoke of the NSPCC and the focus on the child&mdash;either because the child is the bride or groom or because the child is the child of the bride and groom. The noble and learned Baroness has overseas expertise and recognises the critical importance of legislation, among many other things, sending a message.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/15">My noble friend Lord Desai spoke of a culture frozen in time, or a cultural clash, an important issue demanding far more time that I can give it now. He also talked about interviewing the bride. The Forced Marriage Unit works with reluctant spouses. There is a special team of entry clearance officers in Islamabad, established to deal with these visa applications. When a victim of a forced marriage contacts the Forced Marriage Unit about the visa application, the unit and team in Islamabad are the victim's voice, working with the victim to produce a statement about what has happened to&mdash;usually&mdash;her. With that statement, we can prevent the issuing of a visa. It is a long and complex process, requiring trust between the victim and the Forced Marriage Unit. When the victim does not even give their real name, it can often take many months to build up that trust. It also says on my note that we need more resources to help women through the process, with three exclamation marks. I put that on the record.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/16">The noble Baroness, Lady Howe of Idlicote, raised the issue of legal aid, something we shall again need to look at. I pay tribute to her tireless work supporting women over many years, and its importance in developing women's opportunities, particularly in the economic and employment fields.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/17">My noble friend Lord Plant of High field raised issues about Clause 2 on threats and offers. I shall not get into that, but I was immediately drawn to Marlon Brandon and being made an offer you cannot refuse. My noble friend raised an important point, however, which will of course need to be discussed.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/18">Having paid tribute to all the amazing speeches that have been made, I want to say where I think we are with the Bill. I do not yet know whether it is the right answer. As it is a civil justice Bill, my noble and learned friend and I have a real interest in it, and we will work closely with my noble friend Lady Scotland to take it forward. There is clearly huge support for it, rightly so, because it is very important.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/19">Let me pick up some of the issues that will need to be thought about in Committee. A number of noble Lords, including my noble friend Lady Uddin, talked about the importance of consultation and how it should not be only with the obvious places and government. I know the noble Lord would wish to consult many organisations, and that will be an important part of what we do. Resources also need to be thought about. Is this the best use of resources or should they be thought about in a different way? We need to think about the breath of the provisions and, because this matter has been raised by other organisations, we need to look again at whether the gaps to be filled should be filled in different ways by amending other legislation. Some members of the Family Justice Council diversity committee raised the question of damages, which was also was raised by the noble Baroness, Lady Anelay, and it is an important area to consider.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/20">The Forced Marriage Unit is worried that we should take real care about the consequences. We must not inadvertently put young people at greater risk because of the third-party provision or take control out of the hands of the victims. However, it recognises that it is often third parties who ring them for advice on how to support an individual. We need to think about that very carefully.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/21">The Forced Marriage Unit needs to think about and work carefully through the Bill to consider its implications. Most of the people it deals with want to get back to their families and find a way through. That needs to be recognised and has to be considered in that context.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/22">The noble Baroness, Lady Anelay, said reasonably that this should not be window-dressing. This must be something that we believe would work. In that spirit, I am delighted that we will be able to see the Bill through its stages in the Lords and consider it. I cannot commit that the Government will decide that this is the best way, but I can commit to work to ensure that we carefully think through all the issues as the Bill goes through.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/23">I shall end with a quotation from Aisha, a survivor of forced marriage who was assisted by the Forced Marriage Unit last year:</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/24" class="indent">&quot;If it wasn't for the Forced Marriage Unit I wouldn't be here now. Back then I just needed a cuddle. I needed someone to tell me that everything would be OK. Speaking to the Forced Marriage Unit gave me hope. I felt that somebody who understood me was on my side&mdash;no gossip, no judgment and no conditions. I didn't always like the options the Forced Marriage Unit gave me, but they helped me to take my life into my own hands and understand that I have the right to choose.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/25" class="indent">Now when I wake up in the morning I can put it all behind me. Sometimes it pops into my head&mdash;what I went through&mdash;but it's over now. I'm looking forward to the future, maybe meeting a guy who I have chosen for myself&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1361.1/26">We need more women like Aisha who can speak of their experience of escaping forced marriages and who can describe the new lives that they are now enjoying. We need to enable them to speak to those who need their support. We need to support the excellent work of the unit, and I commend it to your Lordships' House. History is littered with forced marriages and it is time to end them. I look forward to working with the noble Lord on the Bill.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1365.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1365.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1365.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100367" speakername="Lord Lester of Herne Hill" colon=":" colnum="1365"  time="014:03:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0007.htm#07012689000251">
	<p pid="a.1365.0/1">My Lords, this is a remarkable place. Where else in the world would a legislative body have a debate of the kind that we have had on a Friday? Noble Lords were willing to be here to speak in a long, extraordinarily rich and well informed debate, and I am grateful to all noble Lords who have spoken, Front-Benchers and Back-Benchers alike. It is clear that one positive thing has come out of this debate, which is that we will today form a parliamentary association of black, Asian and grey sisters and brothers within this House to work together in order to turn the Bill into reality. It is also clear in the light of the wisdom expressed by the noble Baroness, Lady Murphy, that when the Bill becomes law in whatever form, it will become known as Juliet's law, which will avoid stigmatising anybody, except ourselves, perhaps.</p>
	<p pid="a.1365.0/2">I should like to deal with some of the points raised. How lucky we are that it is this Minister, that it is a civil justice Bill and that it is her department that will deal with it in its civil partnership capacity; for that is what it will be, between civil society, ourselves as part of civil society, and the Government. She made a number of really important points and dealt with a good many of the speeches. Therefore, I will be extremely brief. Perhaps I may say one or two things before I turn to the points raised.</p>
	<p pid="a.1365.0/3">In framing the Bill, I have remembered two perfectly obvious things. One was that Rab Butler used to remind us that politics is the art of the possible; the other was that a very wise government lawyer once said, &quot;Razors are made to cut and Bills are made to pass&quot;. The point about this Bill is that it has been made to pass; it is not to be window-dressing and it is to be effective.</p>
	<p pid="a.1365.0/4">The noble Baroness, Lady Uddin, was the only person who gave the Bill a cautious welcome. She is a cautious person and I respect her caution, but I am very grateful for her support. She was one of many to emphasise, perfectly rightly, the need for widespread consultation, a proper infrastructure and resources. Those points are all well taken. She and others have persuaded me that when I sit down in a few minutes I shall not ask for the Bill to be committed to a Committee of the Whole House; it is much more sensible that it goes to the Moses Room so that it will not be dealt with on a Friday all the time and there will be much better scope for consultation in that process. Furthermore, it is possible that the Joint Committee on Human Rights, on which I sit, might decide to take evidence on it as well. It is extremely important that this is regarded as the beginning of this process, which is what it is, and that the views of bodies like Imkaan, which were particularly important in pressing for more consultation, are taken into account.</p>
	<p pid="a.1365.0/5">While on resources, I should say to the Minister&mdash;I hope that she will not be cross with me for doing so&mdash;that the table which arrived yesterday shocked me. Under a heading about Home Office and Foreign and Commonwealth Office resources, what it shows in terms of the current personnel is a little depressing.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1366.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1366.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1366.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1366.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1366.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1366.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1367.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1367.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1367.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1367.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1367.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1367.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1368.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1368.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1368.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1368.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1368.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100206" speakername="Baroness Farrington of Ribbleton" colon=":" colnum="1368"  time="014:13:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0007.htm#07012689000267">
	<p pid="a.1368.1/1">Before we move to the next debate, perhaps I ought to remind your Lordships that although neither of the debates to follow are time-limited, the House has a practice of normally rising by about four o'clock on a Friday sitting. Therefore, brevity would assist us in achieving our goal.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1368.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1368.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1368.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1368.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1368.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100427" speakername="Baroness Miller of Chilthorne Domer" colon=":" colnum="1368"  time="014:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0007.htm#07012689000268">
	<p pid="a.1368.3/1">My Lords, I beg to move that this Bill be now read a second time.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/2">The Bill's purpose is to delete those clauses in the Serious Organised Crime and Police Act 2005 which condition demonstration. Freedom to demonstrate outside Parliament is one of the most important freedoms of expression that Britain has. This Government changed that fundamental freedom to a conditional one. My Bill would simply return the law to the 2005 position when there were many adequate safeguards against violent or disruptive protests but people were not frightened to demonstrate. People are now afraid that they will get a criminal record for simply holding a placard or even wearing a T-shirt with a slogan on it anywhere near Parliament.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/3">I am very sorry that the noble Baroness, Lady Scotland, is not in her place. I fully understand the reason and I am grateful to the noble and learned Lord, Lord Davidson of Glen Clova, for taking this on. But if the noble Baroness were in her place, she might say that she was puzzled why I, who usually speak on environmental matters and did not take part during the passage of the SOCPA, should introduce this Bill. It is because many young people at the start of their careers through to ageing pacifists have said, &quot;Well, I feel like coming up to Parliament and demonstrating, but you just cannot demonstrate there any more like you used to be able to, can you?&quot;. They either think that the right has been lost entirely or they are unsure of how they can be legally able to take part. If an organiser gets it wrong, those taking part are implicated, so people are frightened off. Just being arrested will affect your life for ever. For instance, you lose immediately the right to a visa waiver to the USA, even though you may be innocent of any offence.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/4">The effect of these SOCPA clauses has been to cast a great chill across demonstrating peacefully in the designated zone. As my noble friend Lady Williams of Crosby said,</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/5" class="indent">&quot;Parliament is properly described as 'the people's house'&quot;.&mdash;[<I>Official Report</I>, 14/7/05; col. GC 154.]</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/6">Now, the people have to watch what they wear, hold or shout outside their House or they may be arrested, charged and face a jail sentence of 51 weeks or a fine of &pound;2,500. The situation was foreseen by my noble friend Lord Dholakia when he said:</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/7" class="indent">&quot;What initially started as a debate about demonstrations in Parliament Square has now resulted in legislation which will create &quot;fortress Whitehall&quot;, where no one can protest without permission&quot;.&mdash;[<I>Official Report</I>, 14/7/05; col. GC 149.]</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/8">The purpose of my Bill is to restate the presumption in favour of the citizen and to ensure that the right to peacefully demonstrate outside their Parliament is not conditional.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/9">I am sure that the Minister will tell us that conditions are not usually imposed. But when the applicant fills in the form to apply for permission, he or she states who they are, how many people will be there and what time the demonstration will take place. They become the conditions unless the police impose additional conditions. In addition, spontaneous protest is illegal because at least 24 hours' notice must be given. Additional conditions can be imposed on the hoof under Section 135; for example, a vigil could be moved from Parliament to a side street or a 24-hour protest could be suddenly curtailed.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/10">I want to look at why this was introduced. The Government claimed that the powers were needed around Parliament for three reasons: first, increased security because of terrorism; secondly, aesthetics; and, thirdly, undisturbed parliamentary business. I accept totally that the terrorist threat is very real. When the House authorities talked to us about it, they maintained that the highest threat came from the traffic and the road outside remaining open. Yet that road remains open. Of course, there was a remote possibility that a terrorist could hide a device in Mr Haw's sleeping bag or under his placards, but they also could hide one in the bushes by Victoria Tower or in the vans that deliver vegetables to the kitchens.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/11">The question is whether this legislation was a proportionate response to the terrorist threat posed by Mr Haw's demonstration. As the order went through, the noble Lord, Lord Kingsland, said from the Conservative Benches:</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/12" class="indent">&quot;Interferences with rights to expression and assembly must ... be proportionate&quot;.&mdash;[<I>Official Report</I>; 14/7/05; col. GC 153.]</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/13">Noble Lords will rightly have concerns about the security of people in the area around Parliament and I want to emphasise that both for security on demonstrations and security on designated sites around the UK, there are already powerful laws in place to stop violence or obstruction and to address the terrorism issue. Indeed, in the evidence that came out in the Brian Haw court case under the Terrorism Act, the police have powers to stop and search in the designated area, and Superintendent Terry stated in the evidence that between January and July 2006, 714 searches took place within the government security zone around Westminster and Whitehall and a further 4,465 people were spoken to about their activities. I certainly pay tribute to the efforts of the police in protecting the area, but I do not feel this legislation is helping them; rather, I will show later how it is hindering their work. Since 1997, the Minister will be aware of many Acts that have been added to the statute book which lengthen the list of powers available to the police to control situations that pose a threat to the public interest. Those powers could have been used to address the situation in Parliament Square, in addition to civil action.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/14">I shall now address the aesthetics. It was one demonstration that provoked the Government. In fact, many parliamentarians find Mr Haw's demonstration messy and annoying. Now of course it is the subject of an exhibition at Tate Britain. One man's protest is another man's mess is another man's art. But as my honourable friend David Heath MP said in Committee on the Bill in another place:</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/15" class="indent">&quot;What I cannot believe is that the Government, in response to a demonstration that they happen not to like, in a place where they happen not to want it to be, are prepared to bring forward not a civil remedy to provide for an injunction but a new criminal offence&quot;.&mdash;&quot;.&mdash;[<I>Official Report</I>, Commons Standing Committee D, 20/1/05; cols. 434-35.]</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/16">Did the Government realise the mess they were getting themselves into with their route for addressing what they saw as a problem? Last week Mr Haw won his court case. He also featured in &quot;The Trial of Tony Blair&quot; a fictional TV drama, and he certainly made his point in a much wider way than he probably thought when he started his protest. His principles and perseverance are admirable. I had only one reservation about his original demonstration, which was that it took up the whole south side of Parliament Square, a prime position which was then denied to other causes. But my Bill is not about Mr Haw because he will demonstrate no matter what. My proposal is about Sue Smith from Salisbury, Mr Jones from Cardiff or Jeff Brown from Yorkshire who have been put off from joining demonstrations by the chilling effect of the SOCPA clauses.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/17">The last of the Government's reasons for bringing forward the legislation was the wish for undisturbed parliamentary business. The fact is that Parliament needs disturbing&mdash;not disrupting or obstructing, but there is already enough legislation to prevent that.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/18">I turn now to the mechanics of the system imposed by the Government. How does it work? The demonstrator who wants to demonstrate has to fill in a form. I shall tell the House what happened to me last week when I wanted to get a form to do just that. I looked through the Metropolitan Police website for a form. I could not find the form, so I rang Charing Cross police station where a very helpful policeman agreed that there might not be one on the site, but that I could download it from the Mark Thomas website. It is lucky for the police that Mark Thomas has it because it saves a lot of trouble. So some demonstrations take place with the form filled in but other events take place which may look and sound like demonstrations, but are not. My Parliamentary Questions have revealed that there is no statutory definition of &quot;demonstration&quot;, so it is left entirely to the police to decide.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/19">Last week at the Mark Wallinger exhibition, a young woman told me that she had stood outside Downing Street wearing a T-shirt saying, &quot;Rogue state Britain&quot;. The policeman on duty told her, &quot;You can't wear that here, it is a demonstration&quot;. She replied, &quot;I am advertising an art show at the Tate&quot;. He said, &quot;Oh, that's fine then&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/20">My noble friends will give several other examples of people who have been arbitrarily arrested for matters which I am sure the Government never imagined would be arrestable offences&mdash;for example, reading out a list of names of the people who have died in Iraq. The police have chosen not to apply the law to others such as the carol singers or the owners of the boats demonstrating on <phrase class="date" code="2007-01-10">10 January</phrase>. They received only a warning letter.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/21">As my Parliamentary Question 109 revealed, as I have said, there is no statutory definition of &quot;demonstration&quot;, so the police must make it up as they go along. Is a picnic a demonstration? Perhaps not if it contains only sandwiches, but if it contains a cake iced with the words &quot;Blair out&quot; then, of course, it could be. I do not believe that the time the police have to spend on T-shirted individuals or cake decorators is time well spent. I am not blaming the police. I feel it undermines their credibility and the law in general to give them such ill-considered legislation to enforce.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/22">Many noble Lords will be much better equipped than I to address the issue of whether the arbitrary nature of the enforcement is likely to have any implications under the Human Rights Act. It is a matter which may be debated again.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/23">Why was the legislations so ill considered? It was rushed through Parliament just as it was about to rise for the 2005 election. The remainder of the Bill dealt with very weighty issues and so voting down the Bill as a whole because of these clauses was not an option. But now the Government can have a cool, considered look at the whole matter.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/24">As well as the principle of free expression, the other major reason for the Government to have this cool, reasoned look is that vast amounts of police time and public money are being wasted. We know that the cost of policing only one unauthorised demonstration on <phrase class="date" code="2007-10-09">9 October</phrase> last year was &pound;298,000. As of last week, we also know&mdash;because Judge Purdy, in his judgment on the Brian Haw case, said so&mdash;that it is the police commissioner himself who must impose the conditions on the demonstration. Judge Purdy said:</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/25" class="indent">&quot;I conclude that the Commissioner cannot delegate his powers as he purported to do&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/26">So now the commissioner's time is to be spent looking at condition forms instead of conducting the fight against terrorism and crime.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/27">This may not be so simple, as Brian Haw's defence lawyer, Mr MacDonald, showed As he cross-examined police witnesses the absurdity of some the conditions imposed in that case became very clear. The Minister may say that conditions are applied in only a very few cases&mdash;indeed, only about 10 demonstrations have received added conditions&mdash;but the experience of how the Act works has revealed something else. For every demonstration, under Section 133(4), an applicant must state the date, time, place, length and size of the proposed demonstration, and these become the binding rules for the demonstration. Section 134(7) states:</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/28" class="indent">&quot;Each person who takes part in or organises a demonstration in the designated area is guilty of an offence&quot;,</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/29">if it is,</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/30" class="indent">&quot;carried on otherwise than in accordance with the particulars set out in the authorisation&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/31">That means that every protest is effectively subject to conditions.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/32">The requirement for 24 hours' notice is completely unacceptable anywhere but all the more so outside Parliament where people may want to respond to events as they happen. What will happen if a ministerial statement causes unexpected uproar? Are people to wait a day before they express their feelings?</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/33">I have concentrated on the situation affecting Parliament Square but the sections of the Act which my Bill seeks to delete also give the Secretary of State the power to designate any site in the UK in the interests of national security, and so far he has designated 13. In practice, these sites will carry similar problems and penalties for demonstrators.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/34">I have set out the moral, legal, economic and practical reasons for repealing Sections 128 to 138 of SOCPA, which represent the very worst of hurried legislation in an especially serious way. I was struck by the speech of the Leader of the Conservative Benches, the noble Lord, Lord Strathclyde, on the gracious Speech on <phrase class="date" code="2007-11-15">15 November</phrase> last year. He said,</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/35" class="indent">&quot;I was born in the Cold War era, in which we faced a society where the surveillance of every individual was a commonplace, where the state was master and not servant, and where freedom was conditional and every citizen a suspect. That is not a society in which I wish to die, and I suspect that that goes for many noble Lords on all sides of this House. Freedom does not die in one blow; it dies by inches in public legislation&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/36">I thoroughly agree with that sentiment, and I therefore suggest to the House that the time is right to remove these completely disproportionate restrictions on people's liberties, both here outside Parliament and around the country. What we had before may not have been perfect&mdash;carefully circumscribed rules limiting the disruption of protests&mdash;but they were adequate. If it had been really necessary, they could have been strengthened by more moderate amendments that were laid down during the passage of the Act, but which the Government chose to defeat in order to introduce their much more extreme solution. What we have ended up with, however, is totally unworkable and unacceptable. I beg to move.</p>
	<p pid="a.1368.3/37">Moved, That the Bill be now read a second time.&mdash;(<I>Baroness Miller of Chilthorne Domer</I>.)</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1372.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1372.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1374.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1374.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1374.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100827" speakername="Baroness D'Souza" colon=":" colnum="1374"  time="014:31:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0008.htm#07012689000299">
	<p pid="a.1374.0/1">My Lords, I add my voice to that as yet small group of people who remain unhappy about certain clauses in the Serious Organised Crime and Police Act 2005. It seems worth while underlining the point that silence until now has not necessarily implied assent. The Bill went through in a rush in 2005 and compromises had to be made. I congratulate the noble Baroness, Lady Miller of Chilthorne Domer, on her courage and persistence in enabling us to express our discontent.</p>
	<p pid="a.1374.0/2">There are three main points of contention. First, there is the power of the Secretary of State, if he so wishes and it is appropriate, to designate a site,</p>
	<p pid="a.1374.0/3" class="indent">&quot;in the interests of national security&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1374.0/4">Once designated, that site becomes subject to the controls set out in the Act. The second issue concerns the controls and the rules that govern them. Thirdly, and most crucially, any deviation from such rules can result in criminal sanctions.</p>
	<p pid="a.1374.0/5">I have worked for many a long year on censorship issues and I can fairly say that the most common justification throughout the world for curtailing free expression, which of course includes freedom to demonstrate, is that a restriction is &quot;in the interests of national security&quot;. It is a blanket term that can cover anything and everything from prohibiting ridicule and/or the supposed insult of a president to the concealment of large-scale corruption. It is a wide term and in the SOCPA, where it is combined with the powers of government to designate sites and the criminal sanctions, it appears to be entirely disproportionate. That fact immediately puts these measures up against fundamental freedoms, because they go beyond what is necessary in a democratic society. For the Government to assert that a single peaceful demonstrator near the Cenotaph reciting the names of those killed in recent wars is a threat to national security is ludicrous and shameful.</p>
	<p pid="a.1374.0/6">It cannot be denied that putting the onus on any single would-be demonstrator or group of demonstrators to inform the authorities as much as six days in advance as to the time, date, place and anticipated number of participants has a chilling effect on political expression. It will deter the few people who, for example, want to show their indignation and anger about the demise of a village post office&mdash;people who are not seasoned demonstrators, but who nevertheless wish to use the democratic means available.</p>
	<p pid="a.1374.0/7">This chilling effect as we know all too well from non-democratic countries gives rise to self censorship&mdash;the most insidious form. Censorship in whatever form has a habit of increasing. You designate sites around the country where people are forbidden to express concern unless strictly controlled by the police and then you start imposing criminal sanctions for those who flout the rules; then you widen the exclusion zones and add extra rules, perhaps limiting the numbers in any one demonstration. At each stage, we become more accustomed to the restrictions and less disposed to undertake the huge task of taking on the state. It is a slippery slope and it is dangerous. We all know that one has to be ever vigilant about fragile democratic freedoms, because it is in the nature of the governmental system to accrue power often by acting too protectively.</p>
	<p pid="a.1374.0/8">The importance of the right to peaceful assembly is recognised time and again in national, regional and international jurisprudence. Let us consider India 20 years or so ago, where a serial television broadcast portrayed the communal tension and violence in Lahore between Muslims and Hindus and Muslims and Sikhs just before partition. The Central Board of Film Certification thought the series suitable for general showing. However, the petitioner applied to the Supreme Court in India for an order to prevent its broadcast on the grounds, among others, that it was likely to incite people to violence and as such was against public order.</p>
	<p pid="a.1374.0/9">The Supreme Court rejected the petition and in so doing affirmed that the standards by which the likelihood of violence should be assessed are those of,</p>
	<p pid="a.1374.0/10" class="indent">&quot;reasonable, strong minded, firm and courageous men and not those of weak and vacillating minds, nor those who smell danger in every hostile point of view&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1374.0/11">The Supreme Court of Israel ruled in 1984 that the right of the Committee Against the War in Lebanon to demonstrate outweighed other conflicting human rights and interests. In 1973, the House of Lords ruled on the conviction of a protester who disrupted a sports match, threw leaflets around and used highly insulting language. The Law Lords set aside the conviction and in so doing said:</p>
	<p pid="a.1374.0/12" class="indent">&quot;It would have been going much too far to prohibit all speech or conduct likely to occasion a breach of the peace because determined opponents may not shrink from organising or at least threatening a breach of the peace in order to silence a speaker whose views they detest&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1374.0/13">Recently, several more judgments have come from the European Court of Human Rights which strongly uphold the unfettered right to demonstrate peacefully and I would argue that, taken together, the clauses in the Act that we now wish to see amended already have and will have a profoundly chilling effect on this democratic freedom. A truly democratic society recognises that there has to be positive and unequivocal support for freedom of expression, because while people can express their will at general and local elections, in the intervening period between elections, individuals cannot have a direct influence on political decisions. Furthermore, the state has a positive duty to enable such freedoms to be enjoyed. Clauses 128 to 138 of SOCPA do not reflect this positive duty.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1375.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1375.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1377.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1377.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1377.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100107" speakername="Lord Carlile of Berriew" colon=":" colnum="1377"  time="014:51:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0009.htm#07012689000315">
	<p pid="a.1377.0/1">My Lords, I, too, congratulate my noble friend Lady Miller on presenting the Bill, the principle of which I support strongly. I am one of many who have been inspired over the years by listening to speeches by my noble friend Lady Williams of Crosby, and today is no exception; I agree with her every word. She did, however, set me to thinking of the demonstrations I marched on in the 1960s, while a student in London, against a Government of which she and possibly the noble Lord, Lord Judd, were members at the time.</p>
	<p pid="a.1377.0/2">I was just thinking of the themes that we marched against. We used to do a lot of marching. The LSE held an almost permanent demonstration; one occupation lasted many, many months. We used to march up and down Whitehall with students from the LSE to the strains of Dylan's &quot;A Hard Rain's A-Gonna Fall&quot;. Nuclear weapons were a common theme. I recall, too, marching against the decision of my noble friend's then Government that Rudi Dutschke should not be allowed to address us at student meetings in London, and that Danny Cohn-Bendit should not be allowed to make similar speeches in London. Of course I also recall marching up and down Whitehall many times for greater student grants. I can tell your Lordships that we failed on every occasion.</p>
	<p pid="a.1377.0/3">Many of the demonstrations were disorganised. We were certainly more aesthetic than Mr Haw; I agree with the noble Lord, Lord Judd, about the aesthetics of Mr Haw's demonstration. We wore flared trousers and, I suspect, pink or pale green shirts. Much of what we did was entirely spontaneous, and I do not think that it harmed the country a great deal. I regard it as serious formative political experience. I was a member of the Labour Party then, which certainly had an effect on me as I was demonstrating against a Government who I supported. I had the satisfaction of exercising a right of protest in a place where protest sometimes must be heard.</p>
	<p pid="a.1377.0/4">If protests cannot be heard here, where else will it be worth having them? Political protest is not a creature that should be shunted on to car parks. It should not be forced into places where demonstrators are talking merely to each other or to the odd passing journalist who has nothing better to do at the time. I agree entirely with the noble Lord, Lord Judd, that we do not want protests that are distasteful in appearance and that damage the aesthetics of a very attractive and important London, if we can avoid them, although that is another civil liberties matter. My view is that Mr Haw's protest was the &quot;Mousetrap&quot; of demonstrations but far less interesting&mdash;a footnote in the <I>Guinness Book of Records.</I> It will eventually be forgotten, except by lawyers; we always manage to make something of such incidents and there is some seminal law arising from Mr Haw's approach.</p>
	<p pid="a.1377.0/5">This is not about Mr Haw. It is about other people&mdash;the young people today who want to do the sort of, maybe fairly trivial, marches that I was involved in when I was a student at King's College, London. This is about people who want to feel that they are involved in the political process. It may be at a very mundane level, but people want to feel that they can do something. To place this artificial barrier one kilometre around Parliament seems to contradict the standards that, when I was protesting, I regarded as givens in this country.</p>
	<p pid="a.1377.0/6">Of course it is important to deal with public safety and national security. I do not know how many cameras, observation points and surveillance posts there are on Whitehall, but I can guarantee that there are as many as on any street in the world, including Pennsylvania Avenue. If demonstrators go down Whitehall, you can be sure that, as with the demonstrations that we went on all those years ago, there will be plenty of police. Today, there will also be a mass of surveillance. Whitehall is probably the safest place to hold a protest in the United Kingdom. I do not believe that special powers are needed for that one-kilometre radius.</p>
	<p pid="a.1377.0/7">There are extensive specific powers to deal with issues arising from terrorism. As I understand it, my noble friend is not arguing in this Bill for the repeal of Section 44 of the Terrorism Act, which allows for searching for terrorist material without suspicion that the person who is searched has such material. That is a controversial provision, but it is certainly justified in certain parts of London. There are other powers, such as the power to search with reasonable suspicion for drugs and the public order powers of the police.</p>
	<p pid="a.1377.0/8">The real question is: have we made a mistake in legislating in the way that we did, which is now under criticism in my noble friend's Bill? Have we been too cautious? For reasons that have already given, which I will not repeat, I believe that we have. If we have, we need to go one stage further and say that we are prepared, even the Government are prepared, from time to time to admit that we have legislated a step too far. All my noble friend is doing in this Bill is saying that we have gone one step too far. Now let us step back and restore those standards that we regard as essential in our precious democracy.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1379.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1379.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1379.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100942" speakername="Lord Wedderburn of Charlton" colon=":" colnum="1379"  time="014:57:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0009.htm#07012689000323">
	<p pid="a.1379.0/1">My Lords, I am aware of the time and will try to be as brief as possible. I want to make three points. First, I am certainly in favour of the police having the effective, clearly drawn and appropriate powers that they need in the defence of the community, including this place. Secondly, I congratulate the noble Baroness, Lady Miller of Chilthorne Domer on introducing this Bill. I place on record my agreement with much of what was said by the noble Baronesses, Lady D'Souza and Lady Williams of Crosby. I would just add that the noble Lord, Lord Carlile, does not appear to understand that it is the genius of the London School of Economics to be able to mount a full teaching programme while their student body is mounting the best demonstrations in London.</p>
	<p pid="a.1379.0/2">Thirdly, the reason I opposed this legislation has something to do with its character. Legislation tends to be badly drawn when it is hasty and, although its apparent target is everyone, its actual target is very narrow&mdash;one or more individuals. I remember debating this point as a student. Criminal law tends to be very bad when, behind its apparent face, it targets one man, one women or a very small group.</p>
	<p pid="a.1379.0/3">England has a habit of producing rather difficult heroes on the face of such provisions. On <phrase class="date" code="1381-09-15">15 September 1381</phrase>, not far from this place, a simple roof worker from Colchester led thousands of peasant in demonstrations&mdash;there had been many previous demonstrations&mdash;and spoke to the young King, who, it is recorded on a previous occasion, he had addressed as &quot;comrade&quot;; they were not so far behind the times as we think. Although the King appeared to have some sympathy with the demands, which included the end of serfdom in England, when he turned away, his retinue and supporters arrested Wat Tyler, for that was the man; and one of them ran him through with his sword.</p>
	<p pid="a.1379.0/4">On <phrase class="date" code="2007-01-22">22 January 2007</phrase>, in the City of Westminster court, Judge Purdey passed judgment on a simple carpenter who had been born in Barking, and whose protests against the war in Iraq for six years, day and night, have surpassed the demonstrations against the war by many of those who choose to make speeches about it. I do not say anything about the style to which my noble friend Lord Judd alluded&mdash;but it is remarkable that that man has been there, placing himself on the line for such a long time. I spoke of heroes in England&mdash;I note that the noble and learned Lord who is to reply for the Government is making a note, and I cannot speak to the record in Scotland, but he will, of course, add Scottish names to the heroes who have resisted&mdash;and Brian Haw is one of them. He has suffered a large number of police obstructions&mdash;78 policemen visited him at one time. We cannot complain about the police in trying to carry out the terms of this hasty and curious law. All of us who were here in 2005 know that, in terms of the vicinity of Parliament, the law was primarily an expression of outrage by those who could no longer bear his megaphone.</p>
	<p pid="a.1379.0/5">It would be silly not to notice that Judge Purdey said last week that the conditions imposed on Mr Haw were insufficiently precise and that the Metropolitan Police Commissioner had, on inspection, no power to delegate his role, as he had purported to have done in that case. It is silly to have terrorism legislation passed in a rush and in such a rush that it cannot meet simple legal points of that sort.</p>
	<p pid="a.1379.0/6">The case proved that the old principle is correct&mdash;it suggested that public legislation should be aimed at the public, not an individual. The police are hardly to be blamed for what they have done in trying to put the law into effect. We need a pause; we need clear, well drafted and proportionate legislation&mdash;I underline proportionate, as the noble Baroness, Lady Miller, said. Her Bill comes in the nick of time, and now is the moment to sweep away provisions that are easy meat for simple lawyers' points and to discuss new legislation in the full knowledge that the ability to demonstrate before, and in the vicinity of, Parliament should be preserved at all costs.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1380.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1380.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1380.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100387" speakername="Baroness Ludford" colon=":" colnum="1380"  time="015:04:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0009.htm#07012689000329">
	<p pid="a.1380.0/1">My Lords, as a former LSE student, I, too, congratulate my noble friend Lady Miller on the Bill. The right to peaceful protest goes to the heart of the British tradition of liberty established over past centuries, but it has had to be fought for.</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/2">The Law Lords' judgment in the case of Laporte last November found that anti-Iraq war protesters had been unlawfully turned away from reaching a protest at RAF Fairford in Gloucestershire in March 2003. The noble and learned Lord, Lord Bingham, recalled that:</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/3" class="indent">&quot;The approach of the English common law to freedom of expression and assembly was hesitant and negative, permitting that which was not prohibited&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/4">He quotes Dicey as saying:</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/5" class="indent">&quot;At no time has there in England been any proclamation of the right to liberty of thought or to freedom of speech&quot;,</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/6">and that,</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/7" class="indent">&quot;it can hardly be said that our constitution knows of such a thing as any specific right of public meeting&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/8">Therefore, he continued:</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/9" class="indent">&quot;The Human Rights Act 1998, giving domestic effect to articles 10 and 11 of the European Convention, represented ... a constitutional shift&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/10">He notes that the Strasbourg court has recognised that,</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/11" class="indent">&quot;the right to freedom of assembly is a fundamental right in a democratic society and, like the right to freedom of expression, is one of the foundations of such a society&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/12">After the conviction of Maya Evans, the then Leader of the other place, Geoff Hoon MP, claimed that the legislation was widely supported by MPs and had worked &quot;remarkably well&quot;. One press report said that his remarks were met by cries of &quot;disgraceful&quot;. Maya Evans lost her appeal in the High Court, as it was said that the requirement of authorisation in itself did not breach the European Convention on Human Rights. I understand that there is a possibility that this case will go to Strasbourg. However, if the case had reached the House of Lords&mdash;in fact, leave was refused&mdash;I wonder whether the noble and learned Lord, Lord Bingham, would have agreed with the reasonableness of her conviction against the test of the Human Rights Act.</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/13">Mr Brian Haw is the awkward squad, and long may he continue being so. Like most Liberal Democrats, what brought me into this party was our constitution's assertion that,</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/14" class="indent">&quot;none shall be enslaved by ... conformity&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/15">I should like that as my epitaph. I have joined Mr Haw in Parliament Square, along with campaigning comedian Mark Thomas, whose activism I salute, on a &quot;mass lone protest&quot;. We decided not to get arrested; instead, each individual among the couple of hundred of us taking part sought their own personal authorisation from Charing Cross police station. I have mine here&mdash;I should have it framed&mdash;from poor, overworked Superintendent Hanson Coles, who I am sure has better things to do catching criminals.</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/16">One thing that intrigues me&mdash;so far as I understand it; no doubt I shall be corrected by noble Lords if I am wrong&mdash;is that Section 11 of the Public Order Act 1986 allows for the waiver of the requirement for notice to be given of a procession where,</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/17" class="indent">&quot;it is not reasonably practicable&quot;,</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/18">or,</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/19" class="indent">&quot;where the procession is one commonly or customarily held in the ... area&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/20">That sounds like an interesting loophole. Mr Haw or Maya Evans&mdash;or, indeed, I or Mark Thomas&mdash;just need to march round and round and then we would be a procession, not a demonstration. The only saving grace of all these bans and restrictions is the humour that they supply.</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/21">Conservative Party activist, Julia Gobert, was threatened with arrest outside Earl's Court tube station last April when handing out local elections leaflets. It is said that a Labour member&mdash;I confess that this has not been verified&mdash;complained to the station manager. This was because she was wearing a jacket emblazoned with the words&mdash;I have to report this factually, otherwise the point is lost, and I therefore apologise for the expression&mdash;&quot;Bollocks to Blair&quot;. She was told that she was in contravention of an apparent ban under the Public Order Act 1986 on &quot;words causing offence&quot;. It really has come to a pretty pass when language which most of us would think rude, even risqu&eacute; but hardly criminal, could land you in court. What on Earth is going on in this country?</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/22">Then&mdash;I hope that I am not straying too much from the topic of the Bill&mdash;we have the absurd abuse of stop-and-search powers under Section 60 of the Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994 and Section 44 of the Terrorism Act 2000, the latter not even requiring reasonable suspicion for stop and search. This was the provision deployed quite illegally to bar 82 year-old Walter Wolfgang from the Labour Party conference after he had had the temerity to heckle Jack Straw. I am surprised that they have not made that a capital offence. Section 44 was also used against 80 year-old peace campaigner and RAF Second World War veteran, John Catt, for wearing a T-shirt with anti-Bush and anti-Blair slogans near the Labour Party conference in September 2005. The form that he had to sign said that the purpose of the stop and search was &quot;terrorism&quot; and the grounds for intervention were, &quot;carrying plackard&quot;&mdash;spelt with a &quot;k&quot;,</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/23" class="indent">&quot;and T-shirt with anti-Blair info&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/24">Section 44 has been used to criminalise potentially a whole city. For the past few years, the whole of London&mdash;my constituency in my role as MEP for London&mdash;has been designated a stop-and-search zone on a continuous rolling basis. As that was authorised by the Home Secretary, the Government are squarely responsible. People who wanted to protest at the London Arms Fair in Docklands were turned back by police. I stress that the police had to give no reasons for suspicion of intended violence, as the Act exempts such a requirement. No wonder that in 2004-05, 36,000 people were stopped and searched. It is far too easy.</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/25">As a Member of the European Parliament, I am familiar with Euro-phobes castigating the European Union&mdash;as it happens, wrongly&mdash;for seeking to suppress traditional British liberties. Brussels is not the culprit here. I am afraid it is Blair. The Prime Minister's own sister-in-law, Lauren Booth, said, when five anti-war protesters were arrested in August 2005, as the SOCPA ban came into force:</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/26" class="indent">&quot;This is all about silencing critics of the war in Iraq and ID cards and denying people the right to free speech&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/27">If one heard on television that someone in another country was banned from gathering near a government building to stage a legitimate protest, one would probably think, &quot;Thank goodness that does not happen in this country&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1380.0/28">At a time when the European Union is expanding to include countries that have had a long and difficult struggle to establish democracy, the rule of law and fair justice, leadership from member states such as Britain to entrench freedom and liberty as defining EU values and practices is urgently needed. The example that we set to the rest of the world is also vital. How ironic that the Prime Minister, who is so vocal regarding the respect agenda&mdash;he wants to set up 40 respect zones around the country&mdash;has so little respect for his fellow citizens' rights to enjoy freedom of expression and peaceful assembly that he imposes a protest-free exclusion zone around Parliament and Downing Street. That will be one part of his legacy for which he deserves no respect at all. It is time to say: &quot;This is our country, these are our public spaces and no arrogant and authoritarian Government should take away our basic freedoms&quot;.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1383.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1383.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1383.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100851" speakername="Baroness Tonge" colon=":" colnum="1383"  time="015:12:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0009.htm#07012689000339">
	<p pid="a.1383.0/1">My Lords, I congratulate my noble friend Lady Miller on introducing this Bill. I also endorse the remarks made about her by the noble Lord, Lord Judd. In September 2003, I was one of the Members of Parliament called to give evidence to the Select Committee on Procedure in the other place. The chairman was Sir Nicholas Winterton and the three witnesses were Mr Nicholas Soames, Mr Jeremy Corbyn and myself. With that cast, it somewhat resembled an undiscovered opera by Gilbert and Sullivan. The main topics of that session were, first, whether a pavement protest obstructed the general public and therefore caused a danger&mdash;regardless of the fact that no one uses that pavement, one cannot get on to it very easily, and one almost has to commit suicide to reach it&mdash;and, secondly, whether the demonstration was noisy, unaesthetic and scruffy. That point was made very strongly by Mr Soames who, not long before, had camped out with dogs in Parliament Square when the Countryside Alliance came to town and made one hell of a racket with hunting horns, but the banners were professionally made and aesthetic. Incidentally, the noise could have been dealt with easily by the environmental health officers of the City of Westminster. I do not understand why they did not do that.</p>
	<p pid="a.1383.0/2">The real reason for the clauses in this Bill, dubbed by some people as the &quot;Seriously Scruffy Police Bill&quot;, is that the Government were and are seriously discomforted and embarrassed on a daily basis as they go in and out of Parliament. They are discomforted by that brave and patient man, Brian Haw, who happens to think&mdash;as many people in this country think&mdash;that our Government's foreign policy is wrong and has caused untold damage and suffering to people in the Middle East. I say to noble Lords and especially to the noble Lord, Lord Judd, that war is unaesthetic, scruffy, untidy, dirty, noisy and dangerous, but we must be allowed to protest against it.</p>
	<p pid="a.1383.0/3">Our Government have broken international law by going to war with Iraq. Despite the Government's legislation prohibiting such action, we are still selling arms to countries that will use them for internal repression or external aggression. The Government have stopped an investigation into allegations that a British company has bribed the Government of Saudi Arabia. On a domestic note, we had the unedifying spectacle of a convicted paedophile on our TV screens last night telling us not to blame the judge for not sending him to prison, but the Government. Yet we can go to court, and perhaps be sent to prison for making a peaceful protest within a one-mile radius of Parliament Square without police permission. What a mad, mad country we inhabit.</p>
	<p pid="a.1383.0/4">I conclude&mdash;because I know noble Lords want me to be brief&mdash;by reflecting on something my noble friend Lady Scott said to me this morning. She asked, &quot;What are these Britishness classes we shall subject our children to?&quot;. What on earth is Britishness if we cannot have the freedom to speak out and protest peacefully in public?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1384.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1384.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1384.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100173" speakername="Lord Dholakia" colon=":" colnum="1384"  time="015:16:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0009.htm#07012689000343">
	<p pid="a.1384.0/1">My Lords, I congratulate my noble friend Lady Miller on introducing the Bill. She has my full support.</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/2">In the debate on designated areas in July 2005, I spoke about the order dealing with demonstrations in the vicinity of Parliament. The arguments I advanced about public demonstrations are just as valid today. Demonstrations are an essential part of our highly valued democratic institutions, and a healthy democracy tolerates opinions with which we disagree.</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/3">This year I complete 50 years in Britain. I remember, in 1956, writing to my parents in Africa about my first visit to Speakers' Corner in Hyde Park. They could not believe that people had the freedom to get up on a platform and vent their feelings on any and all issues that concerned them. A little while ago, I was in Chile after the fall of the Pinochet regime. I saw a trade union demonstration in Santiago. Everyone I spoke to said that this was the difference between democracy and dictatorship. What a wonderful example of tolerance through democratic institutions.</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/4">Like my noble friend Lord Carlile, I have participated in many demonstrations; against apartheid in South Africa, the war in Vietnam and the war in Iraq to name a few. I see that many Labour activists with whom I demonstrated now occupy high places in Government. Some are in ministerial positions. They are the very people who have now supported the legislation banning public demonstrations in the vicinity of Parliament. They should hang their heads in shame, for they deny to others the very rights which they enjoyed in their youth.</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/5">In July 2005, answering questions on the Statement about terrorist attacks in London, on a day when there were demonstrations outside this Parliament, the noble Baroness, Lady Amos, Leader of the House of Lords, said:</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/6" class="indent">&quot;I cannot think of any other country in the world where the demonstration that is going on right outside Parliament this afternoon&mdash;right outside my window&mdash;would be going on. We should take immense pride in that&quot;.&mdash;[<phrase class="offrep" id="lords/2005-07-11.905"><I>Official Report</I>, 11/7/05; col. 905</phrase>.]</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/7">The noble Baroness rightly reflects the views which have sustained our democracy, values which are the envy of the world.</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/8">I have serious concerns about the restrictions being placed on peaceful protests in the vicinity of Parliament&mdash;Section 138&mdash;and other designated sites as specified for the purposes of Sections 128 and 129 of the Serious Organised Crime and Police Act 2005. We now have a situation where demonstrating in designated areas without authorisation is an offence under Section 132(1). The Minister may argue that demonstrations are not banned but now require the authorisation of the Commissioner of the Metropolitan Police. That authorisation must be obtained not less than six days or at least 24 hours before the demonstration starts. Requirements of that nature do not allow for spontaneous protests in the vicinity of Parliament. One of the grounds for refusal of authorisation is disruption to the life of the community. I am afraid everything we do is a disruption of some sort. Such blanket powers are more akin to a dictatorial regime than to our democracy.</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/9">The argument advanced was that previous legislation did not provide the police with all the powers they need to control all protests and demonstrations around Parliament. I reject that argument. I do not dispute that, at times, placards and slogans in Parliament Square cause annoyance to some parliamentarians; we all agree that they do. However, Parliament, the seat of our democracy, is big enough to take such protests in its stride. In any case, so fundamental are the geographical changes proposed by the Government that they strike at the very heart of the citizen's right to protest well outside the ambit of Parliament Square. The changes will have a major effect for generations to come. Let me start with the geography of the designated area. What initially started as a debate about demonstrations in Parliament Square resulted in legislation that created &quot;Fortress Whitehall&quot; where no one can protest without permission.</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/10">However, business in Parliament can change quickly. There are many days when we are unaware that a Statement will be made in Parliament by the Government. The reality is that one cannot protest freely in that case because 24 hours may not be available in which it is &quot;reasonably practicable&quot; for someone to notify the commissioner.</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/11">The massive area covered by this draconian law includes almost all government offices, Scotland Yard, Smith Square and many places of interest in this part of London. Civil servants working in government departments in an area including almost all the major government offices are not able to protest without permission. We have created a situation in which Ministers and members of the Labour Party can walk with their heads held high because there will be no picket lines to cross. I hope the unions and others will note how fundamentally their rights to picket peacefully are hampered by such legislation.</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/12">The designated area order made in 2005 is the outcome of the Serious Organised Crime and Police Act 2005. I need to ask an important question: has protesting outside Parliament ever been regarded as serious organised crime? Did Mr Wolfgang commit a serious organised crime at the Labour Party conference where he was manhandled and thrown out? Is it is a serious organised crime to shout out at the gate of Downing Street the names of our soldiers who died in Iraq? Can the Minister cite a single example where those who are at present protesting with their placards have hampered the business of Parliament in any way, let alone have committed a serious organised crime that has affected Parliament's work? It is embarrassing to politicians when their policies are exposed, and it is embarrassing when the Government's human rights record is questioned, but they are no reasons to silence a minority that will always find a way to get its message through.</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/13">I have no doubt that freedom of expression and assembly, which are protected under Articles 10 and 11 of the European Convention on Human Rights, are seriously restricted in the designated area. Do we want to violate European human rights law? According to the European Commission:</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/14" class="indent">&quot;The European Court of Human Rights (ECHR) has repeatedly emphasised that freedom of expression constitutes an essential foundation of democratic society and one of the basic conditions for its progress and for each individual's self-fulfilment&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/15">The Commission also said that freedom of assembly is a,</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/16" class="indent">&quot;fundamental right in a democracy and ... is one of the foundations of such a society&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/17">We do not believe that the measures the Government seeks are proportionate, nor do we believe that there is a legitimate aim, such as the prevention of disorder or crime.</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/18">We see no evidence of adequate and effective safeguards to protect against arbitrary interferences with convention rights. If there are no such safeguards, then police power could become fairly oppressive. We have gone though such a sad period in the past, and I do not need to spell out the dangers of such actions by those in power and authority.</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/19">I do not underestimate the need for security, but democracy is well served when there is a balance between what is required and what is appropriate. There is a danger if we do not support the Bill that it will make policing work of control and discipline more difficult.</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/20">Policing in our country is the envy of the world. It is the independence of the police, accompanied by the consent of the public that makes it possible to maintain law and order. I suspect that, to an extent, we are eroding this independence. The police will soon be forced to take actions that will often smack of political interference. Demonstration and protest are a healthy aspect of our democracy, and by creating obstacles we are treading on values that we have treasured for so long.</p>
	<p pid="a.1384.0/21">If we fail to protect these rights, it will be the Robert Mugabes of this world who will have the last laugh, for their actions will seem all the more justified. If we as a democracy give such comfort and strength to the actions of dictators, it will bring shame upon all of us. We have set a bad example to emerging democracies in various parts of the world. This Bill will need the support of all people in this House.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1386.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1386.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1387.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1387.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1390.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1390.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1390.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100686" speakername="Baroness Williams of Crosby" colon=":" colnum="1390"  time="015:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0010.htm#07012689000378">
	<p pid="a.1390.0/1">My Lords, I am grateful to the noble and learned Lord. I think he will understand that his reference to the conditions attached by the Commissioner to demonstrations is very disappointing in the light of criticisms made by the court only on Monday of this week about the fact that the conditions are unclear and not set out in a way that can easily be understood. Perhaps he could address that before he moves on.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1390.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1390.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1390.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100905" speakername="Lord Davidson of Glen Clova" colon=":" colnum="1390"  time="015:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0010.htm#07012689000379">
	<p pid="a.1390.1/1">Certainly, my Lords. As I understand the position in relation to Mr Haw's case, the judge's approach was to say that the specific conditions lacked clarity. That is not an indication that the law itself lacks clarity, but that the specific conditions that were employed in relation to Mr Haw did so. The assistant commissioner has placed further conditions in relation to Mr Haw's position. These, I respectfully suggest, do demonstrate an appropriate level of clarity, but no doubt that inevitably will be a matter for a judge somewhere else to consider.</p>
	<p pid="a.1390.1/2">The designated area was based on police operational experience of where demonstrations may cause a security risk when they hinder the proper operation of Parliament. The risk to safety of members of the public was also considered. I recognise that there will always been a debate about the boundaries of the designated area and that this will be kept under review. Since <phrase class="date" code="2005-08-01">1 August 2005</phrase> when the rest of the provisions on demonstrations in the vicinity of Parliament came into effect, the Metropolitan Police have used their powers to facilitate peaceful protest.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1391.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1391.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1391.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1391.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1393.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1393.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1393.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1393.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1393.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1393.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1397.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1397.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1398.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1398.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1398.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100199" speakername="Lord Evans of Temple Guiting" colon=":" colnum="1398"  time="016:11:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200607/ldhansrd/text/70126-0011.htm#07012689000427">
	<p pid="a.1398.0/1">My Lords, I thank the noble Baroness, Lady Noakes, for placing the Bill before the House so that a select group of your Lordships may consider this very important issue.</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/2">The Government view the provision of public spending information that is clear, concise, timely and accurate as extremely important. I agree with all the points that the noble Baroness made at the beginning of her speech. Our view is reflected in the fact that one of the Treasury's formal objectives, as set out on its public website, is to,</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/3" class="indent">&quot;achieve world-class standards of financial management in government&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/4">The noble Baroness asked for confirmation that value for money is still a core value of the Treasury, and I confirm that it is.</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/5">The noble Lord, Lord Newby, asked what the objections are to the Bill. The Bill may appear to imply that the Treasury does not currently make up-to-date and comprehensive government expenditure information freely available. On the contrary, the Treasury's public website, which had well over a million hits last year, already contains a great deal of information about public spending. This includes: copies of the central government supply estimates for a five-year period, which contain detailed departmental spending plans for a particular financial year; and copies of public expenditure statistical analyses going back to 1999.</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/6">Each publication contains detailed spending information covering a number of outturn years, as well as spending plans for future years. Data are broken down in a variety of ways, and include departmental groups, central and local government, and public corporations by country, region, and function. They also include copies of the Budget and Pre-Budget Reports going back to 1998; detailed information about Treasury spending controls, including past and forthcoming spending reviews that set budgetary limits on spending by government departments; and the public sector finances databank, which is updated monthly and contains runs of data for various aspects of expenditure and finance.</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/7">This list is by no means exhaustive but, I hope, gives a flavour of the large amount of public expenditure information that is already made available on the Treasury's public website. This is in addition to the expenditure information available on other government department websites, such as departmental reports. Such reports also provide information on public service agreements to show not only how much we spend but, just as importantly, what we are achieving with those resources.</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/8">Crucially, work is already under way in the Treasury to further expand the quantity of expenditure information on the public website, as well as to restructure the information to make it easier to navigate and search. This means that the public website will, additionally, hold detailed background and guidance material related to public spending issues. The Treasury's aim is to have this enhanced website material in place on its public website later this year.</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/9">This Bill's requirement&mdash;the creation of a new website specifically for spending data&mdash;would be contrary to the recommendations arising from the review of public services by Sir David Varney, <I>Service Transformation: A Better Service for Citizens and Businesses, A Better Deal for The Taxpayer</I>, which was published on <phrase class="date" code="2006-12-06">6 December 2006</phrase>. This review, which is available on the HMT's public website, recommends,</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/10" class="indent">&quot;a freeze on the development of new websites providing citizen or business e-services created by departments, agencies and non-departmental public bodies, unless authorised by the Ministerial Committee on Public Services and Public Expenditure Sub-Committee on Electronic Service Delivery&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/11">It also recommends that,</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/12" class="indent">&quot;by 2011, almost all citizen and business e-services migrate to Directgov and Businesslink.gov and all e-transactions are provided through these two primary websites. This means that all departments should then have one corporate website, utilising shared infrastructure, and all other sites will be closed&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/13">The Varney review was referred to in the main Pre-Budget Report document, also published on <phrase class="date" code="2007-12-06">6 December</phrase>, which again is available on the Treasury's public website. It stated:</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/14" class="indent">&quot;The Government strongly welcomes this report and will take forward its recommendations as a comprehensive service transformation programme&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/15">While I would argue that the reasons that I have given thus far are sufficient to justify this House expressing reservations about this Bill, I feel that I should also refer to one of the Bills specific provisions. Section 1(4) requires that,</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/16" class="indent">&quot;information about expenditure by government departments or executive agencies must be available on the website within 30 days of the date on which the expenditure was incurred&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/17">Although the Treasury seeks monthly expenditure information from all government departments and already makes some information available on its public website, as I have mentioned, such information is inevitably very provisional and could not be regularly produced at a detailed level without a significant impact on resources. It is therefore simply not cost-effective to do this. Most public spending data currently made available relate to full financial years, whether outturn or plans. Audited resource accounts for government departments provide the most comprehensive and accurate information on actual expenditure outturn. The Government have made strides to speed up provision of such information, and faster closing of resource accounts now requires that they are presented to Parliament before the Summer Recess. What is most important is that detailed, accurate and independently audited information about public spending is made available as soon as it is reasonable to do so.</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/18">Before I conclude, may I deal with three points? The first point was raised by the noble Lord, Lord Newby, on the improvement in public services. As the noble Lord knows, departments agree public service agreements with HM Treasury to show the main aims for which the resources are used. These targets are published by all departments. Secondly, I can confirm that the role of the Treasury includes ensuring value for money for public spending, a point that I have made before. The Treasury agrees service targets with all departments. Finally, the noble Baroness, Lady Noakes, and the noble Lord, Lord Newby, mentioned the American Bill. That Bill applies to all spending over $25,000 but it applies only to federal awards, mainly grants and contractual payments. As we know, a great deal of American spending is at state level.</p>
	<p pid="a.1398.0/19">In conclusion, I would urge noble Lords to consider the points that I have made and to conclude that detailed government spending information is already made freely and publicly available and that setting up additional government websites would be contrary to work currently underway to improve the provision of public information and service delivery through government websites.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1400.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1400.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1400.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1400.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1400.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1400.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26a.1400.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2007-01-26b.1400.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

