<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2010-05-19a.3.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="3"  time="015:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100519-0001.htm#10051952000020">
	Speaker of the House of Commons
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2010-05-19a.3.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100621" speakername="Lord Strathclyde" colon=":" colnum="3"  time="015:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100519-0001.htm#10051952000002">
	<p pid="a.3.1/1">My Lords, I beg to acquaint the House that a Commission has been issued under Her Majesty's Great Seal to several Lords therein named authorising the said Lords to declare in the name and on behalf of Her Majesty Her Majesty's Approbation of the choice of the Commons of Mr John Bercow to be their Speaker.</p>
	<p pid="a.3.1/2"><I>Then, the Lords Commissioners (the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster (Lord Strathclyde), the Lord Speaker (Baroness Hayman), Lord McNally, Baroness Royall of Blaisdon and Baroness D'Souza) being robed and seated in front of the Throne, the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster directed Black Rod as follows:</I></p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2010-05-19a.3.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100621" speakername="Lord Strathclyde" colon=":" colnum="3"  time="015:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100519-0001.htm#10051952000004">
	<p pid="a.3.2/1">Let the Commons know that the Lords Commissioners desire their immediate attendance in this House.</p>
	<p pid="a.3.2/2"><I>Then, the Commons being at the Bar, Mr Speaker-Elect (Mr John Bercow), addressing the Royal Commissioners, said:</I></p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2010-05-19a.3.3" speakerid="unknown" speakername="The Speaker-Elect" colnum="3"  time="015:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100519-0001.htm#10051952000006">
	<p pid="a.3.3/1">My Lords, I have to acquaint your Lordships that, in obedience to the Royal Command, Her Majesty's faithful Commons have, in the exercise of their undoubted rights and privileges, proceeded to the election of a Speaker, and that their choice has fallen upon myself. I therefore present myself to your Lordships' Bar and submit myself with all humility to Her Majesty's gracious Approbation.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2010-05-19a.3.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100621" speakername="Lord Strathclyde" colon=":" colnum="3"  time="015:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100519-0001.htm#10051952000007">
	<p pid="a.3.4/1">Mr John Bercow, we are commanded to assure you that Her Majesty is so fully sensible of your zeal in the public service, and of your ample sufficiency to execute the arduous duties which her faithful Commons have selected you to discharge, that Her Majesty does most readily approve and confirm you as their Speaker.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2010-05-19a.4.0" speakerid="unknown" speakername="The Speaker" colnum="4"  time="015:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100519-0001.htm#10051952000008">
	<p pid="a.4.0/1">My Lords, I submit myself with all humility and gratitude to Her Majesty's gracious Commands. It is now my duty, in the name of and on behalf of the Commons of the United Kingdom, to lay claim, by humble petition to Her Majesty, to all their ancient and undoubted rights and privileges, especially to freedom of speech in debate, to freedom from arrest, and to free access to Her Majesty whenever occasion shall arise, and that the most favourable construction shall be put upon all their proceedings. With regard to myself, I pray that, if in the discharge of my duties I shall inadvertently fall into any error, it may be imputed to myself alone, and not to Her Majesty's most faithful Commons.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2010-05-19a.4.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100621" speakername="Lord Strathclyde" colon=":" colnum="4"  time="015:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100519-0001.htm#10051952000009">
	<p pid="a.4.1/1">Mr Speaker, we have it further in Command to inform you that Her Majesty does most readily confirm all the rights and privileges which have ever been granted to or conferred upon the Commons by Her Majesty or any of her Royal predecessors. With respect to yourself, Sir, though Her Majesty is sensible that you stand in no need of such assurance, Her Majesty will ever place the most favourable construction upon your words and actions.</p>
	<p pid="a.4.1/2" class="italic">Mr Speaker and the Commons then retired.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2010-05-19a.4.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="4"  time="015:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100519-0001.htm#10051952000021">
	Peers and Oath of Allegiance
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lords/2010-05-19a.4.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="4"  time="015:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100519-0001.htm#10051952000021">
	<p pid="a.4.3/1" class="italic" pwmotiontext="unrecognized">Several Lords-Took the Oath or Affirmed.</p>
	<p pid="a.4.3/2" class="italic" pwmotiontext="adjourned">House adjourned at 7.30 pm.</p>
	<p pid="a.4.3/3" pwmotiontext="unrecognized">Correction</p>
	<p pid="a.4.3/4" pwmotiontext="unrecognized">In the <I>Official Report</I> for <phrase class="date" code="2010-05-18">Tuesday, 18 May</phrase>, two errors were made. First, a paragraph of text was attributed to Lord Strathclyde which he never said. The relevant lines are in the second column, from &quot;And it further appears&quot; to &quot;such manner as they shall see fit&quot;. Secondly, the Lord Speaker was recorded as having taken the Oath, when in fact she made the solemn Affirmation. We sincerely apologise for these serious mistakes.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

