<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">

<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >

<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >

<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY micro "&#181;" >

<!ENTITY euro "&#8364;" >
]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.225.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="225"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_wqn0">
	Weapons of Mass Destruction
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.225.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100447" speakername="Lord Moynihan" colon="" colnum="225"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.225.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.225.1/2" qnum="HL1668">What steps they are currently taking to deny Iran and Iraq the ability to develop weapons of mass destruction.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.225.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="225"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.225.2/1">Countering the proliferation of WMD is a key priority of the Government. We promote universalisation of the relevant international treaties and exercise tight export controls on both specialist and dual-use equipment capable of use to develop, produce or use WMD. We are active members of the international export control regimes that seek to co-ordinate controls on trade in such items. We continue to play an active role in support of UN efforts to ensure that Iraq's WMD programmes are terminated under international supervision in accordance with Security Council resolutions.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.225.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="225"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_wqn1">
	Weapons of Mass Destruction
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.225.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100447" speakername="Lord Moynihan" colon="" colnum="225"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.225.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.225.4/2" qnum="HL1669">When they last made representations to the Russian Government to halt their support for the civil nuclear projects in Iran.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.225.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="225"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.225.5/1">We regularly discuss Russian nuclear co-operation with Iran in our contacts with the Russian Government, most recently when my right honourable friend the Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs met Foreign Minister Ivanov in October.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.225.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="225"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_wqn2">
	Weapons of Mass Destruction
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.225.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100447" speakername="Lord Moynihan" colon="" colnum="225"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.225.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.225.7/2" qnum="HL1670">Whether they consider Iran's civil nuclear projects and efforts to acquire the means to produce fissile material raise the prospects of Iran being able to deliver nuclear weapons.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.225.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="225"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.225.8/1">As a state party to the Non-Proliferation Treaty (NPT), Iran is entitled to develop a civil nuclear programme, subject to International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) safeguards. The Bushehr reactor, the centrepiece of Iran's civil nuclear programme, is subject to IAEA safeguards. We remain concerned over persistent reports that Iran may have a nuclear weapons programme and urge Iran to sign up to the IAEA's additional 93 plus two protocols which allow more thorough international inspection of all nuclear sites. We attach utmost importance to Iran abiding fully by all of its NPT obligations.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.226.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="226"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_wqn3">
	Entry Clearance Refusals
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.226.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100483" speakername="Lord Parekh" colon="" colnum="226"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.226.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.226.1/2" qnum="HL2019">When they intend to lay before the House the report by Mr Rabinder Singh, the independent monitor of entry clearance refusals.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.226.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="226"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.226.2/1">Mr Singh's report on entry clearance refusals was laid before the House today. I very much welcome the report, which acknowledges the high standards of our entry clearance operation overseas and the Government's commitment to ensuring that it continues to operate fairly and professionally. Mr Singh's comments and suggestions will receive careful consideration.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.226.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="226"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_wqn4">
	Sri Lankan Asylum Seekers
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.226.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100414" speakername="The Countess of Mar" colon="" colnum="226"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.226.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.226.4/2" qnum="HL1826">For each year since 1990, how many asylum seekers who are citizens of Sri Lanka and who have exhausted all legal means of appeal against refusal to recognise them as refugees have been returned to Sri Lanka; and how many have been granted exceptional leave to remain.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.226.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="226"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.226.5/1">Information on the number of Sri Lankan asylum seekers removed from the United Kingdom and granted exceptional leave to remain in the years 1990 to 2000 is given in the table. It is not possible separately to identify how many of those persons granted asylum or ELR under the backlog criteria were granted ELR.</p>
	<p pid="a.226.5/2">I regret that information on the destination of failed asylum seekers removed from the United Kingdom is not collected centrally and could only be obtained by examining individual case files at disproportionate cost.</p>
	<p pid="a.226.5/3">Information on asylum applications, initial decisions, appeals, removals and detention is published quarterly on the Home Office Research, Development and Statistics Directorate website at <a href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/immigration1.html">http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/immigration1.html</a>.</p>
	<table>
		<caption>Sri Lankan asylum seekers(1)</caption>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.226.5/7"> <td>Year</td> <td>Removed from the United Kingdom(2,3)</td> <td>Granted ELR under normal procedures(4)</td> <td>Granted asylum or ELR under backlog criteria(5)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.226.5/8"> <td>1990</td> <td>&mdash;</td> <td>(6)455</td> <td>&mdash;</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.226.5/9"> <td>1991</td> <td>&mdash;</td> <td>(6)730</td> <td>&mdash;</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.226.5/10"> <td>1992</td> <td>60</td> <td>4,265</td> <td>&mdash;</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.226.5/11"> <td>1993</td> <td>75</td> <td>2,420</td> <td>&mdash;</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.226.5/12"> <td>1994</td> <td>55</td> <td>105</td> <td>&mdash;</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.226.5/13"> <td>1995</td> <td>60</td> <td>95</td> <td>&mdash;</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.226.5/14"> <td>1996</td> <td>80</td> <td>25</td> <td>&mdash;</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.226.5/15"> <td>1997</td> <td>95</td> <td>15</td> <td>&mdash;</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.226.5/16"> <td>1998</td> <td>140</td> <td>10</td> <td>&mdash;</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.226.5/17"> <td>1999</td> <td>&mdash;</td> <td>10</td> <td>620</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.226.5/18"> <td>2000</td> <td>&mdash;</td> <td>285</td> <td>895</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.226.5/21">Figures rounded to the nearest five.</p>
	<p pid="a.226.5/22">(1) Persons who had sought asylum at some point. Information on grants of ELR is of initial decisions, excluding the outcome of appeals or other subsequent decisions.</p>
	<p pid="a.226.5/23">(2) Includes persons removed under enforcement processes and persons refused and removed at ports of entry.</p>
	<p pid="a.226.5/24">(3) Includes persons departing Xvoluntary&quot; after enforcement action had been initiated against them.</p>
	<p pid="a.226.5/25">(4) May include some cases decided under the backlog criteria.</p>
	<p pid="a.226.5/26">(5) Cases decided under measures aimed at reducing the pre-1996 asylum application backlog.</p>
	<p pid="a.226.5/27">(6) Decision figures for 1990 and 1991 may understate.</p>
	<p pid="a.226.5/28">Provisional figures.</p>
	<p pid="a.226.5/29">&mdash; Not available.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.227.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="227"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_wqn5">
	Firearms Incidents Involving Police Personnel
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.227.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100056" speakername="Baroness Blatch" colon="" colnum="227"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.227.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.227.1/2" qnum="HL1854">How, given its role in the investigation of individual incidents involving the police and firearms, the Police Complaints Authority will provide the independence required to secure confidence in its review into firearms incidents involving police personnel.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.227.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="227"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.227.2/1">The role of the Police Complaints Authority in supervising investigations means that it is well placed to draw the lessons to be learned from incidents occurring over a number of years in different forces. The authority has engaged an independent expert on police firearms to ensure that all the relevant cases are rigorously scrutinised.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.227.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="227"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_wqn6">
	Highly Skilled Migrants
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.227.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100017" speakername="Lord Archer of Sandwell" colon="" colnum="227"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.227.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.227.4/2" qnum="HL2039">What plans they have to enable highly skilled individuals to come to the United Kingdom to seek employment.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.227.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="227"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w01.htm#11213w01_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.227.5/1">Currently, it is not possible for individuals, other than those with ancestral ties to the United Kingdom, to come to this country to seek and take up work in the absence of a job offer. This makes it difficult to attract highly mobile people with the special talents that are required in a modern economy. We are therefore introducing a programme specifically for highly skilled migrants which will enable them to come to the United Kingdom and seek work.</p>
	<p pid="a.227.5/2">This programme is designed to allow highly skilled people to migrate to the United Kingdom in order to seek and take up work. It differs from the work permit scheme as it does not require an employer to obtain a permit for the individual, and from the existing business routes (for example, the Innovators scheme or other business categories) in that it does not require a detailed business plan or investment in the United Kingdom. It will initially be run as a concession outside the current Immigration Rules.</p>
	<p pid="a.227.5/3">In order to qualify, applicants will need to demonstrate that they score 75 points or more. Points can be scored in five areas: educational qualifications, work experience, past earnings, achievement in chosen field and Highly Skilled Migrant Programme priority applications. This final area has been specifically designed to facilitate the recruitment and retention of suitably qualified overseas doctors who wish to work as general practitioners for the National Health Service.</p>
	<p pid="a.227.5/4">I am today placing in the Library a draft version of the guidance to applicants. This includes full details on how an individual can score sufficient points to meet the standard required to qualify under this programme. Applicants will also have to demonstrate that they can continue their chosen careers and that they will be able to maintain and accommodate themselves and any family whilst in the United Kingdom.</p>
	<p pid="a.227.5/5">Those already in the United Kingdom in a capacity leading to settlement may apply directly to the Home Office to obtain this status. We will also allow those graduating from a United Kingdom university or completing their post-graduate medical studies to apply while remaining in the United Kingdom, provided they have not been sponsored by their home governments.</p>
	<p pid="a.227.5/6">The Highly Skilled Migrant Programme will run for an initial period of 12 months and will come into force in January 2002. Application forms will be available from the Home Office and Foreign and Commonwealth Office websites at <a href="http://www.ind.homeoffice.gov.uk">www.ind.homeoffice.gov.uk</a> and <a href="http://www.fco.gov.uk">www.fco.gov.uk</a> respectively. Applications will be accepted by diplomatic posts overseas from <phrase class="date" code="2002-01-28">28 January 2002</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.227.5/7">This programme represents a further step in developing our immigration system to maximise the benefits to the United Kingdom of highly skilled workers who have the qualifications and skills required by United Kingdom businesses to compete in the global marketplace. It will allow eminent scientists to base their research projects here, should encourage the movement of business and financial experts to the City of London and give those at the top of their chosen profession the choice of making the United Kingdom their home.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.228.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="228"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_wqn0">
	Security Council Resolution 1373
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.228.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100424" speakername="Lord Merlyn-Rees" colon="" colnum="228"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.228.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.228.1/2" qnum="HL2018">What implications the terms of UN Security Council Resolution 1373 on terrorism have for their policy in respect of arms exports.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.228.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="228"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.228.2/1">By UN Security Council Resolution 1373 (2001), the Security Council inter alia calls upon member states both to eliminate Xthe supply of weapons to terrorists&quot; (paragraph 2(a)) and to Xco-operate, particularly through bilateral and multilateral arrangements and agreements, to prevent and suppress terrorist attacks and take action against the perpetrators of such attacks&quot; (paragraph 3(c)).</p>
	<p pid="a.228.2/2">We have therefore reviewed government policy in respect of arms exports in light of this resolution. In view of the Government's strong continued commitment to human rights, regional stability and the campaign against terrorism, and taking account of the fact that our human rights obligations are not affected by the adoption of the resolution, we believe there is no need to amend the consolidated criteria in order for us to comply fully with the terms of the resolution. Our detailed conclusions are as follows:</p>
	<p pid="a.228.2/3">(1) Export licensing decisions are taken on a case-by-case basis against all of the consolidated EU and national arms export licensing criteria, as set out in the Official Report, <phrase class="date" code="2000-10-26">26 October 2000</phrase>, col. 200W, in the light of the circumstances prevailing at the time. The last paragraph of the preamble to the consolidated criteria states that, XAn export licence will not be issued if the arguments for doing so are outweighed by the need to comply with the UK's international obligations and commitments, by concern that the goods might be used for internal repression or international aggression, by risks to regional stability or by other considerations as described in these criteria&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.228.2/4">(2) Criterion two of the consolidated criteria includes the statement that HMG Xconsiders that in some cases the use of force by a Government within its own borders, for example to preserve law and order against terrorists or other criminals, is legitimate and does not constitute internal repression, as long as force is used in accordance with the international human rights standards described above&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.228.2/5">(3) In judging individual applications, the Government will take account of the terms of UNSCR 1373 (2001) and will continue to pay attention to this passage in criterion two within the discretion provided by the consolidated criteria.</p>
	<p pid="a.228.2/6">(4) The consolidated criteria already state that, when considering export licence applications, the Government will take account of the record of the buyer country with regard to Xits support or encouragement of terrorism and international organised crime&quot; (criterion six (a)) and that XThe Government will pay particular attention to the need to avoid diversion of UK exports to terrorist organisations&quot;. (criterion seven) This makes clear our commitment to preventing arms exported from the UK from falling into the hands of terrorists.</p>
	<p pid="a.228.2/7">(5) We are taking additional steps to strengthen our export controls. The Export Control Bill currently going through Parliament gives the Government a number of new powers which will help to improve our ability to prohibit the transfer of arms or related technology to terrorists, including new powers to control the transfer of technology by intangible means and trafficking and brokering in arms. We are aiming to sign the UN Firearms Protocol soon and will encourage others to do so, and have proposed bringing forward analysis of the OSCE's information exchange on the marking of Small Arms. These steps will help us to keep small arms out of terrorists' hands by helping us to trace weapons flows and to combat the illicit manufacture and trafficking in firearms.</p>
	<p pid="a.228.2/8">(6) Finally, the new Anti-terrorism, Crime and Security Bill includes clauses to close the gaps in our present legislation relating to chemical, nuclear and biological weapons to prevent the use, production, possession or participation in unauthorised transfers of these materials.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.230.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="230"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_wqn1">
	Doha Declaration
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.230.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100428" speakername="Baroness Miller of Hendon" colon="" colnum="230"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.230.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.230.1/2" qnum="HL1895">Further to the answer by Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean on 3 December (HL Deb col. 583), what formal or informal understandings were reached with the French Government to induce them to subscribe to the World Trade Organisation declaration of Doha.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.230.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="230"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.230.2/1">All members of the European Union signed up to the Doha Declaration on equal terms. The Government cannot comment on the rationale behind decisions taken by other governments.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.230.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="230"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_wqn2">
	Doha Declaration
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.230.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100428" speakername="Baroness Miller of Hendon" colon="" colnum="230"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.230.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.230.4/2" qnum="HL1897">Further to the comment by Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean on 3 December (HL Deb col. 583) that the agreement of the agricultural section of the World Trade Organisation Doha declaration Xcame more readily from some than others&quot;, which signatories were the most reluctant to sign.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.230.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="230"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.230.5/1">The agreement reached in Doha constitutes a balanced package of commitments reflecting the full range of interests held by the 142 members of the WTO. Individual members naturally had differing attitudes to particular parts of the whole. It would be inappropriate for the Government to speak for other named governments on their attitude to parts of the declaration.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.230.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="230"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_wqn3">
	Near Earth Objects Task Force
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.230.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100280" speakername="Lord Haskel" colon="" colnum="230"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.230.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.230.7/2" qnum="HL2013">What further action will be taken in relation to their responses of 24 February to the recommendations contained in the report of the Near Earth Objects Task Force, which was set up by the Minister of Science.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.230.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="230"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.230.8/1">An updated response is nearing completion and will be published shortly. Copies will be put with the report and the government response which were placed in the Libraries of both Houses. A copy of this response and press release will also be found at <a href="http://www.nearearthobjects.co.uk">www.nearearthobjects.co.uk</a>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.231.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="231"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_wqn4">
	Joint Services Adventurous Training (Gliding)
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.231.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100417" speakername="Lord Marsh" colon="" colnum="231"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.231.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.231.1/2" qnum="HL1792">What is the proposed consultation process before making a final decision relating to the future of gliding activity at RAF Upper Rissington and RAF Bicester.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.231.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="231"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.231.2/1">The consultation process required will depend on the outcome of the study into the permanent location of the Joint Services Adventurous Training (Gliding) function.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.231.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="231"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_wqn5">
	British Troops on Active Service
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.231.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100444" speakername="Lord Morris of Manchester" colon="" colnum="231"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.231.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.231.4/2" qnum="HL1799">In how many and in which overseas locations British troops are now deployed on active service and how many have been given nerve agent pre-treatment sets in combination in multiple inoculations against anthrax and other diseases.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.231.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="231"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.231.5/1">British troops are deployed on active service in 16 countries and Dependent Territories in the Balkans, the Middle East, Cyprus, the Falkland Islands, Georgia, the United States of America, Africa and Asia, as well as at sea. Nerve agent pre-treatment sets (NAPS) tablets are held in theatre where we assess there is a potential threat from chemical agents but are issued only when that chemical agent threat is assessed to be immediate. This has not so far proven necessary and so no British troops on active service have been given NAPS tablets as part of current operations.</p>
	<p pid="a.231.5/2">As for anyone travelling overseas, military personnel deploying abroad are offered appropriate immunisation against disease. The offer of immunisation, including for anthrax, takes full account of any treatment or medication an individual might be receiving at the same time.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.231.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="231"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_wqn6">
	Chinook Mark 2/2a Helicopter
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.231.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100484" speakername="Baroness Park of Monmouth" colon="" colnum="231"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.231.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.231.7/2" qnum="HL1859">Further to the Written Answer by Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean on 9 October 2000 (WA 5), how many of the RAF Chinook Mark 2/2a fleet have now been fitted with cockpit voice and flight data recorders; and, if any of them have not been so equipped, what is the expected completion date.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.231.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="231"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.231.8/1">The 33rd and 34th aircraft from the RAF Chinook Mark 2/2a fleet are currently being fitted with cockpit voice and flight data recorders as part of the Health and Usage Monitoring System programme. This leaves six of the fleet still to be so equipped, which because of operational requirements will not now be completed until the summer of next year, 2002.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.232.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="232"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_wqn7">
	HMS Victory Fore Topsail
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.232.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100016" speakername="Baroness Anelay of St Johns" colon="" colnum="232"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.232.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.232.1/2" qnum="HL1880">What are their plans to conserve and display the fore topsail of HMS Victory in time for the bicentenary celebrations of the battle of Trafalgar in 2005; and whether they will ensure that the display of the topsail takes place in London so that it is accessible to the greatest number of people before it is returned to its permanent home in Portsmouth.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.232.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="232"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w02.htm#11213w02_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.232.2/1">The fore topsail of HMS Victory is currently in protective storage in Portsmouth Historic Dockyard. A programme of conservation and survey is in hand which will shortly be reporting on its future conservation needs and possible display options. We recognise that the sail should be displayed for the Trafalgar bicentenary if possible, but no decisions can be taken until the recommendations of this report are known and proper account can be taken of the long-term preservation needs of this unique heritage item.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.232.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="232"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn0">
	Future Offensive Air System
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.232.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100274" speakername="Lord Hardy of Wath" colon="" colnum="232"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.232.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.232.4/2" qnum="HL1904">Whether the United Kingdom is likely to be involved in the research into, and development of, unmanned aircraft being undertaken by Boeing.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.232.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="232"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.232.5/1">The United Kingdom has a requirement to replace, towards the end of the next decade, the strike capability currently provided by the Tornado GR4 strike aircraft. This programme is known as the Future Offensive Air System (FOAS). While no decisions have yet been taken, we are currently looking at a potential mix of platforms to deliver precision strike capability, including long range cruise missiles, unmanned and manned aircraft.</p>
	<p pid="a.232.5/2">The FOAS programme is currently evaluating ways in which unmanned aircraft will contribute to the FOAS capability, and Ministry of Defence (MoD) officials have had discussions with a number of companies, including Boeing, and with other governments and agencies. However, the FOAS programme remains at an early stage and no decisions have been made about MoD involvement in developing specific unmanned aircraft.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.232.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="232"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn1">
	Private Hospitals in London: NHS Occupancy
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.232.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100077" speakername="Lord Brightman" colon="" colnum="232"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.232.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.232.7/2" qnum="HL1678">How many beds in private hospitals in the London area were occupied by National Health Service patients on the first day of each month, from 1 January to 1 October 2001; and approximately what percentage National Health Service occupancy represented on each such monthly date of the total private hospital capacity in the London area.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.233.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="233"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.233.0/1">The information requested is not collected by the Department of Health.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.233.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="233"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn2">
	Autism
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.233.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100056" speakername="Baroness Blatch" colon="" colnum="233"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.233.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.233.2/2" qnum="HL1725">How many research projects into autism and related conditions they have commissioned or funded in the last five years.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.233.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="233"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.233.3/1">The Medical Research Council (MRC), the main government agency that funds research into the causes of and treatments for disease, has funded 11 grants in the field of autism that have started in the last five years. In the same period the MRC has also funded 10 projects at the MRC Child Psychiatry Unit and 2 at the MRC Cognitive Development Unit. These units closed in July 2000 and September 1998 respectively but work following on from these units' programmes continues to be supported by some of the new grants mentioned above.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.3/2">The Department of Health funds research to support policy and the delivery of effective practice in the National Health Service. The department's NHS Research and Development programme funded a project on auditory integration training for autism: effects on harmful and stigmatising behaviours that finished in 1999. The department also provides NHS support funding for research commissioned by the research councils and charities that take place in the NHS. There is a large volume of research on all aspects of autism. Details of projects can be found on the National Research Register (NRR) which is available on the Internet at: <a href="http://www.doh.gov.uk/research/nrr.htm">http://www.doh.gov.uk/research/nrr.htm</a>. The NRR records show that there are currently 58 ongoing and 86 completed research projects on autism that started in the last five years.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.3/3">The Department for Education and Skills has funded two projects in the last five years, one jointly with the Department of Health.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.3/4">In March, the Department of Health commissioned the MRC to conduct a detailed review of the current state of knowledge about autism and to suggest possible areas for further research. The report, published today, provides a picture of what scientific research has revealed about the occurrence and causes of autism and other autism spectrum disorders, identifies gaps in knowledge and makes recommendations on future research strategy for the United Kingdom.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.234.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="234"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn3">
	Breast Cancer
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.234.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="234"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.234.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.234.1/2" qnum="HL1893">What strategy they have in place to combat the expected rise by over 2 per cent per annum between now and 2023 in the breast cancer rate among women aged 45 to 59, which the recent report from Patrick Carroll of the Pension and Population Research Institute concludes will be largely due to the high rate of nulliparous abortions and the decline in the birth rate.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.234.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="234"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.234.2/1">The suggested link with abortion is not proven.</p>
	<p pid="a.234.2/2">The Government are already taking comprehensive action to detect breast cancer at an early stage and to ensure prompt, high quality treatment.</p>
	<p pid="a.234.2/3">The National Health Service Breast Screening Programme routinely screens women aged 50 to 64 (currently being extended to women aged up to 70) every three years. In 1999&ndash;2000, over 8,000 cancers were detected by breast screening in England. Improvements are also being introduced to the way in which mammography images are taken.</p>
	<p pid="a.234.2/4">Genetic factors may increase the risk of breast cancer for some women. The Department of Health is working, in partnership with Macmillan Cancer Relief, to improve cancer genetic risk assessment and counselling services in England. This will involve working with primary care teams to help them identify the level of risk for individual patients based on their family history.</p>
	<p pid="a.234.2/5">Around 95 per cent of suspected breast cancer patients referred urgently are seen within two weeks. By December 2001, women with breast cancer will wait one month from diagnosis to treatment and by 2002 will wait a maximum of two months from urgent general practitioner referral to treatment for breast cancer.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.234.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="234"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn4">
	Human Embryonic Stem Cells
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.234.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="234"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.234.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.234.4/2" qnum="HL1933">What information they hold concerning the import into the United Kingdom of human embryonic stem cells, particularly from the United States; and what information they collect on their use; and</p>
	<p pid="a.234.4/3" qnum="HL1934">What provision will be made to regulate the import and export of human embryonic stem cells; and what penalties will be imposed for their improper use.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.234.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="234"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.234.5/1">At present the Government have no plans to collect information on the importation and use of human embryonic stem cells.</p>
	<p pid="a.234.5/2">All aspects of stem cell research are being examined currently by a Select Committee of the House of Lords, and the Government will consider its recommendations carefully when they are published.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.235.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="235"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn5">
	Human Embryonic Stem Cells
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.235.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="235"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.235.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/2" qnum="HL1936">Given the circumstances which prevailed prior to January 2001 when donor consent was provided for human embryos to be used for research purposes, whether they consider that such consent will remain valid for research envisaged under the Human Fertilisation and Embryology (Research Purposes) Regulations 2001.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.235.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="235"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.235.2/1">The consent provisions of the Human Fertilisation and Embryology Act 1990 are unaffected by the HFE (Research Purposes) Regulations 2001, and the 1990 Act continues to apply to all embryos created by fertilisation.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.2/2">Consent to the use of an embryo must specify one or more of the purposes stated in schedule 3 to the 1990 Act, one of which is X(C) use for the purposes of any project of research&quot;, and may specify conditions subject to which the embryo may be so used. Embryo donors are offered the opportunity for counselling and will receive relevant information before giving consent. Additionally an embryo donor may withdraw their consent at any time by notice, provided that the embryo has not been used.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.235.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="235"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn6">
	Human Embryonic Stem Cells
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.235.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="235"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.235.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.235.4/2" qnum="HL1947">What account has been taken by the Department of Health in framing legislation determining the status of human embryos of studies in animals showing that embryonic stem cells have successfully grown into adult mice and cows.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.235.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="235"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.235.5/1">The Department of Health continues to keep scientific developments in stem cell research under review.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.5/2">The scientific papers that were referred to in the passage of the Human Reproductive Cloning Bill through the House of Lords do not, as was claimed, report the development of adult animals from embryonic stem cells.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.5/3">The research quoted involved the development of animals from existing embryos which had been artificially fused with embryonic stem cells.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.235.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="235"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn7">
	Geron Bio-med
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.235.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="235"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.235.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.235.7/2" qnum="HL1949">How many times the Department of Health has consulted representatives of Geron Bio-med or Geron Corp in the last two years; and whom they have met.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.235.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="235"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.235.8/1">One specific meeting took place at the Department of Health with Mr Simon Best of Geron Bio-med in 2000.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.8/2">In addition, the department regularly consults with a large number of companies, organisations and individuals but no central record is held of these.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.236.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="236"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn8">
	Cannabis: Therapeutic Uses Report
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.236.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100260" speakername="Lord Gregson" colon="" colnum="236"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.236.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.236.1/2" qnum="HL2012">When they intend to publish their response to the second report of the House of Lords Select Committee on Science and Technology on the Therapeutic Uses of Cannabis.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.236.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="236"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w03.htm#11213w03_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.236.2/1">The Government's response to the second report of the House of Lords Select Committee on Science and Technology on the Therapeutic Uses of Cannabis has been published today and copies will be placed in the Library.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.236.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="236"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w04.htm#11213w04_wqn0">
	Diabetes
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.236.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100284" speakername="Baroness Hayman" colon="" colnum="236"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w04.htm#11213w04_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.236.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.236.4/2" qnum="HL2014">When they intend to publish the Diabetes National Service Framework standards document.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.236.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="236"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w04.htm#11213w04_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.236.5/1">We shall be publishing the Diabetes National Service Framework standards tomorrow. Copies will be placed in the Library.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.236.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="236"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w04.htm#11213w04_wqn1">
	Statutory Provisions: Commencement
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.236.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100694" speakername="Lord Windlesham" colon="" colnum="236"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w04.htm#11213w04_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.236.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.236.7/2" qnum="HL1684">Whether the following statutory provisions have yet been brought into force; and, if not, when it is intended they will be: Child Support, Pension and Social Security Act 2000, Section 62; Criminal Justice and Court Services Act 2000, Section 53; and Criminal Justice and Police Act 2001, Sections 1 to 11.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.236.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100298" speakername="Baroness Hollis of Heigham" colon=":" colnum="236"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w04.htm#11213w04_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.236.8/1">Sections 62 to 66 (excluding the subsections relevant to Scotland) of the Child Support, Pensions and Social Security Act 2000 which support the Community Sentences and Benefits pilots were commenced with respect to four probation areas on <phrase class="date" code="2001-10-15">15 October 2001</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.236.8/2">Both Section 53 of the Criminal Justice and Court Services Act 2000 and Sections 1 to 11 of the Criminal Justice and Police Act are the responsibility of the Home Office.</p>
	<p pid="a.236.8/3">Section 53 of the Criminal Justice and Court Services Act 2000 will be commenced when resources, including prison places, are available.</p>
	<p pid="a.236.8/4">Sections 1 to 11 of the Criminal Justice and Police Act 2001 will be piloted, with the co-operation of the police, in a small number of areas next year. Commencement orders will be laid to bring the measures into force at that time.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.237.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="237"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w04.htm#11213w04_wqn2">
	Deaths in Custody
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.237.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100072" speakername="Lord Brett" colon="" colnum="237"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w04.htm#11213w04_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.237.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.237.1/2" qnum="HL1961">Whether they are satisfied with the current arrangements for prosecuting cases concerning deaths in custody.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.237.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100245" speakername="Lord Goldsmith" colon=":" colnum="237"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w04.htm#11213w04_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.237.2/1">I am fully aware of the public interest issues of concern that arise when someone dies in custody, whether in prison or in a police station.</p>
	<p pid="a.237.2/2">I have raised this important issue with the DPP and together we are reviewing the role of the CPS in the prosecution process to see whether any changes need to be made. If changes are needed, they will be made. If they are not, it will be important to reassure the public that the CPS deals with these difficult cases in an appropriate way.</p>
	<p pid="a.237.2/3">In conducting this review, we shall look at the approach taken by the Law Officers, as well as by the DPP and the CPS. We shall also consult other relevant government departments, as well as non-governmental organisations with an interest. We expect to complete our review by <phrase class="date" code="2002-06-30">30 June 2002</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.237.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="237"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w04.htm#11213w04_wqn3">
	Rural Task Force
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.237.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100654" speakername="Lord Varley" colon="" colnum="237"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w04.htm#11213w04_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.237.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.237.4/2" qnum="HL2016">When they will respond to the reports by the Rural Task Force and by Lord Haskins.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.238.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="238"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w04.htm#11213w04_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.238.0/1">We will be publishing the Government's response to the report of the Rural Task Force tomorrow. The published document will also be a response to the report of Lord Haskins, also published on the <phrase class="date" code="">18 October</phrase>, and will also take stock on the progress on delivering the Rural White Paper.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.238.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="238"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w04.htm#11213w04_wqn4">
	Primary School Teachers: Male Graduates
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.238.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100517" speakername="Lord Quirk" colon="" colnum="238"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w04.htm#11213w04_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.238.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.238.2/2" qnum="HL1924">What action they are taking to attract suitable young men to become teachers in primary schools.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-13a.238.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100024" speakername="Baroness Ashton of Upholland" colon=":" colnum="238"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011213/text/11213w04.htm#11213w04_spmin3">
	<p pid="a.238.3/1">Her Majesty's Government hope that, over time, the introduction of &pound;6,000 teacher training bursaries for primary Postgraduate Certificate in Education (PGCE) courses from September 2000 will encourage more male graduates to train as primary school teachers. The proportion of men among recruits to primary training has risen in both 2000&ndash;01 and 2001&ndash;02. Numbers are now 2.5 per cent higher than in 1999&ndash;2000. The improvements that Her Majesty's Government are making to teachers' pay and working conditions should also encourage more of the men and women who qualify as primary teachers to take up teaching posts in the maintained sector.</p>
	<p pid="a.238.3/2">On <phrase class="date" code="">1 November</phrase>, my right honourable friend announced that training bursaries would continue to be offered to trainees starting primary PGCE courses in the 2002&ndash;03 academic year.</p>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

