<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;" >
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;" >
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;" >
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;" >
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;" >

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="c" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.9.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn0">
	Armed Forces: Voter Registration
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.9.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100778" speakername="Lord Garden" colon="" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.9.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.9.1/2" qnum="HL6078">Whether they are now ready to publish the results of the Defence Analytical Services Agency survey on Armed Forces voter registration which was completed in March 2006, and which the Lord Drayson in his Written Answer on 3 May (<i>WA 66</i>) indicated was expected shortly.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.9.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.9.2/1">A copy was placed in the Library on <phrase class="date" code="">5 June</phrase> and my honourable friend the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence wrote to the noble Lord on the same day, enclosing a copy of the report.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.9.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn1">
	Army: Royal Irish Regiment
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.9.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.9.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.9.4/2" qnum="HL6008">What is the capital value of assets which will be available for sale if the proposed closure of the Royal Irish installations at Ballykelly, Omagh and Ballymena goes ahead.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.9.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.9.5/1">To release an estimate of the disposal value of these properties before the sale is complete could unduly influence the market and prejudice the commercial interests of the Ministry of Defence.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.9.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn2">
	Benefits: Personal Capability Assessment
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.9.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100444" speakername="Lord Morris of Manchester" colon="" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.9.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.9.7/2" qnum="HL6138">What groups have been set up by the Department for Work and Pensions to consider reforms of the personal capability assessment; and, in each case, what is the group's remit, terms of reference and membership.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.9.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_spmin2">
	<p pid="c.9.8/1">The department has created a series of working groups, comprising medical, technical and stakeholder experts, to advise and assist in the work to transform the personal capability assessment (PCA). The terms of reference and membership of these groups have been placed in the Library.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.10.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn3">
	Bovine Tuberculosis
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.10.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.10.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.10.1/2" qnum="HL6060">When they expect to publish their report on the recent consultation about controlling bovine tuberculosis; and how soon after that date they intend to take a decision on methods for controlling and, if possible, eradicating bovine tuberculosis.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.10.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_spmin3">
	<p pid="c.10.2/1">At this stage we cannot give an indication on the specific timing of the publication of the report on the consultation or a decision. However, given the seriousness of the disease situation, we aim to proceed as quickly as possible, while giving the issue the thorough consideration it requires. The decision is not a simple one. We are taking into account all the evidence, including the science.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.10.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn4">
	Bovine Tuberculosis and Badgers
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.10.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.10.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.10.4/2" qnum="HL6056">Whether they will authorise the use of rifles to reduce and control the badger population, generally and in particular in areas with high rates of tuberculosis; and whether such permission could be given without the need for primary legislation to authorise it.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.10.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_spmin4">
	<p pid="c.10.5/1">Badgers are protected from intentional killing under the Protection of Badgers Act 1992. However, the Act makes provision for granting licences to kill badgers for certain purposes such as preventing the spread of disease or damage to property. In these circumstances, badgers may be killed using rifles that do not use ammunition prohibited by Section 2 of the Act. No decisions have been made on whether a cull of badgers to prevent the spread of bovine tuberculosis is appropriate.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.10.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn5">
	Common Agricultural Policy: Single Farm Payment
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.10.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100339" speakername="Lord Jopling" colon="" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn5">
	<p pid="c.10.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.10.7/2" qnum="HL5618">Whether the Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs wrote to the European Union Agriculture Commissioner on 12 April asking for an extension from the end of June to mid-October as the deadline for the payment of the single farm payment; and, if so, why this was not relayed to Parliament in the Secretary of State's Statement of 19 April (<i>Official Report</i>, House of Commons, 13WS).</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.11.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="11"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_spmin5">
	<p pid="c.11.0/1">While the intention has been, and remains, for the Rural Payments Agency (RPA) to make outstanding payments under the 2005 single payment scheme as soon as possible, it has always been the case that some payments may be made after the end of the EU payment window on <phrase class="date" code="">30 June</phrase>. In those cases, the claimant will still be paid in full, but EU funding of those payments could be reduced. With that in mind, and to safeguard the interests of UK taxpayers, a request was made to the European Commission at official level on <phrase class="date" code="2007-04-12">12 April</phrase> to extend the payment window. It was evidently felt that this precautionary measure did not warrant mentioning alongside the key announcement for the industry that my right honourable friend the Member for Derby South had authorised the RPA to make partial payments, which resulted in over &pound;730 million reaching farmers in the week beginning <phrase class="date" code="2007-05-09">9 May</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.11.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="11"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn6">
	Crime: Knives
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.11.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100476" speakername="Lord Ouseley" colon="" colnum="11"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn6">
	<p pid="c.11.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.11.2/2" qnum="HL6115">What advice they have received from the Association of Chief Police Officers about measures to eliminate knife-related violent incidents.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.11.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="11"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_spmin6">
	<p pid="c.11.3/1">The Government work closely with the Association of Chief Police Officers in tackling knife crime. We are in agreement that a variety of approaches, encompassing legislation, enforcement, education and prevention, is required. The nationwide knife amnesty, launched on <phrase class="date" code="2007-05-24">24 May</phrase> and running until <phrase class="date" code="">30 June</phrase>, has been developed in partnership with ACPO and with the support of police forces. We are also supporting programmes of enforcement and education that will follow the knife amnesty. Proposals are contained in the Violent Crime Reduction Bill which would give police and local communities new powers to tackle knife-related violence. The Bill includes new powers to make it an offence to use other people to hide or carry guns or knives and introduces powers for head teachers and other members of staff to search pupils for knives. It is already an offence to sell knives to people under the age of 16 and we are proposing to increase this age to 18 in the Bill.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.11.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="11"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn7">
	Football: Northern Ireland
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.11.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="11"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn7">
	<p pid="c.11.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.11.5/2" qnum="HL5688">What funding is being provided to upgrade football stadia in Northern Ireland to meet the F&eacute;d&eacute;ration Internationale de Football Association (FIFA) or the Union of European Football Associations (UEFA) requirements.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.11.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="11"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.11.6/1">The Sports Council for Northern Ireland (SCNI), which is responsible for the development of sport including the distribution of funding, has recently awarded a total of &pound;1.77 million to assist with the upgrading of spectator facilities at football stadia in Northern Ireland consistent with Union of European Football Associations (UEFA) requirements. The SCNI has committed a further circa &pound;500,000, under its UEFA under-19 finals 2005 programme, to enable the IFA to meet the costs of football stadia upgrades necessary for the staging of the tournament in Northern Ireland. The SCNI also continues to work closely with the IFA and football clubs to assist them in meeting their responsibility for upgrading football stadia to F&eacute;d&eacute;ration Internationale de Football Association (FIFA) or UEFA requirements.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.12.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="12"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn8">
	Fuel Duty: Northern Ireland
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.12.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100795" speakername="Lord Rana" colon="" colnum="12"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_wqn8">
	<p pid="c.12.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.12.1/2" qnum="HL6066">For the most recent year for which figures are available, what was the yield from duty on fuel sold in Northern Ireland; and</p>
	<p pid="c.12.1/3" qnum="HL6067">Whether they have made an assessment of the possible annual yield from duty on fuel sold in Northern Ireland if duty had been levied at the rate or rates prevailing in the Republic of Ireland; and</p>
	<p pid="c.12.1/4" qnum="HL6068">Whether they have made an assessment of the tax lost through the illegal consumption of fuel in Northern Ireland without payment of duty; and</p>
	<p pid="c.12.1/5" qnum="HL6069">Whether they have made an assessment of the additional tax yield in the event that those resident in Northern Ireland, including businesses, purchased all fuel in Northern Ireland rather than the Republic of Ireland; and</p>
	<p pid="c.12.1/6" qnum="HL6070">Whether they have made an assessment of the annual staff and other costs, including policing and army costs, involved in the pursuit of those engaged in illegal activities arising from the disparity in fuel prices between Northern Ireland and the Republic of Ireland.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.12.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100802" speakername="Lord McKenzie of Luton" colon=":" colnum="12"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w01.htm#60613w01_spnew1">
	<p pid="c.12.2/1">Information on revenue from hydrocarbon oils can be found in table 3 of the HM Revenue and Customs <i>Hydrocarbon Oils Bulletin</i>, which can be found on the HM Revenue and Customs website at <a href="http://www.uktradeinfo.com/index.cfm?task=bullhydro">www.uktradeinfo.com/index.cfm?task=bullhydro</a>.</p>
	<p pid="c.12.2/2">Information on revenue from fuel sold in devolved nations is not available. No formal assessment has been made of the possible impact on revenue if duty on fuel sold in Northern Ireland had been levied at the rate or rates prevailing in the Republic of Ireland.</p>
	<p pid="c.12.2/3">Estimates of the total non-UK duty-paid consumption are available, and are reported in <i>Measuring Indirect Tax Losses&mdash;2005,</i> which is published alongside the PBR and can be found in the House of Commons Library.</p>
	<p pid="c.12.2/4">It is not yet possible to split revenue losses between those resulting from the illicit market and those from legitimate cross-border shopping. No formal assessment has been made of the duty revenue lost through illegal consumption of fuel or the extra revenue that would be raised if Northern Ireland residents consumed all road fuel from Northern Ireland.</p>
	<p pid="c.12.2/5">In 2004&ndash;05, 159 members of staff in Northern Ireland were involved in operations aimed at tackling oils fraud. These officers were deployed across customs and excise, including intelligence, criminal investigation, assurance and detection activity, and tackling all forms of illicit hydrocarbon oils activity, including cross-border smuggling.</p>
	<p pid="c.12.2/6">HMRC does not have access to resource information for the other agencies that contribute to the reduction of oils fraud in Northern Ireland.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.13.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="13"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn0">
	Government: Official Residences
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.13.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100271" speakername="Lord Hanningfield" colon="" colnum="13"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.13.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.13.1/2" qnum="HL5910">Which (a) officials and (b) former officials of the Home Office currently have the use of a residence owned or financed by the Government; and, in each case, what is (i) the title of the official in residence, serving or retired; and (ii) the annual running cost of the residence.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.13.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="13"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.13.2/1">The Home Office does not provide official residences for its officials. Information on any residences that may be provided to former officials by other parts of the Government is not collected by the Home Office. Where required, the Home Office either provides or meets whole, or part of, the cost of provision of residential accommodation for staff in various circumstances connected with their employment. This includes prison officers' quarters, seconded staff on detached duty and staff posted outside the UK.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.13.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="13"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn1">
	Government: Prerogative Powers
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.13.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="13"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.13.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.13.4/2" qnum="HL5833">What acts of the Executive, acting under a prerogative power, cannot be challenged in the courts.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.13.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="13"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.13.5/1">This is a matter for the courts. The courts have taken the view that whether the exercise of a power under authority of the prerogative is susceptible to judicial review depends upon the subject matter of that power. It is therefore a question that is determined on a case-by-case basis. The courts have considered matters that involve questions of high policy, such as the power to enter into treaties (or to deploy the Armed Forces), as not being amenable to the judicial process. They have, however, seen matters affecting the private rights and legitimate expectations of individuals, such as the decision to refuse to issue a passport or the decision to issue a warrant to intercept telephones, as being susceptible to judicial review.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.14.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn2">
	Housing: Building Regulations
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.14.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100042" speakername="Lord Berkeley" colon="" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.14.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.14.1/2" qnum="HL5171">What extra funding has been added to the Housing Corporation and registered social landlords' budgets for construction of new homes in 2006&ndash;07 to allow for extra costs in building, in line with the Office of the Deputy Prime Minister's code for sustainable homes level 3; and on what basis this was decided.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.14.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_spmin2">
	<p pid="c.14.2/1">From this April, all new Housing Corporation-funded houses have been expected to meet code level 3 or EcoHomes &quot;very good&quot;. It was announced back in June 2005 that the homes would need to meet EcoHomes &quot;very good&quot;, so registered social landlords had a chance to plan and ensure that the bids for the current round would be able to comply with the standard. No additional funding for the Housing Corporation has been provided for this standard. The Housing Corporation and registered social landlords are expected to meet the standard through existing budgets, including through efficiency savings where necessary.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.14.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn3">
	Housing: Disability
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.14.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100685" speakername="Baroness Wilkins" colon="" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.14.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.14.4/2" qnum="HL5715">What consideration has been given to the compatibility of the draft code for sustainable homes and the Department for Communities and Local Government's obligations under the forthcoming public sector duty to promote disability equality.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.14.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_spmin3">
	<p pid="c.14.5/1">The Department for Communities and Local Government is currently developing its response to the public sector duty, working in partnership with the Disability Rights Commission to use the department as the pathfinder government department for developing a disability equality scheme. The first step in developing the scheme is to assess DCLG's policies, programmes and functions for their impact on achieving disability equality. The consultation document for the code for sustainable homes was developed before the publication of the DRC code of practice on the public sector duty, but the Government will of course ensure that the final code is fully compliant with the duty.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.14.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn4">
	Housing: Disability
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.14.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100685" speakername="Baroness Wilkins" colon="" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.14.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.14.7/2" qnum="HL5716">Whether they consulted disabled people and their organisations before drawing up the draft code for sustainable homes.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.14.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.14.8/1">The working party of the Building Regulations Advisory Committee, which had been looking at the feasibility of incorporating lifetime homes standards into Part M of the building regulations, prior to the decision to include those standards in the code for sustainable homes, included disabled people and representatives of their organisations, including the Disability Rights Commission.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.15.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn5">
	Housing: Disability
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.15.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100685" speakername="Baroness Wilkins" colon="" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn5">
	<p pid="c.15.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.15.1/2" qnum="HL5717">What discussions they had with the Office of Disability Issues as regards the provision of accessible housing for disabled people.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.15.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_spnew1">
	<p pid="c.15.2/1">The Government's consideration of the provision of accessible housing for disabled people, in the context of Part M of the building regulations and the code for sustainable homes, took place from March 2004 to the end of 2005, before the establishment of the Office for Disability Issues in December 2005. Future development of lifetime homes elements of the code will of course be discussed with the ODI.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.15.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn6">
	Housing: Disability
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.15.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100685" speakername="Baroness Wilkins" colon="" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn6">
	<p pid="c.15.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.15.4/2" qnum="HL5719">Whether, as stated in 2004, they will now incorporate the lifetime homes standard into Part M of the building regulations.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.15.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_spnew2">
	<p pid="c.15.5/1">The Government's response to Kate Barker's report on housing supply announced:</p>
	<p pid="c.15.5/2" class="indent">&quot;The lifetime homes standard will . . . be incorporated into the Code for Sustainable Homes. It is very important that there is progress on increasing take up of the lifetime homes standard. The Government will monitor take up and review the future need for regulation if appropriate&quot;.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.15.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn7">
	Immigration, Asylum and Nationality Act 2006
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.15.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn7">
	<p pid="c.15.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.15.7/2" qnum="HL5751">When the various parts of the Immigration, Asylum and Nationality Act 2006 will come into force.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.15.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_spmin4">
	<p pid="c.15.8/1">We are considering when the provisions of the Immigration, Asylum and Nationality Act 2006 should be commenced and anticipate some being commenced shortly.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.15.9" nospeaker="true" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn8">
	Israel and Palestine: East Jerusalem
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.15.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn8">
	<p pid="c.15.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.15.10/2" qnum="HL6057">Whether they will make representations to the Government of Israel concerning any attempt to expel residents from east Jerusalem; and whether they will invite the quartet to resist any such expulsion.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.15.11" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_spmin5">
	<p pid="c.15.11/1">The Government continue to monitor closely the humanitarian and security situation in the occupied territories, and regularly raise their concern with the Government of Israel. Together with our quartet partners, the Government pursue a policy of constructive engagement with the Government of Israel on a wide range of humanitarian issues, including the issue of expulsions from east Jerusalem, and we will continue to do so.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.16.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn9">
	Israel and Palestine: Gaza
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.16.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100851" speakername="Baroness Tonge" colon="" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_wqn9">
	<p pid="c.16.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.16.1/2" qnum="HL6082">What discussions they have had with the Government of Israel concerning the opening of the Karni and Erez crossings in the Gaza Strip.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.16.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w02.htm#60613w02_spmin6">
	<p pid="c.16.2/1">The Government regularly raise their concerns with the Government of Israel on a wide range of issues regarding the humanitarian and security situation in the Occupied Territories. This includes discussion of the opening of crossings in Gaza, which the Government believe is a key issue affecting the humanitarian situation in the region. We, and the EU, are working with the US security co-ordinator, General Ward, to allay Israel's security concerns at Karni and Erez.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.16.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn0">
	Israel and Palestine: Tax
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.16.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100851" speakername="Baroness Tonge" colon="" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.16.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.16.4/2" qnum="HL6080">What recent discussions they have had with the Government of Israel concerning the transfer of tax moneys collected on behalf of the Palestinian Authority.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.16.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.16.5/1">All EU Foreign Ministers called on Israel on <phrase class="date" code="2007-05-15">15 May</phrase> to release this Palestinian money to the Palestinian Authority.</p>
	<p pid="c.16.5/2">The Government continue to have wide-ranging discussions with the Government of Israel on a broad range of humanitarian issues, including the withholding of customs revenues by the Government of Israel.</p>
	<p pid="c.16.5/3">Together with our quartet partners, our EU partners and a range of international financial institutions, we are working towards the establishment of a temporary mechanism to provide financial assistance to the Palestinian people directly, bypassing the Hamas-led Palestinian Authority.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.16.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn1">
	Lloyd's of London: Ministerial Responsibility
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.16.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100271" speakername="Lord Hanningfield" colon="" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.16.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.16.7/2" qnum="HL6197">Which Minister within the Department for Trade and Industry has ministerial responsibility for insurance matters relating specifically to the Lloyd's of London insurance market; and</p>
	<p pid="c.16.7/3" qnum="HL6198">Which Minister within HM Treasury has ministerial responsibility for taxation matters relating specifically to the Lloyd's of London insurance market.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.17.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100802" speakername="Lord McKenzie of Luton" colon=":" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.17.0/1">All matters relating to the Lloyd's of London insurance market are the responsibility of HM Treasury. The Minister responsible is the Economic Secretary, Mr Ed Balls MP.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.17.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn2">
	North/South Implementation Bodies
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.17.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.17.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.17.2/2" qnum="HL5338">In view of the connection between the Northern Ireland Assembly and the cross-border bodies in the Belfast agreement of 1998 and consequential legislation, how long it will take to disband the bodies if the Assembly is not in existence after 24 November.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.17.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_spnew1">
	<p pid="c.17.3/1">I can assure the noble Lord that both the British and Irish Governments will be making every effort in the coming months to ensure that the situation set out in his question does not arise. However the Prime Minister and the Taoiseach made it clear in their statement of <phrase class="date" code="2007-04-06">6 April</phrase> that, if restoration of the Assembly and Executive has to be deferred, the Governments will take steps to ensure that,</p>
	<p pid="c.17.3/2" class="indent">&quot;the Good Friday Agreement is actively developed across its structures and functions&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="c.17.3/3">In those circumstances, the issue of disbanding the implementation bodies does not arise.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.17.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn3">
	Peace Funding: Northern Ireland
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.17.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.17.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.17.5/2" qnum="HL6158">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Rooker on 5 June (<i>WA 159</i>) concerning reconciliation criteria for Peace II funding, who selected the guidance based on Brandon Hamber and Grainne Kelly's publication, <i>A Working Definition of Reconciliation</i>; on what basis; and after what consultation.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.17.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_spnew2">
	<p pid="c.17.6/1">The Peace II extension consultation committee, following a period of extensive consultation and a review of Peace II evaluation research, agreed that the guidance be based on <i>A Working Definition of Reconciliation</i>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.17.7" nospeaker="true" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn4">
	Police: Reorganisation
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.17.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100271" speakername="Lord Hanningfield" colon="" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.17.8/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.17.8/2" qnum="HL5319">How many items of correspondence, including letters, e-mails, faxes and telephone calls, they have received from the general public (a) broadly in favour of and (b) broadly opposing their plans for police force restructuring, both in total and broken down by each area subject to the proposals.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.17.9" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.17.9/1">To provide an Answer to this Question would incur disproportionate costs.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.18.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn5">
	Police: Reorganisation
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.18.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100271" speakername="Lord Hanningfield" colon="" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn5">
	<p pid="c.18.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.18.1/2" qnum="HL5835">Further to the Written Answer by the Baroness Scotland of Asthal on 15 May (<i>WA 12</i>), whether they will place in the Library of the House (a) a copy of the minutes for each meeting of the Restructuring Finance Working Group where a minute was taken; (b) a summary of the group's work to date; and (c) details of the group's membership.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.18.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_spnew3">
	<p pid="c.18.2/1">The Restructuring Finance Working Group has discussed a range of finance-related issues, including the set-up costs of restructuring, police precept equalisation, general grant to police authorities from 2007-08 and route maps for finance change. There remain no plans to publish the minutes of the group which has helped to inform the development of ongoing work. The working group is chaired by the head of the Home Office police finance unit. Members are drawn from the Home Office, the Department for Communities and Local Government, HM Treasury, the Welsh Assembly Government, the Local Government Association, the Association of Chief Police Officers, the Association of Police Authorities, the Metropolitan Police Authority and the Metropolitan Police Service.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.18.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn6">
	Police: Reorganisation
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.18.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100271" speakername="Lord Hanningfield" colon="" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn6">
	<p pid="c.18.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.18.4/2" qnum="HL5880">What mechanisms they have, or will put in place, to ensure that the opinions of citizens are heard during the four-month consultation period relating to their proposals for police force restructuring in England and Wales in the affected areas.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.18.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_spnew4">
	<p pid="c.18.5/1">The affected police authorities, local authorities and chief constables have until the close of the four-month consultation period to submit any objections to the proposal. It is a matter for these bodies to determine how they compile their objections. In order to do this, they may wish to engage with and consult local stakeholders including local communities. Any such arrangements for local consultation are sensibly a matter for local determination; accordingly the Government do not propose to put in place any mechanisms of their own. All objections received by the Home Secretary by the deadline, from the chief constables, police authorities or local authorities, will be fully considered before any decision to lay a draft amalgamation order is taken.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.18.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn7">
	Police: Stephen Oake
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.18.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100444" speakername="Lord Morris of Manchester" colon="" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn7">
	<p pid="c.18.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.18.7/2" qnum="HL6044">What representations they have received from officers of the Police Federation and others for posthumous recognition of the excelling bravery of Special Branch officer Stephen Oake, murdered while on counter-terrorist police duty in Manchester; and what reply they have made.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.19.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_spmin2">
	<p pid="c.19.0/1">The Police Federation has written to the Prime Minister and the former Home Secretary. It also raised the matter at its conference on <phrase class="date" code="2007-05-17">17 May</phrase>. The Prime Minister, the Cabinet Office and the Home Office have received a total of 101 further letters on the subject and an Early Day Motion was tabled in the House of Commons in February this year.</p>
	<p pid="c.19.0/2">All members of Her Majesty's Government were deeply saddened by the tragic circumstances of DC Oake's death. The sacrifice he made in the line of duty is appreciated by us all. His courage will inspire officers young and old for years to come.</p>
	<p pid="c.19.0/3">The recommendation on whether to award the George Cross is made not by the Prime Minister or any other Minister but by the senior officials who form the George Cross Committee. Any recommendation by the committee to award a George Cross is submitted to Her Majesty the Queen by the Prime Minister.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.19.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn8">
	Residential Homes
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.19.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_wqn8">
	<p pid="c.19.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.19.2/2" qnum="HL5973">What complaint procedures are available for residents and relations of those in residential homes regarding the standard of care, accommodation and food provided.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.19.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100670" speakername="Lord Warner" colon=":" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w03.htm#60613w03_spmin3">
	<p pid="c.19.3/1">The national minimum standards (NMS) for care homes, which are available in the Library, include specific requirements for homes to have complaints procedures for service users, relatives and friends.</p>
	<p pid="c.19.3/2">The NMS, which the regulator, the Commission for Social Care Inspection (CSCI), must take into account when inspecting residential homes, stipulate that complaints procedures should be made available to all service users as part of their guide to the services homes provide, that complaints procedures must be simple, clear and accessible, that complaints should be responded to within a maximum of 28 days and that detailed records should be kept, which should include details of investigations and any action taken.</p>
	<p pid="c.19.3/3">Service users whose care is arranged by their local authority are also entitled to pursue complaints via the local authority or the individual residential home complaints procedure. All service users and their representatives have a further right to refer matters to CSCI and then to the Parliamentary Ombudsman for further investigation if they are not satisfied with the way in which their complaints are dealt with.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.19.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn0">
	Revenue and Customs: Accountancy Rules
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.19.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100467" speakername="Baroness Northover" colon="" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.19.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.19.5/2" qnum="HL6140">Under new accountancy rules introduced from 22 June 2005 under UITF40 (urgent issues task force), whether HM Revenue and Customs are proposing to treat contractual activity by a service provider as taxable income at full value in situations where (a) a seller subsequently decides not to charge for work, having completed a contractual activity; (b) a seller subsequently decides to charge for work at less than commercial value, having completed a contractual activity; and (c) a seller is offering his or her services to a charity where he or she is not proposing to charge and this fact is conveyed prior to commencing the work.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.20.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100802" speakername="Lord McKenzie of Luton" colon=":" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.20.0/1">The taxable profits of a business are based on its profits calculated according to generally accepted accounting practice (GAAP) subject only to the adjustments required or authorised by tax law. The amount of revenue recognised in profits in specific situations and the timing of the recognition of revenue in accounts are matters of accountancy and will depend in part on the actual facts of those situations. Provided the taxpayer has followed GAAP in compiling his accounts, the amount included in his accounts will be acceptable as the starting point for the calculation of taxable profits. Schedule 15 to the Finance (No. 2) Bill includes provision for the spreading of the one-off taxable adjustments which will arise when a business has to change its accounting policies to conform with UITF40.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.20.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn1">
	Roads: M11 Toll Lane
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.20.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100271" speakername="Lord Hanningfield" colon="" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.20.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.20.2/2" qnum="HL6108">What discussions the Department for Transport has had, and with whom, regarding the creation of a toll lane on or in proximity to the M11.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.20.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100164" speakername="Lord Davies of Oldham" colon=":" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_spnew1">
	<p pid="c.20.3/1">The use of a tolled lane on the M11 was considered and discussed with BAA plc as part of the modelling of surface access infrastructure supporting Stansted's second runway. This idea was dismissed at an early stage. No further discussions on this issue have taken place.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.20.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn2">
	Scientific Advisory Committees
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.20.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100414" speakername="The Countess of Mar" colon="" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.20.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.20.5/2" qnum="HL6179">Who are the members of their scientific advisory committees, stating for each person what capacity they have served, any previous service on such committees and the periods of service.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.20.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.20.6/1">We do not hold a central list of all members of scientific advisory committees. To compile such a list would be at a disproportionate cost to the Office of Science and Innovation due to the number of members and frequent changes to membership. These are held by government departments and/or committee secretariats. A full list of scientific advisory committees for all government departments (and website links) is available on the DTI website at <a href="http://www.dti.gov.uk/science/science-in-govt/works/advice-policy-making/codeofpractice/page27719.html">www.dti.gov.uk/science/science-in-govt/works/advice-policy-making/codeofpractice/page27719.html</a>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.21.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn3">
	Scientific Advisory Committees
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.21.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100414" speakername="The Countess of Mar" colon="" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.21.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.21.1/2" qnum="HL6180">Whether there is an official retirement age for members of their scientific advisory committees; and whether there are any constraints on the length of time that members serve on one particular committee or on scientific advisory committees in general.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.21.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_spnew2">
	<p pid="c.21.2/1">There is no official retirement age for members of scientific advisory committees, which are classed as non-departmental public bodies (NDPBs). There are, however, constraints on the total length of time that members can serve on one particular NDPB. Guidance from the Office of the Commissioner for Public Appointments states that the number of terms an individual may serve and the conditions for reappointment may vary, but the maximum period in office must not normally exceed 10 years on the same board. Please see <a href="http://www.ocpa.gov.uk">www.ocpa.gov.uk</a> for further details.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.21.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn4">
	Scientific Advisory Committees
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.21.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100414" speakername="The Countess of Mar" colon="" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.21.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.21.4/2" qnum="HL6181">What are the provisions for dealing with physical or mental incapacity that might occur in a serving member of one of their scientific advisory committees.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.21.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_spnew3">
	<p pid="c.21.5/1">There is no central guidance on the provisions for dealing with physical or mental incapacity. This is left to the individual sponsoring departments of the committees and NDPBs in question.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.21.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn5">
	Sexual Exploitation
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.21.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn5">
	<p pid="c.21.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.21.7/2" qnum="HL5911">Whether all the women freed this year by Operation Pentameter from sexual exploitation are receiving good care, support and rehabilitation.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.21.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.21.8/1">Operation Pentameter has been victim focused. Police forces across the country have worked with Poppy and local community and voluntary organisations to ensure that the women that have been rescued and identified as victims of human trafficking receive the support and care that they need. Many of the victims are assisting police with ongoing investigations and we are unable to comment on individual cases. However, we will shortly be bringing together the statutory practitioners and non-governmental organisations (NGOs) that have been involved in Operation Pentameter to discuss the lessons learnt, to establish best practice and to identify areas of improvement for the future.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.22.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn6">
	Somalia
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.22.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn6">
	<p pid="c.22.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.22.1/2" qnum="HL6117">What assessment they have made, following the progress of the Islamic militia under Sheikh Sharif Ahmed in Mogadishu, of President Abdullahi Yusuf's ability to establish effective government in Somalia.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.22.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_spmin2">
	<p pid="c.22.2/1">The UK supports the transitional federal institutions in pursuing dialogue, reconciliation and stable governance in Somalia in accordance with the transitional federal charter. We will continue to provide assistance to Somalia within this framework. We urge all states in the region to respect the UN arms embargo on Somalia and refrain from supplying armaments, which exacerbate conflict there. We encourage the transitional federal Government to engage with the Islamic courts and welcome the fact that both sides have made conciliatory statements.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.22.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn7">
	Terrorism: Proscribed Organisations
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.22.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn7">
	<p pid="c.22.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.22.4/2" qnum="HL6019">How many prosecutions were initiated in 2005 for alleged membership of each of the organisations proscribed under the Terrorism Act 2000, as amended.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.22.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_spmin3">
	<p pid="c.22.5/1">In 2005, two individuals were charged with offences under Section 11 of the Terrorism Act 2000. Details of the organisations to which the offences related are not kept centrally.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.22.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn8">
	Visas: US Methodist Ministers
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.22.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100794" speakername="Lord Roberts of Llandudno" colon="" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_wqn8">
	<p pid="c.22.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.22.7/2" qnum="HL6021">Why 15 Methodist probationer ministers from the United States have been refused visas to enable them to work in the Methodist Church in the United Kingdom.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.22.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w04.htm#60613w04_spmin4">
	<p pid="c.22.8/1">No applications have in fact been received this year from Methodist probationers from the United States. Those non-EEA nationals seeking to come to the UK to preach and perform pastoral duties in the UK are considered under the Immigration Rules for ministers of religion. It is a long-standing requirement of this category that, where relevant, applicants are ordained. Under the current system, probationers who are not ordained would be refused entry to work as ministers of religion. The Government are keen to replace the requirement for ordination with a more flexible pre-entry qualification requirement. On <phrase class="date" code="">19 December</phrase> last year, the Minister for Immigration, Citizenship and Nationality (Tony McNulty) made a Written Ministerial Statement announcing the Home Office response to the second stage of consultation with faith communities on the immigration provisions for religious workers from abroad (<i>Official Report</i>, cols. <i>WS 162-63</i>). He announced then that we would aim to move to a pre-entry qualification requirement. We have offered to implement this pre-entry qualification requirement early. In order to do this, we need the Christian Churches to establish how they will assess whether each applicant is suitably qualified, and we will be working further with them on this. This offer equally applies to other faith groups who develop their own pre-entry qualification requirements to replace the current ordination requirement.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.23.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_wqn0">
	Water Supply
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.23.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100098" speakername="Baroness Byford" colon="" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.23.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.23.1/2" qnum="HL6135">Whether they have studied the feasibility of extending storm drains in areas of chronic water shortage directly to reservoirs instead of water courses.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.23.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.23.2/1">Water companies are responsible for considering new infrastructure developments needed to fulfil their duties to maintain adequate supplies of water. Any such proposals would require proper options appraisal, and would need to demonstrate their cost-effectiveness and practicability against other resource options.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.23.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_wqn1">
	Waterways Ireland
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.23.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.23.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.23.4/2" qnum="HL5711">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Rooker on 1 March (<i>WA 84</i>) regarding a salary increase for the chief executive of Waterways Ireland, what measures were used to assess the body's performance; what corporate governance requirements have been complied with; what was involved in the chief executive's formal reporting to the sponsor departments; and whether there are any plans to make further pay awards to the chief executive officer.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.23.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.23.5/1">The measures used to assess the body's performance were: its achievements in meeting plans and objectives, as set out in its 2003 and 2004 corporate and business plans; compliance with corporate governance requirements, as outlined in its agreed financial memorandum; and the implementation of audit recommendations. The chief executive outlined to the sponsor departments the body's achievements against these measures through his formal reports to the monitoring committee. Further pay awards will be considered in line with a decision made by the North/South Ministerial Council on <phrase class="date" code="2005-03-08">8 March 2005</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.23.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_wqn2">
	Waterways Ireland
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.23.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.23.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.23.7/2" qnum="HL5712">In each of the past five years, whether Waterways Ireland has used the services of Deloitte &amp; Touche and of PSM consultants; and, if so, when; for what; at what cost; and whether all amounts have been paid.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.24.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_spnew1">
	<p pid="c.24.0/1">I refer the Noble Lord to the Answer given on <phrase class="date" code="2006-03-22">22 March 2006</phrase> (<i>WA 71</i>). PSM was also paid &euro;1,000 in 2005 to provide training on public stress elimination to a number of staff at Waterways Ireland.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.24.1" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_wqn3">
	Waterways Ireland
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.24.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.24.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.24.2/2" qnum="HL5744">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Rooker on 22 March (<i>WA 70</i>) regarding the bulk purchase of chocolates by Waterways Ireland, why quotations were sought on 3 December 2002 when there was no approval at that stage.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.24.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_spnew2">
	<p pid="c.24.3/1">I refer the noble Lord to my Answer of <phrase class="date" code="2006-04-26">26 April 2006</phrase> (<i>WA 38</i>). The documents in the Library include details of the approval on <phrase class="date" code="2002-12-03">3 December 2002</phrase> to seek quotations for the supply of chocolates at Waterways Ireland.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.24.4" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_wqn4">
	Waterways Ireland
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.24.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.24.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.24.5/2" qnum="HL5758">What are the proposed budgets for Waterways Ireland for the years 2006 and 2007; whether they have been agreed; what processes have taken place; and what percentage difference they represent over 2005.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.24.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_spnew3">
	<p pid="c.24.6/1">The Waterways Ireland budget for 2006 was approved by the North/South Ministerial Council (NSMC) at &euro;47.84 million (&pound;33.01 million). This is a decrease from its approved 2005 budget of &euro;50.98 million (&pound;34.16 million) and represents a reduction of 6.16 per cent. in euro terms and a reduction of 3.37 per cent. in terms of sterling. The budget for 2007 has not yet been considered or approved.</p>
	<p pid="c.24.6/2">Business plans and budgets are submitted by the body to their sponsor departments and when they are agreed at that level are forwarded to the respective departments of finance north and south. When approved by finance Ministers, they are then passed to the North/South Ministerial Council for formal approval.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.24.7" nospeaker="true" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_wqn5">
	Zimbabwe
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.24.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_wqn5">
	<p pid="c.24.8/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.24.8/2" qnum="HL6165">What discussions they will hold with other members of the United Nations Security Council concerning the current situation in Zimbabwe.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-06-13c.24.9" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060613/text/60613w05.htm#60613w05_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.24.9/1">We confer frequently with Security Council partners, and with the UN Secretary-General, about the appalling situation in Zimbabwe. We welcome the Secretary-General's intention to convey international concerns in a planned visit to Zimbabwe later this year, and look forward to discussing the outcome of that visit with our council partners when he returns.</p>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

