<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">

<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >

<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >

<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY micro "&#181;" >

<!ENTITY euro "&#8364;" >
<!ENTITY sup2 "&#178;" >
]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.167.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="167"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn0">
	Police Forces: Airwave
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.167.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100416" speakername="Lord Marlesford" colon="" colnum="167"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.167.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.167.1/2" qnum="HL1606">Whether they will name those police forces which are now equipped with a secure digital radio system, indicating in respect of each force the date on which the new equipment was in service.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.167.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="167"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.167.2/1">Airwave, the new secure encrypted digital radio system, is now in operation in two police forces, Lancashire and Greater Manchester police. Service started in Lancashire on <phrase class="date" code="2001-09-21">21 September 2001</phrase> and in Greater Manchester Police on <phrase class="date" code="2001-09-29">29 September 2001</phrase>. A further five forces are due to take the Airwave service by April 2002.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.167.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="167"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn1">
	Asylum Seekers
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.167.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100584" speakername="Baroness Sharples" colon="" colnum="167"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.167.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.167.4/2" qnum="HL1666">What steps are required by asylum seekers to gain asylum status in the United Kingdom; what steps they take to verify entitlement; and what documents are issued at each phase.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.167.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="167"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.167.5/1">In order to qualify for asylum under the terms of the 1951 United Nations Convention relating to the Status of Refugees, an applicant must show that he has a well-founded fear of persecution for reasons of race, religion, nationality, membership of a particular social group or political opinion. Having made an application for asylum an asylum seeker must: attend a screening interview to establish identity and to enable us to determine whether their claim should be considered by the United Kingdom or a third country; where appropriate, complete a statement of evidence form (SEF) and return it within 10 working days; and attend an interview to substantiate the claim.</p>
	<p pid="a.167.5/2">Each asylum claim is considered on its individual merits when all the evidence that the applicant has provided is taken into account, together with detailed country information from a variety of sources.</p>
	<p pid="a.167.5/3">An asylum seeker will be issued with various documents at the different stages of the process: a standard acknowledgement letter (SAL) once the screening process has been satisfactorily completed; a SEF and notes in a language that the applicant understands, and (in most cases) a Section 75 notice which asks for any other reasons the applicant may have for staying in the United Kingdom, where appropriate; an invitation to interview letter; a letter conveying the decision. If asylum is granted, further papers explaining the benefits attached to the new status are sent; if the application is refused, the decision letter will be accompanied by appeal papers and notes on how to appeal.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.168.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="168"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn2">
	Community Grants Programme
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.168.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100074" speakername="Viscount Bridgeman" colon="" colnum="168"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.168.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.168.1/2" qnum="HL1673">When the Home Office will announce the programme and timetable for the active community grants programme 2002&ndash;03 mentioned on its website as due to be announced in September.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.168.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="168"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.168.2/1">I am pleased to say that the time limited development grant was announced on <phrase class="date" code="2001-12-05">5 December 2001</phrase>. Full details and application form can be seen on the Home Office website, <a href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/acu/acu.htm">www.homeoffice.gov.uk/acu/acu.htm</a>.</p>
	<p pid="a.168.2/2">Four-and-a-half million pounds will be available for each of the next three years (&pound;1.5 million per year) and it is anticipated that around 90 projects will be funded. The grant will aid voluntary and community groups that work within deprived communities.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.168.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="168"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn3">
	European Arrest Warrant
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.168.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100491" speakername="Lord Pearson of Rannoch" colon="" colnum="168"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.168.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.168.4/2" qnum="HL1782">Further to the Written Answer by Lord Rooker on 28 November (WA 35), whether at the Justice and Home Affairs Council on 6 to 7 December in Brussels they will attempt to include Xpublic denial or trivialisation of crimes committed by communist regimes&quot; as an offence under Article 2 of the Framework Decision on the proposed European Union Arrest Warrant; and, if not, why not.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.168.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="168"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.168.5/1">No. The list of offences at Draft Article 2 of the framework decision are in the main Xharmonised&quot; offences. There are no common EU definitions, but all member states have criminal offences under the generic headings.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.168.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="168"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn4">
	European Arrest Warrant
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.168.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100491" speakername="Lord Pearson of Rannoch" colon="" colnum="168"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.168.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.168.7/2" qnum="HL1783">Further to the Written Answer by Lord Rooker on 28 November (WA 35), how they define the crimes of (a) Xswindling&quot; and (b) Xforgery of administrative documents and trafficking therein&quot;, as identified in Article 2 of the Framework Decision on the proposed European Union arrest warrant.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.168.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="168"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.168.8/1">Offences will be defined by the issuing member state. Depending on the circumstances, if issued by a judicial authority in the United Kingdom, Xswindling&quot; would include any offence under the Theft Acts 1968 and 1978, and Xforgery of administrative documents and trafficking therein&quot; would include any offence under the Forgery and Counterfeiting Act 1981.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.169.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="169"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn5">
	European Arrest Warrant
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.169.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100491" speakername="Lord Pearson of Rannoch" colon="" colnum="169"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.169.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.169.1/2" qnum="HL1784">Whether, under the proposed European Union arrest warrant, the British plane spotters detained in Greece would be extradited for interrogation and trial in that country had they returned to the United Kingdom prior to arrest.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.169.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="169"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.169.2/1">The Government cannot speculate on the possible outcome of an extradition request that has not been made. The draft framework decision has not been brought into force.</p>
	<p pid="a.169.2/2">If a European arrest warrant had been issued by a judicial authority in a European Union member state for the offence of espionage, that would have fallen within the scope of the draft framework decision. This is also an offence carrying a sentence of more than 12 months in United Kingdom law. Although the draft framework decision proposes removing the dual criminality test from a number of serious offences and making it optional for other offences, the retention of the dual criminality test would not be a barrier to extradition for espionage. The draft framework decision does not provide for any person subject to its provisions to be interrogated. It follows the standard provisions of extradition instruments, which provide for the handing over of persons either suspected or convicted of extraditable offences solely for the purposes of trial and/or imprisonment. Requests for the taking of evidence are dealt with under separate instruments.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.169.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="169"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn6">
	Asylum Seekers: Return to Country of Origin
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.169.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100414" speakername="The Countess of Mar" colon="" colnum="169"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.169.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.169.4/2" qnum="HL1827">Whether there are any countries to which it is not currently their policy to return asylum seekers; and if so, which.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.169.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="169"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.169.5/1">A decision on whether or not a person is returned will depend on the facts of the particular case and the conditions pertaining at that time in the country concerned.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.169.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="169"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn7">
	Human Rights Convention
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.169.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="169"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.169.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.169.7/2" qnum="HL1416">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Privy Seal on 12 November (WA 53) concerning their international obligations, whether they incorporated the European Convention on Human Rights directly into the law of Northern Ireland; and whether they are prepared to incorporate it into the law of Scotland, Wales and England.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.169.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100325" speakername="Lord Irvine of Lairg" colon=":" colnum="169"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.169.8/1">The Human Rights Act 1998 applies throughout the United Kingdom. Although the Act does not, as such, incorporate the European Convention on Human Rights, it gives further effect to the rights and freedoms guaranteed under the convention and allows people within the United Kingdom to rely upon the convention rights in proceedings.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.170.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="170"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn8">
	Foot and Mouth Epidemic: Use of Service Personnel
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.170.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100414" speakername="The Countess of Mar" colon="" colnum="170"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.170.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.170.1/2" qnum="HL1654">How many Army units were employed in the slaughter of animals during the foot and mouth epidemic in the summer and autumn months of 2001; and</p>
	<p pid="a.170.1/3" qnum="HL1655">Which regiments supplied the Army units employed in the slaughter of animals during the foot and mouth epidemic in the summer and autumn months of 2001; and</p>
	<p pid="a.170.1/4" qnum="HL1656">How many (a) officers, (b) non-commissioned officers and (c) soldiers were employed in the slaughter of animals during the foot and mouth epidemic in the summer and autumn months of 2001; and</p>
	<p pid="a.170.1/5" qnum="HL1657">In which geographical areas Army units were employed in the slaughter of animals during the foot and mouth epidemic in the summer and autumn months of 2001; and</p>
	<p pid="a.170.1/6" qnum="HL1658">Whether any of the Army units employed in the slaughter of animals during the foot and mouth epidemic in the summer and autumn months of 2001 have been posted on duty abroad.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.170.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="170"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w01.htm#11210w01_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.170.2/1">No formed Army units or individual personnel were employed as slaughtermen during the foot and mouth epidemic in the summer and autumn months. Indeed, no formed Army units were employed in the slaughter of animals at any time during the epidemic.</p>
	<p pid="a.170.2/2">At the height of the crisis, over 2,000 personnel drawn from all three services deployed in support of Maff/Defra. Of these, a total of 109 were employed as slaughtermen between <phrase class="date" code="2006-03-27">27 March</phrase> and <phrase class="date" code="">4 May</phrase>. All those who worked as slaughtermen were volunteers and they were drawn from the following units and agencies.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.170.2/5"> <td>Regiments:</td> <td>The Household Cavalry Regiment</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.170.2/6"> <td></td> <td>16 Regiment Royal Artillery</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.170.2/7"> <td></td> <td>39 Regiment Royal Artillery</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.170.2/8"> <td></td> <td>1st Battalion the Kings Regiment</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.170.2/9"> <td></td> <td>3 Close Support Regiment RLC</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.170.2/10"> <td></td> <td>4 General Supply Regiment RLC</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.170.2/11"> <td></td> <td>9 Supply Regiment RLC</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.170.2/12"> <td></td> <td>13 Air Assualt Regiment RLC</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.170.2/13"> <td></td> <td>23 Pioneer Regiment RLC</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.170.2/14"> <td></td> <td>ACE Mobile Force (Land) Combat Services  Support Battalion</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.170.2/15"> <td></td> <td>Commando Logistic Regiment</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.170.2/16"> <td></td> <td>Army School of Catering</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.170.2/17"> <td></td> <td>Headquarters RLC TA</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.170.2/18"> <td></td> <td>Scottish Logistic Supply Regiment</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.170.2/19"> <td>Agencies:</td> <td>Defence Postal and Courier Service Agency</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.170.2/20"> <td></td> <td>Defence Munitions Agency Kineton</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.170.2/23">Of these personnel, one was an officer, 47 were non-commissioned officers and 61 were soldiers. They were deployed in Cumbria, Northumberland, Dumfries and Galloway and the Scottish Borders.</p>
	<p pid="a.170.2/24">Four of the regiments that provided personnel who were employed as slaughtermen have been deployed abroad. The Household Cavalry Regiment and 13 Air Assault Regiment RLC deployed on operations and 16 Regiment Royal Artillery and 39 Regiment Royal Artillery deployed on exercise. The bio-security procedures agreed between the Ministry of Defence and Maff/Defra were followed by all the service personnel who were deployed during the crisis.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.171.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="171"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn0">
	Business Tourism
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.171.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100016" speakername="Baroness Anelay of St Johns" colon="" colnum="171"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.171.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.171.1/2" qnum="HL1454">What support is given by Ministers, ambassadors, trade consuls and commercial attaches to the bidding process carried out by the business tourism sector for international events.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.171.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="171"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.171.2/1">Her Majesty's Government attach importance to the promotion of the UK business tourism sector and overseas diplomatic posts have been asked to be alert to potential opportunities to bring international trade fairs and conferences to the UK through the Trade Partners UK network.</p>
	<p pid="a.171.2/2">We also support the UK bids to attract international events to the UK through inward missions sponsored by Trade Partners UK, which provides an opportunity to bring overseas buyers, journalists and other opinion formers to major UK events and venues.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.171.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="171"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn1">
	Green Claims
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.171.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100427" speakername="Baroness Miller of Chilthorne Domer" colon="" colnum="171"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.171.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.171.4/2" qnum="HL1573">When were the guidelines for non-advertising green claims last revised.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.171.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="171"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.171.5/1">Green claims made by advertising are already subject to self-regulatory regimes operated by the Advertising Standards Authority (ASA), the Independent Television Commission (ITC) and the Radio Authority (RA). These bodies have all issued guidance on the treatment of environmental claims in advertising. This guidance has been brought together in a booklet, Environmental Claims in Advertising: A single guide to all applicable advertising codes.</p>
	<p pid="a.171.5/2">The guidelines were published in 1994 and have not been revised.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.171.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="171"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn2">
	Trade Barriers
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.171.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100279" speakername="Lord Harrison" colon="" colnum="171"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.171.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.171.7/2" qnum="HL1649">Whether they support the World Bank's call to the European Union to extend its decision to remove barriers to imports of most products from the current 48 poorest countries of the world to the further 70 low-income countries, including India, Pakistan and Indonesia, possibly routed through the Everything But Arms (EBA) initiative.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.172.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="172"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.172.0/1">Like the World Bank, the UK, working as part of the EU, strongly supports the increased liberalisation of trade, which we believe will be broadly beneficial to all developing countries. Hence our welcome for the recent WTO Ministerial Declaration at Doha, launching a development-focused trade round, which should remove barriers to developing country exports and so offer the best route for the developing world to escape from poverty. We particularly welcome the commitment on the part of all WTO members to the objective of duty-free, quota-free market access for products originating from Least Developed Countries (LDCs), which encourages other WTO members to match the EU's EBA initiative. This already allows tariff-free imports for everything but arms, bananas, rice and sugar from LDCs.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.172.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="172"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn3">
	DTI: Value for Money Review
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.172.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100489" speakername="Lord Patten" colon="" colnum="172"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.172.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.172.2/2" qnum="HL1674">Whether they will ask the National Audit Office to conduct a review of value for money of the recently announced reorganisation of the Department of Trade and Industry after its first full year of working.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.172.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="172"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.172.3/1">The programme of value for money studies is decided by the Comptroller and Auditor General in consultation with the Public Accounts Committee. The department is discussing with the National Audit Office how the department's revised aims and objectives might be evaluated in future vfm studies.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.172.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="172"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn4">
	Fixed-term Employment Directive
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.172.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100552" speakername="Lord Rotherwick" colon="" colnum="172"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.172.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.172.5/2" qnum="HL1762">When they plan to bring forward legislation to implement the European Community directive on fixed-term employment.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.172.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="172"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.172.6/1">The Government plan to implement the directive through regulations to be made under a power to be taken in the Employment Bill. It is expected that draft regulations will be published in the new year, for consultation prior to implementation by the date of <phrase class="date" code="2002-07-10">10 July 2002</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.172.7" nospeaker="true" colnum="172"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn5">
	Rosyth Europort: Transport
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.172.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100415" speakername="The Earl of Mar and Kellie" colon="" colnum="172"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.172.8/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.172.8/2" qnum="HL1520">Whether they are satisfied with the proposed arrangements for transport to and from the proposed Rosyth Europort; and</p>
	<p pid="a.172.8/3" qnum="HL1521">Whether they believe that the proposed Rosyth Europort will be making the best possible use of rail transport.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.173.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="173"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.173.0/1">The Government have made clear that they wish to see more freight carried by rail and will support in principle proposals that will help achieve that. Approval of current proposals for developing rail links between Stirling and Kincardine, and any proposed rail link to the Rosyth Europort, are primarily a matter for the Scottish Executive. The Strategic Rail Authority is working closely with the Scottish Executive to help deliver the best possible solution for rail freight in the region in accordance with the authority's strategic agenda and the Government's long-term vision for the railways.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.173.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="173"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn6">
	Graffiti Damage
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.173.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100068" speakername="Lord Bradshaw" colon="" colnum="173"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.173.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.173.2/2" qnum="HL1764">How many cases of scratching windows of trains were detected by the British Transport Police in the last 12 months for which figures are available; and how these cases were disposed of by the police or by the courts.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.173.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="173"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.173.3/1">The British Transport Police (BTP) does not separately identify window etching within its records on graffiti. As stated in my previous Answer on <phrase class="date" code="">20 November</phrase> (Official Report, WA 131) 200 cases involving graffitti were detected by the BTP in the year 2000. The BTP does not hold central records on the final outcome of each case and such figures could only be provided at disproportionate cost.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.173.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="173"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn7">
	Horticulture Research International
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.173.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100291" speakername="Baroness Hilton of Eggardon" colon="" colnum="173"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.173.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.173.5/2" qnum="HL1958">Whether there are plans to conduct a quinquennial review of Horticulture Research International.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.173.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="173"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_spmin3">
	<p pid="a.173.6/1">A quinquennial review of Horticulture Research International has been announced today. The terms of reference are as follows: to conduct an evaluation of the performance of Horticulture Research International since the last review in 1996; and to consider in the light of this evaluation and the views of customers and other stakeholders whether executive NDPB status remains the most cost effective way of achieving its own and departmental aims, as well as government-wide aims such as those relating to science policy, sustainable development and Modernising Government. As part of the review, to consider the sponsorship arrangements between HRI and Defra, including funding.</p>
	<p pid="a.173.6/2">In reaching a view about HRI's status, to consider whether the current arrangements are responsive to the needs of the UK horticulture industry and HRI's other stakeholders; financially sustainable; and operationally flexible so as to be able to adjust easily and quickly to changes in technology, industry requirements, consumer demands and funding opportunities.</p>
	<p pid="a.173.6/3">If the review concludes that HRI should continue to function as an NDPB, then it will consider what changes, if any, are required to its management statement in the light of the findings of the review. If, however, the review concludes that a different delivery system would provide high quality, more effective and better value for money services, then it will set out the rationale and recommend appropriate costed options to Ministers.</p>
	<p pid="a.173.6/4">The review will be conducted by a review team attached to Defra's Science Directorate, working in consultation with the Cabinet Office, Treasury and the Office of Science and Technology.</p>
	<p pid="a.173.6/5">Interested parties are invited to submit their views to the review team by <phrase class="date" code="2002-03-22">22 March 2002</phrase>. Details of how to contact them are contained in Defra's news release issued today.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.174.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="174"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn8">
	Nursing Staff
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.174.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100394" speakername="Lord McColl of Dulwich" colon="" colnum="174"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.174.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.174.1/2" qnum="HL1689">How many nursing staff have left their place of employment and thereby forfeited their terminal gratuity in the last two years.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.174.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="174"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w02.htm#11210w02_spmin4">
	<p pid="a.174.2/1">Data in the form requested are not readily available. The number of all qualified and unqualified nursing staff in England and Wales who left National Health Service employment in each of the last two financial years without immediate entitlement to a pension award is set out in the table.</p>
	<p pid="a.174.2/2">Where members leave the pension scheme early, their accrued benefits, including the pension lump sum, can be preserved for payment at age 60. They do not therefore forfeit their terminal gratuity.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.174.2/5"> <td>Financial year</td> <td>Nursing staff</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.174.2/6"> <td>April 1999 to March 2000</td> <td>9,879</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.174.2/7"> <td>April 2000 to March 2001</td> <td>11,232</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.174.2/10">Notes</p>
	<p pid="a.174.2/11">1. With a million active members, pension scheme records are continually, and retrospectively, being updated to reflect further membership activity and revised data. This data extract represents a Xsnapshot&quot; in time.</p>
	<p pid="a.174.2/12">2. The figures may include, therefore, nurses who left the pension scheme but not their employment or nurses who have left one NHS employer and are in the process of joining another in further NHS employment.</p>
	<p pid="a.174.2/13">3. XNursing staff&quot; includes qualified nurses, unqualifed nurses, nursing assistants, nursing auxiliaries, midwives, health visitors, nurse managers, nurse tutors and physiotherapists.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.175.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="175"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn0">
	Health Professions Order
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.175.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100444" speakername="Lord Morris of Manchester" colon="" colnum="175"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.175.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.175.1/2" qnum="HL1778">Further to the statement by the Minister of State, Department of Health, in the House of Commons Fourth Standing Committee on Delegated Legislation on 26 November on the draft Health Professions Order, what proposals they have to ensure that all 12 allied health professions in the four United Kingdom countries will be effectively represented through professional advisory committees.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.175.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="175"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.175.2/1">It will be for the new Health Professions Council to decide on membership of the professional advisory committees. The legislation provides for professional majorities and access to the council and its statutory committees.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.175.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="175"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn1">
	Health Professions Order
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.175.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100444" speakername="Lord Morris of Manchester" colon="" colnum="175"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.175.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.175.4/2" qnum="HL1796">Further to the statement by the Minister of State for Health in Standing Committee in the House of Commons on the draft Health Professions Order on 26 November (col. 30), whether they are proposing that the professional advisory committees should hold regular meetings and be given adequate powers to perform their role.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.175.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="175"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.175.5/1">The Health Professions Order 2001 provides for the Health Professions Council to set up professional advisory committees (PACs) with a majority of professional members to advise the council or its statutory committees on matters affecting any relevant profession. The order also permits the council to delegate functions to the PACs other than rule-making. How the PACs actually function will be a matter for the new council.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.175.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="175"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn2">
	Health Professions Order
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.175.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100444" speakername="Lord Morris of Manchester" colon="" colnum="175"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.175.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.175.7/2" qnum="HL1797">Whether non-state registered chiropodists will be involved in the election of representatives on the new health professions committee only if they become registered.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.175.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="175"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.175.8/1">It will be a matter for the new Health Professions Council to determine the election scheme by which professional members are elected to the new council. Only registrants will be able to take part in the election.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.175.9" nospeaker="true" colnum="175"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn3">
	Chiropodists
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.175.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100444" speakername="Lord Morris of Manchester" colon="" colnum="175"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.175.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.175.10/2" qnum="HL1798">Whether they will provide indepedently audited evidence of the number of chiropodists in the non-state registered sector.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.176.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="176"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.176.0/1">The Government do not keep records of the number of chiropodists in the non-state registered sector.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.176.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="176"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn4">
	Physical Activity
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.176.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100016" speakername="Baroness Anelay of St Johns" colon="" colnum="176"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.176.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.176.2/2" qnum="HL1675">In which fora the Department for Culture, Media and Sport works jointly with the Department for Education and Skills and the Department of Health on policy issues regarding the promotion of physical activity.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.176.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="176"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.176.3/1">The Department for Culture, Media and Sport works jointly with the Department for Education and Skills and the Department of Health in the following fora: monthly cross-governmental ministerial meetings which are chaired by my right honourable friend the Minister for Sport; the School Sport Alliance; the Older People and Physical Activity Working Group; the Cabinet Committee on Older People; and the Qualification and Curriculum Authority group steering the review of PE and school sport. We are also working closely with the other departments on the joint spending review on children at risk and reducing health inequalities.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.176.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="176"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn5">
	Apsley House
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.176.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100016" speakername="Baroness Anelay of St Johns" colon="" colnum="176"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.176.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.176.5/2" qnum="HL1717">Whether they have reached an agreement with regard to the transfer of Apsley House to a charitable trust; and, if so, whether such an agreement will require parliamentary approval.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.176.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="176"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.176.6/1">My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for Culture, Media and Sport has decided to introduce new arrangements for the future management of both the fabric of Apsley House, the last historic building for which DCMS retains responsibility, and the Wellington Museum, currently run by the V&amp;A. A contracting out order to be laid before Parliament will, if approved by both Houses, allow certain of the Secretary of State's functions under the Wellington Museum Act 1947 to be contracted out. The functions to be contracted out are intended to relate to the maintenance of the fabric of Apsley House and the running of the Wellington Museum. It is expected that expressions of interest in taking on the contract will be sought through an advertisement and that tenders will then be invited.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.177.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn6">
	Republic of Ireland President: Police Escort
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.177.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.177.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.177.1/2" qnum="HL1456">Whether on a recent visit to the Belfast area by the President of the Republic of Ireland, Mary McAleese, her police escort were required to remove their remembrance poppies; and, if so, by whom and why.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.177.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.177.2/1">The officers of the police escort who accompanied the President of the Republic of Ireland on a recent visit to the Belfast area were not required to remove their poppies. However, following a discussion between the officers it was agreed that poppies would not be openly displayed during an evening function.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.177.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn7">
	Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.177.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.177.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.177.4/2" qnum="HL1529">Whether, in view of the letter from the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland of 24 March 1999 asking for advice on a Bill of Human Rights for Northern Ireland and indicating that there was no time limit, they consider the consultation period of less than three months set by the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission to be adequate; and, if so, why.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.177.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.177.5/1">I refer the noble Lord to the answer I gave on <phrase class="date" code="">Tuesday 27 November</phrase> (Official Report, col. WA21).</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.177.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn8">
	Northern Ireland Police Service
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.177.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.177.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.177.7/2" qnum="1554">Whether candidates for recruitment to the Police Service of Northern Ireland who because of their religious background are requested to resit the tests more than once will have all of their expenses paid, including loss of other earnings. [H</p>
	 <p pid="a.177.7/3" class="error">Question number missing in Hansard, possibly truncated question.</p> 
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.177.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.177.8/1">Each police recruitment, competition is discrete. Candidates who were not successful in the first competition, for whatever reason, will not have their expenses paid should they decide to re-apply.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.177.9" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn9">
	Northern Ireland Police Service
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.177.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100345" speakername="Lord Kilclooney" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn9">
	<p pid="a.177.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.177.10/2" qnum="0">(a) what was the cost of the designs of the alternative proposals for badges for members of the Police Service of Northern Ireland; and</p>
	<p pid="a.177.10/3" qnum="HL1558">(b) whether consideration will be given to further proposals for the design of police badges for the Police Service of Northern Ireland.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.177.11" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.177.11/1">The aggregate costs for the sample emblem designs were &pound;41,329.45 inclusive of VAT. This figure includes research, presentation materials and colour photocopying.</p>
	<p pid="a.177.11/2">As the Minister of State, Jane Kennedy, said when she wrote to the statutory consultees on the emblems: Xthe Government has provided possible designs for the emblem or badge. These by no means cover all the possibilities. They are intended to assist the board in their consideration of this important matter. The board may well have ideas of their own&quot;.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.178.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="178"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn10">
	Northern Ireland Police Service
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.178.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="178"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn10">
	<p pid="a.178.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.178.1/2" qnum="HL1595">How many applications they have had from serving officers in other police forces to join the Police Service of Northern Ireland; and whether he will list the forces and the numbers concerned.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.178.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="178"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_spnew8">
	<p pid="a.178.2/1">Applicants to the Police Service of Northern Ireland are not required to state their current occupation; this information is sought only from candidates who progress to a certain stage in the recruitment competition. It is not, therefore, possible to determine how many applicants were from other forces.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.178.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="178"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn11">
	Senior Salaries Review Body
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.178.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100072" speakername="Lord Brett" colon="" colnum="178"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_wqn11">
	<p pid="a.178.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.178.4/2" qnum="HL1959">If they will set out the revised terms of reference of the Senior Salaries Review Body.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-10a.178.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="178"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011210/text/11210w03.htm#11210w03_spnew9">
	<p pid="a.178.5/1">The terms of reference of the Senior Salaries Review Body have been revised as follows to allow the Scottish Parliament, the Northern Ireland Assembly, the National Assembly for Wales and the Greater London Authority to ask for advice on the pay, pensions and allowances of their members and office holders.</p>
	<p pid="a.178.5/2">The Review Body on Senior Salaries provides independent advice to the Prime Minister, the Lord Chancellor and the Secretary of State for Defence on the remuneration of holders of judicial office; senior civil servants; senior officers of the armed forces; and other such public appointments as may from time to time be specified.</p>
	<p pid="a.178.5/3">The Review Body also advises the Prime Minister from time to time on the pay and pensions of Members of Parliament and their allowances; on Peer's allowances; and on the pay, pensions and allowances of Ministers and others whose pay is determined by the Ministerial and Other Salaries Act 1975. If asked to do so by the Presiding Officer and the First Minister of the Scottish Parliament jointly; or by the Speaker of the Northern Ireland Assembly; or by the Presiding Officer of the National Assembly for Wales; or by the Mayor of London and Chair of the Greater London Assembly jointly; the Review Body also from time to time advises those bodies on the pay, pensions and allowances of their members and office holders.</p>
	<p pid="a.178.5/4">In reaching its recommendations, the Review Body is to have regard to the following considerations:</p>
	<p pid="a.178.5/5" class="indent">the need to recruit, retain and motivate suitably able and qualified people to exercise their different responsibilities;</p>
	<p pid="a.178.5/6" class="indent">Government policies for improving the public services including the requirement on departments to meet the output targets for the delivery of departmental services;</p>
	<p pid="a.178.5/7" class="indent">the funds available to departments as set out in the Government's departmental expenditure limits;</p>
	<p pid="a.178.5/8" class="indent">the Government's inflation target.</p>
	<p pid="a.178.5/9">In making recommendations, the Review Body shall consider any factors that the Government and other witnesses may draw to its attention. In particular it shall have regard to:</p>
	<p pid="a.178.5/10" class="indent">differences in terms and conditions of employment between the public and private sectors and between the remit groups, taking account of relative job security and the value of benefits in kind;</p>
	<p pid="a.178.5/11" class="indent">changes in national pay systems, including flexibility and the reward of success; and job weight in differentiating the remuneration of particular posts; and</p>
	<p pid="a.178.5/12" class="indent">the need to maintain broad linkage between the remuneration of the three main remit groups, while allowing sufficient flexibility to take account of the circumstances of each group.</p>
	<p pid="a.178.5/13">The Review Body may make other recommendations as it sees fit:</p>
	<p pid="a.178.5/14" class="indent">to ensure that, as appropriate, the remuneration of the remit groups relates coherently to that of their subordinates, encourages efficiency and effectiveness, and takes account of the different management and organisational structures that may be in place from time to time;</p>
	<p pid="a.178.5/15" class="indent">to relate reward to performance where appropriate;</p>
	<p pid="a.178.5/16" class="indent">to maintain the confidence of those covered by the Review Body's remit that its recommendations have been properly and fairly determined; and</p>
	<p pid="a.178.5/17" class="indent">to ensure that the remuneration of those covered by the remit is consistent with the Government's equal opportunities policy.</p>
	<p pid="a.178.5/18">The Review Body will take account of the evidence it receives about wider economic considerations and the affordability of its recommendations.</p>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

