<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">

<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >

<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >

<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY micro "&#181;" >

<!ENTITY euro "&#8364;" >
]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.31.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn0">
	Intelligence and Security Committee: Interim Report
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.31.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100490" speakername="Lord Paul" colon="" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.31.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.31.1/2" qnum="HL1476">When the Intelligence and Security Committee's Interim Report will be laid before Parliament.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.31.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100331" speakername="Baroness Jay of Paddington" colon=":" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.31.2/1">The Intelligence and Security Committee's Report has today been laid before Parliament. Following consultation over matters which could not be published without prejudice to the continued discharge of the functions of the intelligence and security agencies and in accordance with the Intelligence Services Act 1994, the Confidential Annex has been excluded.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.31.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn1">
	Local Authority Employees: Transfer to Private Firms
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.31.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100403" speakername="Lord MacKenzie of Culkein" colon="" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.31.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.31.4/2" qnum="HL1297">Whether the Cabinet Office Statement of Practice for Staff Transfers where council employees transfer to private firms or consortia applies throughout the United Kingdom.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.31.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.31.5/1">The Statement of Practice sets out a framework to be followed by the public sector organisations to implement the Government's policy on the treatment of staff transfers where the public sector is the employer when contracting out, or the client in a subsequent retendering. It applies directly to all United Kingdom central government departments and agencies and to the NHS but the Government expect other public sector organisations, including local government, to follow it.</p>
	<p pid="a.31.5/2">The Statement noted that local government was subject to some different considerations, particularly the restrictions in legislation contained in Part I and II of the Local Government Act 1988. However, abolition of CCT from January 2000 and the Local Government, Best Value (Exclusion of Non-commercial Considerations) Order 2001, which came into effect on <phrase class="date" code="2001-03-13">13 March 2001</phrase>, means that best value authorities in England may now consider &quot;workforce matters&quot; and hence adopt the policy set out in the Statement. In doing so, they must have regard to the need to comply with their best value duties.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.31.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn2">
	Local Authority Employees: Transfer to Private Firms
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.31.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100403" speakername="Lord MacKenzie of Culkein" colon="" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.31.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.31.7/2" qnum="0">In relation to the transfer of council employees to private firms or consortia, whether a money purchase pension scheme is broadly comparable to a defined benefit or final salary pension scheme.[HL1298[</p>
	 <p pid="a.31.7/3" class="error">Question number missing in Hansard, possibly truncated question.</p> 
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.32.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.32.0/1">Guidance issued by the Government Actuary in May 1999 indicated that, when it undertakes assessments of broad comparability, only defined benefit schemes will be certified as broadly comparable to defined benefit schemes, and only defined contribution schemes will be certified as broadly comparable to defined contribution schemes. I understand that the same principles normally apply in other actuarial assessment arrangements.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.32.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn3">
	&quot;El Nino&quot; Forecast
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.32.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100341" speakername="Lord Judd" colon="" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.32.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.32.2/2" qnum="HL1315">What is their evaluation of the climate, economic, social and agricultural implications of the reported forecast by NASA of a &quot;sub El Nino&quot; occurrence in 2002; what contingency plans they are themselves preparing and what contingency plans they are advocating in the European Union and the United Nations.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.32.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.32.3/1">The occurrence of a weak &quot;El Nino&quot; in 2002 would have little, if any, effect in the UK or the rest of Europe. Recent strong El Ninos, such as that in 1997-98, had little impact in Europe. There is therefore no need for the Government or the European Union to consider contingency plans, beyond existing plans, which in some cases are already being developed because of recent adverse experiences, such as floods.</p>
	<p pid="a.32.3/2">In those countries likely to be affected by El Nino, there is now a generally high awareness of its likely impacts and they keep a close watch on its behaviour. Regional Climate Outlook Forums, convened under the auspices of the World Meteorological Organisation, take into account current El Nino predictions and other forecast information (including the Met Office's seasonal predictions) and involve regional end-users who can act on the forecasts and likely impacts.</p>
	<p pid="a.32.3/3">El Nino forecasts have low reliability much beyond a few months.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.32.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn4">
	A.303, Wincanton: Noise Reduction
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.32.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100489" speakername="Lord Patten" colon="" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.32.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.32.5/2" qnum="HL1388">What action the Highways Agency is taking to reduce noise levels on the A.303 trunk road in the Wincanton, Somerset area.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.32.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.32.6/1">In Transport 2010--The 10 Year Plan, published in July 2000, the Government set the Highways Agency a target to install quieter surfaces on over 60 per cent of the network over the next 10 years. When the A.303 Wincanton Bypass is next due for resurfacing, low noise materials will be used, as long as it is technically possible to do so.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.33.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn5">
	Road Traffic Noise
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.33.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100489" speakername="Lord Patten" colon="" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.33.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.33.1/2" qnum="HL1389">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Whitty on 21 March (WA 159), when will the survey of the effectiveness of noise reduction measures be completed; and whether it will be published.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.33.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.33.2/1">Surveys of the effectiveness of noise reduction measures are planned to cover projects completed in the next two years and interviews will be completed in the year following. A report analysing the responses and drawing conclusions is expected within 12 months of the final round of interviews. A copy of the report, when available, will be placed in the Library of the House.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.33.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn6">
	A.21 Lamberhurst Bypass
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.33.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100274" speakername="Lord Hardy of Wath" colon="" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.33.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.33.4/2" qnum="HL1446">Whether they have decided to agree to the National Trust's proposals for a bridge across the A.21 Lamberhurst Bypass at Scotney.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.33.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.33.5/1">We are pleased to say that, following discussion with the Trust over the last few months, we have asked the Highways Agency to develop proposals to maintain the existing access to Scotney Castle and remove the severance caused by the bypass. Further development work will now be undertaken leading to the publication of those proposals in the Summer.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.33.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn7">
	Trunk Road Improvement Programme
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.33.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100250" speakername="Baroness Gould of Potternewton" colon="" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.33.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.33.7/2" qnum="HL1448">What plans they have to add to the targeted programme of trunk road improvements.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.33.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.33.8/1">The regional planning bodies brought forward proposals for 30 schemes which could be separately progressed from the Multi Modal Studies (which are currently looking at solutions to problems within main trunk road corridors). These schemes have been assessed using the New Approach to Appraisal (NATA) and we have arranged for copies of the appraisal summary tables to be placed in the Library. We have also sought the views of the Government's statutory advisers (English Nature, the Countryside Agency, English Heritage and the Environment Agency) on the proposed schemes. Having considered the NATA appraisals and comments from the statutory advisers we have decided to add the following schemes to the targeted programme of improvements:</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/2" class="indent">M.62 Junction 6 Improvement</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/3" class="indent">A.1 Peterborough--Blyth Grade Separated Junctions</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/4" class="indent">A.14 Haughley New St--Stowmarket Improvement</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/5" class="indent">A.38 Dobwalls Bypass</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/6" class="indent">A.46 Newark--Widmerpool Improvement</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/7" class="indent">A.595 Parton--Lillyhall Improvement</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/8">These schemes will now be taken forward by the Highways Agency in consultation with the statutory advisory bodies to ensure that any concerns which they might have are properly addressed in developing detailed designs for the schemes. Every effort will be made to minimise impacts on sensitive sites.</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/9">In addition, we are also able to announce today that, after further studies undertaken since the 1998 Roads Review, the following schemes are being added to the targeted programme of improvements:</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/10" class="indent">A.3 Hindhead Improvement</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/11" class="indent">A.30 Bodmin-Indian Queens Improvement</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/12">We believe these eight major schemes will be widely welcomed. They will benefit road users by reducing congestion and improving safety, create safer and healthier environments for local communities by the removal of through traffic and, in some cases, contribute to regeneration initiatives. Close co-operation with the statutory advisory bodies in developing scheme designs will ensure that important sensitive sites are protected.</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/13">The Highways Agency will also take forward the following smaller schemes recommended by the regional planning bodies as part of the recent consultation exercise and costing less than &pound;5 million as part of their programme of local network management schemes.</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/14" class="indent">M.40/A.404 Handy Cross Junction Improvement</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/15" class="indent">A.1(M) Junction 60-62 Improvement</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/16" class="indent">A.66 Long Newton Grade Separated Junction</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/17">We are informing the regional planning bodies about our decisions.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.34.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn8">
	Light Rail Schemes
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.34.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100235" speakername="Baroness Gibson of Market Rasen" colon="" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.34.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.34.1/2" qnum="HL1450">When they will announce their decision about light rail schemes.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.34.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w01.htm#10328w01_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.34.2/1">We are today announcing decisions on three schemes, as set out below.</p>
	<p pid="a.34.2/2">Leeds Supertram</p>
	<p pid="a.34.2/3">Following completion of our appraisal of the proposed Leeds Supertram system of three light rail lines, we are satisfied that the project passes the tests for government funding to be made available and that it should be taken forward as a single scheme. We have also agreed a funding package with the promoters which includes a local contribution towards scheme costs.</p>
	<p pid="a.34.2/4">Orders have been made under the Transport and Works Act giving powers for the scheme. However, these cannot come into force until a special parliamentary procedure has been completed, because the orders authorise the compulsory purchase of open space for which no land is to be given in exchange. Funding approval is given on the assumption that this process is completed satisfactorily.</p>
	<p pid="a.34.2/5">South Hampshire Rapid Transit</p>
	<p pid="a.34.2/6">Following completion of our appraisal of the South Hampshire Rapid Transit project, we are satisfied that the project passes the tests for government funding to be made available. Subject to the scheme receiving Transport and Works Act (TWA) powers and no material change to the scheme as submitted, we intend to provide funding and have agreed a package with the promoters which would include a local contribution towards scheme costs.</p>
	<p pid="a.34.2/7">This decision is given solely in respect of the economic appraisal of the scheme as submitted to us and the associated funding arrangements. It does not in any way indicate any view that we may take on the TWA application that is currently being considered on its own merits, having regard to the Inspector's report of the inquiry.</p>
	<p pid="a.34.2/8">Bristol and South Gloucester Rapid Transit</p>
	<p pid="a.34.2/9">In accordance with the policy set out in my Department's Guidance on Local Transport Plans, Bristol City Council and South Gloucestershire Council sought a provisional view on the economic appraisal for the Bristol and South Gloucester Rapid Transit scheme, prior to seeking the necessary powers under the Transport and Works Act (TWA). We are aware that the authorities are continuing to work on some aspects of the proposed scheme. However, we are satisfied that, on the basis of the available information, were the current proposals and their appraisal to be confirmed by the authorities following that further work they would pass our economic appraisal tests for deciding eligibility for funding.</p>
	<p pid="a.34.2/10">This provisional view is given solely in respect of the economic appraisal, and does not in any way indicate any view that we may take on any subsequent TWA application. Any such application would be determined entirely on its merits in the light of all the relevant considerations, and only after all interested persons had been given a full opportunity to state their views.</p>
	<p pid="a.34.2/11">Should TWA powers be obtained, final approval of the project for funding would depend both on whether an updated economic appraisal, reflecting any changes to the scheme as a result of the TWA process or any other developments, demonstrates that the project still represents good value for money and on conclusion of a satisfactory agreement on funding.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.36.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w02.htm#10328w02_wqn0">
	European Central Bank Communications Under Treaty Article 110
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.36.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100734" speakername="Lord Shore of Stepney" colon="" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w02.htm#10328w02_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.36.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.36.1/2" qnum="HL966">What regulations, decisions, recommendations and opinions have been delivered by the European Central Bank under Article 110 of the European Treaties since the launch of the single currency on 1 January 1999.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.36.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w02.htm#10328w02_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.36.2/1">The material requested is in the public domain and available from the ECB. A copy is available in the Library.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.36.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w02.htm#10328w02_wqn1">
	Exchange Rate Stability
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.36.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100734" speakername="Lord Shore of Stepney" colon="" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w02.htm#10328w02_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.36.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.36.4/2" qnum="HL1372">Further to their reaffirmation of the policy not to rejoin the exchange rate mechanism (ERM), as stated in the Written Answer by Lord McIntosh of Haringey on 14 March (WA 95), what alternative measure of exchange rate stability has been agreed between the United Kingdom Government and their European Union partners.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.36.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w02.htm#10328w02_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.36.5/1">As my right honourable friend the Chancellor said on <phrase class="date" code="2001-03-01">1 March 2001</phrase> (Official Report, col. 1030), &quot;The best contribution that the Government can make to delivering a stable and competitive pound over the medium term is to adhere to stability-oriented policies based on delivering low inflation and sound public finances&quot;.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.36.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w02.htm#10328w02_wqn2">
	Fifty-metre Swimming Pools: Provision
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.36.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100381" speakername="Lord Lloyd-Webber" colon="" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w02.htm#10328w02_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.36.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.36.7/2" qnum="HL1221">Whether they have any proposals to increase the stock of swimming pools of a 50--metre length that are suitable for training young swimmers to Olympic standards.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.36.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w02.htm#10328w02_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.36.8/1">Sport England are working closely with the Amateur Swimming Association and the Amateur Swimming Federation of Great Britain to produce a National Facilities Strategy for Swimming which I hope will be published before the end of April. This strategy will contain details on the provision of 50--metre pools throughout the UK.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.36.9" nospeaker="true" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w02.htm#10328w02_wqn3">
	Royal Parks Constabulary: Review
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.36.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100003" speakername="Lord Acton" colon="" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w02.htm#10328w02_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.36.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.36.10/2" qnum="HL1474">When the report on the inspection of the Royal Parks Constabulary by Mr Anthony Speed will be published.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.37.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w02.htm#10328w02_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.37.0/1">The report was published yesterday and copies have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses. The report is also published on the DCMS website (<a href="http://www.culture.gov.uk">www.culture.gov.uk</a>). We are grateful to Mr Anthony Speed and his assistant for conducting a thorough inspection of the Royal Parks Constabulary (RPC).</p>
	<p pid="a.37.0/2">The review was commissioned by the Royal Parks Advisory Board, which has considered the report carefully. In reaching my conclusions on the report's recommendations, we have had the benefit of the Board's advice for which we are grateful.</p>
	<p pid="a.37.0/3">We accept the report's analysis and its recommendations for improved efficiency and effectiveness. Immediate action has been taken to remedy deficiencies and further changes and improvements are being taken forward. Mr Speed makes 23 recommendations. Listed below is the action taken on each of them to date.</p>
	<p pid="a.37.0/4">It is essential for the morale of the RPC and for recruitment and retention that the force is properly remunerated. The Government have agreed, therefore, to make more money available to maintain the link between the salaries of RPC officers and of the Metropolitan Police Service at 85. The award is being backdated to <phrase class="date" code="2000-09-01">1 September 2000</phrase>. The question of an additional London allowance is under consideration.</p>
	<p pid="a.37.0/5">The Department for Culture, Media and Sport is discussing with the Home Office the future relationship between the RPC and the Metropolitan Police Service. The current position is that the RPC remains part of the Royal Parks Agency. There are options for change, as Mr Speed's report recognises. These options require further detailed examination and discussion. We recognise that uncertainty can be unsettling and we shall reach a conclusion as soon as possible.</p>
	<p pid="a.37.0/6">Mr Speed's report acknowledges the level of public satisfaction with the way in which the Royal Parks are policed. They are relatively crime-free areas. This is due to the dedication and professionalism of the officers of the RPC, which we recognise and to which we pay tribute.</p>
	<table>
		<caption>Report of the Formal Inspection of the Royal Parks Constabulary by Mr Anthony Speed</caption>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/10"> <td>Recommendation</td> <td>Progress</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/11"> <td>1. The duality of function of the Chief Officer should cease. (Paras 2.3-2.10)</td> <td>The Chief Officer no longer has responsibilities as head of personnel. He remains a member of the Management Board.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/12"> <td>2. The Chief Officer should be a superintendent on secondment from a Home Office Police Force. (Paras 2.20-2.23)</td> <td>This is being discussed with the Home Office.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/13"> <td>3. The Deputy Chief Officer should be a Chief Inspector. (Para 2.24)</td> <td>A Promotion Board for Chief Inspector/Deputy Chief Officer post was held on 26 March 2001.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/14"> <td>4. The Chief Officer should be allowed to run the Royal Parks Constabulary alone, on properly constituted lines. (Paras 2.26-2.27)</td> <td>The Chief Officer now has full operational control of the Force.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/15"> <td>5. The Royal Parks Constabulary should produce an annual, costed, policing plan, which gives a clear account of performance in the previous financial year. (Paras 3.12-3.15)</td> <td>Properly costed policing plan for 2001-02 prepared, following full consultation. Currently being professionally reproduced for distribution. Further work necessary in respect of comparisons with performance in previous financial years.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/16"> <td>6. Planning guidelines should be produced by the Force showing the link between the community and the Constabulary and include a clear timetable for the contribution from all parties to the plan. (Paras 3.16-3.17)</td> <td>Interim guidelines produced to enable preparation of the policing plan for 2001-02. These guidelines are being reviewed now and a more detailed document will be produced for distribution in April 2001.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/17"> <td>7. A properly constituted Police Authority should be formed, with clear links to Her Majesty's Inspector of Constabulary to hold the Chief Officer to account for Force performance. (Paras 3.19-3.22)</td> <td>This is being discussed with the Home Office.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/18"> <td>8. A budget should be set for the Force allowing the Chief Officer to set staffing levels. (Para 3.24)</td> <td>Budget currently being set for financial year 2001-02.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/19"> <td>9. A full participative management programme should be published which clearly shows how policy is developed and how each rank contributes to that process. (Paras 3.26-3.34</td> <td>Manual of Guidance now produced and distributed. Minutes of Senior Management Team meetings being prepared in greater detail, with policy decisions highlighted. Hard copies being circulated to supplement distribution by e-mail. Target set to circulate minutes within seven working days of meetings. A newsletter has been distributed to every officer to explain the process of change taking place and further editions will be sent out at regular intervals. The consultation guidelines for the Policing Plan 2001-02 include the opportunity to take the views of staff (both police and civil) into account in the setting of Force aims and objectives. Further actions to follow.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/20"> <td>10. The Force should produce a detailed Human Resources strategy document. (Para 4.1)</td> <td>This document is being prepared.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/21"> <td>11. The Constabulary should not seek any further Investors in People (IIP) assessments until recommendations from previous assessments have been implemented. (Para 4.4)</td> <td>Meeting with IIP assessors held and areas identified for further action. Work continuing.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/22"> <td>12. Staff development should be improved including the use of acting ranks to cover absences. (Paras 4.10-4.11)</td> <td>Temporary promotions made in the ranks of chief inspector, inspector and sergeant. Substantive promotion made in the rank of sergeant and about to be made in the rank of chief inspector. Training plan for 2001-02 prioritises staff development.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/23"> <td>13. Pay parity should be immediately linked to 85%, and allowances increased, in line with the total remuneration of the MPS package. (Paras 4.20-4.22)</td> <td>Pay award has just been made for payment at the end of March. Award backdated to 1 September 2000. Award links pay to 85% of national police pay rates and includes payment of MPS allowances in respect of London Weighting and London Allowance (2)*. Discussions will be held with the Treasury over payment of the Metropolitan Police Service allowance known as London Allowance (1), currently &pound;1,011 pa. *London Allowance (2), currently &pound;3,327 pa, is paid to officers who joined after 1994 and who are not in receipt of recent allowance.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/24"> <td>14. The Constabulary should immediately start monitoring gender and racial matters.</td> <td>Additional monitoring of gender and racial matters is now taking place.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/25"> <td>15. The Constabulary should immediately commence diversity training using the help and expertise in the Home Office. (Para 4.42)</td> <td>Additional diversity training for all officers is already scheduled to take place between January and April 2001. Further diversity training to be carried out between September and December 2001. This second stage training will encompass best practice from the Home Office and will be designed so as to reflect both Force policy and the specific needs of the community and RPC officers.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/26"> <td>16. The Constabulary should establish clear guidelines on grievance procedures. (Para 4.42)</td> <td>Grievance procedures have been redrafted taking account of comments received as a result of consultation. Final draft will be produced for publication by May 2001.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/27"> <td>17. Meetings of all parties involved in event management should be held to further the understanding of each other's roles and improve co-ordination. (Para 5.31)</td> <td>Meetings already held to prepare an Events Seminar for RPA/RPC managers in April 2001. Further seminar to be developed for RPA/RPC and all outside agencies involved in events, for delivery before Summer 2001.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/28"> <td>18. An IT policy and procedures manual should be produced. (Para 6.2)</td> <td>Interim IT User Security Operating Procedures instruction issued in November 2000.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/29"> <td>19. The RPC should commence negotiations with the British Transport Police for enhanced call handling facilities and install the necessary infrastructure as soon as possible. (Para 6.11)</td> <td>Contract for the provision of control room services by the BTP became operative on 1.12.2000. System went live on 7.1.2001. New control room facility is dealing with an average of around 200 calls for police action/attention per week. It is projected that it will handle over 10,000 calls per year. A significant improvement in call handling and response has already been achieved.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/30"> <td>20. The Constabulary install locks on the open drive of each computer terminal. (Para 6.14)</td> <td>New software system introduced to prevent the use of unauthorised floppy discs.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/31"> <td>21. A submission should be made to the Home Secretary to change the law so that RPC officers retain full police powers throughout the judicial process. (Para 6.22)</td> <td>This is being discussed with the Home Office.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/32"> <td>22. The RPC should seek full Computerised Crime Reporting System enablement with the MPS as soon as possible. (Para 7.12)</td> <td>Cost implication of this measure currently being examined.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/33"> <td>23. Start up monies should be provided for the RPC to come under Home Office control as a ring-fenced division of the MPS or, alternatively, funds should be provided to allow proper management, accountability and policing by the Royal Parks Constabulary.</td> <td>Exercise currently being undertaken as to the cost effectiveness of the two options. This will be discussed with the Home Office.</td> <td colspan="2">Outside the 23 main recommendations, the following specific areas were singled out for action:</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/34"> <td>Consultants. In the opinion of the Review Team there was no need for further use of the consultants in the spheres of dogs and the mounted section and, when their contracts are complete, they should not be renewed. (Paras 4.12-4.13)</td> <td>It may be necessary to retain the consultants for a longer period because of the departure of key personnel in the dog and mounted sections.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/35"> <td>Search Team. The RPC have a dedicated, trained search team, who know and understand their particular search area. This should continue. (Para 5.22)</td> <td>Relicensing of search trained officers commenced November 2000. Force now has a properly relicensed search team.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/36"> <td>Brompton Cemetery Warden Scheme. The Review Team urges that negotiations commence immediately with all parties, the RPC, the Friends of Brompton Cemetery, the local community and the local authority to prepare a properly structured community safety plan for the cemetery. (Para 6.21)</td> <td>Initial meeting with Friends of Brompton Cemetery took place in January 2001. Follow up action continuing.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.37.0/37"> <td>Richmond Park, Isabella Plantation Warden Scheme. The Review Team urges all parties to draw up detailed plans for dealing with issues of training, equipment, accountability, powers and personal safety, with regular monitoring and feedback. (Para 6.22)</td> <td>Once properly arranged, the Brompton Cemetery Warden Scheme will be used as a model for Richmond.</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.40.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="40"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn0">
	Special Educational Needs Placing: Referrals to the Sheriff
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.40.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100415" speakername="The Earl of Mar and Kellie" colon="" colnum="40"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.40.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.40.1/2" qnum="HL943">How many cases have gone before Sheriff Courts in connection with the resolution of disputes over special educational needs in the last three years.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.40.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100519" speakername="Baroness Ramsay of Cartvale" colon=":" colnum="40"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.40.2/1">The only special educational needs cases which go to the Sheriff are those concerning placing requests. Appeals relating to the record of needs (i.e. non-placement cases) went to the Secretary of State before devolution took effect on <phrase class="date" code="1999-07-01">1 July 1999</phrase> and now go to the Scottish Ministers. There were no special educational needs placing request referrals to the Sheriff between 1995-96 and 1998-99.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.40.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="40"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn1">
	BSE: Cost
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.40.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100324" speakername="Lord Inglewood" colon="" colnum="40"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.40.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.40.4/2" qnum="HL1296">What has been the total cost of BSE to the United Kingdom taxpayer.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.41.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100284" speakername="Baroness Hayman" colon=":" colnum="41"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.41.0/1">Total expenditure on the BSE crisis is estimated to be &pound;4.4 billion to the end of the financial year 2001-02. Of that amount, the other European Union member states contribute about &pound;500 million when the Fontainebleau mechanism is taken into account. Therefore, the net cost of BSE to the UK taxpayer to the end of the next financial year is about &pound;3.9 billion.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.41.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="41"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn2">
	Transport of Live Animals: Monitoring
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.41.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100414" speakername="The Countess of Mar" colon="" colnum="41"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.41.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.41.2/2" qnum="HL1331">When the decision was taken to abolish the branch of the Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food that monitored certain consignments of farm animals being handled by British animal dealers and hauliers; what advantages were obtained from the abolition; what representations they received about the abolition; and whether they intend to review the decision to abolish the branch.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.41.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100284" speakername="Baroness Hayman" colon=":" colnum="41"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.41.3/1">Contrary to the recent press reports, the branch in Animal Welfare Division concerned with policy towards the transport of live animals and the monitoring of international journeys has not been abolished.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.41.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="41"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn3">
	EU Tobacco Subsidies
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.41.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100332" speakername="Baroness Jeger" colon="" colnum="41"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.41.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.41.5/2" qnum="HL1375">What was the amount in the last financial year contributed by United Kingdom taxpayers to subsidise the growing and exporting of tobacco by European Union member states: and how this accords with the Government's smoking and health policies.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.41.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100284" speakername="Baroness Hayman" colon=":" colnum="41"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.41.6/1">The last year for which figures are available for subsidies paid out of the EU budget to tobacco growers is the European Agriculture Guidance and Guarantee Fund financial year ending <phrase class="date" code="2000-10-15">15 October 2000</phrase>, when payments totalled 984.8 million euros (&pound;592.1 million*).</p>
	<p pid="a.41.6/2">Member states contribute to the EU budget as a whole and not to any particular part. The UK contribution is about 17 per cent before the Fontainebleau abatement is taken into account.</p>
	<p pid="a.41.6/3">The Government strongly disapproves of the common agricultural policy support scheme for tobacco which was introduced in 1970 to support production in disadvantaged areas, maintain farmers incomes and reduce surpluses by adapting production to market needs. We believe that the Community should progressively disengage from support for tobacco production on grounds of health and cost.*&pound;=1.6631 euro.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.42.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn4">
	Crime Strategy: Lord Birt's Role
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.42.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100629" speakername="Lord Tebbit" colon="" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.42.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.42.1/2" qnum="HL883">Further to Lord Bassam's undertaking of 31 January (H.L. Deb., col. 686) that the advice given and conclusion reached by Lord Birt in his role as adviser on crime will be reported to Parliament, whether they will now publish such material as has been submitted.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.42.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100038" speakername="Lord Bassam of Brighton" colon=":" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.42.2/1">The work undertaken by Lord Birt was considered alongside that undertaken by the Home Office, the Lord Chancellor's Department, the Law Officer's Department and Her Majesty's Treasury in preparing the Government's strategy document, Criminal Justice: The Way Ahead (CM 5074), which was published on <phrase class="date" code="2001-02-26">26 February 2001</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.42.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn5">
	Haslar Detainees
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.42.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.42.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.42.4/2" qnum="HL1262">Whether two detainees were held in HM Prison Haslar for 15 and 20 months respectively; if so, why; and how many others have been held there for more than six months during the past three years.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.42.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100038" speakername="Lord Bassam of Brighton" colon=":" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.42.5/1">The information requested is not readily available and could only be provided at disproportionate cost. It is not possible to identify the two detainees mentioned in the question who were detained at Haslar. There are, however, three detainees currently held at HOHC Haslar who have been detained for between 15 and 20 months.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.42.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn6">
	Zimbabwean Asylum Seekers
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.42.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100484" speakername="Baroness Park of Monmouth" colon="" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.42.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.42.7/2" qnum="HL1290">How many Zimbabweans whose applications for asylum have been refused since November 2000 were put in detention, whether any have been returned to their country of origin, and, of the remaining, whether it is proposed to return any of them to their country of origin.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.42.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100038" speakername="Lord Bassam of Brighton" colon=":" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.42.8/1">Information about the number of Zimbabwean nationals who have been detained following the refusal of their asylum application is not held centrally and could only be obtained by examining individual case files.</p>
	<p pid="a.42.8/2">Information about removals under Immigration Act powers is collected by nationality rather than destination. It is therefore not possible to say how many failed asylum seekers have been returned to Zimbabwe since November 2000 without examining the individual files.</p>
	<p pid="a.42.8/3">Where a Zimbabwean is found not to be a refugee and does not qualify for leave to enter or remain in the United Kingdom, our normal course of action would be to remove them to Zimbabwe. The current situation is kept under constant review and there are presently no reasons why refused asylum seekers should not be returned to Zimbabwe.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.43.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn7">
	Animal Rights Extremists
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.43.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100274" speakername="Lord Hardy of Wath" colon="" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.43.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.43.1/2" qnum="HL1447">What measures they are taking to combat animal rights extremism.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.43.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100038" speakername="Lord Bassam of Brighton" colon=":" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.43.2/1">The Government has included a number of measures in the Criminal Justice and Police Bill, currently before Parliament, aimed at combating the activities of animal rights extremists. These include a new power for police to remove protestors from outside homes; measures to strengthen provisions on the sending of malicious communications; and a system to prevent disclosure of the home addresses of directors of vulnerable companies.</p>
	<p pid="a.43.2/2">We have also consulted closely with the police and the Crown Prosecution Service to encourage a consistent approach to enforcement in this area. A consultation document is being issued tomorrow, <phrase class="date" code="2006-03-28">28 March</phrase>, setting out a package of measures in this area, and copies will be placed in the Library.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.43.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn8">
	Applications to Remain in UK: New Forms
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.43.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100250" speakername="Baroness Gould of Potternewton" colon="" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.43.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.43.4/2" qnum="HL1449">What plans they have to replace the application forms for foreign nationals wishing to apply for leave to remain in the United Kingdom.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.43.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100038" speakername="Lord Bassam of Brighton" colon=":" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.43.5/1">The current application forms are valid for use until <phrase class="date" code="2001-04-14">14 April 2001</phrase>. Revised forms will be prescribed before then and should be available by the end of March 2001. From the time they are issued until <phrase class="date" code="2001-04-14">14 April 2001</phrase>, applications may be made on either the newly prescribed forms or the current versions. Only the new forms may be used for applications made on or after <phrase class="date" code="2001-04-15">15 April 2001</phrase>. Copies will be placed in the Library as soon as they are available.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.43.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn9">
	Border Controls
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.43.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100003" speakername="Lord Acton" colon="" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn9">
	<p pid="a.43.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.43.7/2" qnum="HL1475">When they will respond to the Home Affairs Select Committee's report on border controls.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.43.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100038" speakername="Lord Bassam of Brighton" colon="" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.43.8/1">The Government has submitted its response to the report to the chairman of the Home Affairs Committee and a copy has been placed in the Library. I understand that the Home Affairs Committee has decided to publish this today as its fourth special report HC 375 and this will be available on the Home Affairs Committee website at <a href="http://www.parliament.uk/commons/selcom/hmafhome.htm">www.parliament.uk/commons/selcom/hmafhome.htm</a>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.44.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="44"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn10">
	Human Reproductive Cloning
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.44.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="44"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_wqn10">
	<p pid="a.44.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.44.1/2" qnum="HL939">Following reports in the Sunday Times of 18 February, what action they intend to take to raise with the Bush Administration the consequences of permitting the development of a cloned baby; and what is their policy concerning the proposed adoption of babies produced via reproductive cloning by British nationals.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.44.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="44"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w03.htm#10328w03_spmin3">
	<p pid="a.44.2/1">The United Kingdom and the United States discuss topical health issues in a number of international bodies. However, we have no plans to raise with the US the specific issue of cloning babies.</p>
	<p pid="a.44.2/2">The US has observer status at the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation and the Council of Europe where human reproductive cloning has been condemned. In 1997 the World Health Assembly (WHA) also passed a resolution condemning human reproductive cloning. The WHA is the annual meeting of the World Health Organisation with a membership of 191 member states including the US.</p>
	<p pid="a.44.2/3">The decision to grant an adoption order must be taken in the light of what is in the best interests of the child. This, and the law on adoption, applies regardless of the circumstances of the child's birth.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.44.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="44"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w04.htm#10328w04_wqn0">
	Mobile Phone Mast Emissions: Health Assessment
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.44.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100502" speakername="Lord Pilkington of Oxenford" colon="" colnum="44"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w04.htm#10328w04_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.44.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.44.4/2" qnum="HL986">Whether they can assure residents living within two kilometres of the proposed TETRA (Trans European Trunked Radio Access) mast to be built at Dowlish Ford, near Ilminster, Somerset, that this will have no adverse impact on their health.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.44.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="44"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w04.htm#10328w04_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.44.5/1">The report of the Independent Expert Group on Mobile Phones (the Stewart report) provided a rigorous and comprehensive assessment of existing research related to concerns about the possible effects on health of emissions from mobile phones and base stations (masts). The report concluded &quot;that the balance of evidence indicates that there is no general risk to health of people living near base stations on the basis that exposures are expected to be small fractions of guidelines&quot;. For instance, under the current measurement programme of mobile phone base stations near schools, the highest level measured has been one six hundredth (1/600) of the recommended guideline level. As with mobile phone base stations, those supporting TETRA need to comply with guidelines. In view of the concerns expressed by residents near base stations and the indirect effect on people's well-being, the Stewart group made a number of recommendations aimed at improving the public consultation and the availability of information about the siting of base stations. The Government are implementing these recommendations and information can be found on the mobile phones web site (<a href="http://www.doh.gov.uk/mobilephones">www.doh.gov.uk/mobilephones</a>).</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.45.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="45"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w04.htm#10328w04_wqn1">
	RAF Feltwell: Purpose of US Use of Facilities
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.45.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="45"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w04.htm#10328w04_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.45.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.45.1/2" qnum="HL1299">What information they have received from the United States authorities about the use of the facilities at the deep and near space tracking facility at Feltwell in Norfolk in connection with the proposed United States missile defense system; whether they will seek assurances from the United States Government that no such use will be made of these facilities in the future; and whether the agreement they have with the United States on the operation of Feltwell allows it to be applied to military purposes of any kind.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.45.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="45"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w04.htm#10328w04_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.45.2/1">RAF Feltwell is made available to the United States visiting forces under the NATO Status of Forces Agreement of 1951 for the purposes of our common defence. It has no role in ballistic missile detection or tracking, and nor are we aware of any suggestions that it could do so as part of any missile defence system.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.46.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="46"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w04.htm#10328w04_wqn2">
	Meat Consumed by Services Personnel: Percentage Purchased from Overseas
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.46.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100427" speakername="Baroness Miller of Chilthorne Domer" colon="" colnum="46"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w04.htm#10328w04_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.46.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.46.1/2" qnum="HL1317">What percentage of meat consumed by services personnel was purchased from overseas in 1999-2000 and 2000-01.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.46.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="46"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w04.htm#10328w04_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.46.2/1">From 1999-2000, 51 per cent of the meat consumed by services personnel was purchased from overseas. From 2000-01 the figure was 52 per cent.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.46.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="46"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w04.htm#10328w04_wqn3">
	Countries Supplying Meat to Ministry of Defence
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.46.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100427" speakername="Baroness Miller of Chilthorne Domer" colon="" colnum="46"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w04.htm#10328w04_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.46.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.46.4/2" qnum="HL1318">From which countries suppliers of meat to the Ministry of Defence obtained meat in 1999-2000 and 2000-01.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-03-28a.46.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="46"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200001/ldhansrd/vo010328/text/10328w04.htm#10328w04_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.46.5/1">The Ministry of Defence obtained supplies of meat from the following countries: Australia, Belgium, Brazil, Denmark, France, the Republic of Ireland, the Netherlands, New Zealand, Spain and Uruguay as well as the United Kingdom.</p>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

