<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">

<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >

<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >

<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY micro "&#181;" >

<!ENTITY euro "&#8364;" >
]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.49.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="49"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_wqn0">
	Incitement to Hatred
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.49.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100387" speakername="Baroness Ludford" colon="" colnum="49"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.49.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.49.1/2" qnum="HL1236">What protection exists under existing legislation against incitement to hatred or discrimination towards particular groups, such as women or homosexuals; under the inspiration of religious thinking.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.49.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="49"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.49.2/1">The Government recognise that there are a number of groups which may be seen to be vulnerable to attack or vilification. It is already the case that the courts will consider a premeditated attack on a person because, for example, of their gender or sexual orientation as an aggravated offence meriting a more serious sentence.</p>
	<p pid="a.49.2/2">In the Anti-terrorism, Crime and Disorder Act we sought to deal with the specific areas of race and religion because those areas presented a particular problem which needed to be addressed and which apply equally to all members of society. It is not the role of government to take a position on the rites, beliefs or practices of any particular religious faith other than where these give rise to conflict with common or criminal law.</p>
	<p pid="a.49.2/3">We have recently published a consultation document containing proposals for taking forward the implementation of the EC Article 13 Race and Employment Directives. The proposals include introducing new legislation prohibiting discrimination on the grounds of religion or belief, age and sexual orientation in the areas of employment, occupation and training.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.49.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="49"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_wqn1">
	Anti-terrorism, Crime and Security Bill Consultation
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.49.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="49"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.49.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.49.4/2" qnum="HL1744">Whether they have received advice from Professor Brice Dickson, Chief Commissioner of the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission, on the Anti-terrorism, Crime and Security Bill; what was that advice; and whether they intend to accept it.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.49.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="49"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.49.5/1">My ministerial colleagues and I have received representations from many organisations, groups and individuals, including the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission, concerning the proposals contained within the Anti-terrorism, Crime and Security Bill. We have read and carefully considered all the concerns raised by the commission and others throughout the development and passage of this Bill and this has been reflected in the decisions we have taken at each stage.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.50.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_wqn2">
	Prisons: Chaplaincy Areas
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.50.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.50.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.50.1/2" qnum="HL1887">Whether they will place in the Library of the House drawings of the chaplaincy areas in prisons using the Bullingdon repeat design and those provided in the new private prisons such as Rye Hill.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.50.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.50.2/1">The Prison Service will place appropriate drawings of chaplaincy areas in the Library of the House.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.50.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_wqn3">
	Racially-aggravated Offences
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.50.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.50.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.50.4/2" qnum="HL2027">Whether they are considering the merits and potential benefits of a review of existing legislation giving protection against racial hatred and racially aggravated crimes; whether parliamentary post-legislative scrutiny would throw light on any need for new protection for religious minorities.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.50.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.50.5/1">The Government have commissioned reseach on the implementation of the laws on racially-aggravated offences contained in the Crime and Disorder Act 1998. The research will be published in due course.</p>
	<p pid="a.50.5/2">The Government have given detailed consideration to the question of amendments to the legislation on incitement to racial hatred and racially-aggravated offences in the context of the Anti-terrorism, Crime and Security Act which last week received Royal Assent. Under this Act, the maximum penalty available to the courts for the offence of incitement to racial hatred has been increased from two to seven years. It is also now an offence to incite hatred against a racial group abroad as well as in this country. In addition, the Act expands the existing provisions on racially-aggravated offences to cover offences motivated by religious hostility.</p>
	<p pid="a.50.5/3">The Government have not ruled out the possibility of a further review of the law to consider whether religious or other groups might be offered the same kind of protection as exists for racial groups. However, there are no current plans to undertake such a review.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.50.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_wqn4">
	Asylum Seekers: Accommodation
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.50.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100255" speakername="Lord Greaves" colon="" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.50.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.50.7/2" qnum="HL2028">Which accommodation providers are currently contracted with the National Asylum Support Service to provide accommodation for asylum seekers; and for each provider how many places they are contracted to provide and where.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.50.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.50.8/1">The National Asylum Support Service (NASS) has entered into contracts with accommodation providers from both the private and public sector, a registered social landlord and a charity. The organisations are as follows:</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/2">Public sector</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/3" class="indent">Cardiff City Council</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/4" class="indent">Devon County Council</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/5" class="indent">East Midlands Consortium</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/6" class="indent">Glasgow City Council</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/7" class="indent">North East Consortium</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/8" class="indent">North West Consortium</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/9" class="indent">Northern Ireland Housing Executive</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/10" class="indent">Peterborough City Council</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/11" class="indent">Southampton City Council</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/12" class="indent">West Midlands Consortium</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/13" class="indent">Yorkshire and Humberside Consortium</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/14">Private sector</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/15" class="indent">Adelphi Hotels</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/16" class="indent">Angel Group Limited</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/17" class="indent">Capital Accommodation Limited</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/18" class="indent">Clearsprings</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/19" class="indent">Landmark</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/20" class="indent">Leena Corporation</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/21" class="indent">Roselodge Limited</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/22">Registered social landlord</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/23" class="indent">Safehaven</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/24">Charity</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/25" class="indent">YMCA Glasgow</p>
	<p pid="a.50.8/26">Accommodation for asylum seekers is most usually located in cluster areas. To date NASS has established 75 cluster areas as follows:</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.50.8/29"> <td>Region</td> <td>Cluster</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.50.8/30"> <td>East of England</td> <td>Ipswich Norwich Cambridge Great Yarmouth Peterborough</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.50.8/31"> <td>East Midlands</td> <td>Leicester Nottingham Lincoln Derby</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.50.8/32"> <td>Greater London</td> <td>London</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.50.8/33"> <td>South Central and East</td> <td>Brighton &amp; Hove Hastings &amp; St. Leonards Southampton Portsmouth</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.50.8/34"> <td>North East</td> <td>Newcastle Middlesbrough Sunderland North Tyneside Gateshead South Tyneside Redcar &amp; Cleveland Hartlepool Darlington Stockton on Tees</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.50.8/35"> <td>North West</td> <td>Manchester (Gtr Manchester) Bolton (Gtr Manchester) Bury (Gtr Manchester) Oldham (Gtr Manchester) Rochdale (Gtr Manchester) Salford (Gtr Manchester) Stockport (Gtr Manchester) Tameside (Gtr Manchester) Trafford (Gtr Manchester) Wigan (Gtr Manchester) Burnley Blackburn Liverpool Nelson</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.50.8/36"> <td>Northern Ireland</td> <td>Belfast Other</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.50.8/37"> <td>Scotland</td> <td>Edinburgh Glasgow</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.50.8/38"> <td>South West</td> <td>Bristol Gloucester Swindon Taunton &amp; Bridgewater Exeter South Gloucestershire Torbay Plymouth North Somerset Bath</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.50.8/39"> <td>Wales</td> <td>Cardiff Newport Swansea Wrexham Bridgend &amp; Porthcawl</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.50.8/40"> <td>West Midlands</td> <td>Birmingham Coventry Wolverhampton Dudley Sandwell Solihull Walsall Stoke on Trent</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.50.8/41"> <td>Yorkshire &amp; Humberside</td> <td>Sheffield Bradford &amp; Keighley Leeds Rotherham Wakefield Hull Kirklees Doncaster Halifax Barnsley Grimsby</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.50.8/44">I regret that I am unable to supply information about how many spaces they are contracted to provide since details of individual contracts between NASS and its suppliers are commercial in confidence.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.52.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="52"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_wqn5">
	Prisons: Performance Testing
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.52.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100421" speakername="Baroness Massey of Darwen" colon="" colnum="52"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.52.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.52.1/2" qnum="HL2133">What plans they have for identifying and improving poorly performing prisons.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.52.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="52"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.52.2/1">On <phrase class="date" code="2006-01-12">12 January</phrase> my right honourable friend the then Minister of State at the Home Office announced the intention to develop a performance testing scheme under which poorly performing prisons would be identified and required to develop a plan for improvement within a fixed period; if the plan was acceptable, the prison would operate under a service level agreement, with strict monitoring of delivery against its proposals; if unacceptable, the prison would face closure or contracting out to the private sector.</p>
	<p pid="a.52.2/2">The director general has selected two establishments, Her Majesty's Prison Leicester and Her Majesty's Young Offender Institution and Remand Centre Reading, for performance testing. They will be given six months to produce proposals for a much improved level of service.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.53.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="53"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_wqn6">
	Anti-terrorism, Crime and Security Act Powers
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.53.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100642" speakername="Lord Tomlinson" colon="" colnum="53"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.53.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.53.1/2" qnum="HL2134">What plans they have to use the powers under the Anti-terrorism, Crime and Security Act 2001.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.53.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="53"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w01.htm#11219w01_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.53.2/1">Earlier today, on the basis of certificates my right honourable friend the Home Secretary signed under Part 4 of the Act, following careful and detailed consideration, the Immigration Service detained eight foreign nationals whom my right honourable friend suspects to be international terrorists. They were detained earlier today and will be held in secure prison accommodation. My right honourable friend will not disclose their names unless they themselves first do so.</p>
	<p pid="a.53.2/2">Part 4 of the Act gives my right honourable friend powers to issue a certificate in respect of someone whom he believes to be a risk to national security and suspect to be an international terrorist. The Act also gives powers for his deportation and, where his removal or departure from the United Kingdom is prevented (whether temporarily or indefinitely), for his detention.</p>
	<p pid="a.53.2/3">A person detained has the right to apply for bail to the Special Immigration Appeals Commission, which is a superior court of record under the Act. He may also appeal to the commission to have the certificate cancelled. In these circumstances it would be inappropriate for my right honourable friend to comment further. A person detained is free to leave the United Kingdom at any time.</p>
	<p pid="a.53.2/4">My right honourable friend will continue to keep the exercise of the powers in Part 4 of the Act under close review.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.53.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="53"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn0">
	Appeals by Healthcare Professionals
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.53.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100367" speakername="Lord Lester of Herne Hill" colon="" colnum="53"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.53.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.53.4/2" qnum="HL1379">How many sitting days of Lords of Appeal in Ordinary are currently occupied in hearing and deciding appeals to the Judicial Committee of the Privy Council by healthcare professionals.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.53.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100325" speakername="Lord Irvine of Lairg" colon=":" colnum="53"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.53.5/1">This year appeals by healthcare professionals were heard on 16 days in the Judicial Committee of the Privy Council; on four of those days other business was dealt with as well. Medical appeals are heard by boards of three members of the committee. These 16 days, therefore, represent 48 judge days. Not all the judges who sit on these boards are serving Lords of Appeal in Ordinary, since some are other members of the Judicial Committee, eg retired Law Lords, senior judges from the Commonwealth and past or present members of the Court of Appeal. Of the 48 judge days this year, 28 were sat by Lords of Appeal in Ordinary and 20 by other members of the Judicial Committee.</p>
	<p pid="a.53.5/2">The corresponding figures for last year were that medical appeals were heard on 14 days, three of which were mixed business days, and the appeals occupied 25 judge days of the Lords of Appeal in Ordinary.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.54.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="54"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn1">
	Magistrates' Courts: Closure
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.54.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100499" speakername="Lord Phillips of Sudbury" colon="" colnum="54"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.54.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.54.1/2" qnum="HL2132">Further to the Written Answer of the Lord Chancellor on 12 November 2001 (Official Report, col. WA 49) whether he has been advised of any further closures of magistrates' courthouses in England and Wales in each of the last 10 years for which statistics are available; and what are the locations of such closures.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.54.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100325" speakername="Lord Irvine of Lairg" colon=":" colnum="54"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.54.2/1">I have been further advised that Gravesend courthouse in Kent closed on <phrase class="date" code="2000-06-09">9 June 2000</phrase>, bringing the annual total to 13 in 2000. I was unaware on <phrase class="date" code="2001-11-12">12 November 2001</phrase> that it had been closed. All other figures and locations in my earlier Answer are unchanged.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.54.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="54"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn2">
	Sierra Leone
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.54.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100011" speakername="Lord Alli" colon="" colnum="54"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.54.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.54.4/2" qnum="HL2066">What plans they have concerning the deployment of British troops in Sierra Leone.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.54.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="54"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.54.5/1">Our military training and assistance programme continues to make good progress towards its goal of developing a professional, accountable and effective Sierra Leone Army, able to protect the security and integrity of Sierra Leone on its own. My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for Defence (Mr Hoon) announced in another place in September that, following the completion of the work of British short-term training teams, our military presence would reduce to 360 shore-based personnel by January 2002, remaining at that level until April. Since then, it has been announced that presidential and parliamentary elections in Sierra Leone are to be held on <phrase class="date" code="2002-05-14">14 May 2002</phrase>. We have therefore decided to maintain our presence at the force levels announced in September over the period of the elections. The International Military Advisory and Training Team will continue the military training and assistance task with the Sierra Leone Army.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.55.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="55"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn3">
	Gas Transportation Tariffs
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.55.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="55"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.55.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.55.1/2" qnum="HL1330">What assessment they made of the strategic development importance of natural gas when designing the gas transportation tariffs in the United Kingdom.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.55.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="55"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_spmin3">
	<p pid="a.55.2/1">In Great Britain gas transportation tariffs are levied by Transco and regulated by Ofgem through licence conditions, including the licence condition relating to the price control.</p>
	<p pid="a.55.2/2">In setting the price control, Ofgem is mindful of the need to ensure that Transco has sufficient finance and incentive to invest in additional capacity to meet future gas needs.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.55.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="55"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn4">
	Nuclear Reactors: Radioactive Waste
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.55.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100427" speakername="Baroness Miller of Chilthorne Domer" colon="" colnum="55"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.55.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.55.4/2" qnum="HL1868">Whether British Nuclear Fuels Limited has advised the South African Government that radioactive waste generated by the new nuclear reactors being developed by British Nuclear Fuels Limited and Eskom, the South African-owned electricity corporation, can be stored at sites within the United Kingdom; and, if so, which sites.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.55.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="55"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.55.5/1">No such discussions have taken place.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.55.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="55"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn5">
	Scotland: Railways
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.55.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100415" speakername="The Earl of Mar and Kellie" colon="" colnum="55"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.55.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.55.7/2" qnum="HL2004">Whether in Scotland the expansion of the railway network is a devolved matter and the maintenance of the railway network is a reserved matter.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.55.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="55"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_spmin4">
	<p pid="a.55.8/1">The expansion and maintenance of the railway network, including Scotland, are reserved matters. Funding of the Scottish franchise and the preparation of directions and guidance for the SRA's work in Scotland are matters for the Scottish Executive. If the Scottish Executive wishes to expand the railway network beyond the existing agreement, it may look to do so. However, it must provide the necessary funding from within its own budget. Work is in progress to devolve to Scottish Ministers the responsibility for the parliamentary process for approving the construction and operation of new railways in Scotland, but this does not affect the SRA's overall responsibility for the development of the GB network.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.56.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="56"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn6">
	Trans-Pennine Express Franchise
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.56.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100255" speakername="Lord Greaves" colon="" colnum="56"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.56.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.56.1/2" qnum="HL2030">Whether it is their policy that the passenger train operations should be consolidated into a smaller number of regional and operational franchises; and, if so, whether they believe that the trans-Pennine express franchise would be better combined with the main franchise for local services in the North of England.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.56.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="56"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.56.2/1">Consolidation of franchises may provide benefits in particular cases from operational efficiency and value for money but may also entail risks in other cases from loss of competition and management focus. My right honourable friend has yet to receive final proposals for a trans-Pennine express franchise from the Strategic Rail Authority but provisionally takes the view that in this case the benefits, which include stronger management focus on a distinctive set of routes and services, outweigh the potential drawbacks.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.56.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="56"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn7">
	Driving Licence Applications
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.56.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100374" speakername="Lord Lipsey" colon="" colnum="56"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.56.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.56.4/2" qnum="HL2031">Why the Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency asks customers to send it their passports when applying for a driving licence; and</p>
	<p pid="a.56.4/3" qnum="HL2033">Why, and following what risk assessment, the Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency refuses to accept photocopied documents in support of licence applications.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.56.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="56"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.56.5/1">As the driving licence now contains a photograph, identity checks have been tightened up compared with those previously made for paper licences. In line with the Government's policy on combating identity fraud, all drivers are required to provide evidence of identity such as a passport or birth certificate.</p>
	<p pid="a.56.5/2">Applicants for photocard driving licences were initially permitted to supply photocopies of identity documents. As the Government's strategy on fraud prevention evolved, the risks of accepting photocopied documents rather than originals became apparent. This gave rise to the current requirement to provide original documents. Once a driver has provided proof of identity they will not normally need to do so again.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.56.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="56"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn8">
	DVLA: Loss of Returned Documents
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.56.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100374" speakername="Lord Lipsey" colon="" colnum="56"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.56.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.56.7/2" qnum="HL2032">In how many cases last year passports or birth certificates went missing between being sent to the Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency and being returned.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.56.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="56"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.56.8/1">During the past financial year the number of compensation claims met as a result of a customer not having received documentation such as a passport or birth certificate returned by DVLA in support of a driving licence application were 3,474, or 0.06 per cent of the 5.4 million photocard licences issued in the same period.</p>
	<p pid="a.56.8/2">Of these claims, Royal Mail (Consignia) accepted responsibility for the loss of 70 per cent and reimbursed DVLA accordingly.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.57.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="57"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn9">
	Planning Obligations
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.57.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100152" speakername="Baroness Crawley" colon="" colnum="57"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_wqn9">
	<p pid="a.57.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.57.1/2" qnum="HL2104">When they will publish their consultation document on planning obligations.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.57.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="57"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w02.htm#11219w02_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.57.2/1">We are publishing today a consultation document entitled Planning obligations: delivering a fundamental change, which is one of a series of consultation papers that together propose a radical reform of the planning system.</p>
	<p pid="a.57.2/2">Planning obligations (also known as Section 106 agreements) are typically agreements between developers and local authorities negotiated in the context of granting a planning consent. They have been criticised by the Committee on Standards in Public Life (the Nolan Committee) for being insufficiently transparent. Business finds them slow to negotiate, unpredictable and, in some cases, unfair. They are then a disincentive to developers, who may find themselves with long, expensive planning delays.</p>
	<p pid="a.57.2/3">We are proposing to replace the present system of negotiated planning obligations with a tariff that will be set by local authorities in their local development plans. The tariff will apply in principle to all development that receives a planning consent. It will therefore give business much more certainty about what cost, in terms of planning obligations, it faces if it chooses to buy and develop a particular piece of land or property. We are also proposing that some development should be exempt because it is too small, it is financially marginal&mdash;such as development of an urban brownfield site&mdash;or serves a clear purpose in promoting sustainable development.</p>
	<p pid="a.57.2/4">The tariff would be spent in line with the priorities set out in local development plans. We would expect the provision of affordable housing to be a high priority in most plans.</p>
	<p pid="a.57.2/5">Our proposals will create an open, accountable and predictable system that will enable business to see at the outset of a development what level of planning obligation is likely to be incurred. The tariff will so far as possible require no negotiation. It will be much easier for local authorities to administer and should allow planning permissions to be issued much faster.</p>
	<p pid="a.57.2/6">We propose in the consultation document to allow planning obligations to be used to enable communities to share in the benefits of sustainable growth. Development pressures in some areas are placing heavy burdens on the existing infrastructure and especially on the supply of affordable housing for nurses, teachers, police officers and other keyworkers. We need to ensure that new development supports the investment required in new facilities to help improve the quality of life for local communities.</p>
	<p pid="a.57.2/7">Copies of the consultation document will be placed in the Library of the House.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.58.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="58"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_wqn0">
	Foot and Mouth: Slaughter Appeals
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.58.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100414" speakername="The Countess of Mar" colon="" colnum="58"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.58.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.58.1/2" qnum="HL1576">On how many occasions during the recent outbreak of foot and mouth disease appeals against decisions of Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food or Department for the Environment, Food and Rural Affairs officials to slaughter animals were upheld by the courts; how many cases were withdrawn by the animal owners prior to court hearings; and in how many cases were the officials decisions upheld.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.58.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="58"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.58.2/1">Defra officials sought High Court injunctions to slaughter animals on four occasions. In two of these cases the injunction was denied. In the other two cases the department was granted an injunction. There have been 31 cases in which animal owners withdrew their challenge to slaughter prior to court hearings. In addition, one claim for judicial review was withdrawn by the animal owners, one judicial review was won by the department and a further judicial review is ongoing.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.58.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="58"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_wqn1">
	Foot and Mouth: Slaughter Appeals
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.58.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100414" speakername="The Countess of Mar" colon="" colnum="58"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.58.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.58.4/2" qnum="HL1578">In cases where appeals to the courts against decisions of Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food or Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs officials to slaughter animals were withdrawn or refused, how many animals were slaughtered; and how many of those animals showed signs of foot and mouth disease.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.58.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="58"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.58.5/1">Defra headquarters is aware of 14,379 animals that were slaughtered after appeals had been refused or withdrawn from the courts. It is not possible to say how many of these animals showed signs of foot and mouth disease. However, seven of the 34 premises where owners of animals appealed against slaughter subsequently tested positive for the foot and mouth disease virus and were classified as infected premises. Information is currently being sought from regional offices on cases that were dealt with locally so that a full picture can be established.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.58.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="58"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_wqn2">
	Defra: Exeter Office
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.58.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100098" speakername="Baroness Byford" colon="" colnum="58"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.58.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.58.7/2" qnum="HL1588">Whether the &quot;missing equipment&quot; from the Department for the Environment, Food and Rural Affairs Exeter Office was computer equipment, and, if so, whether it has been recovered.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.59.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="59"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.59.0/1">I refer the noble Baroness to the reply I gave her on <phrase class="date" code="">12 November</phrase> (Official Report, cols. WA 58&ndash;59).</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.59.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="59"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_wqn3">
	MMR Vaccine
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.59.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100130" speakername="Lord Clement-Jones" colon="" colnum="59"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.59.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.59.2/2" qnum="0">In the light of the findings of the paper by Spitzer, Aitken et al in the Journal of Adverse Drug Reaction and Toxicology, 2001, 20(3), which found that there is a median delay between immunisation with measles, mumps and rubella (MMR) and diagnosis of autism of 2.5 years, whether:</p>
	<p pid="a.59.2/3" qnum="0">(a) the trial of 200 children in Sheffield with a quadruple vaccine of MMR/chickenpox will include a follow-up for all 200 children for a minimum of three years each, as recommended by Spitzer, Aitken et al, rather than an extended follow-up of only acute immediate reactions;</p>
	<p pid="a.59.2/4" qnum="0">(b) any gradual degeneratiuon into autism, autistic spectrum disorder, or Aspergers Syndrome among the 200 children in this safety trial will be fully investigated before any wider safety trial in the United Kingdom is sanctioned; and</p>
	<p pid="a.59.2/5" qnum="HL1616">(c) a similar safety trial will in any event be repeated with a much larger sample, again with a three-year follow-up of every single child, before there is any general introduction of a quadruple vaccine.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.59.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="59"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.59.3/1">No trials of MMR vaccine combined with chicken pox (varicella) vaccine are being conducted in Sheffield.</p>
	<p pid="a.59.3/2">Although the paper by Spitzer, Aitken et al in the Journal of Adverse Drug Reactions and Toxicology reviews the cases of children whose parents are taking forward legal action against MMR manufacturers, it provides no scientific evidence to link MMR vaccine with autism. The paper reports the first symptoms of autism appeared on average over a year after the children had had MMR vaccine, strongly suggestive that MMR played no role. Spitzer, Aitken et al's findings are also counter to the paper by Dr Andrew Wakefield and colleagues published in the Lancet in 1998 which reported rapid onset of behaviourial symptoms, median 6.3 days, after MMR.</p>
	<p pid="a.59.3/3">Other, more thorough, scientific studies which have looked at the link between MMR and autism have repeatedly found no link. A paper by Farrington et al published in Vaccine earlier this year examined whether autism might be a risk after MMR&mdash;as an acute event, or as a long-term delayed reaction. The authors concluded, &quot;our results do not support the hypothesis that MMR or measles containing vaccines cause autism at any time after vaccination&quot;.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.60.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_wqn4">
	Artificial Limbs: Silicone Cosmesis
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.60.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100103" speakername="Lord Campbell of Croy" colon="" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.60.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.60.1/2" qnum="HL1899">Why government expenditure of &pound;500,000, announced in October 2000 as intended for silicone cosmesis for artificial limbs, was in the event spent on other parts of the National Health Service.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.60.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.60.2/1">We have increased health authority allocations by &pound;4 million over the next three years to provide silicone cosmesis for prosthetic limb users. This funding started in April this year with &pound;0.5 million for 2001&ndash;02, &pound;1.5 million for 2002&ndash;03 and a further &pound;2 million for 2003&ndash;04.</p>
	<p pid="a.60.2/2">The funding was included in health authorities' allocations, along with funding for community services equipment. In order to ensure that patients do receive this funding we have written to chief executives and finance directors of health authorities that commission prosthetic services to highlight the silicone cosmesis allocation.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.60.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_wqn5">
	Health Authority Boundaries
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.60.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100003" speakername="Lord Acton" colon="" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.60.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.60.4/2" qnum="HL2101">When they expect to be in a position to announce the outcome of the recent consultation on proposed boundaries for new health authorities across England.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.60.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.60.5/1">We have announced that, following 22 simultaneous consultation exercises across the whole of England, we are proposing to establish 28 new health authorities from <phrase class="date" code="2002-04-01">1 April 2002</phrase>, when the existing health authorities will be disestablished. Subject to progress with the NHS Reform and Health Care Professions Bill, these new health authorities are expected to become strategic health authorities by next October. The table indicates the new health authorities and their constituent existing health authorities.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/4"> <td>New Health Authority</td> <td>HAs involved</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/5"> <td>Norfolk, Suffolk and  Cambridgeshire</td> <td>Cambridge Norfolk Suffolk</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/6"> <td>Bedfordshire and  Hertfordshire</td> <td>Bedfordshire Hertfordshire</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/7"> <td>Essex</td> <td>North Essex South Essex</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/8"> <td>North West London</td> <td>Brent and Harrow Ealing, Hammersmith &amp;  Hounslow Hillingdon Kensington, Chelsea &amp;  Westminster</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/9"> <td>North Central London</td> <td>Barnet, Enfield &amp; Haringey Camden and Islington</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/10"> <td>North East London</td> <td>Barking and Havering East London and the City Redbridge and Waltham  Forest</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/11"> <td>South East London</td> <td>Bexley, Bromley and  Greenwich Lambeth, Southwark &amp;  Lewisham</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/12"> <td>South West London</td> <td>Croydon Kingston and Richmond Merton, Sutton &amp;  Wandsworth</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/13"> <td>Northumberland, Tyne and  Wear</td> <td>Gateshead and South Tyneside Newcastle and North Tyneside Northumberland Sunderland</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/14"> <td>County Durham &amp; Tees Valley</td> <td>County Durham &amp; Darlington Tees</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/15"> <td>North and East Yorkshire and  Northern Lincolnshire</td> <td>East Riding &amp; Hull North Yorkshire South Humber</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/16"> <td>West Yorkshire</td> <td>Bradford Calderdale and Kirklees Leeds Wakefield</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/17"> <td>Cumbria &amp; Lancashire</td> <td>North Cumbria East Lancashire Morecambe Bay North West Lancashire South Lancashire</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/18"> <td>Greater Manchester</td> <td>Bury and Rochdale Manchester Salford and Trafford Stockport West Pennine Wigan and Bolton</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/19"> <td>Cheshire &amp; Merseyside</td> <td>Liverpool North Cheshire Sefton South Cheshire St Helens and Knowsley Wirral</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/20"> <td>Thames Valley</td> <td>Berkshire Buckinghamshire Oxfordshire</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/21"> <td>Hampshire and Isle of Wight</td> <td>North and Mid Hampshire Isle of Wight &amp; Portsmouth  and South East Hampshire Southampton and South West  Hampshire</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/22"> <td>Kent and Medway</td> <td>East Kent West Kent</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/23"> <td>Surrey and Sussex</td> <td>East Surrey East Sussex, Brighton and  Hove West Surrey West Sussex</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/24"> <td>Avon, Gloucestershire &amp;  Wiltshire</td> <td>Avon Gloucestershire Wiltshire</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/25"> <td>South West Peninsula</td> <td>Cornwall and Isles of Scilly North and East Devon South and West Devon</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/26"> <td>Somerset &amp; Dorset</td> <td>Dorset Somerset</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/27"> <td>South Yorkshire</td> <td>Barnsley Doncaster Rotherham Sheffield</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/28"> <td>Trent</td> <td>Lincolnshire North Derbyshire North Nottinghamshire Nottingham South Derbyshire</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/29"> <td>Leicestershire,  Northamptonshire &amp;  Rutland</td> <td>Leicestershire Northamptonshire</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/30"> <td>Shropshire and Staffordshire</td> <td>North Staffordshire Shropshire South Staffordshire</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/31"> <td>Birmingham and the Black  Country</td> <td>Birmingham Dudley Sandwell Solihull Walsall Wolverhampton</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.5/32"> <td>Coventry, Warwickshire,  Herefordshire and  Worcestershire</td> <td>Coventry Herefordshire Warwickshire Worcestershire</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.62.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_wqn6">
	Disabled People and the Performing Arts
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.62.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100016" speakername="Baroness Anelay of St Johns" colon="" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.62.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.62.1/2" qnum="HL1968">What research they have carried out into the disadvantages facing disabled people who seek work in the performing arts; and what measures they are taking to enable people who have a disability to overcome such disadvantages.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.62.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w03.htm#11219w03_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.62.2/1">The Arts Council of England last year published a Handbook of Good Practice: Employing Disabled People based on its apprenticeship scheme which provides support for host organisations and apprentices in a wide range of roles&mdash;administrative, technical, managerial, creative and educational. The regional arts boards are also engaged in this area: London Arts commissioned an extensive research and consultation exercise to inform its recently published Disability Action Plan.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.62.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_wqn0">
	Tourism: Foot and Mouth
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.62.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100208" speakername="Lord Fearn" colon="" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.62.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.62.4/2" qnum="HL1991">What help they have given to the tourism industry in areas affected by the foot and mouth epidemic over the last 12 months.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.62.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.62.5/1">The Regional Development Agency Business Recovery Fund, established in April, is designed to provide targeted help for rural businesses, including tourism businesses, affected by the consequent implications of foot and mouth disease. On <phrase class="date" code="">18 October</phrase>, the Government allocated a further &pound;24 million to the fund, taking the total to &pound;74 million. The fund is one element in a package of recovery assistance for tourism that includes hardship business rate relief and interest-free deferral of tax payments.</p>
	<p pid="a.62.5/2">The Department for Culture, Media and Sport provided an additional &pound;3.8 million to the English Tourism Council and &pound;14.2 million to the British Tourist Authority. These measures and existing programmes will help to encourage tourism.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.63.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_wqn1">
	Tourism Forum
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.63.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100208" speakername="Lord Fearn" colon="" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.63.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.63.1/2" qnum="HL1992">How many times the Tourism Forum has met since its inception; and what progress they have made in implementing suggestions and ideas made by that forum.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.63.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.63.2/1">The fifth Tourism Forum was held at Tate Modern on <phrase class="date" code="2001-11-07">7 November 2001</phrase>. The forum is primarily a vehicle for discussion, consultation and debate between government and representatives of the tourism and hospitality industry, rather than one that produces specific action points. The key issue for discussion at the November meeting was the reform and modernising programme for the industry following the foot and mouth outbreak and the events of <phrase class="date" code="">11 September</phrase>. Following the forum, the Government, tourism agencies and the industry have continued to develop short and longer-term strategies for improving quality, service, data and marketing.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.63.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_wqn2">
	Tourists from Overseas
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.63.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100208" speakername="Lord Fearn" colon="" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.63.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.63.4/2" qnum="HL1993">How many tourists arrived in the United Kingdom from (a) the United States, (b) Japan and (c) Europe during the years 1999, 2000 and 2001 to date.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.63.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.63.5/1">Overseas residents visits to the UK (in thousands) were as follows:</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.63.5/4"> <td></td> <td>1999</td> <td>2000</td> <td>2001 January to June</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.63.5/5"> <td>USA</td> <td>3,939</td> <td>4,097</td> <td>1,868</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.63.5/6"> <td>Japan</td> <td>495</td> <td>557</td> <td>188</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.63.5/7"> <td>Europe</td> <td>16,816</td> <td>16,086</td> <td>6,942</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.63.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_wqn3">
	Seaside Resorts
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.63.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100208" speakername="Lord Fearn" colon="" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.63.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.63.7/2" qnum="HL1994">What specific aid has been given to the traditional English seaside resorts in the years 2000 and 2001.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.63.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.63.8/1">The Government believe that the principal responsibility for supporting the infrastructure of British seaside resorts lies with local government, working with other interested parties in the light of a clear vision and strategy for tourism and other economic activity.</p>
	<p pid="a.63.8/2">Resorts have been successful in obtaining various forms of funding in the years 2000 and 2001. For example, there have been 35 successful bids by coastal areas to the Single Regeneration Budget worth a total of &pound;172 million, 28 per cent of the total round 6 award. Some seaside resorts such as Blackpool are also eligible for Neighbourhood Renewal Funding.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.64.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="64"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_wqn4">
	Youth Services and Sports Facilities
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.64.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100463" speakername="Lord Northbourne" colon="" colnum="64"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.64.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.64.1/2" qnum="HL2005">Whether they are committed to securing the provision of playing fields and other sports facilities for all young people, whether or not the users can pay.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.64.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="64"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.64.2/1">This Government are committed to the protection and provision of playing fields for all young people regardless of their ability to pay for these facilities. We recognise that playing fields provide a vital recreational resource for schools and local communities and we have put forward a number of strong measures because too many have been lost in recent years and grassroots sport has suffered as a result.</p>
	<p pid="a.64.2/2">As well as considering further protection measures for playing fields, we are also investing heavily in new and improved playing fields for schools and local communities: &pound;581 million from the National Lottery through the New Opportunities Fund (NOF) will be invested in strengthening the foundation of sport across England by building and refurbishing PE and sports facilities in schools in every local education authority. Innovation will be encouraged, through, for example, groups of local schools sharing facilities, such as playing fields, and making them available to the wider community and attracting partnership funding. Through a separate NOF initiative, Sport England has been tasked with delivering &pound;31 million of lottery money to projects throughout England for the creation and improvement of playing fields and community spaces, as part of NOF's Green Spaces Initiative.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.64.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="64"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_wqn5">
	Youth Services and Sports Facilities
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.64.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100463" speakername="Lord Northbourne" colon="" colnum="64"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.64.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.64.4/2" qnum="HL2006">Whether they will encourage all local authorities to set up and maintain a website showing the names and addresses and a brief description of as many as possible of the youth and sports facilities (statutory, voluntary and private) which are available to 13 to 18 year olds in their area for use by individuals, the Connexions service, parents, schools and those interested in setting up new services in their areas.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.64.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="64"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.64.5/1">Many local authorities already have their own websites which give details of the sporting opportunities available to people of all ages in the locality. The Department for Culture, Media and Sport recently announced plans for a database of sports facilities in England. We are currently discussing with Sport England the possible scope and content of the proposed database and how the project will be taken forward.</p>
	<p pid="a.64.5/2">Sport England's own website provides access to Sports Gateway, a public access portal to a wide variety of sports information over the Internet. Sports Gateway provides access to information on over 6,000 sporting contacts and more than 4,000 sports facilities countrywide; website links provide a further access point for additional information. In the spring of 2002, a sport education courses database comprising 1,200 academic sports courses at institutions around the country will be added. Sport England is also currently piloting Sportsearch, an Internet CD-ROM system designed to enable secondary school-aged young people to match their physical, physiological and skill profiles and preferences with sports they may enjoy. The computer program also provides young people with information about a range of sports and gives them direct access to local club contacts and information through an automated club finder using post codes. Sportsearch will ultimately hold information on all national governing body affiliated clubs in England (approximately 150,000). Initially this information will be targeted at young people but will be extended to provide information for adults in the future.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.65.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_wqn6">
	Youth Services and Sports Facilities
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.65.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100463" speakername="Lord Northbourne" colon="" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.65.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.65.1/2" qnum="HL2007">Whether they will consider imposing on local authorities a duty to provide appropriate youth services and sports facilities available to all 13 to 19 year-olds on a basis which does not exclude any young person simply because they cannot afford to pay for the service or for necessary special clothing and equipment.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.65.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.65.2/1">The provision of youth services and sports facilities is a matter for local authorities to consider. Local authorities are best placed to determine the level of provision required in the light of local needs and the appropriate mixture of public and private provision. The Government have no plans to impose a duty along the lines suggested by the noble Lord.</p>
	<p pid="a.65.2/2">The Department for Culture, Media and Sport is encouraging local authorities to develop local cultural strategies by the end of 2002. These strategies will help local authorities express their own cultural visions and priorities in response to the needs and aspirations of local communities. They will provide a strategic overview, recognising the role of cultural services, including sport, in tackling the wider objectives of social inclusion, regeneration, lifelong learning and creating healthier and safer communities. Cultural strategies will help local authorities to ensure equity and access for everyone to cultural activities.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.65.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_wqn7">
	Youth Services and Sports Facilities
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.65.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100463" speakername="Lord Northbourne" colon="" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.65.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.65.4/2" qnum="HL2008">What studies they have made into the effect of youth services and sports facilities in contributing to the elimination of social exclusion and the reduction of juvenile crime.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.66.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w04.htm#11219w04_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.66.0/1">There is a good deal of evidence to illustrate that the provision of youth, sport and leisure facilities can have a positive impact on tackling social exclusion and reducing crime. The report of Policy Action Team 10, which looked at how to maximise the impact on poor neighbourhoods of government spending and policies on arts, sport and leisure, concluded that arts and sport, cultural and recreational activity can contribute to neighbourhood renewal and make a real difference to health, crime, employment and education in deprived communities.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.0/2">Research undertaken for the Department of Health, Making Research Count, Quality protects research briefing: the value of sports and arts, acknowledges that sport and recreation are regarded as having a significant social cachet among young people and are used as a means of engagement.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.0/3">The evaluation of a programme known as Summer Splash, in a Youth Justice Board report published in November, indicates a significant impact on crime. In the summer of 2000, the Youth Justice Board established 102 projects to provide sports and arts activities for 20,000 13 to 17-year olds in deprived areas of the country. Each of the projects provided five weeks of events combining educational and life classes, such as drug awareness, with video-making, team sports, drama and DJ classes. In areas where the scheme ran, the total crime rate fell by 6 per cent compared with a national rise of 3.8 per cent. Criminal damage fell by 14.2 per cent compared with a national rise of 8 per cent and domestic burglary fell by 26.6 per cent compared with a national fall of 8 per cent. The schemes were supported by the police and engaged local communities, with 35,000 volunteer hours recorded nationally.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.0/4">Youth Works in the North East of England, trained 40 young people in youth/sports leadership awards through supervised activities, with recreational activities organised and facilitated by trained young people. Its report illustrates outcomes of 40 per cent reduction in crime, 70 per cent reduction in calls to the police and &pound;200,000 reduction in vandalism costs.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.0/5">The Positive Futures programme demonstrates joined-up working to achieve a number of complementary objectives for young people. Launched in March 2000, the programme is steered by a national partnership comprising Sport England, the UK Anti-Drugs Co-ordination Unit and the Youth Justice Board and on the ground additional links have been made between a range of bodies, including professional sports clubs, local leisure, youth and social services, the police, schools and universities. The programme, which now operates in 55 targeted areas, aims, &quot;to use sport to reduce anti-social behaviour, crime and drug misuse among 10-16 year olds from selected/disadvantaged neighbourhoods&quot;. Ongoing monitoring and evaluation of the Positive Futures programme will be developed, using a specific management information system database (SIMIS) which is scheduled to become operational by March 2002. Evaluation of Positive Futures is also being assisted by a study undertaken by an independent research company, Leisure Services, which will be available in the new year.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.0/6">A number of studies and reports have been produced which cover the effect of youth services in contributing to the elimination of social exclusion and the reduction of juvenile crime.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.0/7">The Policy Action Team on Young People (PAT 12) looked at how government can improve the way policies and services work for young people. In looking at existing policies, the report found that the need for more consistent coverage and provision for the Youth Service was an issue. The Government have therefore set up the Connexions service. Connexions offers a universal youth support service which will provide advice and guidance to all 13 to 19 year olds. It will improve and enhance a range currently available to young people.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.0/8">The Government White Paper Tackling Drugs Together. A strategy for England 1995-1998 sets out a new drugs strategy for England. A key element of the strategy was the establishment of drug reference groups to assess the nature and scale of local drug misuse problems and advise drug action teams on the apppopriate measures to be taken to tackle them effectively. Youth services were one of the key agencies identified in the White Paper for membership of the drug reference groups.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.0/9">Other reports and studies include:</p>
	<p pid="a.66.0/10">Young women's access to opportunities: external evaluation report:a report by the Young Women's Christian Association which provides an evaluation of a youth and community work programme run by the YWCA in seven locations across England. The programme targets disadvantaged or socially excluded young women and works with them using innovative ways to build up their employability.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.0/11">Doing something positive: youth activities work with disengaged young people: a report by the National Association for the Care and Resettlement of Offenders (NACRO) which illustrates its experience and success in managing its youth activities units and other projects working with young people.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.0/12">Making a difference: preventing crime through youth activity: a report which examines evidence from a range of youth activity projects run by NACRO and other organisations which illustrate the potential of youth work for the prevention of crime.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.67.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="67"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_wqn0">
	Museums: Long-term Loan of Exhibits
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.67.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100016" speakername="Baroness Anelay of St Johns" colon="" colnum="67"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.67.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.67.1/2" qnum="HL2082">What criteria are applied by the Department for Culture, Media and Sport to applications by national museums and galleries which wish to lend exhibits to individuals or museums and galleries overseas on a long-term basis in exchange for payment; and</p>
	<p pid="a.67.1/3" qnum="HL2083">Whether they have received an application from the Royal Armouries Museum, or from any other national museum or gallery, to lend exhibits overseas on a long-term basis in exchange for payment; if so, what applications have been received; and when they were lodged.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.68.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.68.0/1">My department is waiting to receive a business case from the Royal Armouries setting out its plans for an arrangement with the Owsley Brown Frazier Historical Arms Museum in Louisville, Kentucky, USA. The proposal involves the long-term loan of items from the Royal Armouries under Section 21 of the National Heritage Act 1983 in exchange for payments. No similar proposals to lend exhibits overseas on a long-term basis in exchange for payment have been received from other bodies sponsored by my department.</p>
	<p pid="a.68.0/2">National museums and galleries which wish to lend exhibits overseas are required to comply with the relevant legislation on the lending of exhibits. My department may call in for approval novel proposals, for example lending exhibits on a long-term basis in exchange for payment, to ensure that there is no risk to the collection and that value for money has been properly assessed.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.68.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_wqn1">
	Parliamentary Questions
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.68.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100339" speakername="Lord Jopling" colon="" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.68.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.68.2/2" qnum="HL1404">What is the average length of time over the last month for Answers to be given to Written Questions from the time the Questions were put down, comparing the House of Lords and the House of Commons; and</p>
	<p pid="a.68.2/3" qnum="HL1681">What since May 1997 is the longest period between the tabling of a Question for Written Answer and its being answered by a Minister, giving the relevant dates; and</p>
	<p pid="a.68.2/4" qnum="HL1682">Whether the time within which Questions for Written Answer are to be answered is the same for the House of Commons and the House of Lords; and if not, what is the difference and justification; and</p>
	<p pid="a.68.2/5" qnum="HL1683">What instructions have been issued to civil servants with regard to the urgency given to answering Questions for Written Answer tabled by members of the House of Lords compared with members of the House of Commons.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.68.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.68.3/1">Information on the average length of time for Answers to be given to Written Questions, comparing the House of Lords and the House of Commons, is not available, which I regret. My office has commissioned a new computer database to help track and monitor performance on Answers to Written Questions tabled by noble Lords. The database should be in operation early in the new year and will help my office to chase progress on late Answers and provide more helpful replies in future to the Questions raised on this occasion.</p>
	<p pid="a.68.3/2">On the question of the longest period between the tabling of a Question for Written Answer and it being answered, the Minute Room has advised that a Question tabled by Lord Waverley in 1998 took eight months for the Government to issue a reply.</p>
	<p pid="a.68.3/3">On the issue of timescales for answering Questions in the House of Commons and the House of Lords, the systems are of course very different. Written Questions in the House of Commons are tabled to individual Ministers for answer either on a Named Day or Ordinary Written where the aim is to reply within seven days. In the House of Lords, Questions are tabled to &quot;Her Majesty's Government&quot; and are expected to be answered within 14 days. The reason for the longer deadline in the House of Lords is to reflect the fact that Questions can be more wide ranging in the Lords as they are tabled to Her Majesty's Government rather than a specific Minister.</p>
	<p pid="a.68.3/4">The time taken to reply to Parliamentary Questions is an issue that concerns me and my ministerial colleagues. I have reminded colleagues that Questions in the House of Lords are expected to be answered within a fortnight. In addition, Sir Richard Wilson has written to departments reminding them of the need for timely and helpful answers to Parliamentary Questions in both Houses.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.69.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_wqn2">
	Northern Ireland Bill of Rights
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.69.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.69.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.69.1/2" qnum="HL1970">What their response is to the remarks of the Chief Commissoner, Professor Brice Dickson, for the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission at a conference on human rights at Queen's University Belfast on Saturday 8 December when he said the current draft Human Rights Bill, as devised by the commission, needed to be considerably changed, with many sections left out, and that much more time for consultation was required.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.69.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.69.2/1">The way the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission carries out its consultation on the scope for a Bill of Rights is a matter for the commission.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.69.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_wqn3">
	Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.69.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.69.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.69.4/2" qnum="HL1998">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Privy seal on 26 November (WA 18) about the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission, what they understand by consultation conducted by a public body; and whether &quot;education and awareness-raising&quot; are normal practices for public bodies consulting the public.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.69.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.69.5/1">The way the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission carries out any consultation is a matter for the commission itself.</p>
	<p pid="a.69.5/2">Section 69(6) of the Northern Ireland Act 1998 places a specific duty on that commission to promote understanding and awareness of the importance of human rights in Northern Ireland; and for this purpose it may, among other things, undertake educational activities.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.70.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_wqn4">
	Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.70.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.70.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.70.1/2" qnum="HL2037">Further to the Written Answer [HL1765 by the Lord Privy Seal on 11 December (WA 199&ndash;200), whether the commission represents the entire community in Northern Ireland.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.70.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.70.2/1">In terms of its scope and purpose, the commission's remit extends to the entire community in Northern Ireland. In terms of its membership, the Northern Ireland Act 1998 requires the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland &quot;as far as practicable [to] secure that the Commissioners, as a group, are representative of the community in Northern Ireland&quot;. The Government remain satisfied that the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland has fulfilled that statutory requirement.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.70.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_wqn5">
	Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.70.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.70.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.70.4/2" qnum="HL2038">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Privy Seal on 11 December (WA 198&ndash;199) which indicated that five of the commissioners appointed to the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission are appointed for three years and three are appointed for two years, whether they will indicate which commissioners fall into each appointment period, and why.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.70.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.70.5/1">Of the commissioners who sought reappointment to the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission, those appointed for three years were Professor Brice Dickson, Mrs Margaret-Ann Dinsmore, Mr Tom Donnelly, Professor Tom Hadden and Ms Paddy Kelly. Those appointed for two years were the Reverend Harold Good, Ms Inez McCormack and Mr Frank McGuinness. A decision on the position of Professor Christine Bell has, at her own request, been deferred until the new year.</p>
	<p pid="a.70.5/2">The Secretary of State for Northern Ireland decided to vary the length of the various appointments to the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission to stagger the times at which the commissioners would need to be replaced or reappointed in future. He wanted to ensure both an element of continuity within the commission and a regular turnover in membership.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.70.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_wqn6">
	Northern Ireland: Baton Rounds
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.70.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.70.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.70.7/2" qnum="HL2001">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Privy Seal on 3 December (WA 77&ndash;78), whether the Chief Commissioner of the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission has now stated that they accept the statement of the Chief Constable of the Police Service of Northern Ireland that baton rounds are not used for the purposes of crowd control.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.71.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.71.0/1">I refer the noble Lord to the letter sent to him by the Chief Commissioner of the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission dated <phrase class="date" code="">5 December</phrase> in reply to a previous Question (WA 77&ndash;78), a copy of which was also placed in the Library of the House of Lords.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.71.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_wqn7">
	Northern Ireland Police Service Recruitment
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.71.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100546" speakername="Lord Rogan" colon="" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.71.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.71.2/2" qnum="HL1869">Which publications in Great Britain carried advertisements for (a) the first and (b) the second recruitment competitions to the Police Service of Northern Ireland; and</p>
	<p pid="a.71.2/3" qnum="HL1870">Which (i) terrestrial and (ii) satellite television channels carried advertisements for (a) the first and (b) the second recruitment competitions to the Police Service of Northern Ireland.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.71.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w05.htm#11219w05_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.71.3/1">The following publications in Great Britain carried recruitment advertisements for the Police Service of Northern Ireland recruitment competitions:</p>
	<p pid="a.71.3/2" class="indent">First Competition: Glasgow Evening Herald, Edinburgh Evening News, Manchester Evening News,</p>
	<p pid="a.71.3/3">Birmingham Evening Mail,</p>
	<p pid="a.71.3/4">Evening Standard (London),</p>
	<p pid="a.71.3/5">Liverpool Echo.</p>
	<p pid="a.71.3/6" class="indent">Second Competition: The Universe,</p>
	<p pid="a.71.3/7">The Catholic Times,</p>
	<p pid="a.71.3/8">The Irish Post,</p>
	<p pid="a.71.3/9">The Irish World,</p>
	<p pid="a.71.3/10">The Police Review.</p>
	<p pid="a.71.3/11">The advertisement has featured on the following television channels:</p>
	<p pid="a.71.3/12" class="indent">First Competition: Ulster Television, Channel 4, Channel 9 (North West Ireland), Tara Television (Satellite).</p>
	<p pid="a.71.3/13" class="indent">Second Competition: Ulster Television, Channel 4,</p>
	<p pid="a.71.3/14">Channel 9</p>
	<p pid="a.71.3/15">(North West Ireland), Radio Telefis Eireann 1, Network 2.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.71.4" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_wqn0">
	Northern Ireland Police Service Recruitment
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.71.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100546" speakername="Lord Rogan" colon="" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.71.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.71.5/2" qnum="HL1871">On what basis the cost-benefit analysis by the independent recruitment agent following the first recruitment competition to the Police Service of Northern Ireland was carried out; and</p>
	<p pid="a.71.5/3" qnum="HL1872">How much money was spent conducting the cost-benefit analysis carried out by the independent recruitment agent following the first recruitment competition to the Police Service of Northern Ireland.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.72.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.72.0/1">The cost-benefit analysis in respect of the advertising strategy was carried out by Consensia on the basis of number of applicants. The analysis was undertaken as part of the agreed contract management arrangements and there was no specific cost to the Chief Constable.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.72.1" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_wqn1">
	Northern Ireland Police Service Recruitment
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.72.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100546" speakername="Lord Rogan" colon="" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.72.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.72.2/2" qnum="HL1873">Whether they will provide a breakdown of the advertising costs of (a) the first and (b) the second recruitment competitions to the Police Service of Northern Ireland; and</p>
	<p pid="a.72.2/3" qnum="HL1874">How much money was spent advertising (a) the first and (b) the second recruitment competitions to the Police Service of Northern Ireland in (i) Northern Ireland; (ii) Great Britain; (iii) the Republic of Ireland; and (iv) outside the British Isles.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.72.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.72.3/1">The cost of advertising in each recruitment competition by geographical area was as follows:</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.72.3/4"> <td></td> <td>First Competition &pound;</td> <td>Second Competition &pound;</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.3/5"> <td>Northern Ireland</td> <td>241,840</td> <td>126,575</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.3/6"> <td>Great Britain</td> <td>46,730</td> <td>15,600</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.3/7"> <td>Republic of Ireland</td> <td>31,964</td> <td>70,175</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.3/8"> <td>Outside British Isles</td> <td>7,620</td> <td>8,602</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.3/9"> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.3/10"> <td>Total</td> <td>328,154</td> <td>220,852</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.72.3/13">All figures are exclusive of VAT.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.72.4" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_wqn2">
	Northern Ireland Police Service Recruitment
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.72.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.72.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.72.5/2" qnum="HL1973">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Privy Seal on 5 December (WA 139), whether the Answer means that the Northern Ireland Office did not conduct, or commission, an independent study of the relationship between symbols and recruitment before it chose to accept the Patten report on policing.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.72.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.72.6/1">The Patten report was itself an independent study on policing which based its findings on meetings with a wide range of interested parties and members of the public. As the report itself makes clear, more than 10,000 people attended the public meetings the commission held over 60 days. In addition, the commission appointed consultants to undertake an extensive public attitude survey: this survey used a random sample of over 1,000 adults in Northern Ireland. The commission also took account of attitude surveys carried out on behalf of others such as the Police Authority.</p>
	<p pid="a.72.6/2">The Northern Ireland Office did not itself conduct or commission a further survey of the relationship between symbols and recruitment.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.73.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="73"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_wqn3">
	Devolved Administrations: Memorandum of Understanding
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.73.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100424" speakername="Lord Merlyn-Rees" colon="" colnum="73"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.73.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.73.1/2" qnum="HL2106">What plans there are to publish a revised edition of the memorandum of understanding between the UK Government and the devolved administrations.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.73.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100395" speakername="Lord Macdonald of Tradeston" colon=":" colnum="73"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.73.2/1">We are publishing today, as Cm 5240, a revised edition of the memorandum of understanding and supplementary agreements between the UK Government, Scottish Ministers, the Cabinet of the National Assembly for Wales and the Northern Ireland Executive Committee. Copies of this document have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses and will be made available on the Cabinet Office website shortly.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.73.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="73"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_wqn4">
	Scottish Salmon Farms
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.73.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100420" speakername="Lord Mason of Barnsley" colon="" colnum="73"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.73.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.73.4/2" qnum="HL1821">What has been the output of the Scottish salmon farms in each of the last five years; and</p>
	<p pid="a.73.4/3" qnum="HL1823">Whether they have been in consultation with the Salmon and Trout Association for information from their surveys regarding mass escapes from Scottish fish farms; and whether it has been established that interbreeding has taken place between the farmed and wild salmon; and</p>
	<p pid="a.73.4/4" qnum="HL1836">How many salmon farms have been found to be using toxic chemicals in the production of salmon; and what is their latest assessment of the environmental damage caused by pollution from salmon farming; and</p>
	<p pid="a.73.4/5" qnum="HL1837">To what extent sea lice are damaging the Scottish salmon farming industry; what new strategies have been introduced to combat this predation; and, whether, and to what extent, Invermectin is being used as a control agent; and</p>
	<p pid="a.73.4/6" qnum="HL1838">What is the present method of treating effluent from fish farms; what tonnage is dealt with annually; and how effective present methods are proving to be; and</p>
	<p pid="a.73.4/7" qnum="HL1839">What are the names of the foreign and United Kingdom companies which are in ownership of the Scottish fish farming industry, giving in each case their percentage share of the industry; and</p>
	<p pid="a.73.4/8" qnum="1840">Whether salmon anaemia has been totally eradicated in all the salmon farms in Scotland; what lessons have been learnt since the last outbreak; and what, if any, extra precautions have been taken to safeguard salmon stocks; and [GL</p>
	<p pid="a.73.4/9" qnum="HL1841">In connection with salmon anaemia in Scotland, how many fish health inspectors are now employed; and how regularly inspections are made; and</p>
	<p pid="a.73.4/10" qnum="HL1883">Whether they will provide a list of the organic salmon fish farms in Scotland; and what is the total annual production of these farms.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.74.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="74"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.74.0/1">These are matters for the Scottish Executive and the noble Lord may wish to write to them about the issues involved.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.74.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="74"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_wqn5">
	Wales: Children's Society Service
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.74.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100107" speakername="Lord Carlile of Berriew" colon="" colnum="74"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.74.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.74.2/2" qnum="HL1347">Whether they have any proposals to replace services and the funding of services run by the Children's Society in Wales following the recently announced decision of the Children's Society to cease functioning in Wales.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.74.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100206" speakername="Baroness Farrington of Ribbleton" colon=":" colnum="74"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.74.3/1">It is for the National Assembly for Wales to take the lead in resolving this problem.</p>
	<p pid="a.74.3/2">Jane Hutt, Assembly Minister for Health and Social Services, has asked Children in Wales to convene a task force to secure the continuation of as many as possible of the services currently provided by the society.</p>
	<p pid="a.74.3/3">The task force is being chaired by Christine Walby, a trustee of Children in Wales and Honorary Research Fellow at the University of Wales, Swansea. Local authorities, voluntary organisations, the Church in Wales and staff groups are all represented on the task force, which is expected to report early in the new year.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.74.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="74"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_wqn6">
	Houses of Parliament: Energy Consumption
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.74.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100427" speakername="Baroness Miller of Chilthorne Domer" colon="" colnum="74"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.74.5/1">asked the Chairman of Committees:</p>
	<p pid="a.74.5/2" qnum="HL1756">What was the energy consumption of the Houses of Parliament in 1996, 1997, 1999 and 2000.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-12-19a.74.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100644" speakername="Lord Tordoff" colon=":" colnum="74"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011219/text/11219w06.htm#11219w06_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.74.6/1">The size of the parliamentary estate has increased substantially in recent years, and this is reflected in increased energy consumption. Consumption is calculated each financial, rather than each calendar, year. Figures for the last five completed years are given below:</p>
	<p pid="a.74.6/2" class="indent">1996&ndash;97: 45.4 million KWhrs</p>
	<p pid="a.74.6/3" class="indent">1997&ndash;98: 47.4 million KWhrs</p>
	<p pid="a.74.6/4" class="indent">1998&ndash;99: 49.7 million KWhrs</p>
	<p pid="a.74.6/5" class="indent">1999&ndash;2000: 50.1 million KWhrs</p>
	<p pid="a.74.6/6" class="indent">2000&ndash;01: 55 million KWhrs</p>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

