<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.59.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="59"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_wqn0">
	Universal Primary Education
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.59.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100341" speakername="Lord Judd" colon="" colnum="59"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.59.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.59.1/2" qnum="HL1387">Whether current trends will mean that the 1995 United Nations Social Summit target of free universal education for all children by 2015 will be achieved; if not, by how big a gap it will be missed; and what action they are taking to correct any inadquate trends.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.59.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="59"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.59.2/1">There are widely different levels of progress against the millennium development goal of achieving universal primary education (UPE) by 2015. In sub-Saharan Africa an additional 88 million children will need to be enrolled in school between 1997 and 2015. This requires a threefold improvement in the rate of expansion achieved from 1990&ndash;97. If the current rate of enrolment increase were to be maintained, less than half of the 43 countries would achieve even a gross enrolment rate of 100 per cent by 2015. Ten times the previous rate of increase will be needed in countries such as Angola, Burundi, Democratic Republic of the Congo (DRC), Liberia and Somalia. In South and West Asia it is estimated that an additional 40 million children will need to be enrolled to achieve the UPE target and that this will require the same pace of enrolment increase that was achieved from 1990 to 1997.</p>
	<p pid="a.59.2/2">Achieving UPE requires reform and action at the country level. The international community committed itself in the Dakar Framework for Action that Xno countries seriously committed to education for all will be thwarted in their achievement of this goal by a lack of resources&quot;. At the Education for All High-Level Group meeting convened by UNESCO's Director-General in Paris last month, the Secretary of State for International Development called for change in national and international efforts to achieve UPE by 2015. She presented DFID's paper Children out of School which identifies the different circumstances of children who are not in school and proposes an eight-point plan of action for accelerating progress towards the 2015 target.</p>
	<p pid="a.59.2/3">The Government give high priority to addressing this challenge. We believe that UPE can be achieved by 2015 if the lessons of the past are learned and if governments in developing countries put in place the right policies and receive appropriate external assistance. We have committed over &pound;600 million to support the development of primary education since 1997. We will do more.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.60.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_wqn1">
	M4 Hostage Situation: Police Involvement
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.60.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100481" speakername="Lord Palmer" colon="" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.60.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.60.1/2" qnum="HL917">How many police, and from how many forces, were involved in the recent hostage situation which culminated in the temporary closure of part of the M4 on 20 to 21 October; and at what cost.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.60.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.60.2/1">The hostage situation was a complex operation undertaken at extremely short notice. The Chief Constable of Wiltshire has informed me that the force will be holding a debriefing meeting on <phrase class="date" code="2001-12-18">18 December</phrase> to review the operation. When that meeting has taken place the numbers of officers involved in the situation, from how many forces and the cost will be known. I will write to the noble Lord when the information is available.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.60.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_wqn2">
	European Arrest Warrant: XXenophobia&quot;
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.60.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100491" speakername="Lord Pearson of Rannoch" colon="" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.60.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.60.4/2" qnum="HL1518">Further to the question asked by Lord Pearson of Rannoch on 19 November (HL Deb, col. 978), how they define the crime of Xxenophobia&quot; as listed in Article 2 of the proposed European Union arrest warrant directive.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.60.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.60.5/1">The term Xracism and xenophobia&quot; as listed in Article 2 of the framework decision on the European arrest warrant is a generic description. It is a decision for the issuing state as to how it frames the offence under its national law when it makes a request under a European arrest warrant.</p>
	<p pid="a.60.5/2">If the United Kingdom were making an extradition request for offences under the heading of Xracism and xenophobia&quot;, we would do so in terms of our law on incitement to racial hatred, racially aggravated offences and racial discrimination under the Race Relations Act, where a sentence of at least 12 months applied. All of these offences are drafted in terms of behaviour directed against members of a racial group. A racial group is defined as a group of persons by reference to colour, race, nationality (including citizenship) or ethnic or national origins. In that sense our existing race hate laws cover hatred motivated by xenophobia.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.60.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_wqn3">
	Terrorism Act 2000: Detention
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.60.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.60.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.60.7/2" qnum="HL1563">How many persons have been detained and questioned under the Terrorism Act 2000 (a) since 11 September and (b) in the year before that date; and what were the outcomes in terms of releases, prosecutions, convictions and sentences.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.60.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.60.8/1">There have been a total of 53 arrests under the Terrorism Act 2000 since <phrase class="date" code="2001-09-11">11 September</phrase>. In the year previous there were 43 arrests under terrorist legislation (Prevention of Terrorism Act 1989 prior to <phrase class="date" code="2001-02-19">19 February</phrase> and Terrorism Act 2000 post this date). These can be broken down to the following results:</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.60.8/4"> <td></td> <td>Since 11 Sept</td> <td>Sept 2000&mdash;Sept 2001</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.8/5"> <td>Charged with terrorist related  offences</td> <td>6</td> <td>16</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.8/6"> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.8/7"> <td>Undergoing extradition  proceedings</td> <td>1</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.8/8"> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.8/9"> <td>Charged with other criminal  offences</td> <td>3</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.8/10"> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.8/11"> <td>Bailed for further enquiries into  criminal matters</td> <td>5</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.8/12"> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.8/13"> <td>Released into custody of HM  Immigration Service</td> <td>14</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.8/14"> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.8/15"> <td>Released without charge</td> <td>24</td> <td>21</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.8/16"> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.60.8/17"> <td>Total</td> <td>53</td> <td>43</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.61.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="61"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_wqn4">
	Criminal Courts: District Tier Proposal
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.61.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100107" speakername="Lord Carlile of Berriew" colon="" colnum="61"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.61.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.61.1/2" qnum="HL1348">Whether, in the event of the district tier of criminal courts being created as recommended by Lord Justice Auld, measures would be introduced to reimburse magistrates for lost earnings to enable as wide a cross section of justices as possible to hear cases.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.61.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100325" speakername="Lord Irvine of Lairg" colon=":" colnum="61"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.61.2/1">Justices may already claim some compensation for loss of earnings. If the Government accept Lord Justice Auld's recommendation for a district division, it is not clear that a different kind of allowance would be needed. No decision will be taken on the recommendation for a district division until after the end of the period for public comment.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.61.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="61"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_wqn5">
	Jurors and District Judges: Allowances
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.61.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100107" speakername="Lord Carlile of Berriew" colon="" colnum="61"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.61.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.61.4/2" qnum="HL1349">What is the average cost of allowances and any other payments made to (a) a juror and (b) a district judge in the last financial year for which figures are available.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.61.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100325" speakername="Lord Irvine of Lairg" colon=":" colnum="61"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_spmin3">
	<p pid="a.61.5/1">Jurors can claim financial loss allowance, travel and subsistence, within specified maxima, for the time they spend at court. The payments made will vary according to the personal circumstances of each individual. There is no information available on the number of people who actually serve on juries each year and so it is not possible to produce an average figure.</p>
	<p pid="a.61.5/2">The current salary for district judges (magistrates' courts) and district judges (county courts) is &pound;79,767. All district judges appointed to the London area receive an additional London allowance of &pound;2,000 and a London salary lead of &pound;2,000. District judges may, in certain circumstances, claim travel and night subsistence allowances from my department when sitting away from their principal court. District judges (magistrates' courts) may also receive expenses from their relevant magistrates' courts committee (MCC) when travelling within the MCC area to which they are assigned or from the senior district judge's office when travelling outside their MCC area at the request of the senior district judge (chief magistrate). Information about these is not held centrally by my department. It is not possible, therefore, to produce an average figure.</p>
	<p pid="a.61.5/3">Details of the rates payable to both jurors and district judges will be placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.62.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_wqn6">
	Freedom of Information Act: Implementation
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.62.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100432" speakername="Lord Mitchell" colon="" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.62.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.62.1/2" qnum="HL1747">When the Lord Chancellor intends to report to Parliament his proposals for bringing fully into force those provisions of the Freedom of Information Act 2000 which are not yet in force.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.62.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100325" speakername="Lord Irvine of Lairg" colon=":" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_spmin4">
	<p pid="a.62.2/1">I have today laid my Report on the Implementation of the Freedom of Information Act 2000 before both Houses. Copies of the report have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.62.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_wqn7">
	Lord Chancellor's Department DEL
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.62.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100677" speakername="Lord Wedderburn of Charlton" colon="" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.62.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.62.4/2" qnum="HL1748">Whether they have any proposals to amend the Lord Chancellor's Department departmental expenditure limit and running costs limits for 2001&ndash;02.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.62.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100325" speakername="Lord Irvine of Lairg" colon=":" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w01.htm#11129w01_spmin5">
	<p pid="a.62.5/1">Subject to parliamentary approval of the necessary Request for Resources 1, the Lord Chancellor's Department departmental expenditure limit for 2001&ndash;02 will be increased by &pound;22,034,000 from &pound;2,732,900,000 to &pound;2,754,934,000. The increase is the net effect of take up of end year flexibility entitlement of: &pound;9,000,000 in respect of Capital Modernisation Fund; &pound;1,031,000 in respect of DEL capital expenditure; &pound;1,355,000 in respect of an award from the Invest to Modernise Fund; &pound;408,000 in respect of the Invest to Save Budget; awards from the Capital Modernisation Fund totalling &pound;1,888,000 in respect of new projects and &pound;1,174,000 from the Invest to Modernise Fund; transfers in respect of transfers of business from the Home Office in the sum of &pound;614,000; from the Department for Work and Pensions in the sum of &pound;20,000; from the Department for Transport, Local Government and the Regions in the sum of &pound;100,000 and from the Ministry of Defence in the sum of &pound;176,000. Transfers of business arising from the machinery of government changes of &pound;406,000 from the Cabinet Office and &pound;5,862,000 from the Home Office are also included in this supplementary estimate.</p>
	<p pid="a.62.5/2">The administration cost limit for the Lord Chancellor's Department Request for Resources 1 will be increased by &pound;5,344,000 from &pound;612,786,000 to &pound;618,130,000. The increase is caused by take up of end year flexibility entitlement of &pound;1,355,000; an award of &pound;1,174,000 from the Invest to Modernise Fund; transfers in respect of transfers of business from the Home Office in the sum of &pound;480,000; from the Ministry of Defence in the sum of &pound;176,000; from the Department for Transport, Local Government and the Regions in the sum of &pound;100,000 and to the Department for Work and Pensions in the sum of &pound;200,000. Transfers of business arising from the machinery of government changes of &pound;406,000 from the Cabinet Office and &pound;1,853,000 from the Home Office are also included in this supplementary estimate.</p>
	<p pid="a.62.5/3">The increases will be offset by transfers from the departmental expenditure limits of the Home Office, Department for Work and Pensions, Department for Transport, Local Government and the Regions, and the Ministry of Defence, take up of end year flexibility entitlement, an award from the Invest to Modernise Fund and awards from the Capital Modernisation Fund and will not therefore add to the planned total of public expenditure.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.63.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn0">
	Court Service Annual Report
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.63.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100685" speakername="Baroness Wilkins" colon="" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.63.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.63.1/2" qnum="HL1749">When they intend to publish the Court Service annual report for 2000&ndash;01.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.63.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100325" speakername="Lord Irvine of Lairg" colon=":" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.63.2/1">The Court Service annual report for 2000&ndash;01 has been published today and copies have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.63.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn1">
	Manchester to London: Non-regulated Train Fares
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.63.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100068" speakername="Lord Bradshaw" colon="" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.63.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.63.4/2" qnum="HL1405">By what amount the various categories of unregulated train fares have increased between Manchester and London since the railway was privatised, comparing them with the retail prices index.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.63.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.63.5/1">Fares regulation in franchise agreements is based on the prices of British Rail fares in the summer of 1995, the year when the first franchises were let. The table below shows the price of non-regulated fares between Manchester and London in 1995 against present prices. Virgin Trains which operates services from Manchester to London, did not begin running the franchise until March 1997. Accumulative RPI since June 1995 is 20.2 per cent.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.63.5/4"> <td>Fare</td> <td>June 1995</td> <td>June 2001</td> <td>% Increase</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.63.5/5"> <td>First Class Open (Single)</td> <td>&pound;67.00</td> <td>&pound;126.00</td> <td>88%</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.63.5/6"> <td>First Class Open (Return)</td> <td>&pound;134.00</td> <td>&pound;252.00</td> <td>88%</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.63.5/7"> <td>Standard Open (Single)</td> <td>&pound;50.00</td> <td>&pound;92.50</td> <td>85%</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.63.5/8"> <td>Standard Open (Return)</td> <td>&pound;96.00</td> <td>&pound;164.00</td> <td>71%</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.63.5/9"> <td>Super Saver (Single)*</td> <td>&pound;32.00</td> <td>&pound;46.00</td> <td>44%</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.63.5/10"> <td>Super Saver (Return)*</td> <td>&pound;33.00</td> <td>&pound;47.00</td> <td>42%</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.63.5/13">*routeing has changed from Xany reasonable&quot; to Xvia Chesterfield&quot;. A number of other non-regulated fares have been introduced in the intervening period, the cheapest of which allows return travel for &pound;20. Regulated fares have been pegged to RP1-1 per cent since January 1999.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.64.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="64"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn2">
	London Underground Performance Regime
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.64.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100068" speakername="Lord Bradshaw" colon="" colnum="64"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.64.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.64.1/2" qnum="HL1462">Given the past experience of railways in Britain, what is their estimate of the number of people required for, and the cost of, the operation of the performance regime proposed for London Underground.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.64.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="64"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.64.2/1">It is for London Underground to determine the appropriate number of staff to operate the performance regime for the Tube modernisation contracts and to set the relevant budgets.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.64.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="64"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn3">
	London Underground Performance Regime
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.64.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100068" speakername="Lord Bradshaw" colon="" colnum="64"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.64.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.64.4/2" qnum="HL1463">Whether there will have to be a real performance improvement on London Underground before the three infracos make any money from the performance regimes being considered for the system; and</p>
	<p pid="a.64.4/3" qnum="HL1464">Whether profits of the three infracos proposed for London Underground will be dependent upon improved performance on the Underground.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.64.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="64"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.64.5/1">The performance regime for the Government's Tube modernisation plans has been carefully designed to ensure that the private sector infrastructure companies are incentivised to deliver significant improvements in performance. Bidders for the Tube modernisation contracts have responded to this by targeting real and sustained improvements, with plans to invest at least &pound;13 billion in the Tube over the first 15 years. If the private sector infrastructure companies fail to meet the levels of performance they are targeting, this will have a direct impact on the payments they receive from London Underground. Shareholders will receive the financial return they expect only if we receive the performance improvements we expect.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.65.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn4">
	Best Value Inspection Service
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.65.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100175" speakername="Lord Dixon" colon="" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.65.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.65.1/2" qnum="HL1497">How many staff are employed at the Best Value Inspection Service audit commission nationally and in its office in the northern region based at Killingbeck, Leeds.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.65.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.65.2/1">The Best Value Inspection Service employs 493 staff nationally; 104 of these staff are based in the northern region.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.65.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn5">
	Best Value Inspection Service
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.65.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100175" speakername="Lord Dixon" colon="" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.65.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.65.4/2" qnum="HL1498">What is the total cost of the Best Value Inspection Service audit commission nationally and in its northern region office based at Killingbeck, Leeds.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.65.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.65.5/1">The Best Value Inspection Service costs for November 2001 to October 2002 are estimated at &pound;44 million; of this &pound;7.8 million is the estimated cost for the northern region during this period.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.65.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn6">
	Building Regulations: Uncontrolled Fires
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.65.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100310" speakername="Lord Howie of Troon" colon="" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.65.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.65.7/2" qnum="HL1559">Whether the Building Regulations for England and Wales offer adequate protection from the structural collapse of buildings caused by uncontrolled fires.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.65.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.65.8/1">The Building Regulations require that a building shall be designed and constructed so that in the event of fire its stability will be maintained for a reasonable period.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.65.9" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn7">
	Building Regulations: Uncontrolled Fires
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.65.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100310" speakername="Lord Howie of Troon" colon="" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.65.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.65.10/2" qnum="HL1560">Whether the Building Regulations for England and Wales fully comply with all parts of Essential Requirement 2 (Safety in Case of Fire) contained in Annex 1 to the Construction Products Directive (Council Directive 89/106/EEC).</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.65.11" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.65.11/1">The Building Regulations take into account all aspects of Essential Requirement 2, except that they do not address the issue of smoke generation from products used within buildings. This is because fire safety is achieved through other means such as the installation of fire resisting construction to protect escape routes from smoke and fire. The Construction Products Directive does not require individual member states to regulate for all of the aspects contained within the essential requirements.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.66.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn8">
	Building Regulations: Uncontrolled Fires
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.66.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100310" speakername="Lord Howie of Troon" colon="" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.66.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/2" qnum="HL1561">What steps they are taking to assess the results of the concrete frame fire test conducted by the Building Research Establishment on 26 September at Cardington; and whether they will ensure that these results are made public.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.66.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.66.2/1">This particular fire test was privately funded and was not commissioned by the Government. Although my department has been interested to see the results of the test and will consider the implications, as it was not involved in the project we cannot insist on involvement with the assessment of results or that the results be made public.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.66.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn9">
	Farm (Safety) Awareness Days
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.66.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100098" speakername="Baroness Byford" colon="" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn9">
	<p pid="a.66.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.66.4/2" qnum="HL1564">How much the Health and Safety Executive farm awareness days will cost per attendee; and who will pay for each attendance at such an event.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.66.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.66.5/1">The Health and Safety Executive's farm (safety) awareness days are planned to be attended by 300 to 400 farmers. Actual attendance varies but is normally between these figures. The cost of running each event is about &pound;8,500. The cost per attendee, therefore, varies from approximately &pound;21 to &pound;28.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.5/2">The cost of these events is largely met by the Health and Safety Executive but each includes a &pound;500 sponsorship contribution from the insurance company, National Farmers Union Mutual.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.5/3">It is intended that these events will continue into 2002&ndash;03.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.66.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn10">
	Recyclable Waste
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.66.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100241" speakername="Lord Glentoran" colon="" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn10">
	<p pid="a.66.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.66.7/2" qnum="HL1556">Whether the United Kingdom will face fines from 2010 onwards if it fails to comply with the European Union laws regarding the recycling of household waste; and whether they will introduce measures to increase the collection of recyclable waste on the doorstep.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.66.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.66.8/1">The EC Landfill Directive requires the United Kingdom, by 2010, to reduce the amount of biodegradable municipal waste going to landfill to 75 per cent of the total amount of biodegradable municipal waste produced in 1995, and then to 50 per cent by 2013 and 35 per cent by 2020. Failure to meet the target will place the UK in breach of the directive. However, any sanctions to be taken in the case of a failure to meet the target would be a matter for the European Commission.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.8/2">Waste Strategy 2000 sets out targets for doubling the recycling and composting of household waste in three years and nearly tripling it in five years in order to ensure that Landfill Directive targets are met. We have underpinned these targets by setting statutory performance standards for each local authority to achieve by 2003&ndash;04 and 2005&ndash;06.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.8/3">Kerbside collection of recyclables can be a very effective means of increasing recycling rates but it is for individual waste collection authorities to determine how best to meet their statutory recycling targets.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.67.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="67"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn11">
	Open Access for the Countryside
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.67.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100098" speakername="Baroness Byford" colon="" colnum="67"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_wqn11">
	<p pid="a.67.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.67.1/2" qnum="HL1565">Further to the Written Answer by Lord Whitty on 22 May 2000 (WA 44), what methodologies they have put in place to measure the effect of open access on the environment and on those who earn their living from the land.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.67.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="67"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w02.htm#11129w02_spnew8">
	<p pid="a.67.2/1">The Countryside Agency has recently advertised in the European Journal for expressions of interest in a contract to monitor the benefits and impacts of access on the way people use the countryside for recreation, rural economies (and the activities that contribute to them) and the environment.</p>
	<p pid="a.67.2/2">In addition, English Nature (EN) set up a workshop earlier this year in which leading authorities on access-related disturbance have identified core priorities for further research and monitoring. The Access Scientific Research and Monitoring Group, comprising representatives from EN, the agency, the Royal Society for the Protection of Birds, the Countryside Council for Wales, the Game Conservancy Trust and others, are co-ordinating research and monitoring priorities identified in the workshop. The group has already commissioned work on impacts on woodlarks and nightjars and on rare reptiles and is now considering project proposals for impacts on a wide range of other species associated with access land.</p>
	<p pid="a.67.2/3">The department and other bodies with functions under Part I of the Countryside and Rights of Way Act 2000 will have regard to the findings of these studies in implementing the provisions of the Act.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.67.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="67"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn0">
	Countryside Stewardship Claims
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.67.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100098" speakername="Baroness Byford" colon="" colnum="67"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.67.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.67.4/2" qnum="0">Further to the Written Answer by Baroness Hayman on 20 February (WA 88), what proportion of stewardship payments are overdue:</p>
	<p pid="a.67.4/3" qnum="0">(a) by number; and</p>
	<p pid="a.67.4/4" qnum="0">(b) by value;</p>
	<p pid="a.67.4/5" qnum="HL1566">and by how much they are overdue.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.68.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.68.0/1">Of the Countryside Stewardship claims that were outstanding at the date of the previous written answer, there are 26 which are still partly or wholly unpaid. This represents around 0.3 per cent both by number and by value of all claims received.</p>
	<p pid="a.68.0/2">We would normally aim to have paid all the outstanding claims within two months of receipt. However, these 26 claims required further investigation, such as field inspections, prior to payment and in some cases these were delayed for biosecurity reasons. All claimants have been kept informed about the reasons for the delay.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.68.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn1">
	East Midlands: National Forest
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.68.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100654" speakername="Lord Varley" colon="" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.68.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.68.2/2" qnum="HL1695">When they will report on the National Forest Company's progress in creating a national forest in the East Midlands.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.68.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.68.3/1">We have arranged for copies of the National Forest Company's annual report and its accounts for 2000&ndash;01 to be placed in the House Libraries.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.68.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn2">
	Food and Farming Policy Commission
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.68.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100250" speakername="Baroness Gould of Potternewton" colon="" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.68.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.68.5/2" qnum="HL1698">When they expect the Policy Commission on Food and Farming to report.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.68.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.68.6/1">The independent policy commission was tasked in the summer with reporting to the Government by the end of this year. The commission is making good progress and will complete the bulk of its work in that timetable but it will now deliver its final report by the end of January 2002.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.68.7" nospeaker="true" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn3">
	Sheep Brain Pool Experiment
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.68.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100238" speakername="Lord Gladwin of Clee" colon="" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.68.8/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.68.8/2" qnum="HL1699">Whether they will publish the reports of audits they commissioned into the sheep brain pool experiment at the Institute for Animal Health.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.68.9" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.68.9/1">We have now received the reports of the two independent auditors, the UK Accreditation Service (UKAS) and Risk Solutions. We intend to publish them, along with a response from the Institute of Animal Health to the issues raised in the audits, at 9.30 a.m. tomorrow (<phrase class="date" code="2001-11-30">Friday 30 November</phrase>) and will make the documents available to right honourable and honourable Members through the Vote Office and Libraries.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.69.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn4">
	Business Tourism
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.69.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100016" speakername="Baroness Anelay of St Johns" colon="" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.69.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.69.1/2" qnum="HL1452">What is their estimate of the contribution made to the United Kingdom economy by business tourism; and what percentage this sum represents as a proportion of all tourism income in the United Kingdom.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.69.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.69.2/1">According to estimates by the Business Tourism Partnership, business tourism is worth some &pound;15 billion per year, of which &pound;11 billion comes from domestic tourism and &pound;4 billion from inbound visitors. This represents 20 per cent of tourism expenditure in the UK.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.69.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn5">
	Business Tourism
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.69.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100016" speakername="Baroness Anelay of St Johns" colon="" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.69.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.69.4/2" qnum="HL1453">What is their estimate of the number of people employed directly and indirectly by the business tourism sector.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.69.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.69.5/1">The Business Tourism Partnership has estimated that business tourism employs some 530,000 people directly and indirectly.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.69.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn6">
	Stakeholder Pensions
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.69.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100103" speakername="Lord Campbell of Croy" colon="" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.69.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.69.7/2" qnum="HL748">Whether the system of stakeholder pensions is coming into operation in the way in which the Government had intended it should.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.69.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100298" speakername="Baroness Hollis of Heigham" colon=":" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.69.8/1">The statutory provisions for stakeholder pensions have been introduced as planned. Stakeholder pensions have been on sale since April of this year and on <phrase class="date" code="2001-10-08">8 October</phrase> the requirement for employers to provide their staff with workplace access to a stakeholder pension scheme came into effect.</p>
	<p pid="a.69.8/2">It is too early to draw detailed conclusions about trends, but early figures show that over 400,000 stakeholder pensions have been taken out in the first six months, which is very encouraging.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.69.9" nospeaker="true" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn7">
	Winter Fuel Payments
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.69.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100460" speakername="Baroness Noakes" colon="" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.69.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.69.10/2" qnum="HL1017">Further to the answer by Baroness Hollis of Heigham on 23 October (HL Deb, col. 913), in which year were the 50 people she referred to not receiving the winter fuel payments to which they were entitled.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.70.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100298" speakername="Baroness Hollis of Heigham" colon=":" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.70.0/1">These claims were in relation to winter 2000. The number of claims outstanding for that winter is now 33.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.70.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn8">
	State Pension
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.70.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100336" speakername="Lord Jenkins of Putney" colon="" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.70.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.70.2/2" qnum="HL1513">Whether they intend to bring the state pension in the United Kingdom to the same levels as those in other countries in the European Union.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.70.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100298" speakername="Baroness Hollis of Heigham" colon=":" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.70.3/1">Unlike many member states where there is little private provision, the United Kingdom's pension system is a partnership between the state and the private sector. This ensures both sustainable public finances and sustainable social protection systems. The basic state pension provides the foundation for income in retirement. It has always been the case that people were expected to build up a second pension or other savings on top of their basic state pension and the Government encourage them to do so where this is appropriate. People have been retiring with increasingly good company or other private pensions, and as a result pensioner incomes have risen faster than the incomes of people at work.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.70.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn9">
	Food Standards Agency DEL
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.70.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100274" speakername="Lord Hardy of Wath" colon="" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn9">
	<p pid="a.70.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.70.5/2" qnum="HL1694">Whether there are any proposals to amend the Food Standards Agency departmental expenditure limit (DEL) and administration costs limit for 2001&ndash;02.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.70.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.70.6/1">Subject to parliamentary approval of the necessary Supplementary Estimate for the Food Standards Agency (FSA), the overall resource departmental expenditure limit for 2001&ndash;02 will be increased by &pound;10,911,000 (of which &pound;4,274,000 is administrations costs) from &pound;111,243,000 to &pound;122,154,000.</p>
	<p pid="a.70.6/2">The increase is the net effect of the addition of the FSA's end year flexibility (EYF) entitlement. Delays in appointing external board members meant that the overall FSA strategy, and hence certain projects, were also delayed. This amounts to &pound;6,637,000 programme and &pound;2,867,000 administration costs. Additionally, transfers from Scotland (&pound;783,000) and Wales (&pound;609,000) are needed to cover the estimated fall in Meat Hygiene Service income in these countries resulting from the revised charging methodology recommended in the Maclean report. A transfer of &pound;15,000 administration costs from the Department of Health is needed as contribution towards the cost of the Scientific Advisory Committee on Nutrition. Finally, the FSA's EYF capital entitlement needs to be incorporated. The move of the FSA to a new office in central London was later than anticipated, caused by building delays. This has resulted in the need to incorporate &pound;433,000 EYF capital expenditure.</p>
	<p pid="a.70.6/3">As a result of these changes, the gross administration cost limit for the FSA has increased by &pound;4,274,000 from &pound;48,908,000 to &pound;53,182,000.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.71.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn10">
	HIV Infected Healthcare Workers
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.71.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100421" speakername="Baroness Massey of Darwen" colon="" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn10">
	<p pid="a.71.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.71.1/2" qnum="HL1697">What has been the outcome of the policy review on patient notification exercises relating to HIV infected healthcare workers.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.71.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.71.2/1">We have recently accepted advice from the Expert Advisory Group on Aids (EAGA) and the United Kingdom Advisory Panel for Health Care Workers infected with Blood-borne Viruses (UKAP). They advise that it is no longer necessary to notify every single patient who has undergone an exposure prone procedure <sup>1</sup> by an HIV infected healthcare worker because of the low risk of transmission and the anxiety caused to large numbers of patients.</p>
	<p pid="a.71.2/2">In future, the need for and extent of a patient notification exercise will depend on the level of risk of exposure. This may mean that in some instances there is no patient notification exercise or it is limited in its scope. Until now, all patients who have undergone exposure prone procedures have been notified regardless of their level of risk. EAGA and UKAP are in the process of developing these critiera and we will be issuing operational guidance to the National Health Service in the new year.</p>
	<p pid="a.71.2/3" class="indent"><sup>1</sup> Exposure prone procedures are those where there is a risk that injury to the healthcare worker could result in their blood contaminating a patients' open tissues. Exposure prone procedures in general terms include most surgery, gynaecology and obstetrics, dentistry and some aspects of midwifery and specialist nursing.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.71.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn11">
	E-democracy
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.71.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100003" speakername="Lord Acton" colon="" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_wqn11">
	<p pid="a.71.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.71.4/2" qnum="HL1746">What plans they have to further e-democracy.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.71.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w03.htm#11129w03_spmin3">
	<p pid="a.71.5/1">The Prime Minister has asked the President of the Council and Leader of the House of Commons to chair a new Cabinet Committee on e-democracy. The composition and terms of reference of the new committee are: Ministerial Committee on e-Democracy (MISC17) Composition The President of the Council and the Leader of the House of Commons (Chair) Secretary of State for Trade and Industry Financial Secretary to the Treasury Minister Without Portfolio Minister of State for Transport, Local Government and the Regions Minister of State for Home Affairs Minister of State for Trade and Industry Minister of State for Cabinet Office Parliamentary Secretary for the Leader of the House of Commons Office Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Education and Skills Invited to Attend The e-Envoy Terms of Reference XTo consider ways of strengthening the democratic process by engaging the public and their elected representatives through the use of the internet and other electronic means&quot;.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.72.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w04.htm#11129w04_wqn0">
	Events Industry: Vocational Qualifications
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.72.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100016" speakername="Baroness Anelay of St Johns" colon="" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w04.htm#11129w04_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.72.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.72.1/2" qnum="HL1455">What support is being given by the Department for Education and Skills for the national qualification for the events industry.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.72.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100024" speakername="Baroness Ashton of Upholland" colon=":" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w04.htm#11129w04_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.72.2/1">Currently the Department for Education and Skills works with and supports the Travel, Tourism Services and Events National Training Organisation (TTENTO), whose remit includes the development and promotion of national and Scottish vocational qualifications for the events industry.</p>
	<p pid="a.72.2/2">We hope that the events industry will, along with others in the sector, play a full part in the development of a sector skills council (SSC). SSCs will be influential employer-led bodies with a strategic responsibility to identify and tackle priority skills, productivity and employability issues for sectors they represent.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.72.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w04.htm#11129w04_wqn1">
	Education Action Zones
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.72.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100056" speakername="Baroness Blatch" colon="" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w04.htm#11129w04_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.72.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.72.4/2" qnum="HL1445">For each education action zone, what has been the private sector contribution in (a) cash and (b) kind in each year since they were introduced.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2001-11-29a.72.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100024" speakername="Baroness Ashton of Upholland" colon=":" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldhansrd/vo011129/text/11129w04.htm#11129w04_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.72.5/1">The amount of private sector contributions in (a) cash and (b) kind in each year since they were introduced, for each education action zone (EAZ), is in the attached table, along with each zone's start date.</p>
	<table>
		<caption>Statutory Education Action Zones Summary of private sector contributions raised in cash and in kind as recorded by zones up to 31 March 2001</caption>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/5"> <td></td> <td></td> <td>2000&ndash;01</td> <td>2000&ndash;01</td> <td>2000&ndash;01</td> <td>1999&ndash;2000</td> <td>1999&ndash;2000</td> <td>1999&ndash;2000</td> <td>1998&ndash;99</td> <td>1998&ndash;99</td> <td>1998&ndash;99</td> <td>Total to March 2001</td> <td>Total to March 2001</td> <td>Total to March 2001</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/6"> <td></td> <td>Start</td> <td>In Cash</td> <td>In Kind</td> <td>Total</td> <td>In Cash</td> <td>In Kind</td> <td>Total</td> <td>In Cash</td> <td>In Kind</td> <td>Total</td> <td>In Cash</td> <td>In Kind</td> <td>Total</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/7"> <td>Name of Zone</td> <td>Date</td> <td>&pound;000</td> <td>&pound;000</td> <td>&pound;000</td> <td>&pound;000</td> <td>&pound;000</td> <td>&pound;000</td> <td>&pound;000</td> <td>&pound;000</td> <td>&pound;000</td> <td>&pound;000</td> <td>&pound;000</td> <td>&pound;000</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/8"> <td>Grand Total</td> <td></td> <td>3,875</td> <td>12,939</td> <td>16,814</td> <td>2,045</td> <td>3,549</td> <td>5,594</td> <td>253</td> <td>1,050</td> <td>1,303</td> <td>6,173</td> <td>17,538</td> <td>23,711</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/9"> <td>Round One Zones</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/10"> <td>Barnsley</td> <td>Sep 98</td> <td>11</td> <td>279</td> <td>290</td> <td>2</td> <td>149</td> <td>151</td> <td>0</td> <td>20</td> <td>20</td> <td>13</td> <td>448</td> <td>461</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/11"> <td>Birmingham (Aston and Nechells)</td> <td>Jan 99</td> <td>70</td> <td>49</td> <td>119</td> <td>63</td> <td>0</td> <td>63</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>133</td> <td>49</td> <td>182</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/12"> <td>Birmingham (Kitts Green and Shard End)</td> <td>Jan 99</td> <td>70</td> <td>159</td> <td>229</td> <td>66</td> <td>125</td> <td>191</td> <td>5</td> <td>2</td> <td>7</td> <td>141</td> <td>286</td> <td>427</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/13"> <td>Blackburn with Darwen</td> <td>Sep 98</td> <td>59</td> <td>139</td> <td>198</td> <td>7</td> <td>212</td> <td>219</td> <td>50</td> <td>101</td> <td>151</td> <td>116</td> <td>452</td> <td>568</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/14"> <td>East Basildon</td> <td>Jan 99</td> <td>97</td> <td>41</td> <td>138</td> <td>39</td> <td>35</td> <td>74</td> <td>1</td> <td>4</td> <td>5</td> <td>137</td> <td>80</td> <td>217</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/15"> <td>East Brighton</td> <td>Jan 99</td> <td>36</td> <td>142</td> <td>178</td> <td>37</td> <td>146</td> <td>183</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>73</td> <td>288</td> <td>361</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/16"> <td>East Middlesbrough</td> <td>Sep 98</td> <td>215</td> <td>40</td> <td>255</td> <td>210</td> <td>40</td> <td>250</td> <td>53</td> <td>4</td> <td>57</td> <td>478</td> <td>84</td> <td>562</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/17"> <td>Halifax</td> <td>Jan 99</td> <td>346</td> <td>8</td> <td>354</td> <td>262</td> <td>14</td> <td>276</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>608</td> <td>22</td> <td>630</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/18"> <td>Herefordshire</td> <td>Sep 98</td> <td>21</td> <td>19</td> <td>40</td> <td>40</td> <td>0</td> <td>40</td> <td>0</td> <td>28</td> <td>28</td> <td>61</td> <td>47</td> <td>108</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/19"> <td>Kingston upon Hull</td> <td>Jan 99</td> <td>0</td> <td>225</td> <td>225</td> <td>176</td> <td>110</td> <td>286</td> <td>5</td> <td>0</td> <td>5</td> <td>181</td> <td>335</td> <td>516</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/20"> <td>CfBT/Lambeth</td> <td>Sep 98</td> <td>126</td> <td>0</td> <td>126</td> <td>0</td> <td>77</td> <td>77</td> <td>0</td> <td>41</td> <td>41</td> <td>126</td> <td>118</td> <td>244</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/21"> <td>Leicester South and West</td> <td>Sep 98</td> <td>121</td> <td>144</td> <td>265</td> <td>70</td> <td>106</td> <td>176</td> <td>0</td> <td>3</td> <td>3</td> <td>191</td> <td>253</td> <td>444</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/22"> <td>Leigh (Wigan)</td> <td>Jan 99</td> <td>1</td> <td>189</td> <td>190</td> <td>5</td> <td>187</td> <td>192</td> <td>1</td> <td>49</td> <td>50</td> <td>7</td> <td>425</td> <td>432</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/23"> <td>New Addington (Croydon)</td> <td>Sep 98</td> <td>41</td> <td>195</td> <td>236</td> <td>2</td> <td>233</td> <td>235</td> <td>7</td> <td>5</td> <td>12</td> <td>50</td> <td>433</td> <td>483</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/24"> <td>Newcastle</td> <td>Sep 98</td> <td>0</td> <td>62</td> <td>62</td> <td>0</td> <td>152</td> <td>152</td> <td>0</td> <td>120</td> <td>120</td> <td>0</td> <td>334</td> <td>334</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/25"> <td>Newham</td> <td>Sep 98</td> <td>62</td> <td>123</td> <td>185</td> <td>107</td> <td>175</td> <td>282</td> <td>96</td> <td>304</td> <td>400</td> <td>265</td> <td>602</td> <td>867</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/26"> <td>North East Lincolnshire (Grimsby)</td> <td>Sep 98</td> <td>0</td> <td>178</td> <td>178</td> <td>0</td> <td>56</td> <td>56</td> <td>0</td> <td>111</td> <td>111</td> <td>0</td> <td>345</td> <td>345</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/27"> <td>North East Sheffield</td> <td>Jan 99</td> <td>20</td> <td>130</td> <td>150</td> <td>0</td> <td>237</td> <td>237</td> <td>0</td> <td>6</td> <td>6</td> <td>20</td> <td>373</td> <td>393</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/28"> <td>North Somerset (Weston-Super-Mare)</td> <td>Sep 98</td> <td>17</td> <td>158</td> <td>175</td> <td>6</td> <td>42</td> <td>48</td> <td>1</td> <td>33</td> <td>34</td> <td>24</td> <td>233</td> <td>257</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/29"> <td>North Southwark</td> <td>Jan 99</td> <td>70</td> <td>289</td> <td>359</td> <td>70</td> <td>199</td> <td>269</td> <td>11</td> <td>105</td> <td>116</td> <td>151</td> <td>593</td> <td>744</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/30"> <td>Nottingham</td> <td>Jan 99</td> <td>0</td> <td>147</td> <td>147</td> <td>0</td> <td>130</td> <td>130</td> <td>0</td> <td>19</td> <td>19</td> <td>0</td> <td>396</td> <td>296</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/31"> <td>Plymouth</td> <td>Jan 99</td> <td>193</td> <td>40</td> <td>233</td> <td>170</td> <td>18</td> <td>188</td> <td>0</td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> <td>363</td> <td>59</td> <td>422</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/32"> <td>Salford &amp; Trafford</td> <td>Sep 98</td> <td>36</td> <td>218</td> <td>254</td> <td>62</td> <td>188</td> <td>250</td> <td>23</td> <td>40</td> <td>63</td> <td>121</td> <td>446</td> <td>567</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/33"> <td>South Tyneside</td> <td>Jan 99</td> <td>10</td> <td>77</td> <td>87</td> <td>0</td> <td>100</td> <td>100</td> <td>0</td> <td>34</td> <td>34</td> <td>10</td> <td>211</td> <td>221</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/34"> <td>Thetford (Norfolk)</td> <td>Jan 99</td> <td>2</td> <td>333</td> <td>335</td> <td>0</td> <td>77</td> <td>77</td> <td>0</td> <td>20</td> <td>20</td> <td>2</td> <td>430</td> <td>432</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/35"> <td>Total for all 25 Zones</td> <td></td> <td>1,624</td> <td>3,384</td> <td>5,008</td> <td>1,394</td> <td>2,808</td> <td>4,202</td> <td>253</td> <td>1,050</td> <td>1,303</td> <td>3,271</td> <td>7,242</td> <td>10,513</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/36"> <td>Round Two Zones</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/37"> <td>Ashington</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>84</td> <td>84</td> <td>168</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>84</td> <td>84</td> <td>168</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/38"> <td>Barrow-in-Furness</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>247</td> <td>247</td> <td>0</td> <td>4</td> <td>4</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>251</td> <td>251</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/39"> <td>Bedford</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>77</td> <td>295</td> <td>372</td> <td>0</td> <td>34</td> <td>34</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>77</td> <td>329</td> <td>406</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/40"> <td>Bolton</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>4</td> <td>186</td> <td>190</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>4</td> <td>186</td> <td>190</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/41"> <td>Bridgwater</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>40</td> <td>100</td> <td>140</td> <td>3</td> <td>0</td> <td>3</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>43</td> <td>100</td> <td>143</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/42"> <td>Bristol</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>183</td> <td>183</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>183</td> <td>183</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/43"> <td>Camborne Pool Redruth</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>12</td> <td>144</td> <td>156</td> <td>1</td> <td>79</td> <td>80</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>13</td> <td>223</td> <td>236</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/44"> <td>Clacton &amp; Harwich</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>89</td> <td>269</td> <td>358</td> <td>0</td> <td>16</td> <td>16</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>89</td> <td>285</td> <td>374</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/45"> <td>Corby</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>268</td> <td>268</td> <td>150</td> <td>0</td> <td>150</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>150</td> <td>268</td> <td>418</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/46"> <td>Coventry Millennium</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>68</td> <td>143</td> <td>211</td> <td>0</td> <td>10</td> <td>10</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>68</td> <td>153</td> <td>221</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/47"> <td>Derby North East</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>73</td> <td>73</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>73</td> <td>73</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/48"> <td>Dingle, Granby &amp; Toxteth (Liverpool)</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>13</td> <td>162</td> <td>175</td> <td>30</td> <td>35</td> <td>65</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>43</td> <td>197</td> <td>240</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/49"> <td>Downham &amp; Bellingham (Lewisham)</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>204</td> <td>204</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>204</td> <td>204</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/50"> <td>Dudley</td> <td>Dec 99</td> <td>8</td> <td>365</td> <td>373</td> <td>15</td> <td>0</td> <td>15</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>23</td> <td>365</td> <td>388</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/51"> <td>Easington &amp; Seaham</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>3</td> <td>482</td> <td>485</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>3</td> <td>482</td> <td>485</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/52"> <td>East Cleveland</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>63</td> <td>208</td> <td>271</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>63</td> <td>208</td> <td>271</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/53"> <td>East Manchester</td> <td>Dec 99</td> <td>7</td> <td>363</td> <td>370</td> <td>10</td> <td>0</td> <td>10</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>17</td> <td>363</td> <td>380</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/54"> <td>Epicentre LEAP (Ellesmere Port)</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>80</td> <td>82</td> <td>162</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>80</td> <td>82</td> <td>162</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/55"> <td>Gillingham Partnership</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>210</td> <td>210</td> <td>0</td> <td>14</td> <td>14</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>224</td> <td>224</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/56"> <td>Gloucester</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>13</td> <td>263</td> <td>276</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>13</td> <td>263</td> <td>276</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/57"> <td>Great Yarmouth</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>34</td> <td>255</td> <td>289</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>34</td> <td>255</td> <td>289</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/58"> <td>Greenwich</td> <td>Sep 99</td> <td>86</td> <td>122</td> <td>208</td> <td>60</td> <td>38</td> <td>98</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>146</td> <td>160</td> <td>306</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/59"> <td>Hackney</td> <td>Dec 99</td> <td>83</td> <td>345</td> <td>428</td> <td>28</td> <td>29</td> <td>57</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>111</td> <td>374</td> <td>485</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/60"> <td>Hastings &amp; St Leonards</td> <td>Dec 99</td> <td>56</td> <td>366</td> <td>422</td> <td>0</td> <td>6</td> <td>6</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>56</td> <td>372</td> <td>428</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/61"> <td>Kent/Somerset Virtual</td> <td>Dec 99</td> <td>109</td> <td>19</td> <td>128</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>109</td> <td>19</td> <td>128</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/62"> <td>Leigh Park (Havant)</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>3</td> <td>195</td> <td>198</td> <td>0</td> <td>4</td> <td>4</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>3</td> <td>199</td> <td>202</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/63"> <td>North East Derbyshire Coalfields</td> <td>Dec 99</td> <td>20</td> <td>240</td> <td>260</td> <td>20</td> <td>7</td> <td>27</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>40</td> <td>247</td> <td>287</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/64"> <td>North Islington</td> <td>Dec 99</td> <td>108</td> <td>165</td> <td>273</td> <td>50</td> <td>21</td> <td>71</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>158</td> <td>186</td> <td>344</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/65"> <td>North Stockton</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>33</td> <td>38</td> <td>71</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>33</td> <td>38</td> <td>71</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/66"> <td>North West Shropshire</td> <td>Mar 00</td> <td>4</td> <td>24</td> <td>28</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>4</td> <td>24</td> <td>28</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/67"> <td>Hamilton Oxford Schools</td> <td>Sep 00</td> <td>229</td> <td>244</td> <td>473</td> <td>146</td> <td>207</td> <td>353</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>375</td> <td>451</td> <td>826</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/68"> <td>Peterlee</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>23</td> <td>376</td> <td>399</td> <td>20</td> <td>32</td> <td>52</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>43</td> <td>408</td> <td>451</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/69"> <td>Preston</td> <td>Dec 99</td> <td>22</td> <td>136</td> <td>158</td> <td>12</td> <td>4</td> <td>16</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>34</td> <td>140</td> <td>174</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/70"> <td>Rainbow Zone (Stoke-on-Trent)</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>165</td> <td>90</td> <td>255</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>165</td> <td>90</td> <td>255</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/71"> <td>Heart of Slough</td> <td>Dec 99</td> <td>8</td> <td>176</td> <td>184</td> <td>0</td> <td>63</td> <td>63</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>8</td> <td>239</td> <td>247</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/72"> <td>South Bradford</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>110</td> <td>42</td> <td>152</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>110</td> <td>42</td> <td>152</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/73"> <td>South East England Virtual</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>10</td> <td>377</td> <td>387</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>10</td> <td>377</td> <td>387</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/74"> <td>South East Sheffield</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>149</td> <td>22</td> <td>171</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>149</td> <td>22</td> <td>171</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/75"> <td>Southend</td> <td>Dec 99</td> <td>0</td> <td>160</td> <td>160</td> <td>60</td> <td>35</td> <td>95</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>60</td> <td>195</td> <td>255</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/76"> <td>Speke Garston (Liverpool)</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>52</td> <td>164</td> <td>216</td> <td>18</td> <td>2</td> <td>20</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>70</td> <td>166</td> <td>236</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/77"> <td>Sunderland</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>10</td> <td>124</td> <td>134</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>10</td> <td>124</td> <td>134</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/78"> <td>Telford &amp; Wrekin</td> <td>Dec 99</td> <td>31</td> <td>147</td> <td>178</td> <td>25</td> <td>32</td> <td>57</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>56</td> <td>179</td> <td>235</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/79"> <td>Wakefield</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>20</td> <td>93</td> <td>113</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>20</td> <td>93</td> <td>113</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/80"> <td>Wednesbury (Sandwell)</td> <td>Dec 99</td> <td>38</td> <td>186</td> <td>224</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>38</td> <td>186</td> <td>224</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/81"> <td>Westminster</td> <td>May 00</td> <td>100</td> <td>10</td> <td>110</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>100</td> <td>10</td> <td>110</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/82"> <td>Withernsea &amp; Southern Holderness</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>17</td> <td>256</td> <td>273</td> <td>3</td> <td>8</td> <td>11</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>20</td> <td>264</td> <td>284</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/83"> <td>Wolverhampton</td> <td>Jan 00</td> <td>3</td> <td>218</td> <td>221</td> <td>0</td> <td>37</td> <td>37</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>3</td> <td>255</td> <td>258</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/84"> <td>Wythenshawe</td> <td>Dec 99</td> <td>15</td> <td>272</td> <td>287</td> <td>0</td> <td>24</td> <td>24</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>15</td> <td>296</td> <td>311</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/85"> <td>Total for all 48 Zones</td> <td></td> <td>2,099</td> <td>9,193</td> <td>11,292</td> <td>651</td> <td>741</td> <td>1,392</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>2,750</td> <td>9,934</td> <td>12,684</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/86"> <td>Total for all 73 Zones</td> <td></td> <td>3,723</td> <td>12,577</td> <td>16,300</td> <td>2,045</td> <td>3,549</td> <td>5,594</td> <td>253</td> <td>1,050</td> <td>1,303</td> <td>6,021</td> <td>17,176</td> <td>23,197</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/87"> <td>EiC Action Zones</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/88"> <td></td> <td colspan="6">Summary of Private Sector Contributions raised in cash and in kind</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/89"> <td></td> <td colspan="3">as recorded by Zones up to 31 March 2001</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/90"> <td>Achieving Excellence in Battersea</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>5</td> <td>5</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>5</td> <td>5</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/91"> <td>Birmingham Athena</td> <td>Sep 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/92"> <td>Birmingham Highgate</td> <td>Jan 01</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/93"> <td>Birmingham King's Norton</td> <td>Sep 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/94"> <td>Birmingham Kingstanding</td> <td>Sep 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/95"> <td>Birmingham Quinzone</td> <td>Sep 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/96"> <td>Central Camden Learning Network</td> <td>Sep 00</td> <td>33</td> <td>8</td> <td>41</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>33</td> <td>8</td> <td>41</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/97"> <td>Creating Success (Lewisham)</td> <td>Jan 01</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/98"> <td>East Shipley (Bradford)</td> <td>Jan 01</td> <td>10</td> <td>0</td> <td>10</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>10</td> <td>0</td> <td>10</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/99"> <td>Education Partners in Islington and Camden</td> <td>Jan 01</td> <td>50</td> <td>0</td> <td>50</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>50</td> <td>0</td> <td>50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/100"> <td>Excellence 2000 (Knowsley)</td> <td>Sep 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/101"> <td>Excellence Plus (Waltham Forest)</td> <td>Jan 01</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/102"> <td>Fulham Schools Partnership</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/103"> <td>Haringey Zone of Excellence</td> <td>Sep 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/104"> <td>Inner West Achievement Zone (Leeds)</td> <td>Jan 01</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/105"> <td>King's Cross (Camden)</td> <td>Sep 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/106"> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/107"> <td>Learning Together (Sheffield)</td> <td>Jan 01</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/108"> <td>Liverpool Alt</td> <td>Jan 01</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/109"> <td>Liverpool Excite</td> <td>Sep 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/110"> <td>Liverpool FOCUS</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/111"> <td>Liverpool North Deanery</td> <td>Sep 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/112"> <td>Manor Park (Newham)</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>37</td> <td>37</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>37</td> <td>37</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/113"> <td>Millenium Gateshead</td> <td>Jan 01</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/114"> <td>Moss Side and Hulme (Manchester)</td> <td>Sep 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/115"> <td>New River Partnership (Islington)</td> <td>Sep 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>29</td> <td>29</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>29</td> <td>29</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/116"> <td>Peckham (Southwark)</td> <td>Sep 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/117"> <td>Plumstead Pathfinder (Greenwich)</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>17</td> <td>0</td> <td>17</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>17</td> <td>0</td> <td>17</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/118"> <td>Poplar Partnership (Tower Hamlets)</td> <td>Jan 01</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/119"> <td>Richmond Hill (Leeds)</td> <td>Sep 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/120"> <td>Rotherham Clifton Partnership</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>17</td> <td>35</td> <td>52</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>17</td> <td>35</td> <td>52</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/121"> <td>Rotherham Kimberworth</td> <td>Jan 01</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/122"> <td>Rotherham Thrybergh</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>7</td> <td>58</td> <td>65</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>7</td> <td>58</td> <td>65</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/123"> <td>Salford East</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>1</td> <td>45</td> <td>46</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>1</td> <td>45</td> <td>46</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/124"> <td>Sheffield Abbeydale Corridor</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/125"> <td>The Learning Zone (Leeds)</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>53</td> <td>53</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>53</td> <td>53</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/126"> <td>Together We Can (Sheffield)</td> <td>Jan 01</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/127"> <td>Tower Hamlets (Globetown)</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>0</td> <td>90</td> <td>90</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>90</td> <td>90</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/128"> <td>Waltham Forest REAP</td> <td>Jan 01</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/129"> <td>Woolwich Reach (Greenwich)</td> <td>Apr 00</td> <td>17</td> <td>0</td> <td>17</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>17</td> <td>0</td> <td>17</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/130"> <td>Wyke (Bradford)</td> <td>Jan 01</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.72.5/131"> <td></td> <td colspan="2">Total for all 40 EiC Action Zones</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>152</td> <td>362</td> <td>514</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>152</td> <td>362</td> <td>514</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

