<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="c" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.15.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_wqn0">
	Airlines
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.15.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100208" speakername="Lord Fearn" colon="" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.15.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.15.1/2" qnum="HL2056">How many &quot;low-cost&quot; airlines operate in England and Wales.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.15.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100164" speakername="Lord Davies of Oldham" colon=":" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.15.2/1">There is no simple answer to this Question. The market in air services in England and Wales is intensely competitive and all airlines operating within it, British and foreign, are under pressure to control their costs. While it is possible to draw distinctions of a general nature between types of airline&mdash;for example, between scheduled and charter, or between those offering a full range of services and the so-called &quot;no-frills&quot; carriers&mdash;these appellations are to an extent simply marketing devices and have in any case become increasingly blurred as the industry has developed in response to changes in the regulatory and competitive environment. Accordingly, the Government would not wish to categorise any individual airline as belonging to a specific &quot;low-cost&quot; category.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.15.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_wqn1">
	Airports
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.15.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100208" speakername="Lord Fearn" colon="" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.15.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.15.4/2" qnum="HL2054">How many airports operate services carrying passengers in England and Wales.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.15.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100164" speakername="Lord Davies of Oldham" colon=":" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_spnew1">
	<p pid="c.15.5/1">Statistics compiled and collated by the Civil Aviation Authority, with the co-operation of airport operators, indicate that there are 36 airports carrying passengers in England and Wales. This number is based on air transport movements for both scheduled and charter services.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.15.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_wqn2">
	Airports
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.15.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100208" speakername="Lord Fearn" colon="" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.15.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.15.7/2" qnum="HL2055">How many personnel work within English and Welsh airports.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.15.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100164" speakername="Lord Davies of Oldham" colon=":" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_spnew2">
	<p pid="c.15.8/1">This information is not held centrally and it can be obtained only at disproportionate costs. At the time the Air Transport White Paper was published in 2003, around 200,000 people were directly employed at UK airports but these data were not broken down between English and Welsh airports.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.15.9" nospeaker="true" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_wqn3">
	Avian Flu
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.15.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100427" speakername="Baroness Miller of Chilthorne Domer" colon="" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.15.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.15.10/2" qnum="HL2436">Whether, in the event that poultry flocks are required to be culled as a biosecurity measure in the event of an avian flu outbreak in the United Kingdom, the compensation payable will be on a notional value; or whether account will be taken of the actual value of the birds slaughtered depending upon poultry types and different production systems.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.16.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.16.0/1">In the event of an outbreak of avian influenza in the United Kingdom, any necessary slaughter of birds to prevent spread of the disease would be compensated for under the provisions for payment in Schedule 3 to the Animal Health Act 1981 which states that:</p>
	<p pid="c.16.0/2" class="indent">&quot;The Minister shall for poultry, other than diseased poultry, slaughtered under this paragraph pay compensation, which shall be the value of the bird immediately before it was slaughtered&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="c.16.0/3">The value of the slaughtered birds will, in most cases, be determined by reference to valuation tables that have been developed by ADAS for the department in consultation with the industry. We have developed a number of valuation tables which take account of different poultry types and different production systems. For those poultry species and types not covered by valuation tables the value will be determined by suitably experienced poultry specialists.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.16.1" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_wqn4">
	Avian Flu
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.16.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100098" speakername="Baroness Byford" colon="" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.16.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.16.2/2" qnum="HL2452">Whether a list of key workers has been established to be used in the event of an outbreak of avian flu in birds.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.16.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_spnew3">
	<p pid="c.16.3/1">A number of individuals have been identified and are listed to take up key posts in an outbreak of exotic animal disease such as avian influenza. This includes people to be appointed as regional operations directors, divisional operations managers and local office finance managers. These would support and strengthen the existing staff and would be further augmented by people deployed from other parts of Defra and other government departments under established arrangements.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.16.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_wqn5">
	Benefit Fraud
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.16.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100855" speakername="Lord Jones of Cheltenham" colon="" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_wqn5">
	<p pid="c.16.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.16.5/2" qnum="HL2211">What targets have been set to reduce benefit fraud.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.16.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.16.6/1">Public Service Agreement (PSA) targets commit DWP to reducing fraud and error in working age income support and jobseeker's allowance by 33 per cent by March 2004 and by 50 per cent by March 2006. By September 2004, we had reduced fraud and error in these benefits by 41 per cent and had reduced fraud by two-thirds.</p>
	<p pid="c.16.6/2">For housing benefit for working age people, we have a PSA target to reduce fraud and error by 25 per cent by March 2006. By September 2004, the estimated percentage of housing benefit expenditure overpaid had fallen by 6 per cent.</p>
	<p pid="c.16.6/3">The Pension Service has also been set a service delivery agreement (SDA) target to reduce overpayments through fraud and error in pension credit by 20 per cent by March 2006. We estimated that by September 2004, fraud and error had been reduced by around 2 per cent.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.17.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_wqn6">
	Bovine Tuberculosis
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.17.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100098" speakername="Baroness Byford" colon="" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_wqn6">
	<p pid="c.17.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.17.1/2" qnum="HL2512">Further to the Explanatory Memorandum on the Veterinary Surgery (Testing for Tuberculosis in Bovines) Order 2005 (S.I. 2005/2015), in which areas the backlog of 1,750 outstanding tuberculosis tests is concentrated; whether the 12-month pilot will concentrate on these areas; and whether the interim report, scheduled under Point 8.3 of the regulatory impact assessment for autumn 2005, is still on target.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.17.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_spnew4">
	<p pid="c.17.2/1">On <phrase class="date" code="2005-09-30">30 September 2005</phrase>, 2,049 <sup>1</sup> GB cattle herds had tuberculin tests overdue. Almost 60 per cent of these overdue tests were located in the counties <sup>2</sup> of Devon (358), Dyfed (352), Cornwall (248), and Hereford and Worcestershire (238).</p>
	<p pid="c.17.2/2">We initially proposed that the pilot would take place in four animal health divisional office areas (Carmarthen, Caernarfon, Reading and Reigate). This has now been extended to include Cardiff, Exeter, Gloucester, Stafford, Taunton, Truro and Worcester. We will train the same number of State Veterinary Service technical staff. However, the pilot is now focused on the areas where TB is more prevalent.</p>
	<p pid="c.17.2/3">Progress with the pilot has been slower than originally planned. However, we still hope to complete the pilot by the end of the summer 2006. We expect there to be around 16 to 20 approved testers by the end of March 2006 and aim to publish an interim report around this time.</p>
	<p pid="c.17.2/4" class="indent"><sup>1</sup> Provisional data, downloaded from the State Veterinary Service (SVS) database on <phrase class="date" code="2005-10-06">6 October 2005</phrase>. Subject to change as more data become available.</p>
	<p pid="c.17.2/5"><sup>2</sup> Statistics on bovine TB are aggregated according to the office structure of the SVS. As a result, data for the current authorities of Pembrokeshire, Carmarthenshire and Ceredigion are aggregated as the former county of Dyfed; and data for the counties of Herefordshire and Worcestershire are combined.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.17.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_wqn7">
	Bovine Tuberculosis
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.17.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100098" speakername="Baroness Byford" colon="" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_wqn7">
	<p pid="c.17.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.17.4/2" qnum="HL2513">Whether, under European Union Regulation 64/432, an authorised person conducting a test for tuberculosis is required to be a veterinary surgeon in order for the test to be recognised for the purposes of international trade; and, if so, what is the status of those animals tested by lay persons.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.17.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w01.htm#51129w01_spnew5">
	<p pid="c.17.5/1">We are currently unable to export live cattle as a result of the export ban due to BSE. However, this is something which the Government have been working hard to get lifted.</p>
	<p pid="c.17.5/2">We have written advice from the European Commission, which we have shared with the veterinary profession, concerning our proposal to use trained lay testers to carry out TB testing. The Commission has clarified the circumstances where lay TB testers may not be used and recognised the benefits to the UK of employing lay testers.</p>
	<p pid="c.17.5/3">We will not use lay testers for pre-export testing where it is a requirement of the export health certificate that individual animals are subjected to a tuberculin test prior to being consigned for export. Our interpretation of the Commission's advice is that tests performed by lay testers would not invalidate a herd's officially tuberculosis-free status, provided that any pre-export test was performed by a veterinary surgeon.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.18.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w02.htm#51129w02_wqn0">
	Deaf Children
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.18.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100023" speakername="Lord Ashley of Stoke" colon="" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w02.htm#51129w02_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.18.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.18.1/2" qnum="HL2414">What information has been collected about deaf children in (a) mainstream schools, and (b) special units within those schools; and what are the main features which that information reveals.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.18.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100839" speakername="Lord Adonis" colon=":" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w02.htm#51129w02_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.18.2/1">Information available on the number of pupils with hearing impairments in mainstream primary and secondary schools is given in the table. The data show that the percentage of pupils with a hearing impairment in primary and secondary schools is a small percentage (2.3 per cent) of the overall number of pupils with identified SEN(1) in those schools.</p>
	<p pid="c.18.2/2">Pupils in special units within mainstream schools cannot be separately identified at present but this information will be collected from 2007.</p>
	<p pid="c.18.2/3">(1) Pupils at School Action Plus and with statements of SEN.</p>
	<p pid="c.18.2/4">Maintained Primary and Secondary Schools <sup>1</sup></p>
	<table>
		<caption>Number and Percentage of Pupils Whose Primary Need Has Been Classified as Hearing Impairment 2 As at January 2005.</caption>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="c.18.2/8"> <td></td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.18.2/9"> <td></td> <td>Pupils whose primary need has been classified as Hearing Impairment2 3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.18.2/10"> <td>England</td> <td>Primary</td> <td>Secondary</td> <td>Primary and Secondary</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.18.2/11"> <td></td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.18.2/12"> <td><i>Number of pupils at School Action Plus</i></td> <td><i>3,280</i></td> <td><i>3,010</i></td> <td><i>6,290</i></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.18.2/13"> <td>Percentage of pupils at School Action Plus4</td> <td>1.5</td> <td>2.1</td> <td>1.7</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.18.2/14"> <td>Number of pupils with statements of SEN</td> <td>2,920</td> <td>2,300</td> <td>5,230</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.18.2/15"> <td>Percentage of pupils with statements of SEN5</td> <td>4.3</td> <td>3.0</td> <td>3.6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.18.2/16"> <td>Number of pupils at School Action Plus and with statements of SEN</td> <td>6,200</td> <td>5,310</td> <td>11,510</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.18.2/17"> <td>Percentage of pupils at School Action Plus and with statements of SEN6</td> <td>2.1</td> <td>2.5</td> <td>2.3</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="c.18.2/20">Source: Annual Schools Census</p>
	<p pid="c.18.2/21">1 Includes middle schools as deemed. Excludes maintained nursery schools as this information is not available from all such schools.</p>
	<p pid="c.18.2/22">2 Pupils at School Action Plus and those pupils with statements of SEN provide information on their primary and, if appropriate, their secondary need. Information relating to primary need only is given here.</p>
	<p pid="c.18.2/23">3 Excludes dually registered pupils.</p>
	<p pid="c.18.2/24">4 The number of pupils at School Action Plus whose primary need is hearing impairment expressed as a percentage of all pupils at School Action Plus in the same school type.</p>
	<p pid="c.18.2/25">5 The number of pupils with statements of SEN whose primary need is hearing impairment expressed as a percentage of all pupils with statements of SEN in the same school type.</p>
	<p pid="c.18.2/26">6 The number of pupils at School Action Plus and with statements of SEN whose primary need is hearing impairment expressed as a percentage of all pupils at School Action Plus and with statements of SEN in the same school type.</p>
	<p pid="c.18.2/27">Totals may not appear to equal the sum of the component parts because numbers have been rounded to the nearest 10.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.18.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w02.htm#51129w02_wqn1">
	European Union General Affairs and External Relations Council
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.18.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100804" speakername="Lord Dykes" colon="" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w02.htm#51129w02_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.18.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.18.4/2" qnum="HL2193">What decisions for action were reached at the General Affairs and External Relations Council meeting on 7 November in regard to Israel's commitment to re-opening borders with the Palestinian occupied territories.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.18.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w02.htm#51129w02_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.18.5/1">At the General Affairs and External Relations Council (GAERC) on <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-07">7 November</phrase>, the council reiterated its support for the work of James Wolfensohn, the quartet special envoy for disengagement, and urged both Israel and the Palestinians to reach rapid agreement on the issues within the rapid action plan, including arrangements for Gaza's borders and crossings.</p>
	<p pid="c.18.5/2">The council also accepted Mr Wolfensohn's request, on behalf of the parties, that the EU consider playing a third party monitoring role at the Rafah crossing point on the Gaza-Egypt border. At the GAERC on <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-21">21 November</phrase>, the council took a decision in principle to undertake this role and monitor operations at the Rafah crossing point as set out in the <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-15">15 November</phrase> agreement on movement and access between the government of Israel and the Palestinian Authority. Preparations for the mission are developing rapidly and we hope formally to agree, and launch the mission, over the coming days.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.18.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w02.htm#51129w02_wqn2">
	EU-Russia Relations
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.18.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100279" speakername="Lord Harrison" colon="" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w02.htm#51129w02_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.18.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.18.7/2" qnum="HL2420">What is their view of the European Union-Russia co-operation partnership which expires in 2007; whether they favour a new European Union-Russia framework as a replacement; and what salient features they will press for in such a new framework.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.18.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w02.htm#51129w02_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.18.8/1">Much of the improvement in EU-Russia relations since 1997, from contacts on justice and home affairs issues to economic co-operation and joint working on international affairs, was assisted by the partnership and co-operation agreement, which establishes a strong framework for the relationship. Consideration, with EU partners, of what will provide the best basis for developing EU-Russia relations in the future is at an early stage. The UK is clear that any future framework between the EU and Russia must provide a basis for strengthening co-operation between the EU and Russia, including on issues such as counter-terrorism and counter-proliferation. Any future framework must also build on common understandings of the importance of democratic values and respect for fundamental freedoms.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.20.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w02.htm#51129w02_wqn3">
	Exotic Birds
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.20.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100098" speakername="Baroness Byford" colon="" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w02.htm#51129w02_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.20.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.20.1/2" qnum="HL2451">Regarding the 2,922 illegally imported exotic birds seized in 2004, how many birds were within each consignment; how many people were arrested; how many successful prosecutions were made; and what was the maximum fine imposed.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.20.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w02.htm#51129w02_spnew1">
	<p pid="c.20.2/1">Her Majesty's Revenue and Customs (HMRC) has the power to seize imported live birds only where import is in contravention of the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Flora and Fauna (CITES). In 2004 HMRC seized 2,922 live birds. These came from 11 different consignments and are detailed below.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/4"> <td>Consignment Number</td> <td>    Latin Name</td> <td>Common<br/>    Name</td> <td>    Quantity</td> <td>Country Of<br/>    Export</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/5"> <td>1</td> <td>Falco Rusticolus</td> <td>gyr falcon</td> <td>1</td> <td>Canada</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/6"> <td>2</td> <td>Parrots</td> <td>Parrots</td> <td>7</td> <td>South Africa</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/7"> <td>3</td> <td>Estrilda Caerulescens</td> <td>Lavendar Waxbill</td> <td>100</td> <td>Guinea</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/8"> <td></td> <td>Estrilda Melpoda</td> <td>Orange-Cheeked Waxbill</td> <td>600</td> <td>Guinea</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/9"> <td></td> <td>Estrilda Troglodytes</td> <td>Black-Rumped Waxbill</td> <td>500</td> <td>Guinea</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/10"> <td></td> <td>Lagonosticta Rubricata</td> <td>African Fire-Finch</td> <td>400</td> <td>Guinea</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/11"> <td></td> <td>Ortygospiza Articollis</td> <td>African Quail-Finch</td> <td>100</td> <td>Guinea</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/12"> <td></td> <td>Serinus Mozambicus</td> <td>Yellow Fronted Canary</td> <td>200</td> <td>Guinea</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/13"> <td></td> <td>Uraeginthus Bengalus</td> <td>Red-Cheeked Cordon-bleu</td> <td>600</td> <td>Guinea</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/14"> <td>4</td> <td>Tauraco Persa</td> <td>Green-Crested Turaco</td> <td>1</td> <td>Ghana</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/15"> <td>5</td> <td>Psittacus Erithacus Timneh</td> <td>Grey Parrot</td> <td>1</td> <td>Egypt</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/16"> <td>6</td> <td>Pytilia Hypogrammica</td> <td>Red-Faced Pytilia</td> <td>400</td> <td>Guinea</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/17"> <td>7</td> <td>Amazona Finschi</td> <td>Lilac Crowned Amazon</td> <td>1</td> <td>USA</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/18"> <td>8</td> <td>Aquila Wahlbergi</td> <td>Wahlberg's Eagle</td> <td>1</td> <td>Mali</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/19"> <td>9</td> <td>Milvus Migrans</td> <td>Yellow Billed Kites</td> <td>7</td> <td>Mali</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/20"> <td>10</td> <td>Spizaetus Cirrhatus</td> <td>Crested Hawk Eagles</td> <td>2</td> <td>Malaysia</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.20.2/21"> <td>11</td> <td>Haliaeetus Albicilla</td> <td>White-tailed Sea Eagle</td> <td>1</td> <td>Russia</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="c.20.2/24">The vast majority of these birds were seized because of regulatory or documentary errors&mdash;for example, the 2,500 birds in consignment 3 were seized because the importer had yet to complete the proper import notification form. Once that form was completed the birds were restored to the importer and the importation was allowed. A further 400 were seized because they were not of the species expected.</p>
	<p pid="c.20.2/25">HMRC brought no prosecutions in respect of these seizures. Where prosecutions are brought, the maximum penalty is an unlimited fine and/or seven years' imprisonment.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.21.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w02.htm#51129w02_wqn4">
	Fishing Organisations
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.21.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100420" speakername="Lord Mason of Barnsley" colon="" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w02.htm#51129w02_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.21.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.21.1/2" qnum="HL2486">What fishing organisations have received financial help in the past five years from (a) the Environment Agency; (b) the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs; and (c) other government departments.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.21.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w02.htm#51129w02_spnew2">
	<p pid="c.21.2/1">The Environment Agency does not fund fishing organisations directly, but it does collaborate with organisations to complete fisheries development projects of mutual benefit.</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/2">The following fishing organisations have received financial help from the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs:</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/3" class="indent">Cadgwith Winch Committee</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/4" class="indent">Cornish Fish Producers Organisation</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/5" class="indent">Flushing &amp; Falmouth Fishermen's Association</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/6" class="indent">Frozen at Sea Fillets Association</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/7" class="indent">Hastings Fishermen's Protection Society</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/8" class="indent">Isles of Scilly Fishermen's Association</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/9" class="indent">Sea Fish Industry Authority</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/10" class="indent">South West Handline Fishermen's Association</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/11" class="indent">Thanet Fishermen's Association</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/12">The following fishing organisations have received financial help from other government departments (i.e. Scottish Executive Environment and Rural Affairs Department; Department of Agriculture and Rural Development Northern Ireland; Welsh Assembly Government):</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/13" class="indent">Anglo North Irish Fish Producers' Organisation</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/14" class="indent">Association of Scottish Shellfish Growers</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/15" class="indent">Bolsach Boat Fishing Association</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/16" class="indent">Cardigan Bay Fishermen's Association</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/17" class="indent">EU Salmon Producers Group</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/18" class="indent">Federation of Scottish Aquaculture Producers</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/19" class="indent">Llyn Fishermen's Association</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/20" class="indent">Northern Coast Lobster Fishermen's Association</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/21" class="indent">North East Lobster Fishermen's Co-Operative Society</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/22" class="indent">Northern Ireland Fish Producers' Organisation</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/23" class="indent">Scot Trout Farming Ltd</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/24" class="indent">Scottish Quality Salmon</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/25" class="indent">Sea Fish Industry Authority</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/26" class="indent">Seafood Scotland</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/27" class="indent">Shetland Salmon Farmers' Association</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/28" class="indent">South and West Wales Fishing Communities Ltd</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/29">Fishing organisations have also received help from regional development agencies. Fisheries grants have also been given to many other bodies, e.g. individual fishermen, sea fisheries committees, local authorities and harbour authorities.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.22.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn0">
	Incapacity Benefit
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.22.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100597" speakername="Lord Skelmersdale" colon="" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.22.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.22.1/2" qnum="HL2205">Further to the Answer by the Lord Hunt of Kings Heath on 7 November (Official Report, col. 393), which CMS call centres are failing to reach the 84 per cent target referred to for responding to calls.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.22.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.22.2/1">The most up to date information available, for the week ending <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-11">11 November 2005</phrase> indicates that we are now answering an average of 85.7 per cent of calls to CMS contact centres from customers making benefit claims. Out of 22 CMS contact centres, nine contact centres are operating below the 85.7 per cent level. The target is 90 per cent.</p>
	<p pid="c.22.2/2">These contact centres concerned are listed below along with their opening date.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="c.22.2/5"> <td></td> <td>Date went live with CMS</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.22.2/6"> <td>Marton Mere</td> <td>24.11.03</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.22.2/7"> <td>Garston</td> <td>08.12.03</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.22.2/8"> <td>Poole</td> <td>12.01.04</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.22.2/9"> <td>Dundee</td> <td>06.02.04</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.22.2/10"> <td>Grimsby</td> <td>09.02.04</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.22.2/11"> <td>Derby</td> <td>22.03.05</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.22.2/12"> <td>Bridgend</td> <td>11.05.05</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.22.2/13"> <td>Blackburn</td> <td>10.08.05</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.22.2/14"> <td>Taunton</td> <td>05.09.05</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="c.22.2/17">Jobcentre Plus is undergoing a massive change programme. Change on this scale does create challenges in maintaining levels of service and it has put the business under some pressure. We acknowledge that, in many cases, there will be a temporary loss in performance in this transitional period and it is clear that some customers have experienced difficulties in getting through to the contact centre.</p>
	<p pid="c.22.2/18">Immediate measures have been put in place to address this, including temporary adjustments to streamline business processes in order to maintain the service Jobcentre Plus provides to customers during this transitional period. Recruitment plans have also been strengthened. Indeed, we increased headcount by 475 people in the past two months and we have future plans to recruit more staff up to our approved headcount. This recruitment is supported by robust staff training programmes.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.23.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn1">
	Iraq: White Phosphorus Munitions
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.23.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100778" speakername="Lord Garden" colon="" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.23.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.23.1/2" qnum="HL2346">On what date they, or their civilian or military officials, first become aware that white phosphorus munitions were being used by coalition forces in an offensive role against Iraqi citizens; and</p>
	<p pid="c.23.1/3" qnum="HL2350">Whether they have a policy over the use of white phosphorus munitions in an offensive role in coalition operations; and, if so, what that policy is.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.23.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.23.2/1">We are not aware of evidence to suggest that coalition forces have targeted the Iraqi civilian population during operations in Iraq. White phosphorus is used primarily as an obscurant (i.e. for smokescreens) or for illumination. Although white phosphorus does have a recognised anti-personnel effect, coalition forces take care to minimise the impact of operations on civilians.</p>
	<p pid="c.23.2/2">British forces training in the use of white phosphorus emphasises that it should not be used as an anti-personnel weapon.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.23.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn2">
	Israel: Bethlehem
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.23.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100851" speakername="Baroness Tonge" colon="" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.23.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.23.4/2" qnum="HL2385">What representations they will make to the Israeli Government concerning Bethlehem and the tourist industry; and</p>
	<p pid="c.23.4/3" qnum="HL2386">What support they are giving to Christians in Bethlehem and the organisation &quot;Open Bethlehem&quot;.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.23.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_spnew1">
	<p pid="c.23.5/1">Bethlehem is of unique religious and cultural significance to Christians. Restrictions on access and freedom of worship there are among the many negative consequences of the Israeli restrictions on access and movement in the West Bank and Jerusalem. We, along with our EU partners, continue to call on Israel to ease restrictions on movement wherever possible. We are not giving any direct support to the organisation &quot;Open Bethlehem&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="c.23.5/2">We understand that, at this time of year, there will be many people wanting to visit this area and that free movement around Christmas is particularly important.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.24.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn3">
	Israel: Gaza
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.24.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100851" speakername="Baroness Tonge" colon="" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.24.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.24.1/2" qnum="HL2384">What representations they have made to the Israeli Government regarding the acquittal of the army captain in connection with the death of 13 year-old Sami al-Hams near Rafah last year.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.24.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_spnew2">
	<p pid="c.24.2/1">We deplore all civilian casualties, particularly children, which have resulted from this conflict. We recognise Israel's right to defend itself from acts of violence, but call upon the Israeli Government to act with restraint and in accordance with international law including taking every effort to avoid civilian casualties. In this case, we have made no representations following the acquittal. At the time of the trial in 2004 we registered our concern about the killing with the Israeli Government.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.24.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn4">
	Israel: Gaza and the West Bank
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.24.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100851" speakername="Baroness Tonge" colon="" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.24.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.24.4/2" qnum="HL2387">What representations they will make to the Israeli Government on the economic future of Gaza and the West Bank.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.24.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_spnew3">
	<p pid="c.24.5/1">We have stressed to the government of Israel, including at senior levels, the importance of their facilitating efforts to help revitalise the Palestinian economy. These efforts have been led by James Wolfensohn, who has our full support. On <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-25">25 November</phrase>, US Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice, EU Special Representative Javier Solana and James Wolfensohn announced the opening of the Rafah border and agreement on a number of other access issues. We will continue to press the government of Israel to help ensure conditions exist for Palestinian economic development.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.24.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn5">
	Israel: Occupied Territories
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.24.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100851" speakername="Baroness Tonge" colon="" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn5">
	<p pid="c.24.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.24.7/2" qnum="HL2383">What representations they have made to the Israeli Government following the recent raid in Nablus and the killing of a Hamas leader.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.24.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_spnew4">
	<p pid="c.24.8/1">We have not raised specifically the killing of a Hamas leader in Nablus on <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-14">14 November</phrase>. My honourable friend the Minister of State at the Foreign and Commonwealth Office (Kim Howells) and the British Embassy in Tel Aviv have made representations to Israeli officials on several occasions about our concerns regarding Israeli actions in the occupied territories, particularly the West Bank, which threaten to undermine the Tahdi'a (&quot;calm&quot;). We will continue to do so.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.25.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn6">
	Israel: Palestinian Prisoners
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.25.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100851" speakername="Baroness Tonge" colon="" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn6">
	<p pid="c.25.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.25.1/2" qnum="HL2388">What action they have taken to ensure the Government of Israel's compliance with its international legal requirements in respect of Palestinian prisoners in Israeli prisons.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.25.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_spnew5">
	<p pid="c.25.2/1">We continue to monitor the situation with regard to Palestinian prisoners and raise our concerns with the Israeli authorities, including with the Israel Prison Service.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.25.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn7">
	Lisbon Agenda
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.25.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100324" speakername="Lord Inglewood" colon="" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn7">
	<p pid="c.25.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.25.4/2" qnum="HL2345">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord President on 2 November (<i>WA 23</i>), whether they can confirm that a single Minister has specific responsibility for the Lisbon Agenda.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.25.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.25.5/1">No single Minister has sole responsibility for the EU's Lisbon Agenda of economic and social reform. The agenda covers a wide range of government activity encompassing economic, social, and environmental policy. The Government have therefore chosen to encourage all relevant departments to contribute directly to the achievement of the Lisbon jobs and growth agenda, with Cabinet and the committee system providing policy oversight and consistency.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.25.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn8">
	Lundy No-Take Zone
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.25.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100427" speakername="Baroness Miller of Chilthorne Domer" colon="" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_wqn8">
	<p pid="c.25.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.25.7/2" qnum="HL2192">What conclusions English Nature has reached from the experimental Lundy no-take zone.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.25.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w03.htm#51129w03_spnew6">
	<p pid="c.25.8/1">The Lundy no-take zone was established in 2003 by means of a Devon Sea Fisheries Committee by-law which prohibited fishing in and off the east coast of the island. Monitoring of the area of around 3.3 kilometres <sup>2</sup> impact of the no-take zone is being undertaken with funding provided by English Nature, Defra and WWF.</p>
	<p pid="c.25.8/2">In July 2005, English Nature reported that this monitoring was demonstrating promising results, with lobsters showing a significant increase in numbers. It is understood that monitoring will need to continue for several years before conclusions can be reached on the impact of the no-take zone on fish stocks and the wider marine environment.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.25.9" nospeaker="true" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_wqn0">
	Powers of Entry
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.25.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100580" speakername="Lord Selsdon" colon="" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.25.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.25.10/2" qnum="HL2363">In what circumstances officials of the Treasury, and of public bodies answerable to the Chancellor of the Exchequer, can search and enter the homes of business premises of United Kingdom citizens; and, in each case, what is the statutory authority for that power.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.26.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100802" speakername="Lord McKenzie of Luton" colon=":" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.26.0/1">I refer the noble Lord to the Answer given to him on <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-23">23 November</phrase> by Baroness Scotland of Asthal (<phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2005-11-23.218"><i>Official Report</i>, Col. WA 218&ndash;19</phrase>).</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.26.1" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_wqn1">
	Powers of Entry
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.26.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100580" speakername="Lord Selsdon" colon="" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.26.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.26.2/2" qnum="HL2366">In what circumstances officials of the Department for Work and Pensions, and of public bodies answerable to the Secretary of State for Work and Pensions, can search and enter the homes or business premises of United Kingdom citizens; and, in each case, what is the statutory authority for that power.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.26.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_spnew1">
	<p pid="c.26.3/1">I refer the noble Lord to the Answer given by my noble friend Lady Scotland of Asthal on <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-23">23 November 2005</phrase> (<phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2005-11-23.218"><i>Official Report, </i>cols. WA 218&ndash;19</phrase>).</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.26.4" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_wqn2">
	Powers of Entry
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.26.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100580" speakername="Lord Selsdon" colon="" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.26.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.26.5/2" qnum="HL2367">In what circumstances officials of the Department for Transport, and of public bodies answerable to the Secretary of State for Transport, can search and enter the homes or business premises of United Kingdom citizens; and, in each case, what is the statutory authority for that power.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.26.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100164" speakername="Lord Davies of Oldham" colon=":" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_spnew2">
	<p pid="c.26.6/1">I refer the noble Lord to the Answer given by my right honourable friend the Minister of State for the Home Department (Baroness Scotland of Asthal) on <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-23">23 November 2005</phrase> (<phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2005-11-23.218"><i>Official Report</i>, cols. WA 218&ndash;19</phrase>).</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.26.7" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_wqn3">
	Powers of Entry
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.26.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100580" speakername="Lord Selsdon" colon="" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.26.8/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.26.8/2" qnum="HL2408">In what circumstances officials of the Ministry of Defence and of public bodies answerable to the Secretary of State for Defence can search and enter the homes or business premises of United Kingdom citizens; and, in each case, what is the statutory authority for that power.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.26.9" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_spnew3">
	<p pid="c.26.9/1">I refer the noble Lord to the reply given by my noble friend Lady Scotland of Asthal on <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-23">23 November 2005</phrase> (<phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2005-11-23.218"><i>Official Report</i>, cols. WA 218&ndash;19</phrase>).</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.26.10" nospeaker="true" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_wqn4">
	Sudan: Darfur
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.26.11" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.26.11/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.26.11/2" qnum="HL2325">What investigations they have made or suggested during the United Kingdom presidency of the European Union into the sources of weapons and equipment used by the Janjaweed.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.26.12" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_spnew4">
	<p pid="c.26.12/1">The UK carefully monitors the situation in Darfur. We have discussed the need to control the weapons held by the Arab militias with the government of Sudan.</p>
	<p pid="c.26.12/2">The EU already has a country-wide embargo against the whole of Sudan which we implement assiduously. We have not made or suggested any investigations but we have supported the adoption of UN Security Council Resolution (UNSCR) 1591 of <phrase class="date" code="2005-03-29">29 March</phrase> which imposes an arms embargo on Darfur, and provides for a travel ban and assets freeze against certain individuals. Under the terms of this resolution, the sanctions committee must provide approval for the government of Sudan to move any military equipment into Darfur. The panel of experts, established by UNSCR 1591, is investigating the implementation and effectiveness of this arms embargo, and will report to the Security Council at the beginning of December. Any individuals found to be violating the resolution, including by breaking the arms embargo, may be subjected to targeted sanctions by the committee. The UK is pressing for action on designation of individuals and on other measures which the Security Council could take such as widening the arms embargo to cover the whole country.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.28.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="28"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_wqn5">
	University Degrees
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.28.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100469" speakername="Lord Oakeshott of Seagrove Bay" colon="" colnum="28"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_wqn5">
	<p pid="c.28.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.28.1/2" qnum="HL2461">What percentage of students who gained first degrees in 2003 and 2004 from the Universities of Oxford and Cambridge and each member of the Russell group of universities received (a) a first class honours degree, and (b) a 2(1) honours degree.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.28.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100839" speakername="Lord Adonis" colon=":" colnum="28"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_spnew5">
	<p pid="c.28.2/1">The latest available data, showing students who graduated in 2003 and 2004, are given in the table.</p>
	<table>
		<caption>First Degree Graduates by Class of Degree Obtained, 2002&ndash;03 and 2003&ndash;04</caption>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/5"> <td></td> <td>Academic Year</td> <td>Total qualifiers</td> <td>1st class (percentage)</td> <td>Upper 2nd class (percentage)</td> <td>Others (percentage)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/6"> <td><i>The University of Birmingham</i></td> <td><i>2002&ndash;03</i></td> <td><i>4,010</i></td> <td><i>10.3</i></td> <td><i>49.9</i></td> <td><i>39.8</i></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/7"> <td></td> <td><i>2003&ndash;04</i></td> <td><i>4,430</i></td> <td><i>10.5</i></td> <td><i>51.3</i></td> <td><i>38.2</i></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/8"> <td><i>The University of Bristol</i></td> <td><i>2002&ndash;03</i></td> <td><i>2,755</i></td> <td><i>16.8</i></td> <td><i>56.6</i></td> <td><i>26.6</i></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/9"> <td></td> <td><i>2003&ndash;04</i></td> <td><i>2,860</i></td> <td><i>18.0</i></td> <td><i>55.7</i></td> <td><i>26.3</i></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/10"> <td><i>The University of Cambridge1</i></td> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>3,530</td> <td>32.9</td> <td>52.5</td> <td>14.7</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/11"> <td></td> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>3,695</td> <td>22.4</td> <td>57.3</td> <td>20.3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/12"> <td>The University of Leeds</td> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>5,715</td> <td>11.2</td> <td>52.5</td> <td>36.3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/13"> <td></td> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>5,320</td> <td>12.2</td> <td>55.3</td> <td>32.5</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/14"> <td>The University of Liverpool</td> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>3,075</td> <td>10.0</td> <td>44.8</td> <td>45.2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/15"> <td></td> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>3,240</td> <td>12.0</td> <td>43.1</td> <td>44.8</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/16"> <td>Imperial College of Science, Technology and Medicine</td> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>1,715</td> <td>22.7</td> <td>38.5</td> <td>38.8</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/17"> <td></td> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>1,605</td> <td>24.7</td> <td>38.1</td> <td>37.2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/18"> <td>King's College London</td> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>2,750</td> <td>11.8</td> <td>47.3</td> <td>40.9</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/19"> <td></td> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>2,985</td> <td>13.1</td> <td>45.6</td> <td>41.3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/20"> <td>London School of Economics and Political Science</td> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>940</td> <td>20.2</td> <td>54.1</td> <td>25.7</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/21"> <td></td> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>1,065</td> <td>18.7</td> <td>55.7</td> <td>25.7</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/22"> <td>University College London</td> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>3,280</td> <td>16.6</td> <td>50.4</td> <td>33.0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/23"> <td></td> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>3,500</td> <td>17.1</td> <td>47.3</td> <td>35.7</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/24"> <td>The Victoria University of Manchester</td> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>4,205</td> <td>15.7</td> <td>48.7</td> <td>35.6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/25"> <td></td> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>4,620</td> <td>15.1</td> <td>50.3</td> <td>34.5</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/26"> <td>The University of Newcastle-upon-Tyne</td> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>2,815</td> <td>10.3</td> <td>49.4</td> <td>40.3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/27"> <td></td> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>3,390</td> <td>10.4</td> <td>49.5</td> <td>40.1</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/28"> <td>The University of Nottingham</td> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>3,875</td> <td>13.8</td> <td>56.6</td> <td>29.7</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/29"> <td></td> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>4,495</td> <td>13.6</td> <td>58.0</td> <td>28.4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/30"> <td>The University of Oxford</td> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>3,275</td> <td>23.4</td> <td>60.5</td> <td>16.1</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/31"> <td></td> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>3,225</td> <td>22.7</td> <td>63.0</td> <td>14.3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/32"> <td>The University of Sheffield</td> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>3,980</td> <td>13.9</td> <td>53.3</td> <td>32.8</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/33"> <td></td> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>3,865</td> <td>13.8</td> <td>53.9</td> <td>32.3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/34"> <td>The University of Southampton</td> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>3,145</td> <td>14.9</td> <td>51.1</td> <td>34.0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/35"> <td></td> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>3,150</td> <td>16.6</td> <td>49.8</td> <td>33.6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/36"> <td>The University of Warwick</td> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>2,615</td> <td>20.3</td> <td>58.2</td> <td>21.5</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/37"> <td></td> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>2,795</td> <td>19.6</td> <td>56.8</td> <td>23.6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/38"> <td>The University of Edinburgh</td> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>3,430</td> <td>14.0</td> <td>49.2</td> <td>36.8</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/39"> <td></td> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>3,470</td> <td>13.8</td> <td>49.3</td> <td>37.0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/40"> <td>The University of Glasgow</td> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>3,260</td> <td>9.0</td> <td>40.7</td> <td>50.3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/41"> <td></td> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>3,025</td> <td>10.7</td> <td>40.7</td> <td>48.6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/42"> <td>Cardiff University</td> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>3,520</td> <td>13.0</td> <td>55.7</td> <td>31.3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.28.2/43"> <td></td> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>3,415</td> <td>12.6</td> <td>55.0</td> <td>32.4</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="c.28.2/46">Source: Higher Education Statistics Agency (HESA) student record. Figures have been rounded to the nearest five.</p>
	<p pid="c.28.2/47">1 The University of Cambridge does not award degree classifications for its BA degree, but instead classifies examinations taken at the end of each academic year. Prior to 2003&ndash;04, the degree classification recorded on the HESA student record was the best classification obtained, not necessarily that obtained in the final year. From 2003&ndash;04 onwards, the classification obtained in the final year is reported on the record and this corresponds more directly with other institutions.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.29.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_wqn6">
	Wild Birds
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.29.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100098" speakername="Baroness Byford" colon="" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_wqn6">
	<p pid="c.29.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.29.1/2" qnum="HL2453">Further to the reply by the Lord Bach on 17 November (<i>Official Report</i>, col. 1298), whether, in addition to sniffer dogs, they support the use of electronic surveillance machinery to detect illegally imported wild birds.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.29.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100802" speakername="Lord McKenzie of Luton" colon=":" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_spnew6">
	<p pid="c.29.2/1">The Government support the use of such machinery including in particular X-ray scanning equipment to detect any illegally imported goods.</p>
	<p pid="c.29.2/2">HM Revenue and Customs already uses X-ray equipment when appropriate and continually monitors the marketplace for other technology that could also assist.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.30.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_wqn7">
	World Trade Organisation: Hong Kong Summit
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.30.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100804" speakername="Lord Dykes" colon="" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_wqn7">
	<p pid="c.30.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.30.1/2" qnum="HL2477">When they expect to hold talks with the President of the United States on the prospects for progress at the forthcoming Hong Kong World Trade Organisation summit.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-29c.30.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo051129/text/51129w04.htm#51129w04_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.30.2/1">Her Majesty's Government are in regular contact with the United States at all levels, official and ministerial, on a range of trade issues, including prospects for progress at the forthcoming Hong Kong World Trade Organisation summit.</p>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

