<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.57.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="57"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_wqn0">
	Northern Ireland: Child Death Review
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.57.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100059" speakername="Baroness Blood" colon="" colnum="57"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.57.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.57.1/2" qnum="HL2881">Whether the regional child death review arrangement in Northern Ireland has been completed; and on what date it is expected to be implemented.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.57.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="57"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.57.2/1">The Department of Health, Social Services and Public Safety is currently considering a draft of the child death review protocol produced by a group established under the auspices of the Southern Area Health and Social Services Board, Area Child Protection Committee. Departmental officials will shortly meet with stakeholders to decide the way forward.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.57.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="57"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_wqn1">
	North/South Ministerial Council: Official Languages Act 2003
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.57.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="57"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.57.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.57.4/2" qnum="HL2947">On what date the North/South Ministerial Secretariat became aware of the involvement of Cross-Border Implementation Bodies in the Republic of Ireland's Official Languages Act 2003; what action the secretariat took; and when; and</p>
	<p pid="a.57.4/3" qnum="HL2948">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord President on 17 May (<i>WA 53</i>) concerning the Republic of Ireland's Official Languages Act 2003, whether there was any discussion between the North/South Ministerial Secretariat and the appropriate government departments and the Eire Government on the Act; if so, when such discussions took place; and what was their nature.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.57.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="57"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.57.5/1">The North/South Ministerial Council Secretariat became aware of the involvement of the North/South Implementation Bodies in the Official Languages Act 2003 on <phrase class="date" code="2003-05-29">29 May 2003</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.57.5/2">Following subsequent discussions between relevant officials, north and south, on a number of occasions, the secretariat facilitated a formal discussion on <phrase class="date" code="2004-03-19">19 March 2004</phrase> when it was agreed that a code of practice reflecting the legal and policy frameworks established in both jurisdictions on the use of Irish language and Ulster Scots would be prepared.</p>
	<p pid="a.57.5/3">I have nothing further to add to the Answer given on <phrase class="date" code="2004-05-06">6 May 2004</phrase> (<i>WA 125</i>) regarding discussions on the Official Languages Act 2003.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.57.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="57"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_wqn2">
	Tourism Ireland
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.57.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="57"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.57.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.57.7/2" qnum="HL3024">What new initiatives Tourism Ireland has introduced since 19 November 2002.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.58.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="58"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.58.0/1">None. Details of Tourism Ireland Ltd's planned activities for 2003 and 2004 appear in the company's published operating plans. The plans were approved by the North/South Ministerial Council and copies of these are available in the Library.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.58.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="58"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_wqn3">
	Northern Ireland Tourism Awards
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.58.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="58"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.58.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.58.2/2" qnum="HL3268">How much the 2004 Northern Ireland Tourist Board awards cost to run; whether income was generated from these awards; and if there was a shortfall, how it was funded.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.58.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="58"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.58.3/1">The 2004 Northern Ireland Tourism Awards event was self-financing, with no shortfall in funding. The Northern Ireland Tourist Board incurred event management services fees of &pound;9,870 plus VAT.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.58.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="58"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_wqn4">
	Northern Ireland: Employer's Liability
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.58.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="58"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.58.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.58.5/2" qnum="HL3403">Whether the 1972 Northern Ireland Order on Compensation (963 (NI 6)) applies to employees of Northern Ireland companies working outside Northern Ireland; and, if not, in what way those employees can be compensated for accidents if the relevant insurance company goes out of business.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.58.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="58"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.58.6/1">It is assumed that the question relates to the Employers Liability (Defective Equipment and Compulsory Insurance) (NI) Order 1972 published by the Health and Safety Executive for Northern Ireland. Guidance relating to that order states:</p>
	<p pid="a.58.6/2" class="indent">&quot;You do not need employer's liability insurance under Northern Ireland law to cover any of your employees who are based abroad (eg if they are on secondment). However, you should check whether the law in the country where they are based requires you to take out insurance or take any other measures to protect your employees.</p>
	<p pid="a.58.6/3" class="indent">If any of your employees are normally based abroad but spend more than 14 days continuously in Northern Ireland, or more than seven days on an offshore installation, you will need employer's liability insurance under Northern Ireland law.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.58.6/4">An employee with a workplace-related claim under their employer's compulsory liability insurance or other insurance may be entitled to compensation under the financial services compensation scheme if their employer's insurer goes out of business.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.58.7" nospeaker="true" colnum="58"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_wqn5">
	Northern Ireland: Education
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.58.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100410" speakername="Lord Maginnis of Drumglass" colon="" colnum="58"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.58.8/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.58.8/2" qnum="0">Whether in pursuance of the objectives of the Costello report on post-primary education in Northern Ireland, the Northern Ireland Office has undertaken any infrastructural audit of current educational facilities outside the Greater Belfast area; if so, what that audit has indicated are:</p>
	<p pid="a.58.8/3" qnum="0">(a) the estimated average hours per week that pupils and teachers will spend travelling between schools; and</p>
	<p pid="a.58.8/4" qnum="HL3424">(b) the estimated costs per annum of providing transport and supervisory support over the first 10 years of education; and when the audit will be made public.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.59.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="59"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.59.0/1">No such audit has taken place. Proposals for new post-primary arrangements, including arrangements for co-operation and collaboration among schools, will be developed locally and organised to minimise disruption to the school day, for example by use of e-learning and distance learning.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.59.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="59"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_wqn6">
	European Union: Association Agreements
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.59.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="59"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.59.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.59.2/2" qnum="HL3307">Whether any record is made of the human rights matters discussed at meetings of association councils held pursuant to European Union association agreements; and how the Government decide whether breaches of human rights in the states concerned are sufficiently grave to justify invoking the penalties specified in the agreements.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.59.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="59"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.59.3/1">Association councils comprise (i) a plenary session and (ii) a political dialogue between Ministers. Human rights issues are typically covered in the latter. The council secretariat produces a restricted note of these discussions.</p>
	<p pid="a.59.3/2">All association agreements contain a human rights clause. This allows the European Union (EU) to take &quot;appropriate measures&quot;, including suspending provisions in the agreement, if it considers that the third country is failing to meet its obligations under the agreement, including respect for fundamental rights. To date these clauses have not been invoked. However, human rights are a core agenda item at many of the association councils. Equivalent articles in the Cotonou agreement have been invoked on a number of occasions.</p>
	<p pid="a.59.3/3">If the Government had concerns about the situation in a particular country, they would initiate discussions with partners in the relevant EU working group. These groups regularly consider the human rights records of third countries in relation to the human rights clauses of association agreements. As a new initiative, human rights sub-committees are being established in relation to some third countries.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.60.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_wqn7">
	Afghanistan: Electoral Registration
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.60.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.60.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.60.1/2" qnum="HL3311">What information the provisional reconstruction team in Afghanistan have about the number of citizens who have registered to vote in each of the provinces; and whether the registration process can be speeded up.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.60.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w01.htm#40705w01_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.60.2/1">The UK and other provincial reconstruction teams do not have any electoral responsibilities other than assisting in ensuring a secure environment in their area of operations. But according to the Afghanistan Joint Electoral Monitoring Body, as of <phrase class="date" code="2004-06-17">17 June</phrase>, over 4 million Afghans had been registered to vote, of whom 35 per cent are women.</p>
	<p pid="a.60.2/2">The following is a regional breakdown for <phrase class="date" code="2004-06-14">14 June</phrase> (we do not have precise information for <phrase class="date" code="2004-06-17">17 June</phrase>):</p>
	<p pid="a.60.2/3" class="indent">Central 1,155,982</p>
	<p pid="a.60.2/4" class="indent">East 521,394</p>
	<p pid="a.60.2/5" class="indent">North East 559,387</p>
	<p pid="a.60.2/6" class="indent">South East 210,155</p>
	<p pid="a.60.2/7" class="indent">Central Highlands 246,486</p>
	<p pid="a.60.2/8" class="indent">North 398,848</p>
	<p pid="a.60.2/9" class="indent">South 309,466</p>
	<p pid="a.60.2/10" class="indent">West 537,317</p>
	<p pid="a.60.2/11">Phase I of voter registration, in Kabul and regional centres, has been completed and Phase II, designed to reach more rural areas, was launched on <phrase class="date" code="2004-05-01">1 May</phrase>. The pace of registration is speeding up.</p>
	<p pid="a.60.2/12">The UK is committed to supporting the electoral process. Last year we contributed &pound;10.55 million to support election registration. We have pledged a further &pound;0.5 million for voter education and &pound;2.77 million to support preparations for elections themselves.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.60.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_wqn0">
	Mr Kenny Richey
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.60.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.60.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.60.4/2" qnum="HL3338">Whether they will submit an <i>amicus curiae </i>brief to the United States Federal 6th Circuit Court of Appeals in support of the application by Mr Kenny Richey, a British Citizen, on the lawfulness of his conviction and sentence for aggravated felony murder in 1987; and what other measures they will take to prevent Mr Richey being executed.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.60.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="60"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.60.5/1">We are following developments in Mr Richey's case closely and shall do all we properly can to try to prevent his execution. The Consul General in Chicago recently raised our interest in and concern about Mr Richey's case with the Governor of Ohio, Bob Taft. We shall continue to lobby the relevant US authorities, as and when appropriate.</p>
	<p pid="a.60.5/2">Any request to submit an <i>amicus </i>brief in a particular case is very carefully considered. We are urgently exploring the most appropriate way to register HMG's concern about Mr Richey's case with the US authorities, and the possibility of filing an <i>amicus curiae </i>brief is being examined in this context.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.61.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="61"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_wqn1">
	Dreams + Teams Programme
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.61.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100447" speakername="Lord Moynihan" colon="" colnum="61"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.61.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.61.1/2" qnum="HL3352">Whether during 2003 and 2004 meetings have been initiated between the British Council, the Department for Culture, Media and Sport, the Department for Education and Skills and UK Sport about the operation of the &quot;Dreams + Teams&quot; programme; and what is the status of the programme.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.61.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="61"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.61.2/1">Meetings have been held in both years between the British Council, the Department for Culture, Media and Sport, the Department for Education and Skills and UK Sport, to share information on the international programme of each organisation. Dreams + Teams is active in over 30 countries, with involvement from governmental and non-governmental partners in those countries. The programme is a British Council programme which focuses on promoting education and school links through sport.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.61.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="61"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_wqn2">
	Dreams + Teams Programme
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.61.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100447" speakername="Lord Moynihan" colon="" colnum="61"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.61.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.61.4/2" qnum="HL3353">What is the budget for the British Council's &quot;Dreams + Teams&quot; programme; and what is the proposed level of funding for each of the partners.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.61.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="61"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.61.5/1">The British Council has a budget of approximately &pound;300,000 for Dreams + Teams activities in over 30 countries. This is supplemented by contributions from both governmental and non-governmental partners in those countries.</p>
	<p pid="a.61.5/2">The British Council and the Youth Sport Trust jointly fund a post to co-ordinate the UK schools links element of the programme. The British Council pays Dreams + Teams tutor trainers via the Youth Sport Trust. In the past financial year, this amounted to some &pound;35,000.</p>
	<p pid="a.61.5/3">There are no plans to increase the level of funding for any partners by the British Council. So far as we are aware, there are no plans for partners to increase their funding either.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.61.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="61"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_wqn3">
	British Indian Ocean Territory
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.61.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="61"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.61.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.61.7/2" qnum="HL3371">How many of the former residents of the Chagos Archipelago have resettled in Mauritius, the Seychelles and the United Kingdom respectively; and how many of each group have indicated that they would like to return to their original homes if they were allowed to do so.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.62.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.62.0/1">It is now more than 30 years since the last of the former inhabitants of the Chagos Archipelago left the islands. There are no reliable figures for the numbers of them who are now living in Mauritius, Seychelles or the UK. However, there is a substantial community of persons in Mauritius who are either former residents of the Chagos islands or the descendants of such residents; and there are smaller such communities in Seychelles and the UK. There are no figures available for those members of these communities who have indicated that they would move to the Chagos Islands if they were allowed to do so.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.62.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_wqn4">
	United States: Detainees
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.62.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.62.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.62.2/2" qnum="HL3381">Further to the Written Answer by the Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean on 21 June (<i>WA 98</i>), what information they have received from the United States Government in the course of their regular exchanges concerning the numbers and locations of persons held outside the United States, given that such prisoners may lack protection from United States law and international humanitarian instruments.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.62.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.62.3/1">The Government do not disclose the details of their confidential exchanges with other governments.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.62.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_wqn5">
	Brazil, Honduras and Guatemala: Children
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.62.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100427" speakername="Baroness Miller of Chilthorne Domer" colon="" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.62.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.62.5/2" qnum="HL3389">What action they have taken to urge the Governments of Brazil, Honduras and Guatemala to prosecute those responsible for the murder of street children; and</p>
	<p pid="a.62.5/3" qnum="HL3390">What action they have taken to raise concerns with the Government of Brazil regarding the commercial sexual exploitation of children in that country; and</p>
	<p pid="a.62.5/4" qnum="HL3391">What action they have taken to urge the Governments of Brazil and Honduras to make significant improvements in the living conditions of juvenile detainees.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.62.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="62"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.62.6/1">We have made clear to the Governments of Brazil, Honduras and Guatemala, bilaterally and with our European Union (EU) partners, the importance we attach to respect for human rights, including those of children. We closely monitor the progress being made by the authorities in these countries on this issue and, in particular, on bringing those responsible for the murders of street children to justice.</p>
	<p pid="a.62.6/2">The chronic and well documented situation faced by street children in Brazil is a matter for concern and forms a regular part of our human rights dialogue with the Brazilian Government. The UK supports a number of practical projects in Brazil including human rights training for the Brazilian police and prison services; a small arms project in the slum areas of Rio de Janeiro, and work in Rio on giving people alternatives to involvement in violent and organised crime. While not exclusively focused on street children, these projects are relevant to many of the problems they face.</p>
	<p pid="a.62.6/3">My honourable friend the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State at the Foreign and Commonwealth Office (Bill Rammell) raised the plight of street children, and more generally the importance of protecting human rights, with the new Guatemalan Government during his visit there in January and with the Honduran Security Minister Oscar Alvarez during his visit to the UK in March. The UK and EU partners recently issued a statement at the consultative group meeting for Honduras in Tegucigalpa, which among other things, encouraged the Honduran Government to continue the progress made on improving human rights, making reference to the rights of children.</p>
	<p pid="a.62.6/4">The UK has also supported projects in Guatemala and Honduras to improve the conditions of and protect vulnerable children.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.63.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_wqn6">
	European Union: Free Trade Agreements
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.63.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100491" speakername="Lord Pearson of Rannoch" colon="" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.63.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.63.1/2" qnum="HL3440">With which non-European Union countries the European Union has free trade agreements; and, in each case, when the agreement entered into force.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.63.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="63"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w02.htm#40705w02_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.63.2/1">The European Union has an extensive network of free trade agreements (FTAs).</p>
	<p pid="a.63.2/2">The EU's longest-standing FTAs are those with the countries of the European Free Trade Area (EFTA). The FTA with Switzerland dates back to 1972, and came into force on <phrase class="date" code="1973-01-01">1 January 1973</phrase>. FTAs in goods with Norway and Iceland entered into force in 1973, <phrase class="date" code="2004-07-01">1 July</phrase> and <phrase class="date" code="2004-04-01">1 April</phrase> respectively. These last two countries, along with Liechtenstein, are now covered by the European Economic Area (EEA) Agreement, which entered into force on <phrase class="date" code="1974-01-01">1 January 1974</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.63.2/3">As regards the EU's candidate countries, the customs union between the EU and Turkey came into effect on <phrase class="date" code="1996-01-01">1 January 1996</phrase>. The pre-accession Europe agreements with Romania and Bulgaria came into force in February 1995, and liberalise over 95 per cent of each country's trade with the EU.</p>
	<p pid="a.63.2/4">A stabilisation and association agreement, including an FTA, with the Former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia entered into force on <phrase class="date" code="2004-05-01">1 May 2004</phrase>; the FTA element of the SAA with Croatia came into force provisionally on <phrase class="date" code="2002-01-01">1 January 2002</phrase> pending the ratification of the full agreement. These render reciprocal the trade concessions granted to these three countries, as well as to Bosnia and Herzegovina and Serbia and Montenegro, by the autonomous trade concessions agreement of 2000.</p>
	<p pid="a.63.2/5">The EU also has association agreements, again including FTAs, with several Mediterranean countries, as part of its goal (through the Barcelona, or EuroMed, process) of the creation by 2010 of a free trade area covering the EU and Mediterranean partners. Such agreements have entered into force with Jordan (<phrase class="date" code="2002-05-01">1 May 2002</phrase>), Morocco (<phrase class="date" code="2000-03-01">1 March 2000</phrase>), Tunisia (<phrase class="date" code="1998-03-01">1 March 1998</phrase>), Israel (<phrase class="date" code="2000-06-01">1 June 2000</phrase>) and Egypt (<phrase class="date" code="2004-06-01">1 June 2004</phrase>). Interim FTAs with the PLO (for the benefit of the Palestinian Authority) came into force on <phrase class="date" code="1997-07-01">1 July 1997</phrase>, and with Lebanon on <phrase class="date" code="2003-03-01">1 March 2003</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.63.2/6">In Latin America, an association agreement with Chile came into force on <phrase class="date" code="2003-02-01">1 February 2003</phrase> (on a provisional basis). The FTAs in goods and services established under the EU-Mexico Economic Partnership, Political Co-ordination and Co-operation Agreement came into force on <phrase class="date" code="2000-07-01">1 July 2000</phrase> and on <phrase class="date" code="2001-03-01">1 March 2001</phrase> respectively. A trade, development and co-operation agreement, also including an FTA, with South Africa entered into force provisionally on <phrase class="date" code="2000-01-01">1 January 2000</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.64.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="64"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn0">
	European Union: Free Trade Agreements
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.64.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100491" speakername="Lord Pearson of Rannoch" colon="" colnum="64"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.64.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.64.1/2" qnum="HL3441">With which non-European Union countries the European Union is currently negotiating free trade agreements.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.64.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="64"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.64.2/1">The European Union is currently in the process of negotiating a free trade agreement (FTA) with the Gulf Co-operation Council (comprising Bahrain, Kuwait, Oman, Qatar, Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates). Association agreements, which include FTAs, are being negotiated with Syria and with Mercosur (Argentina, Brazil, Paraguay and Uruguay). A stablisation and association agreement, also including an FTA, is under negotiation with Albania.</p>
	<p pid="a.64.2/2">Economic partnership agreements (EPAs) with the African, Caribbean and Pacific (ACP) group of countries will replace the 2000 Cotonou agreement and institute FTAs with six sub-groupings. Negotiations have begun on EPAs with west Africa (the ECOWAS states&mdash;Benin, Burkina Faso, Cape Verde, C&ocirc;te d'Ivoire, The Gambia, Ghana, Guinea, Guinea Bissau, Liberia, Mali, Niger, Nigeria, Senegal, Sierra Leone and Togo&mdash;plus Mauretania), central Africa (the CEMAC states&mdash;Cameroon, the Central African Republic, Chad, Congo, Equatorial Guinea and Gabon&mdash;plus Sao Tom&eacute; e Principe), eastern and southern Africa (the COMESA states&mdash;Angola, Burundi, Comoros, DR Congo, Djibouti, Eritrea, Ethiopia, Kenya, Madagascar, Malawi, Mauritius, Namibia, Rwanda, Seychelles, Sudan, Swaziland, Uganda, Zambia and Zimbabwe), and the Caribbean (the CARICOM countries&mdash;Antigua &amp; Barbuda, the Bahamas, Barbados, Belize, Dominica, Grenada, Guyana, Haiti, Jamaica, St Kitts &amp; Nevis, St Lucia, St Vincent &amp; the Grenadines, Suriname and Trinidad &amp; Tobago&mdash;plus the Dominican Republic). Negotiations with the SADC states and with the Pacific sub-group are due to begin later this year.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.65.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn1">
	Iraq: Human Rights
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.65.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100367" speakername="Lord Lester of Herne Hill" colon="" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.65.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.65.1/2" qnum="HL2752">Whether any legal or disciplinary measures have been taken against any members of the Armed Forces or other United Kingdom personnel or persons employed by contractors in Iraq for breaches of international human rights law or international humanitarian law; and, if so, whether they will publish the details of the measures taken.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.65.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.65.2/1">No legal or disciplinary measures have been taken against any members of the United Kingdom Armed Forces in Iraq for breaches of international human rights law or international humanitarian law. UK Armed Forces personnel are subject to English criminal law wherever in the world they are deployed. Service personnel suspected of breaking the law are subject to Military Police investigation and due judicial process. We are not aware of any incidents in which UK MoD personnel or persons employed by firms contracted to the UK Government have allegedly committed a breach of human rights.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.65.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn2">
	Iraq: Interrogation Techniques
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.65.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100367" speakername="Lord Lester of Herne Hill" colon="" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.65.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.65.4/2" qnum="HL2870">Further to the statement by the Lord Bach on 12 May (HL Deb, col. 377) that hooding has not been used in interrogation in Iraq, whether that statement is compatible with the report of the International Committee of the Red Cross of February 2004, and with the explanation of the hooding practice given by the Secretary of State for Transport on 14 May.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.65.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="65"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.65.5/1">The Secretary of State for Transport was correct in saying that direction had been given in September 2003 that United Kingdom forces should cease hooding prisoners, despite this being legitimate in certain specific operational circumstances. The International Committee of the Red Cross report of February 2004 did not allege that UK interrogators had hooded prisoners during interrogations. My statement on <phrase class="date" code="2004-05-12">12 May</phrase> was and remains correct. We are not aware of any incidents in which UK interrogators are alleged to have used hooding as an interrogation technique.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.66.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn3">
	Elections in London: Ballot Papers
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.66.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100275" speakername="Lord Harris of Haringey" colon="" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.66.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/2" qnum="HL3425">What measures were taken by London Elects to pilot the ballot papers used in the recent London elections; and whether they are satisfied with the design of the ballot papers adopted.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.66.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.66.2/1">London Elects did not pilot the ballot papers used. However, prior to the 2004 London elections, London Elects held extensive discussions on ballot paper design and how to provide voters with the information they needed to cast a valid vote. The groups consulted include the Electoral Reform Society, the Electoral Commission, Royal National Institute for the Blind (RNIB) and representatives from the main political parties. The Greater London returning officer also took account of findings of the reviews of the 2000 Greater London Authority elections.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.66.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn4">
	Local Authority Building Control Departments
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.66.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100042" speakername="Lord Berkeley" colon="" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.66.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.66.4/2" qnum="HL3426">Whether they are satisfied that local authority building control departments are complying with the statutory requirements to do no more than break even on the delivery of these services.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.66.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.66.5/1">No. The Office of the Deputy Prime Minister and the Welsh Assembly Government carry out an annual monitoring exercise which has indicated that some local authority building control departments in England and Wales have been accruing what could be considered to be significant surpluses.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.66.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn5">
	Planning Guidance: Places of Worship
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.66.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100385" speakername="Lord Lucas" colon="" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.66.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.66.7/2" qnum="HL3468">Whether they will amend planning guidance to create a presumption in favour of the building of places of worship.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.66.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.66.8/1">Local planning authorities consider planning applications on their individual merits, on a case by case basis, and decide them in accordance with the development plan for the area unless material considerations indicate otherwise. Planning Policy Guidance Note 12, <i>Development Plans</i>, already advises that plans should make provision for places of worship.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.66.9" nospeaker="true" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn6">
	Northern Ireland: Senior Judiciary Selection Criteria
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.66.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="66"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.66.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.66.10/2" qnum="HL3436">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Filkin on 15 June (<i>WA 63</i>) whether the criteria for the appointment of the senior judiciary in Northern Ireland are the same as those in the rest of the United Kingdom; for how long the criteria have been applied in the different jurisdictions.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.67.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100212" speakername="Lord Filkin" colon=":" colnum="67"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.67.0/1">The criteria for appointment to the senior judiciary in Northern Ireland are the same as those used in England and Wales and have applied in both jurisdictions for a number of years.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.67.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="67"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn7">
	Northern Ireland Judicial Appointments Commission
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.67.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="67"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.67.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.67.2/2" qnum="HL3437">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Filkin on 15 June (<i>WA 63</i>) whether the lay, judicial and legal professional members of the community in the Northern Ireland Judicial Appointments Commission will be reflective of the community in Northern Ireland by each category as well as a whole; and how the Lord Chancellor will achieve this for the commission as a whole when he has no control over the nomination of the judicial and legal professional members.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.67.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100212" speakername="Lord Filkin" colon=":" colnum="67"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.67.3/1">I refer the noble Lord to the Answer I gave on <phrase class="date" code="2004-06-17">17 June 2004</phrase>, (<phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2004-06-17.86"><i>Official Report,</i> col. WA 86</phrase>).</p>
	<p pid="a.67.3/2">The statutory duty under Section 3(8) of the Justice (Northern Ireland) Act 2002 as amended is placed on all those making nominations and appointments to the Judicial Appointments Commission.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.67.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="67"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn8">
	Elections: All-postal Ballots
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.67.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100385" speakername="Lord Lucas" colon="" colnum="67"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.67.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.67.5/2" qnum="HL3467">Whether they will consider allowing people in all-postal voting elections who so wish to cast their ballots at a polling station.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.67.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100212" speakername="Lord Filkin" colon=":" colnum="67"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w03.htm#40705w03_spnew8">
	<p pid="a.67.6/1">Places at which people may complete their vote in private and deposit it in a ballot box are already a feature of all-postal ballots. The all-postal pilots which took place in June required at least one assistance and delivery point (ADP) to be set up in each local authority area, with additional points to be used where circumstances required it.</p>
	<p pid="a.67.6/2">The Government have confirmed that arrangements will be in place to ensure the provision of ADPs for the forthcoming referendums on regional government, also due to be run on an all-postal basis.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.67.7" nospeaker="true" colnum="67"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_wqn0">
	Ofsted
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.67.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100250" speakername="Baroness Gould of Potternewton" colon="" colnum="67"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.67.8/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.67.8/2" qnum="HL3509">Whether all schools and further education colleges are inspected by Ofsted in respect of sexual health and education.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.68.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100024" speakername="Baroness Ashton of Upholland" colon=":" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.68.0/1">This is a matter for Ofsted. Her Majesty's Chief Inspector, David Bell, will write to my noble friend and a copy of his reply will be placed in the House Library.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.68.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_wqn1">
	Internet Access: Rural Areas
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.68.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100098" speakername="Baroness Byford" colon="" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.68.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.68.2/2" qnum="HL3475">How they propose to arrange for all rural dwellers to have manageable and affordable access to the Internet so that they can access the employment rights advice provided by the Department of Trade and Industry.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.68.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.68.3/1">Internet access is available to all those who have a telephone line irrespective of location. An Ofcom survey at the end of 2003 showed that UK Internet prices are cheaper than all other countries for peak narrowband metered and unmetered services. For off-peak services UK prices are below average for both metered and unmetered services.</p>
	<p pid="a.68.3/2">However, some people cannot afford the cost of a computer to connect to the Internet and others actively choose not to invest in that equipment. Currently take-up of the Internet stands at 53 per cent of households. The option exists to visit one of the many People's Network Internet terminals in public library branches throughout the UK. The latest survey by Museums, Libraries and Archives shows the People's Network in England made 44 million Internet hours available last year, and 11.7 million user sessions were recorded.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.68.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_wqn2">
	Endangered Species: Imports
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.68.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100552" speakername="Lord Rotherwick" colon="" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.68.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.68.5/2" qnum="HL3415">How many seizures of imports there have been under the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora Regulations in 2003; and how many of those seizures have resulted in prosecutions.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.68.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="68"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.68.6/1">There were 411 seizures at import for the period in question.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.68.6/4"> <td>2003</td> <td>Number of seizures</td> <td>Number of items seized</td> <td>Weight of items seized (kg)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.68.6/5"> <td>Live animals and birds</td> <td>99</td> <td>2,925</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.68.6/6"> <td>Parts and derivatives of endangered species</td> <td>144</td> <td>2,143</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.68.6/7"> <td>Ivory</td> <td>33</td> <td>145</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.68.6/8"> <td>Plants</td> <td>15</td> <td>2,044</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.68.6/9"> <td>Other CITES listed species</td> <td>53</td> <td>18,972</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.68.6/10"> <td></td> <td>29</td> <td></td> <td>73.5</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.68.6/11"> <td>Preparations of oriental medicines that include parts of derivatives of endangered species</td> <td>20</td> <td>5,042,728</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.68.6/12"> <td></td> <td>18</td> <td></td> <td>469.3</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.68.6/15">None of the cases resulted in a prosecution.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.69.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_wqn3">
	Common Land
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.69.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100098" speakername="Baroness Byford" colon="" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.69.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.69.1/2" qnum="HL3471">Further to the announcement in July 2002 setting out proposals for future legislation on common land, when they plan to bring forward measures for removing wrongly registered land from local authority registers.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.69.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.69.2/1">The Government remain committed to bringing forward legislation on common land, including measures to enable the deregistration of wrongly registered common land. We plan to introduce legislation as soon as parliamentary time allows, but at this stage it is not possible to be more specific about the exact timing.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.69.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_wqn4">
	Fuel Efficiency
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.69.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100628" speakername="Lord Taylor of Warwick" colon="" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.69.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.69.4/2" qnum="0">What assessment they have made of the fuel efficiency per passenger of:</p>
	<p pid="a.69.4/3" qnum="0">(a) road transport;</p>
	<p pid="a.69.4/4" qnum="0">(b) rail transport;</p>
	<p pid="a.69.4/5" qnum="0">(c) air transport; and</p>
	<p pid="a.69.4/6" qnum="HL3423">(d) water transport.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.69.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100164" speakername="Lord Davies of Oldham" colon=":" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.69.5/1">The fuel efficiency of alternative modes of transport is presented in tabular form below. The data come from the 2002 National Atmospheric Emissions Inventory (NAEI). Two data types are provided for ease of comparison, CO per passenger kilometre and kilo joules (kJ) per passenger kilometre, and are expressed using assumed load factors, not per seat.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.69.5/4"> <td></td> <td>Load factor</td> <td>CO2</td> <td>Energy consumption</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.69.5/5"> <td>Transport mode</td> <td>passengers/vehicle</td> <td>grams of CO2/passenger km</td> <td>kJ/ passenger km</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.69.5/6"> <td>Mopeds</td> <td rowspan="2" align="center">1.08</td> <td>75</td> <td>1,133</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.69.5/7"> <td>Motorcycles</td> <td>94</td> <td>1,407</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.69.5/8"> <td>Petrol cars</td> <td rowspan="3" align="center">1.56</td> <td>110</td> <td>1,653</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.69.5/9"> <td>Diesel cars</td> <td>106</td> <td>1,535</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.69.5/10"> <td>All cars average</td> <td>109</td> <td>1,634</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.69.5/11"> <td>Buses (national)</td> <td align="center">9</td> <td>76</td> <td>1,106</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.69.5/12"> <td>Passenger rail (diesel)</td> <td rowspan="3" align="center">90</td> <td>41</td> <td>589</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.69.5/13"> <td>Passenger rail (electric)</td> <td>56</td> <td>465</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.69.5/14"> <td>Passenger rail (average UK &mdash;electric and diesel)</td> <td>49</td> <td>524</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.69.5/15"> <td>Air long haul</td> <td>approx. 300</td> <td>110</td> <td>1,614</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.69.5/16"> <td>Air short haul</td> <td>approx. 100</td> <td>180</td> <td>2,640</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.69.5/17"> <td></td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.69.5/18"> <td></td> <td></td> <td>grams CO2/ ship km</td> <td>kJ/ship km</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.69.5/19"> <td>Marine&mdash;roll on roll off ferry</td> <td>See note</td> <td>83,000</td> <td>1,155,786</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.69.5/22">The road transport factors are based on National Atmospheric Emissions Inventory (NAEI) estimates of CO2 emissions by vehicle type in 2002 and combined with road passenger kilometres taken from the 2002 Transport Statistics for Great Britain.</p>
	<p pid="a.69.5/23">Rail factors are also based on NAEI factors for diesel trains and power station emissions. These data were combined with Department of Trade and Industry data on electricity used for electric rail traction and the Department for Transport's statistics on rail passenger kilometres. AEA Technology provided estimates on the split between diesel and electric train kilometres.</p>
	<p pid="a.69.5/24">Air factors are taken from DETR's Company GHG Reporting Manual 1999. Please note that long-haul journeys refer to average journeys of 6,500 km and short-haul refers to journeys of around 500 km.</p>
	<p pid="a.69.5/25">There is no agreed methodology for allocating energy consumed between passengers and freight carried on water transport. The figures for water transport are for a roll-on&ndash;roll-off ferry expressed in grams CO2 and kJ per ship km, since many passenger ships carry both passengers and freight.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.70.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_wqn5">
	Railways
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.70.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100385" speakername="Lord Lucas" colon="" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.70.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.70.1/2" qnum="HL3466">Whether privately owned train operating companies have a principal part to play in the future of United Kingdom railways.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2004-07-05a.70.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100164" speakername="Lord Davies of Oldham" colon=":" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040705/text/40705w04.htm#40705w04_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.70.2/1">I refer the noble Lord to the Statement I repeated in the House on <phrase class="date" code="2004-01-19">19 January 2004</phrase> [<phrase class="offrep" id="debates/2004-01-19.858"><i>Official Report</i>, col. 858</phrase>] which stated that the principle of public and private partnership is right for the railways and it will continue.</p>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

