<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.33.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn0">
	Cabinet Ministers' Responsibilities
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.33.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100489" speakername="Lord Patten" colon="" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.33.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.33.1/2" qnum="HL4090">Whether they regard the posts of Secretary of State for Scotland and Secretary of State for Wales as full time in comparison with the roles of other Cabinet Ministers.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.33.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100331" speakername="Baroness Jay of Paddington" colon=":" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.33.2/1">Yes.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.33.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn1">
	Government Special Advisers
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.33.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100694" speakername="Lord Windlesham" colon="" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.33.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.33.4/2" qnum="HL4132">How many political advisers to Ministers were in post on 30 June 1997 and on the same date in each of the following three years.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.33.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.33.5/1">The information requested is as follows:</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.33.5/4"> <td>Date</td> <td>Numbers of Special Advisers in Post</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.33.5/5"> <td>June 1997</td> <td>53</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.33.5/6"> <td>June 1998</td> <td>74</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.33.5/7"> <td>June 1999</td> <td>70</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.33.5/8"> <td>June 2000</td> <td>79</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.33.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn2">
	Public Bodies: Members' Hours of Work and Remuneration
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.33.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.33.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.33.7/2" qnum="HL3926">Whether they will publish a table showing the average hours of work, remuneration and allowances of chairmen and members of National Health Service trusts; Rail Users' Consultative Committees; parole boards; probation boards; local authorities; and boards of visitors.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.33.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.33.8/1">The information the noble Lord requests on local authorities is not collected centrally.</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/2">The noble Lord will find the annual publication Public Bodies useful in providing information on the remuneration of chairmen, members and chief executives of the non-departmental public bodies and National Health Service bodies to which he refers. Copies are available in the Library and on the Internet (<a href="http://www.official-documents.co.uk/document/caboff/pb99/pb99.htm">www.official-documents.co.uk/document/caboff/ pb99/pb99.htm</a>). I have also sent the noble Lord a copy of Public Bodies 1999, and the next edition will be published in due course.</p>
	<p pid="a.33.8/3">Information on hours worked and allowances paid is not collected centrally. Chairmen and members of probation boards are currently unpaid.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.34.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn3">
	Government Policies: Progress Report
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.34.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100489" speakername="Lord Patten" colon="" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.34.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.34.1/2" qnum="HL3815">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Falconer of Thoroton on 19 June (WA 10), whether they will give three examples of policies that represent their new and distinctive approach, together with an evaluation of their progress to date in each case.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.34.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.34.2/1">For details of progress being made by the Government in delivering their manifesto commitments and their new and distinctive approach, I refer the noble Lord to the Government's annual report 99/00, copies of which are available in the Library.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.34.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn4">
	Prime Minister's Web Statements
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.34.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100465" speakername="The Earl of Northesk" colon="" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.34.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.34.4/2" qnum="HL3911">At what level any decision to scale down the Prime Minister's web-addresses was taken; to what extent the Strategic Communications Unit was involved; and whether the decision is compatible with the Government's promotion of new technology.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.34.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.34.5/1">The Prime Minister continues to put out statements on the Number 10 website when there is a particular issue that needs to be addressed.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.34.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn5">
	Millennium Dome
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.34.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100098" speakername="Baroness Byford" colon="" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.34.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.34.7/2" qnum="HL3849">What they consider are the implications for the directors and shadow directors of the New Millennium Experience Company of the report prepared by PriceWaterhouseCoopers on the finances of the Millennium Dome.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.34.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.34.8/1">The report prepared by PriceWaterhouseCoopers, which is now available in the Libraries of both Houses, includes on page 39 a section entitled Implications for Directors. The last point in this section states in relation to the solvency position of the New Millennium Experience Company (NMEC) (as described on page 39), that &quot;In such circumstances the directors (including executives, non-executives, de facto, and shadow directors) must be on notice and need to take urgent action to address the position after taking appropriate legal and commercial advice.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.34.8/2">Following the presentation of the PriceWaterhouseCoopers report to the Board of NMEC, a further request for grant was submitted by the Board and its Directors to the Millennium Commission. The Commission approved a grant of &pound;47 million to NMEC on <phrase class="date" code="2000-09-05">5 September</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.35.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn6">
	Millennium Dome
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.35.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100026" speakername="Lord Astor of Hever" colon="" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.35.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.35.1/2" qnum="HL3872">What will be the impact on the revenue of the Millennium Dome of the announcement by the New Millennium Experience Company in August that entry tickets to the Dome are to be discounted generally for the period between October and December from &pound;20 per adult down to &pound;12.50 when purchased from travel agents, tour operators and group organisers.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.35.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.35.2/1">The New Millennium Experience Company's (NMEC) sales and ticket promotion strategy has been the subject of ongoing review since the Dome opened to the public on <phrase class="date" code="2000-01-01">1 January</phrase>. By Easter it was apparent that the revised visitor volume and revenue target set in January 2000 would not be achievable. The company decided that it needed to consider strategies aimed at driving up the volume of visitors and revenue. Despite high satisfaction ratings registered among those who had visited the Dome, there were clear indications that the public viewed the Dome as a risky purchase, and that there was price resistance.</p>
	<p pid="a.35.2/2">Travel agents, tour operators and group organisers remain an important sales channel for the Dome. Admission tickets and travel costs are incorporated into the overall cost of the packages they offer. Inevitably, any change of strategy regarding sales and ticket promotions for the Dome would involve these channels. In August the NMEC decided to change the arrangements that had been in place with the travel trade. The reduction in ticket price enables the trade to offer more attractive packages to the market. It is considered by the company that attractive packages will have a more positive impact on volume and revenue by countering price resistance.</p>
	<p pid="a.35.2/3">NMEC have advised that it is not possible to produce definitive figures for the impact on revenue of this change. In the professional judgment of the company, the changes offer a better prospect of increasing volume and revenue than if no action had been taken.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.35.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn7">
	Millennium Dome
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.35.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100016" speakername="Baroness Anelay of St Johns" colon="" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.35.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.35.4/2" qnum="HL3982">Further to the Written Answer by Lord Falconer of Thoroton on 27 September (WA 152-153), whether he will publish a table showing for July and August the numbers of visitors admitted free to the Millennium Dome and the numbers admitted on a reduced price ticket.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.36.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.36.0/1">The estimated figures are as follows:</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.36.0/4"> <td>Month</td> <td>Total free (1)</td> <td>Total discounted (2)</td> <td>Total sponsors from discounted (3)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.36.0/5"> <td>July</td> <td>110,681</td> <td>199,356</td> <td>15,575</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.36.0/6"> <td>August</td> <td>18,266</td> <td>249,348</td> <td>12,958</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.36.0/7"> <td>September</td> <td>98,906</td> <td>210,635</td> <td>13,285</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.36.0/10">(1) This includes free schools visits, carers of disabled people, sponsor ticket allocation, accompanying teachers on paying school visits, coach drivers, Greenwich residents, NMEC guests and VIPs.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.0/11">(2) These reflect a range of promotions and offers which are normal for visitor attraction businesses and which are factored into the company's business strategy and planning. For example, NMEC has and will run a number of offers and promotions with its sponsors for their customers; and NMEC has and continues to run a special ticket price for entry after 4.00pm. The key promotion with Marks and Spencer which concluded on <phrase class="date" code="2000-06-30">30 June</phrase> is evident in the above numbers. Subsequent key promotions with Boots, Tesco and BT will be evident in later months.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.0/12">(3) There are several issues regarding the data integrity for the number of free sponsor admissions in the attendance months to date. Due to NMEC's ticketing and admission systems being different, the company is unable to establish non-attendance versus bookings.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.0/13">The admission system does not differentiate between free and paying attendance at a sufficiently detailed level to provide definitive analysis. For example, it will show that an admission is booked via the ticketing system (Enta), but not that it is a sponsor voucher.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.0/14">The redemption of sponsor vouchers via Enta does not differentiate between a free sponsor voucher being redeemed for a specific entry date and a sponsor voucher purchased via a bulk purchase agreement</p>
	<p pid="a.36.0/15">(e.g. Tesco's 50,000 vouchers at &pound;10 each). Passholders with platinum, gold and silver passes are able to bring up to five guests. These are invariably not booked in advance via the ticketing system and are not noted in the admission system.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.0/16">The above and other data and systems issues mean that definitive analysis and data cannot be provided. This means that the statistics in the above table cannot be regarded as audited or validated.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.36.1" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn8">
	Millennium Dome
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.36.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100016" speakername="Baroness Anelay of St Johns" colon="" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.36.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/2" qnum="HL3983">Further to the statement by Lord Falconer of Thoroton on 27 September (H.L. Deb., col. 779), whether their commitment &quot;to a long-term future for the Dome&quot; involves a commitment to retaining the structure of the Dome as a condition of any contract of sale of the Dome site.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.36.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w01.htm#01025w01_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.36.3/1">The Government are currently in discussion with Legacy plc, in relation to Legacy's proposal for a high technology industrial campus at the Greenwich site. The Government are also exploring other options for the future use of the Dome in parallel with the Legacy plc discussions, but are not soliciting offers nor in serious negotiation with any other party. However, the Government's clear preference is for the Dome to stay at its present site.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.37.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn0">
	Millennium Dome
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.37.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100016" speakername="Baroness Anelay of St Johns" colon="" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.37.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.37.1/2" qnum="HL4081">Whether they are confident that the Millennium Dome can be operated by the New Millennium Experience Company until 31 December without any further moneys being available to it from the Millennium Commission after 5 October 2000.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.37.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.37.2/1">The board of the New Millennium Experience Company (NMEC), led by Executive Chairman David James, is confident that the company will operate the Dome to <phrase class="date" code="2000-12-31">31 December</phrase> within the level of lottery grant already confirmed by the Millennium Commission. That grant is released to the Company by the Commission on an &quot;as needed basis&quot;. Some will have been drawn from the Commission prior to <phrase class="date" code="2000-10-05">5 October</phrase>, and some will be drawn after <phrase class="date" code="2000-10-05">5 October</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.37.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn1">
	Millennium Dome
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.37.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100388" speakername="Lord Luke" colon="" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.37.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.37.4/2" qnum="HL3886">Further to the Written Answer by Lord Falconer of Thoroton on 27 July (WA 84) whether any Minister informed M Gerbeau the Millennium Dome project was on budget at the time when he was engaged as Chief Executive to the Millennium Experience Company; and, if so, on what basis.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.37.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.37.5/1">M Gerbeau was employed by the Board of the New Millennium Experience Company (NMEC). Neither I nor any other Minister had discussions with M Gerbeau about the company's financial position before his appointment.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.37.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn2">
	Belfast Agreement: &quot;Parity of Esteem&quot;
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.37.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.37.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.37.7/2" qnum="HL4136">Whether they will define the meanings of &quot;parity of esteem&quot; and &quot;equality for all traditions&quot;, as specified in the Belfast Agreement 1998.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.37.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.37.8/1">The term &quot;equality for all traditions&quot; does not appear in the Belfast Agreement. &quot;Parity of esteem&quot; is not defined in the agreement and therefore has its natural meaning in the contexts in which it is used.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.37.9" nospeaker="true" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn3">
	Northern Ireland: &quot;Royal&quot; Organisations
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.37.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.37.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.37.10/2" qnum="HL4140">Which organisations operating in Northern Ireland have the word &quot;Royal&quot; in their title; and which of these organisations have received representations from the Government of the Irish Republic asking for the word &quot;Royal&quot; to be removed.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.38.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="38"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.38.0/1">The Northern Ireland Office does not hold a list of organisations in Northern Ireland with the word &quot;Royal&quot; in their titles.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.38.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="38"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn4">
	Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.38.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="38"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.38.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.38.2/2" qnum="HL4239">What are the method of selection and the criteria used in the appointment of members to the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission; which members represent the Ulster Scots Community; whether any of the commission members have links to the Committee for the Administration of Justice; and, if so, what is the nature of those links.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.38.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="38"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.38.3/1">Members of the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission were appointed following an open and well publicised appointment process. Applications were shortlisted against the published criteria and selection was made following interviews. The criteria against which candidates were assessed were:</p>
	<p pid="a.38.3/2" class="indent">teamwork;</p>
	<p pid="a.38.3/3" class="indent">planning and organisation of work;</p>
	<p pid="a.38.3/4" class="indent">managing and supporting the development of policy;</p>
	<p pid="a.38.3/5" class="indent">managing financial and physical resources;</p>
	<p pid="a.38.3/6" class="indent">drive and motivation;</p>
	<p pid="a.38.3/7" class="indent">effective communication; and</p>
	<p pid="a.38.3/8" class="indent">organisational awareness and skills (including having a firm grasp of human rights related issues).</p>
	<p pid="a.38.3/9">In addition, candidates for the post of Chief Commissioner were required to demonstrate competence in:</p>
	<p pid="a.38.3/10" class="indent">leadership;</p>
	<p pid="a.38.3/11" class="indent">developing and maintaining networks; and</p>
	<p pid="a.38.3/12" class="indent">judgment and decision taking.</p>
	<p pid="a.38.3/13">None of the Commissioners was appointed to represent any particular community or section of the community within Northern Ireland. According to the Commission's register of members' interests, which is publicly available, six of the current commissioners are members of the Committee for the Administration of Justice.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.38.4" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="38"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn5">
	Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.38.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="38"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.38.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.38.5/2" qnum="HL4240">What criteria and procedures were used by the Human Rights Commission in the selection of the members of the range of committees involved in consulting on the Bill of Rights for Northern Ireland; what are the committees' compositions; and what section of society does each member represent.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.39.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="39"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.39.0/1">The appointment of committees to assist in consultation on the scope for a Bill of Rights for Northern Ireland is a matter for the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission. I have asked the Chief Commissioner of the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission to write to the noble Lord. A copy of his letter will be placed in the Library.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.39.1" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="39"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn6">
	Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.39.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="39"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.39.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.39.2/2" qnum="HL4241">In what investigations the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission has been involved; and who initiated such involvement.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.39.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="39"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.39.3/1">Section 69(8) of the Northern Ireland Act 1998 provides the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission with the power to conduct,</p>
	<p pid="a.39.3/2" class="indent">&quot;such investigations as it considers necessary or expedient&quot;, for the purpose of exercising its functions. The commission's programme of investigations is a matter for the commission itself. I have asked the Chief Commissioner of the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission to write to the noble Lord. A copy of his letter will be placed in the Library.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.39.4" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="39"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn7">
	Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.39.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="39"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.39.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.39.5/2" qnum="HL4242">What practical assistance the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission has given to the victims of paramilitary violence.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.39.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="39"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.39.6/1">This is a matter for the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission. I have asked the Chief Commissioner of the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission to write to the noble Lord. A copy of his letter will be placed in the Library.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.39.7" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="39"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn8">
	Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.39.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="39"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.39.8/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.39.8/2" qnum="HL4243">Whether the remit of the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission as defined in the Belfast Agreement of 1998 is to consult and to advise on the scope for defining in legislation human rights and not to draft a Bill.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.39.9" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="39"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_spnew8">
	<p pid="a.39.9/1">The Belfast Agreement stated that the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission would be:</p>
	<p pid="a.39.9/2" class="indent">&quot;invited to consult and to advise on the scope for defining in Westminster legislation, rights supplementary to those in the European Convention on Human Rights, to reflect the particular circumstances of Northern Ireland, drawing as appropriate on international instruments and experiences&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.39.9/3">Those are the terms on which my right honourable friend the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland commissioned advice from the commission under Section 69(7) of the Northern Ireland Act 1998.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.39.10" nospeaker="true" colnum="39"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn9">
	EU Charter of Fundamental Rights
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.39.11" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100491" speakername="Lord Pearson of Rannoch" colon="" colnum="39"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn9">
	<p pid="a.39.11/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.39.11/2" qnum="HL4250">Whether the text of the European Union Charter of Fundamental Rights, as unanimously approved by the 15 European Union Heads of State and governments at the informal European Council in Biarritz, will be similarly and separately submitted for approval to the British Parliament; and, if so, when.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.40.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="40"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.40.0/1">The Minister for Europe gave oral evidence on the charter to the Lords Scrutiny Committee on the European Union on <phrase class="date" code="2000-04-05">5 April</phrase> and, most recently, on <phrase class="date" code="2000-10-10">10 October</phrase>. In June, I participated in a debate on Sub-Committee E's report on the charter. The draft text was placed in the Library earlier this month. As the charter will be proclaimed as a political declaration at Nice, there will be no need for parliamentary ratification.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.40.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="40"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn10">
	UN Rapid Deployment Civil Police Force
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.40.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100341" speakername="Lord Judd" colon="" colnum="40"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn10">
	<p pid="a.40.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.40.2/2" qnum="HL4164">What action they are taking together with other governments to promote the creation by the United Nations of a rapid deployment civil police force, together with the resources for a judicial capability to reconstitute a system of justice in post-conflict societies.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.40.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="40"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_spnew9">
	<p pid="a.40.3/1">At the European Council in Santa Maria de Feira in June, EU heads of government agreed a concrete target for EU member states, co-operating voluntarily together, to be able to make 5,000 police officers available for international policing by 2003, 1,000 of whom will be able to deploy at 30 days' notice. These officers should be available for deployment on UN and other international missions. The UK is currently working to ensure we are able to contribute to meeting this target. Together with our EU partners, we are also considering similar arrangements for the deployment of other civilian experts, including those in the judicial field.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.40.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="40"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn11">
	UN High Commissioner for Refugees
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.40.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100341" speakername="Lord Judd" colon="" colnum="40"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_wqn11">
	<p pid="a.40.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.40.5/2" qnum="HL4194">What are the criteria by which they believe the appointment of the next High Commissioner for Refugees should be made; and what representations they have made in this respect.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.40.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="40"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w02.htm#01025w02_spnew10">
	<p pid="a.40.6/1">We believe the next United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees should be a forceful advocate on behalf of refugees and other displaced persons; have the leadership and managerial skills to accelerate work on improving UNHCR's performance and reinvigorating the organisation; and be receptive to the concerns of receiving countries about misuse of the asylum system.</p>
	<p pid="a.40.6/2">We have informed the UN Secretary-General of our views.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.41.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="41"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn0">
	Overseas Territories Governors and Parliamentary Delegations
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.41.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100311" speakername="Lord Hoyle" colon="" colnum="41"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.41.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.41.1/2" qnum="HL4166">Whether Governors of the Overseas Territories are expected to be resident when their territories are visited by United Kingdom parliamentary delegations.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.41.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="41"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.41.2/1">Governors are not necessarily expected to be present when United Kingdom parliamentary delegations visit their territories. It depends on many other considerations, including the purpose of the visit, the length of advance notice and the Governor's own commitments.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.41.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="41"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn1">
	Overseas Territories: Trade Union Membership
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.41.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100311" speakername="Lord Hoyle" colon="" colnum="41"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.41.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.41.4/2" qnum="HL4167">Whether public and private sector employees can be members of trade unions in the Overseas Territories; and what is the position in each Overseas Territory.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.41.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="41"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.41.5/1">Trade unions are permitted in all Overseas Territorities for both public and private sector employees, except for members of the police in the Turks and Caicos Islands and St Helena. In the latter legislation work is in process to remove this prohibition. The issue of trade unions is not applicable in Pitcairn, where there is no former employer, nor in the British Indian Ocean Territory, where all personnel are covered by UK or US law relating to military personnel. In the British Antarctic Territory, where there is no permanent population, staff are employed under UK employment legislation.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.41.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="41"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn2">
	High Commission Locally Employed Staff in India, Pakistan and Bangladesh
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.41.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100652" speakername="Baroness Uddin" colon="" colnum="41"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.41.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.41.7/2" qnum="HL4085">How many locally employed staff there are at the High Commission in Delhi, Islamabad and Dhaka; and what are their grades and status.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.41.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="41"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.41.8/1">Currently data on locally engaged staff are not held on an individual basis but in staff years. The number of LE staff years by grade working in New Delhi, Islamabad and Dhaka is:</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.41.8/4"> <td></td> <td>New Delhi</td> <td>Islamabad</td> <td>Dhaka</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.41.8/5"> <td>LE I</td> <td>12.00</td> <td>1.00</td> <td>2.01</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.41.8/6"> <td>LE II</td> <td>29.10</td> <td>10.00</td> <td>15.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.41.8/7"> <td>LE III</td> <td>100.80</td> <td>87.50</td> <td>13.02</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.41.8/8"> <td>LE IV</td> <td>93.00</td> <td>53.00</td> <td>24.20</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.41.8/9"> <td>LE V</td> <td>139.00</td> <td>74.00</td> <td>43.80</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.41.8/10"> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.41.8/11"> <td></td> <td>373.90</td> <td>225.50</td> <td>98.03</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.42.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn3">
	Burma
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.42.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.42.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.42.1/2" qnum="HL4117">Whether they have raised the issue of the plight of the Karen, Karenni and Shan minorities in Burma at the United Nations Security Council.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.42.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.42.2/1">We have raised our concerns over Burma with our Security Council partners. But there is no consensus at the moment for Security Council engagement on Burma issues. We nevertheless ensure that Burma is on the agenda for all other appropriate UN bodies, such as the UN Commission on Human Rights and the UN General Assembly, both of which have annual resolutions condemning the human rights violations against the ethnic minorities in Burma.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.42.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn4">
	Burma
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.42.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.42.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.42.4/2" qnum="HL4118">Whether they have urged the European Union to raise the plight of the Karen, Karenni and Shan minorities with Burma's military regime.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.42.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.42.5/1">The UK works with EU Partners through the EU's Common Foreign and Security Policy to maintain pressure on the Burmese Government to improve their human rights record. Repression of the ethnic minorities in Burma is a serious concern of the EU and has been included in regular EU statements. The terms of reference for the next EU Troika mission requires them to meet not only Aung San Suu Kyi but also representatives of ethnic minority groups. The last Troika mission, in 1999, had a firsthand account of the plight of ethnic minorities from ethnic representatives in Rangoon.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.42.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn5">
	Burma
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.42.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.42.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.42.7/2" qnum="HL4119">Whether they will urge the European Union to produce a declaration concerning the plight of the Karen, Karenni and Shan minorities in Burma in line with the European Union's initiative concerning human rights abuses against Aung San Suu Kyi and members of the National League for Democracy.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.42.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="42"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.42.8/1">The EU regularly calls upon the Burmese regime to enter into substantive dialogue, not only with Aung San Suu Kyi and the NLD, but also with ethnic minority leaders. For example, the EU Presidency statement of <phrase class="date" code="2000-10-07">7 October</phrase> supported the efforts of the UN Special Envoy to initiate dialogue between the Burmese authorities, democratic parties and ethnic minorities. The statement of <phrase class="date" code="2000-09-28">28 September</phrase>, about the SPDC's treatment of Aung San Suu Kyi following her second attempt to travel in recent weeks, also included a call for such dialogue.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.43.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn6">
	Burma
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.43.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.43.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.43.1/2" qnum="HL4121">Whether they have raised the issue of the plight of the Karen, Karenni and Shan minorities in Burma at the recent United Nations Millennium Summit.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.43.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.43.2/1">The Prime Minister took advantage of the brief time available to him in the plenary session of the UN Millennium Summit clearly to register his dismay at the latest negative developments in Burma. Our deep concern for the human rights of all Burma's people is well known: we will continue to press for improvements in this area.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.43.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn7">
	Burma
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.43.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.43.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.43.4/2" qnum="HL4120">Whether the situation of the Karen, Karenni and Shan minorities in Burma fits within the international legal definition of genocide.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.43.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.43.5/1">I refer the noble Lord to my response during the debate on Burma in the House on <phrase class="date" code="2000-10-02">2 October</phrase> (Official Report, <phrase class="date" code="2000-10-02">2 October</phrase>, col. 1223).</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.43.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn8">
	Mr James Mawdsley
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.43.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.43.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.43.7/2" qnum="HL4249">What response they have received to the conclusion of the United Nations working group on arbitrary detention and arrest, on the wrongful imprisonment of James Mawdsley by the government of Myanmar; and what information they have on his present condition.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.43.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_spnew8">
	<p pid="a.43.8/1">The Burmese Ambassador, Dr Kyaw Win, called on my honourable Friend, the Minister of State, John Battle, on <phrase class="date" code="2000-10-16">16 October</phrase> to inform him that his government had decided to deport James Mawdsley. He made no reference to the UN Working Group on Arbitrary Detention's decision that James was being held arbitrarily.</p>
	<p pid="a.43.8/2">As the noble Lord, Lord Alton of Liverpool, is already aware, James has now been released and returned to the UK on <phrase class="date" code="2000-10-21">Saturday 21 October</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.43.9" nospeaker="true" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn9">
	Dangerous and Severely Personality Disordered Persons
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.43.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100180" speakername="Lord Dubs" colon="" colnum="43"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_wqn9">
	<p pid="a.43.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.43.10/2" qnum="HL4378">When they will publish the outcome of their consultation on their proposals for managing dangerous people with severe personality disorder and what progress has been made on their proposals.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.44.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100038" speakername="Lord Bassam of Brighton" colon=":" colnum="44"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w03.htm#01025w03_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.44.0/1">The Government's proposals for those who are Dangerous and Severely Personality Disordered (D and SPD) address a long-standing challenge to public safety by ensuring that effective powers of detention and high quality services are available to deal with this group. The consultation period for these proposals ended on <phrase class="date" code="1999-12-31">31 December 1999</phrase>. A summary of the analysis of the consultation will today be placed in the Library, together with copies of individual responses, where permission to publish was not withheld.</p>
	<p pid="a.44.0/2">Of those expressing a preference, the majority of respondents to the consultation exercise preferred option B as the more effective way of providing high quality services for this group. The Home Affairs Committee in its report published on <phrase class="date" code="2000-03-14">14 March</phrase>, strongly supported option B. The Government attach great weight to these views.</p>
	<p pid="a.44.0/3">However, the Government have decided that, before taking final decisions on how best to provide services for this group in the long term, they need to pilot and to evaluate the assessment process and the various treatments available for this group within existing service structures. This period of piloting and evaluation will, however, take place at the same time as the expansion of dedicated specialist facilities within both Her Majesty's Prison Service and the NHS, and the introduction, as soon as parliamentary time permits, of new powers of detention for the assessment and treatment of this group.</p>
	<p pid="a.44.0/4">Following the recent Spending Review, my right honourable friend the Minister of State for the Home Department (Mr Boateng) announced during the summer the allocation of substantial resources to pilot and develop new services for those who are D and SPD. This will mean 320 new specialist secure places across the Prison Service and the NHS by the end of the Spending Review period .The first pilot project at Her Majesty's Prison Whitemoor has already begun and the first NHS pilot at Rampton Hospital will commence in November.</p>
	<p pid="a.44.0/5">At the same time, we are pressing ahead with the preparations for those legislative changes which will be required under either option. For example, arrangements for the assessment process and detention, and for safeguards and review, will apply whether those detained are held in existing services or in a new third service. Following the recent review of the Mental Health Act 1983, the Government believe that these changes can be made as part of wider changes to that Act. The effective implementation of new arrangements will require the provision of new, high quality, specialist services for this group which will be part of the process of service development and piloting. Access to these services will be managed through a plan of care and treatment appropriate to the individual. Subject to the results of the pilot projects, these powers would be available for this group as soon as they have been implemented. These proposals will be published in detail in a White Paper before Christmas.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.45.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="45"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn0">
	European Convention on Human Rights, Protocol 12
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.45.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100367" speakername="Lord Lester of Herne Hill" colon="" colnum="45"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.45.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.45.1/2" qnum="HL4178">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Bassam of Brighton of 11 October (WA 37), whether the interests of the United Kingdom and its peoples are likely to be harmed as a result of the generality of the text of Protocol 12 to the European Convention on Human Rights; and, if so, which.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.45.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100038" speakername="Lord Bassam of Brighton" colon=":" colnum="45"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.45.2/1">The Government's reasons for declining to sign and ratify Protocol 12 to the European Convention on Human Rights were summarised in my Written Answer of <phrase class="date" code="2000-10-11">11 October</phrase> (WA 37) and are set out in greater detail in my Answers to the noble Lord's related Questions of <phrase class="date" code="2000-10-23">23 October</phrase> (WA 13-14). New rights are not necessarily cost free (especially when they are economic, social and cultural rights) and may affect the rights of others, as many rights have to be balanced against each other.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.45.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="45"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn1">
	Lieutenant Governors
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.45.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100311" speakername="Lord Hoyle" colon="" colnum="45"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.45.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.45.4/2" qnum="HL4208">Further to the Written Answer by Lord Bassam of Brighton on 24 July (WA 22), what further steps are being taken to open up the selection of Lieutenant Governors from the field of service persons or diplomats.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.45.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100038" speakername="Lord Bassam of Brighton" colon=":" colnum="45"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.45.5/1">There are no plans to take further steps. The field is already open to service personnel or diplomats who meet the criteria for appointment.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.45.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="45"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn2">
	Corpus Juris Project
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.45.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100491" speakername="Lord Pearson of Rannoch" colon="" colnum="45"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.45.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.45.7/2" qnum="HL4252">What is the state of play of the Corpus Juris project in the European Union; and what is their attitude to it.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.45.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100038" speakername="Lord Bassam of Brighton" colon=":" colnum="45"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.45.8/1">I refer the noble Lord to the reply given by my honourable friend the Minister of State for the Home Department (Mr Clarke) in another place, Official Report, col. 51W, <phrase class="date" code="2000-05-15">15 May 2000</phrase>).</p>
	<p pid="a.45.8/2">A follow-up study to the original Corpus Juris paper has been published. Having studied the potential impact of the original Corpus Juris proposals on the national law of each of the member states, the authors proposed a number of changes designed to meet some of the criticisms which had been expressed. Key elements of the original Corpus Juris paper--in particular the creation of a European Public Prosecutor--have been retained, but there are a number of changes in the proposals concerning substantive law and procedure. The Government remain unconvinced of the need for a European Public Prosecutor.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.46.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="46"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn3">
	Road Deaths and Injuries: Reduction Strategy
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.46.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100593" speakername="Viscount Simon" colon="" colnum="46"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.46.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.46.1/2" qnum="HL4223">Whether their commitment to reduce the number of people killed and seriously injured on our roads by 40 per cent by 2010 is compatible with the increase in the cost of a fixed penalty for some serious and endorsable offences to only &pound;60.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.46.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100038" speakername="Lord Bassam of Brighton" colon=":" colnum="46"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.46.2/1">The Government are satisfied that the increase in the level of the fixed penalty is compatible with their road casualty reduction targets. The increase is 50 per cent from <phrase class="date" code="2000-11-01">1 November</phrase> and, as before, it also carries three penalty points. Drivers face disqualification if they acquire 12 points. In addition, the level and effectiveness of enforcement of endorsable offences is being increased through the use of camera technology.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.46.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="46"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn4">
	Road Deaths and Injuries: Reduction Strategy
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.46.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100593" speakername="Viscount Simon" colon="" colnum="46"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.46.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.46.4/2" qnum="HL4224">What advice and encouragement they will be giving to Chief Police Officers to achieve a reduction of 40 per cent by 2010 in the number of people killed and seriously injured on the roads, given that most constabularies are reducing their traffic departments.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.46.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100038" speakername="Lord Bassam of Brighton" colon=":" colnum="46"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.46.5/1">We have made it clear that we consider it essential to work in partnership with all those with a stake in improving road safety, including the police, in order to achieve the Government's targets for reducing road casualties. The Association of Chief Police Officers supports us in that aim. Our Road Safety Strategy details a number of measures we are taking forward to improve the police's enforcement powers and to make it easier for them to combat illegal and irresponsible driving. These include the greater use of technology. We have already provided some special funding to enhance the use of speed cameras in eight police forces. The size of a &quot;traffic department&quot; in a force is not a good indicator of the level of road policing that is carried out.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.46.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="46"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn5">
	National Probation Service Local Boards
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.46.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100056" speakername="Baroness Blatch" colon="" colnum="46"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.46.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.46.7/2" qnum="HL4161">Whether each of the local boards which are to be created under the Criminal Justice and Courts Services Bill will be non-departmental public bodies</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.46.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100038" speakername="Lord Bassam of Brighton" colon=":" colnum="46"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.46.8/1">The new local boards which will be established under the Bill currently before Parliament will be bodies corporate which, together with the National Directorate, will form the new National Probation Service. They will not be non-departmental public bodies.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.47.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="47"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn6">
	Jobrotation Scheme
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.47.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100279" speakername="Lord Harrison" colon="" colnum="47"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.47.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.47.1/2" qnum="HL4221">Whether the Jobrotation initiative, associated with the New Deal Scheme and supported financially by the European Social Fund ADAPT programme, which seeks to recruit staff from marginalised groups to the tourism and hospitality industries, has been a success; and whether they will expand the scheme beyond the South East and South West.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.47.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="47"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.47.2/1">The ADAPT-funded Jobrotation pilot is providing additional training, leading to National Vocational Qualifications, for 120 unemployed people on New Deal and 600 employed people in the South East and South West. It benefits hotel staff at eight centres and 80 per cent of the New Deal trainees have remained in sustainable employment after one year.</p>
	<p pid="a.47.2/2">Funding is available from the European Social Fund Objective 3 programme to enable other organisations to develop this idea in other parts of Great Britain.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.47.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="47"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn7">
	National Lottery
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.47.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100388" speakername="Lord Luke" colon="" colnum="47"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.47.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.47.4/2" qnum="HL4146">When the Prime Minister was informed of the decision to exclude Camelot from the shortlist for the award of the next National Lottery licence.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.47.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="47"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.47.5/1">The Prime Minister was informed of the National Lottery Commission's decision not to award the next National Lottery licence to either bidder and to negotiate exclusively with The People's Lottery to rectify its bid on the morning of <phrase class="date" code="2000-08-23">23 August</phrase>. The Commission's decision was publicly announced later that day.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.47.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="47"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn8">
	National Lottery
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.47.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100388" speakername="Lord Luke" colon="" colnum="47"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.47.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.47.7/2" qnum="HL4147">Whether the Prime Minister has met Sir Richard Branson since the passage of the National Lottery Act 1998; and whether the question of the National Lottery has arisen in any discussion between them.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.47.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="47"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.47.8/1">My right honourable friend has meetings with a wide range of organisations and individuals. As with previous Administrations it is not the practice of Her Majesty's Government to provide details of all such meetings.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.47.9" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="47"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn9">
	National Lottery
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.47.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100388" speakername="Lord Luke" colon="" colnum="47"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn9">
	<p pid="a.47.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.47.10/2" qnum="HL4144">Whether the Prime Minister has any plans to meet Sir Richard Branson.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.47.11" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="47"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_spnew8">
	<p pid="a.47.11/1">I am advised that my right honourable friend has no plans to do so.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.48.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="48"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn10">
	National Lottery
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.48.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100016" speakername="Baroness Anelay of St Johns" colon="" colnum="48"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn10">
	<p pid="a.48.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.48.1/2" qnum="HL4126">When the Secretary of State for Culture, Media and Sport became aware that some members of the National Lottery Commission had links with Sir Richard Branson.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.48.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="48"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_spnew9">
	<p pid="a.48.2/1">Before appointing members of the National Lottery Commission, the Secretary of State for Culture, Media and Sport ensured that they had no conflicts of interest. Commissioners are also required to declare any other relevant interests on the commission's register of interests. This register is publicly available and is sent to the Department for Culture, Media and Sport.</p>
	<p pid="a.48.2/2">All links of any kind, between commissioners and Sir Richard Branson, The Peoples Lottery, or Camelot Group plc, are openly recorded and publicly available on the register.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.48.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="48"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn11">
	Holidays: British National Tourism Survey
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.48.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100279" speakername="Lord Harrison" colon="" colnum="48"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_wqn11">
	<p pid="a.48.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.48.4/2" qnum="HL4222">Whether they consider the finding in the British National Tourism Survey 1998 that 40 per cent of the adult population do not take a proper holiday to be a cause for concern; and what measures they will take to help those who, by reason of poverty or family commitments, do not take an annual holiday.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.48.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="48"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w04.htm#01025w04_spnew10">
	<p pid="a.48.5/1">The 1998 British National Tourism Survey found that 40 per cent of adults had not taken a holidy of more than four nights in the previous year. These findings did give cause for concern and led to the commitment in Tomorrow's Tourism to widen access to tourism for the 40 per cent of people who do not take a long holiday. The English Tourism Council was asked to investigate the BNTS findings. Its research revealed that a major factor is the continuing market trend towards short breaks (with 86 per cent of people having taken at least one in the past three years). They also found that only 14 per cent of adults do not take any holiday for a variety of reasons, many of which are not connected with poverty or family commitments. Some are just too busy to take holidays. The English Tourism Council will continue to work with the industry and other bodies, such as the LGA, to publicise what is already available and to develop new products for untapped markets such as those on low incomes or with caring responsibilities.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.48.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="48"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_wqn0">
	Euro/Sterling Exchange Rate
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.48.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100734" speakername="Lord Shore of Stepney" colon="" colnum="48"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.48.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.48.7/2" qnum="HL4219">On what occasions before the G7 meeting of Finance Ministers and Cental Bank Governors on 23 September have the Chancellor of the Exchequer or other senior Ministers publicly stated that the pound and the euro were misaligned; and, in particular, that the depreciation of the euro against other currencies including sterling was a problem of sufficient importance to warrant international efforts to prop up the euro.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.49.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="49"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.49.0/1">In his James Meade memorial lecture on <phrase class="date" code="2000-05-08">8 May</phrase>, the Chancellor said &quot;Such a euro-sterling exchange rate cannot be justified by any view of long-term economic fundamentals.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.49.0/2">In view of the concerns shared by the members of the G7, including the United Kingdom, about the potential implications of recent movements in the euro for the world economy, the G7 authorities undertook concerted intervention in the markets on <phrase class="date" code="2000-09-22">22 September</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.49.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="49"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_wqn1">
	Tax Harmonisation
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.49.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100491" speakername="Lord Pearson of Rannoch" colon="" colnum="49"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.49.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.49.2/2" qnum="HL4253">What is the state of play of tax harmonisation in the European Union; and what is their attitude to it.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.49.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="49"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.49.3/1">The Government's approach to EU tax issues is based on fair tax competition, not tax harmonisation. At the recent Feira European Council in June, the Prime Minister and the Chancellor persuaded the EU to accept exchange of information rather than a withholding tax on cross-border savings income as the way forward. This illustrated the success of the Government's policy of constructive engagement on EU issues.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.49.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="49"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_wqn2">
	European Commission: Anti-fraud Measures
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.49.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100491" speakername="Lord Pearson of Rannoch" colon="" colnum="49"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.49.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.49.5/2" qnum="HL4254">What progress has been made with the European Union's attempt to eliminate fraud and maladministration by the European Commission.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.49.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="49"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.49.6/1">In June 1999 the EU established a new anti-fraud office, OLAF. The new office has powers to investigate internal fraud within all the institutions, has strong guarantees of its independence within the Commission, can also recommend action to be taken as a result of its reports, and will report to the Council and European Parliament on progress.</p>
	<p pid="a.49.6/2">At the same time, work on administrative reform of the European Commission is progressing broadly in line with the Commission's White Paper on reforming the Commission which was published in March this year.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.50.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_wqn3">
	Criminal Trials: Timetable
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.50.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100173" speakername="Lord Dholakia" colon="" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.50.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.50.1/2" qnum="HL4177">Whether, in the light of the recent comments by Mr Justice Henriques, they believe that the timetable for a criminal trial should be determined by the employment commitments of the accused.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.50.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100325" speakername="Lord Irvine of Lairg" colon=":" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.50.2/1">The timetable for a criminal trial is set by the judge at the Plea and Directions Hearing. In fixing the trial date, the judge takes into account the venue for the hearing, the time estimate and submissions made by the parties. Such decisions are made by the judiciary in their own independent sphere and may not be called in question by the executive.</p>
	<p pid="a.50.2/2">Copies of the statement made by Mr Justice Henriques, issued through the Lord Chancellor's Department Press Office, giving his reasons for setting a trial date of <phrase class="date" code="2001-06-06">6 June 2001</phrase>, together with copies of the transcript of the hearing, have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.50.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_wqn4">
	Multi-Storey Car Parks
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.50.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100593" speakername="Viscount Simon" colon="" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.50.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.50.4/2" qnum="HL4201">What plans they have to disseminate the advice contained in the report Interim Guidance on the Inspection and Maintenance of Multi-Storey Car Parks, published by the National Steering Committee on Multi-Storey Car Parks and to promote its implementation by car park owners, operators and local authorities to ensure that the public are protected from the risk of structural failure.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.50.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.50.5/1">We have no plans to disseminate advice based on the Interim Guidance on the Inspection and Maintenance of Multi-Storey Car Parks, but my department will consider the need to disseminate the findings of the final report in due course.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.50.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_wqn5">
	&quot;Therapeutic Cloning&quot;
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.50.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100394" speakername="Lord McColl of Dulwich" colon="" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.50.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.50.7/2" qnum="HL3958">Whether the prohibition on financial gain from the &quot;making of the human body and its parts&quot; in Article 3(2) of the draft European Union Charter on Fundamental Rights would include &quot;therapeutic cloning&quot;; and, if so, whether they will refuse any future proposals by the Human Fertilisation and Embryology Authority to allow researchers and their financial sources to profit from the development of clinical solutions developed as a result of their research into therapeutic cloning.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-10-25a.50.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="50"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo001025/text/01025w05.htm#01025w05_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.50.8/1">The charter will be a political declaration and is not legally binding. Article 3(2) of the draft European Charter on Fundamental Rights specifies that using &quot;the human body and its parts as such&quot; as a source of financial gain is prohibited. The text of Article 21 of the European Convention on Human Rights and Biomedicine includes a similar provision. The explanatory report to that convention points out that, although organs and tissues should not give rise to financial gains, technical acts which are performed on the basis of these items may legitimately give rise to reasonable remuneration. The Praesidium commentary on Article 3 notes that this Article was intended to reflect the principles of the Convention on Human Rights and Biomedicine and hence that it would be subject to the same interpretation. Thus, permitting researchers to make financial gain from clinical solutions for, for example, the treatment of diseased or damaged tissues or organs which have been developed from research involving cell nuclear replacement (&quot;therapeutic cloning&quot;) would not be inconsistent with Article 3(2).</p>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

