<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">

<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >

<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >

<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY micro "&#181;" >

<!ENTITY euro "&#8364;" >
<!ENTITY sup2 "&#178;" >
]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.155.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="155"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w01.htm#30604w01_wqn0">
	China: Population Control
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.155.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="155"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w01.htm#30604w01_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.155.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.155.1/2" qnum="HL3071">Whether they agree with the United States State Department's Country Report 2002 for China which concludes that the Chinese Government continue to pursue a policy of coercive population control encompassing physical, psychological and economic pressure notwithstanding the presence of the United Nations Population Fund in a number of Chinese countries.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.155.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="155"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w01.htm#30604w01_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.155.2/1">We are working to secure respect for reproductive rights in China. UK support is provided through the United Nations Population Fund (UNFPA) and the International Planned Parenthood Federation (IPPF). There is evidence that UNFPA and IPPF's work is having an impact. Birth targets and quotas have been removed in UNFPA programme counties, and more recently in non-UNFPA programme areas. Abortion and sterilisation rates and maternal and child mortality have reduced in UNFPA programme counties. China's first Population Law, which became effective in September 2002, introduces new legislative protection for the population against abuses from family planning officials and establishes a clear complaints procedure.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.155.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="155"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w01.htm#30604w01_wqn1">
	Cyprus
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.155.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100162" speakername="Baroness David" colon="" colnum="155"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w01.htm#30604w01_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.155.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.155.4/2" qnum="HL3187">What are their plans for the future of the post of Special Representative for Cyprus.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.155.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="155"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w01.htm#30604w01_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.155.5/1">The search for a comprehensive settlement to the Cyprus problem has been and remains a high priority for the Government. For seven years, our contribution has been led with great distinction by Lord Hannay as Special Representative for Cyprus. But in the light of recent developments, we have been reviewing the arrangements for ensuring an active British input into Cyprus diplomacy.</p>
	<p pid="a.155.5/2">My right honourable friends the Prime Minister and Foreign Secretary have therefore accepted Lord Hannay's recommendation that his term should end with effect from the date of this announcement, and have decided, for the time being at least, not to make any further appointment of this kind. Lord Hannay has worked with enormous professionalism and dedication, in support of the United Nations, to bring peace, security and prosperity to Cyprus in the form of a comprehensive settlement so to enable a re-united Cyprus to join the European Union in 2004. Lord Hannay's support and advice during his time as Special Representative&mdash;invaluable here in London, but also singled out for praise by the UN Secretary-General and many of our international partners&mdash;have brought this country great credit.</p>
	<p pid="a.155.5/3">The UK process culminated in the second revision of the plan which the UN Secretary-General presented to the parties on <phrase class="date" code="2006-02-26">26 February</phrase>, and in negotiations which reached a climax in The Hague on <phrase class="date" code="2006-03-11">11 March</phrase> this year. For reasons set out in the subsequent report by the UN Secretary-General and endorsed in UN Security Council Resolution 1475, this final effort ended in failure, for which the Turkish Cypriot leader, Mr Denktash, bore the prime responsibility. It is the British Government's firm view that the Annan plan remains the best way forward. We also concur with the Secretary-General's judgment that he should not take a new initiative unless and until he is given solid reason by all the parties to believe that the political will exists necessary for a successful outcome and that they are prepared to commit to finalising the plan by a specific date and to putting it to separate simultaneous referenda on a date soon thereafter.</p>
	<p pid="a.155.5/4">The House will understand that this announcement in no way indicates a weakening of the Government's determination to work with others under the aegis of the UN to find a solution to the Cyprus Problem. Should events again make it appropriate for a Special Representative to be appointed, the Government will not hesitate to do so.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.156.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="156"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w01.htm#30604w01_wqn2">
	Cyprus
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.156.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100345" speakername="Lord Kilclooney" colon="" colnum="156"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w01.htm#30604w01_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.156.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.156.1/2" qnum="HL3032">Whether United Kingdom residents in Northern Cyprus have had access to the United Kingdom sovereign bases at Dhekelia since 1974; whether the freedom of movement of British citizens into United Kingdom sovereign territory has recently been prohibited.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.156.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="156"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w01.htm#30604w01_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.156.2/1">In line with the commitments made to the Republic of Cyprus in the 1960 Treaty of Establishment, British citizens, like other residents in Cyprus, have freedom of access and communication to and through the sovereign base area, provided they entered the island legally.</p>
	<p pid="a.156.2/2">Any persons, including British citizens, who enter the island of Cyprus through a port of entry that is not internationally recognised are considered illegal immigrants by the Government of the Republic of Cyprus. It has been Her Majesty's Government's policy since 1974 to act in accordance with the Republic of Cyprus' immigration policy.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.156.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="156"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w01.htm#30604w01_wqn3">
	Naval Recruiting and Training Agency
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.156.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100274" speakername="Lord Hardy of Wath" colon="" colnum="156"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w01.htm#30604w01_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.156.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.156.4/2" qnum="HL3144">What key targets have been set for the Naval Recruiting and Training Agency for financial year 2003&ndash;04.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.156.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="156"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w01.htm#30604w01_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.156.5/1">Subsequent to a proposal by the agency's owner, the Second Sea Lord and Commander-in-Chief Naval Home Command, we have today set the 2003&ndash;04 key targets for the Naval Recruiting and Training Agency, as follows:</p>
	<p pid="a.156.5/2" class="indent">To deliver RN personnel to the trained strength (or to other training organisations), to the required quality standard, within 5 per cent variance from the tasked requirement.</p>
	<p pid="a.156.5/3" class="indent">To deliver RM recruits to within 2 per cent variance from the tasked requirement.</p>
	<p pid="a.156.5/4" class="indent">To maintain success rates of 95 per cent in career training (including targeted employment modules) and 97 per cent in examined pre-joining training.</p>
	<p pid="a.156.5/5" class="indent">To increase the trained strength of the RNR to 2,200 by <phrase class="date" code="2004-03-31">31 March 2004</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.156.5/6" class="indent">To reduce the average cost of the trained recruit to 98 per cent of the 2001&ndash;02 baseline figure.</p>
	<p pid="a.156.5/7" class="indent">To achieve net benefits of &pound;15 million in financial year 2003&ndash;94 from the partnering arrangement with Flagship Training Limited.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.157.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="157"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w01.htm#30604w01_wqn4">
	Gurkhas
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.157.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100640" speakername="Baroness Thornton" colon="" colnum="157"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w01.htm#30604w01_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.157.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.157.1/2" qnum="HL3157">What plans they have to review Gurkha married accompanied service arrangements.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.157.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="157"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w01.htm#30604w01_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.157.2/1">The Government are acutely aware of the need to ensure that we have fair and appropriate terms and conditions of service for Gurkha personnel. The current arrangements stem from the 1947 Tripartite Agreement (TPA) between the Governments of UK, Nepal and India. One of the aims of this agreement was to safeguard the cultural, religious and ethnic heritage of Gurkha soldiers in accordance with the wishes of the Nepalese Government. It also linked British Gurkha terms and conditions of service to arrangements in the Indian Army.</p>
	<p pid="a.157.2/2">The Government recognise, of course, that not all the principles that underpinned the TPA in 1974 apply today. It is for this reason that successive governments have regarded the TPA as having a degree of flexibility. This has enabled significant enhancements to be made to Gurkha conditions of service, particularly to Gurkha pay and pension arrangements. Indeed, Gurkha in-service remuneration is now in line with that of British personnel and Gurkha pensions, which were reviewed and at least doubled in April 2000, now compare favourably to professional salaries in Nepal, where all Gurkhas are discharged. Importantly, Gurkhas continue to be paid an immediate pension after only fifteen years' service, whereas the vast majority of British personnel receive a preserved pension payable at the age of 60.</p>
	<p pid="a.157.2/3">The Government are satisfied, therefore, that these key elements of Gurkha terms and conditions of service are tailored to the needs of Gurkhas in 2003 and in particular that the difference between the pension schemes is both necessary and proportionate.</p>
	<p pid="a.157.2/4">Gurkha accompanied service provisions, however, have not been reviewed since the brigade's withdrawal from Hong Kong in 1997. It was decided at that time that married accompanied service should be introduced in the UK, but that, in accordance with the TPA, it should continue to be capped at 25 per cent of brigade strength. In practice, this means that family married quarters are provided for all Gurkhas holding the rank of Colour Sergeant or above. Below that rank, Gurkhas are entitled to one accompanied tour of around three years.</p>
	<p pid="a.157.2/5">The Government are well aware of the problems these restrictions cause, alhough there are important contemporary factors that influence our current practice. These relate to the impact that any change in policy could have on the deployability and effectiveness of the brigade as well the need to maintain links between Gurkhas and their home country. These links were of importance to the Nepalese Government when they agreed to the transfer of Gurkha units into the British Army in 1947 and remain so to this day. Our bilateral relations with Nepal are higly valued and we take our obligations to the Nepalese Government very seriously.</p>
	<p pid="a.157.2/6">It is important, therefore, that we strike the right balance between the aspirations and needs of our Gurkha soldiers and the effectiveness and employability of the brigade as a whole. With this in mind we have asked officials in consultation with the Brigade of Gurkhas, to undertake a thorough review of Gurkha married accompanied service arrangements. In so doing we will, of course, consult the Nepalese Government. We will also consider the implications for the garrison estate in Brunei, given that at any one time nearly a quarter of the brigade is stationed there, and address the education and welfare implications of any increase in the number of Gurkha families based in the UK.</p>
	<p pid="a.157.2/7">We hope to be in a position to announce my findings to the House by the end of the year.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.158.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="158"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w02.htm#30604w02_wqn0">
	Prison Suicides
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.158.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100003" speakername="Lord Acton" colon="" colnum="158"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w02.htm#30604w02_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.158.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.158.1/2" qnum="HL2742">How many prisoners committed suicide in Styal women's prison in each year from 1993 to the present date.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.158.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="158"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w02.htm#30604w02_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.158.2/1">There have been six apparently self-inflicted deaths at Styal prison between <phrase class="date" code="1993-01-01">1 January 1993</phrase> and <phrase class="date" code="2003-05-08">8 May 2003</phrase>. The following table shows the years the deaths occured.</p>
	<table>
		<caption>Self-inflicted deaths at Styal prison since 1993</caption>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.158.2/5"> <td></td> <td>Number</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.158.2/6"> <td>2000</td> <td>1</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.158.2/7"> <td>2001</td> <td>1</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.158.2/8"> <td>2002</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.158.2/9"> <td>2003*</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.158.2/10"> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.158.2/11"> <td>Total</td> <td>6</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.158.2/14">* To <phrase class="date" code="2003-05-08">8 May 2003</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.158.2/15">The female estate contains a large number of prisoners with a combination of psychiatric disorders, alcohol and drug dependency, family background and relationship problems and histories of self-harm and previous abuse, all of which raise their risk of suicide and self-harm. This and the effects of a greater number of prisoners entering prison is probably why the numbers of self-inflicted deaths are rising among women.</p>
	<p pid="a.158.2/16">The Prison Service's suicide and self-harm strategy applies across all types of prisons and prisoners with variations as necessary to reflect the circumstances of particular groups. Styal, along with Brockhill, Eastwood Park, Holloway and New Hall, is one of the five female establishments to have appointed a full-time suicide prevention co-ordinator.</p>
	<p pid="a.158.2/17">The Prison Service is currently developing several interventions that may help female prisoners reduce and manage self-harm in prison. One such example is at Holloway prison, where all prisoners who have been identified as at risk of suicide/self-harm are offered individual crisis counselling. About 40 per cent of prisoners take up the offer, while others may be referred to alternative sources of help within the prison. Staff report that following counselling women have shown increases in self-esteem, decreases in depression and are less likely to see suicide or self-harm as the solution to their problems.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.159.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="159"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w02.htm#30604w02_wqn1">
	Human Remains
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.159.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100385" speakername="Lord Lucas" colon="" colnum="159"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w02.htm#30604w02_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.159.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.159.1/2" qnum="HL2990">Further to the Statement by the Lord Falconer of Thoroton on 19 May (HL Deb, column 576), whether they propose to create additional offences to ensure that the respect that ought to be shown to human remains is not violated; whether the reputation of deceased persons is to be similarly protected; or whether they intend that the sexual penetration of a corpse should, along with exhumation, be the only action to be criminalised.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.159.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="159"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w02.htm#30604w02_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.159.2/1">The Government have no plans to introduce any additional offence of this type. As explained in the debate of <phrase class="date" code="">19 May</phrase>, the new offence in the Sexual Offences Bill relates to the specific area of sex offending, not more generally.</p>
	<p pid="a.159.2/2">However the Government are aware of the concerns in respect of human remains. In July 2002 we published a major consultation report, Human Bodies, Human Choices, as part of a review of the law in England and Wales on the removal, retention and use of human tissue and organs. One of the purposes of this review, which follows the publication of the reports of the Bristol and Alder Hey inquiries, will be to establish consent as the determining principle in the use of human organs and tissue following death and at post mortem. It is also proposed that retention of tissue or organs without consent should be an offence. We will be bringing forward legislation as soon as parliamentary time allows.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.160.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="160"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w02.htm#30604w02_wqn2">
	Death Certification and Coroner Services
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.160.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100179" speakername="Lord Dormand of Easington" colon="" colnum="160"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w02.htm#30604w02_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.160.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.160.1/2" qnum="HL3185">When they will publish a report of the fundamental review of death certification and coroner services.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.160.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100212" speakername="Lord Filkin" colon=":" colnum="160"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w02.htm#30604w02_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.160.2/1">Today Paul Goggins is publishing and placing in the Library the report of the Fundamental Review of Death Certification and Coroner Services. This comprehensive and thoughtful report is the work of an independent review group chaired by Tom Luce, formerly of the Department of Health.</p>
	<p pid="a.160.2/2">We are very grateful to Tom Luce and his colleagues for delivering such a wide-ranging and careful report. In their comprehensive analysis of this complex and difficult area, they have consulted very widely, taking into account the views of families, interest groups, and the many professions and organisations that work in this field. This is not an easy topic, nor is it an area where there are simple answers. A careful balance is required between the requirement to investigate deaths that are a matter of legitimate public concern, and the need to respect the private grief of individual families. This report recommends some very significant changes and improvements to the way in which deaths are currently investigated and certified. It also highlights the good work being done by many of those working in this long-neglected public service.</p>
	<p pid="a.160.2/3">We do not intend to respond to the detailed proposals in the Luce report at this stage. This is because we need to consider them alongside the second report of the Shipman Inquiry, chaired by Dame Janet Smith, which will focus on death and cremation certification, and police investigation.</p>
	<p pid="a.160.2/4">We are pleased to announce that Tom Luce has agreed to do some further work on the links between the two reports. Once that has been completed, we will be able to announce plans for taking this work forward.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.160.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="160"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w02.htm#30604w02_wqn3">
	Queen's Golden Jubilee Awards
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.160.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100250" speakername="Baroness Gould of Potternewton" colon="" colnum="160"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w02.htm#30604w02_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.160.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.160.4/2" qnum="HL3188">When they will announce the Queen's Golden Jubilee Awards for voluntary service by groups in the community.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.160.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100212" speakername="Lord Filkin" colon=":" colnum="160"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w02.htm#30604w02_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.160.5/1">I am pleased to report that the first of the Queen's Golden Jubilee Awards for voluntary service by groups in the community were announced on <phrase class="date" code="">Monday 2 June</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.160.5/2">This prestigious new annual award for groups of volunteers has been given this year to 200 groups whose outstanding voluntary activity has enhanced and improved the quality of life and opportunity for others in the community. The Government actively support the work of the voluntary and community sector and are encouraging more people to participate in community activity. This award will give some of those people the recognition they richly deserve. The details of the winning groups are as follows:</p>
	<table>
		<caption>Winners of the Queen's Golden Jubilee Award for voluntary service by groups in the community 2003</caption>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/6"> <td></td> <td>Voluntary Group</td> <td>Activity Description</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/7"> <td></td> <td>East Midlands</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/8"> <td>1</td> <td>Age Concern Spalding District</td> <td>helping the elderly of Spalding and Pinchbeck and giving respite to their carers.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/9"> <td>2</td> <td>The Ashfield Environmental Project</td> <td>providing free services to the elderly, infirm or disabled, including gardening and horticultural training opportunities.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/10"> <td>3</td> <td>Bakewell &amp; Eyam Community Transport</td> <td>providing transport for those who have no car, or cannot use public transport.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/11"> <td>4</td> <td>The Buxton Mountain Rescue Team</td> <td>preventing loss of life or injury by undertaking mountain rescue operations.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/12"> <td>5</td> <td>Coping with Cancer in Leicestershire &amp; Rutland</td> <td>providing information and practical and emotional support to people affected by cancer.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/13"> <td>6</td> <td>Derbyshire Gypsy Liaison Group</td> <td>supporting Gypsies and promoting understanding of their culture.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/14"> <td>7</td> <td>The Lincoln MS Therapy Centre</td> <td>providing support, therapy, advice and friendship to MS sufferers, their family and friends.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/15"> <td>8</td> <td>The Muslim Khatri Association</td> <td>providing social and recreational activities, advancing education and relieving poverty in Leicester.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/16"> <td>9</td> <td>The Nottinghamshire Bereavement Trust</td> <td>comforting and helping the bereaved and assisting to develop Children's Gardens in major local cemeteries.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/17"> <td>10</td> <td>The Green Health Partnership Volunteers</td> <td>providing practical conservation activities involving people with mental ill-health to benefit both them and the environment in Derbyshire.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/18"> <td>11</td> <td>The Pet Shop Girls Charitable Trust</td> <td>undertaking fund-raising and other events for the local community of Ollerton and District.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/19"> <td>12</td> <td>Wellingborough Prison Visitors' Centre Volunteers</td> <td>providing practical and emotional support for visitors to Wellingborough Prison.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/20"> <td></td> <td>East of England</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/21"> <td>13</td> <td>1220 (March) Squadron&mdash;Air Training Corps</td> <td>promoting interest in aviation, training and development and community service for young people.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/22"> <td>14</td> <td>The Aylsham and District Care Trust</td> <td>strengthening the community through the development and co-ordination of voluntary care services and social activity.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/23"> <td>15</td> <td>Connect Club Welwyn and Hatfield (WOT-NOTS Project)</td> <td>preserving, protecting and promoting the mental health of local residents.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/24"> <td>16</td> <td>Dunstable and District Disabled Sports</td> <td>providing sports and other activities for disabled people.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/25"> <td>17</td> <td>The Garboldisham Village Hall Management Committee</td> <td>providing and maintaining the village hall for recreational, cultural, educational and sporting activities.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/26"> <td>18</td> <td>The Gunton Woodland Community Project</td> <td>providing, maintaining and regenerating a safe, accessible and pleasant woodland environment for the public.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/27"> <td>19</td> <td>Harlow Well Women Centre</td> <td>providing an accessible centre for women with professional counselling, advice, support and information.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/28"> <td>20</td> <td>Hospice at Home Volunteers</td> <td>befriending and supporting those suffering from life-threatening illness, their families and carers.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/29"> <td>21</td> <td>Jimmy's Night Shelter</td> <td>providing accommodation for rough sleepers in Cambridge, helping them move into suitable accommodation and raising awareness.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/30"> <td>22</td> <td>Senior Stop</td> <td>providing a meeting place and advice for older people in Peterborough.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/31"> <td>23</td> <td>SNAP Special Needs and Parents</td> <td>supporting parents and carers of children with any special need or disability in Essex.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/32"> <td>24</td> <td>The Magdalene Group</td> <td>running a drop-in centre, giving support and providing activities for people working in prostitution in Norwich.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/33"> <td>25</td> <td>The Mount Bovingdon Visitors' Centre Association</td> <td>providing a safe, comfortable environment and support for visitors to the prison.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/34"> <td>26</td> <td>The Redbourn Care Group</td> <td>recruiting and organising volunteers to provide caring services to those who need assistance.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/35"> <td>27</td> <td>The Woolverstone Project</td> <td>providing sailing opportunities for those with physical or mental disabilities in East Anglia.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/36"> <td>28</td> <td>Watford Mosque and Welfare Association</td> <td>catering for the religious, social welfare and cultural requirements of the Muslim Community.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/37"> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/38"> <td></td> <td>Guernsey</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/39"> <td>29</td> <td>Guernsey Welfare Service Limited</td> <td>providing food, clothing and fuel vouchers to people on low incomes in the community.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/40"> <td>30</td> <td>WRVS Alderney</td> <td>meeting the needs of the elderly and those less able to help themselves.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/41"> <td></td> <td>Isle of Man</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/42"> <td>31</td> <td>The Volunteers of Hospice Care, Isle of Man</td> <td>supporting and enabling hospice services for the people.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/43"> <td></td> <td>Jersey</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/44"> <td>32</td> <td>Honorary Police of Jersey</td> <td>providing community policing and contributing to the administration of the justice system.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/45"> <td></td> <td>London</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/46"> <td>33</td> <td>Aldgate Advice Centre Volunteers</td> <td>assisting and befriending rough sleepers and homeless people.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/47"> <td>34</td> <td>The Barnet Retired and Senior Volunteer Programme</td> <td>harnessing the expertise and skills of volunteers over 50.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/48"> <td>35</td> <td>Body and Soul</td> <td>supporting those living with and affected by HIV and AIDS, across London.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/49"> <td>36</td> <td>Harlesden Environmental Action Residents and Traders</td> <td>creating a cleaner, safer and healthier environment for the community.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/50"> <td>37</td> <td>Homeless Action in Barnet</td> <td>meeting the needs of homeless people and asylum seekers.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/51"> <td>38</td> <td>Kith and Kids</td> <td>empowering and socially including families in North London where one or more members has a disability.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/52"> <td>39</td> <td>The Lambeth Summer Projects Trust</td> <td>providing educational and recreational holiday activities to reduce the potential for young people to commit crime.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/53"> <td>40</td> <td>MERU</td> <td>providing free specialist equipment for disabled children in South London and the surrounding area.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/54"> <td>41</td> <td>Nubian Life</td> <td>reasserting the dignity of African and African Caribbean Elders by providing for their health, psychological and cultural needs.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/55"> <td>42</td> <td>Redbridge Night Shelter</td> <td>alleviating the effects of poverty by providing cold weather shelter to homeless adults.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/56"> <td>43</td> <td>Alzheimer's Society (Enfield Branch)</td> <td>supporting carers of people with dementia.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/57"> <td>44</td> <td>The Arab Group in Hounslow and Suburbs</td> <td>supporting the Arab community with an advice service and social activities.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/58"> <td>45</td> <td>The Centre for Filipinos</td> <td>responding to the needs of Filipinos in the UK and enabling them to participate fully in society.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/59"> <td>46</td> <td>The Greenwich Chinese Community School</td> <td>advancing education within the Chinese community, understanding Chinese culture and encouraging mutual aid.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/60"> <td>47</td> <td>The Muslim Women's Welfare Association</td> <td>providing help and advice to Asian women in Waltham Forest.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/61"> <td>48</td> <td>The Neutral Ground Child Contact Centre</td> <td>running a support centre in Abbey Wood, where children of separated families can meet estranged parents.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/62"> <td>49</td> <td>The Nightshelter Volunteers</td> <td>providing shelter for homeless people in Newham throughout the winter.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/63"> <td>50</td> <td>The Sikh Community Care Project</td> <td>developing and facilitating community initiatives in Waltham Forest, particularly for the Sikh community.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/64"> <td>51</td> <td>The XL Project</td> <td>working with and supporting schools, families and communities in South London.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/65"> <td>52</td> <td>Wandsworth Community Transport</td> <td>enabling and helping individuals with mobility problems to access facilites in Wandsworth town centre through its shop mobility project.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/66"> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/67"> <td></td> <td>North East</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/68"> <td>53</td> <td>Ferryhill Town Youth</td> <td>bringing together young people through sporting and other activities.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/69"> <td>54</td> <td>Grange Road Methodist Church Resource Centre</td> <td>providing recreational, leisure and educational activities for people of Hartlepool.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/70"> <td>55</td> <td>Quaking Houses Village Hall Association</td> <td>providing facilities and activities for the community of Stanley.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/71"> <td>56</td> <td>Stepney Bank Stables</td> <td>educating and motivating young people from inner-city areas and adults with learning difficulties.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/72"> <td>57</td> <td>The Gateshead Visible Ethnic Minorities Support Group</td> <td>supporting ethnic minority communities and promoting multi-cultural events.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/73"> <td>58</td> <td>The Northumberland Family Camping Group</td> <td>providing low-cost family holidays.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/74"> <td>59</td> <td>The Scotswood Family Drug Support Group</td> <td>providing support and advice to families of drug misusers in Scotswood.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/75"> <td>60</td> <td>West Harton Churches Action Station Limited</td> <td>providing advice and education facilities to South Tyneside residents.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/76"> <td></td> <td>North West</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/77"> <td>61</td> <td>Acorn Venture Urban Farm</td> <td>enabling disabled people in Kirkby to become involved in farming and giving young people opportunities to work with animals.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/78"> <td>62</td> <td>Advocacy in Wirral</td> <td>providing support and advocacy to people experiencing mental health problems.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/79"> <td>63</td> <td>CancerCare (North Lancashire and South Lakeland)</td> <td>providing support, therapy, counselling and practical help for cancer patients and their families.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/80"> <td>64</td> <td>Chorlton Good Neighbours</td> <td>offering support, practical help and friendship to those in need in Chorlton.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/81"> <td>65</td> <td>Delamere Toy and Tape Library</td> <td>providing toys and equipment for children up to 8 years and for individuals with special needs.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/82"> <td>66</td> <td>East Cheshire Hospice Volunteers</td> <td>transporting patients, helping in Day Care and helping bereavement counsellors and receptionists.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/83"> <td>67</td> <td>Friends for Leisure</td> <td>enabling young people with learning, sensory and physical disabilities in Macclesfield to participate in mainstream leisure activities.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/84"> <td>68</td> <td>Halton Child Contact Centre</td> <td>helping children in Runcorn and Widnes in family breakdown to continue or re-establish contact with their non-resident parent or other family members.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/85"> <td>69</td> <td>Keswick (Calvert Trust) RDA Helpers' Group</td> <td>providing disabled people opportunities to ride and carriage drive to benefit their health and well being.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/86"> <td>70</td> <td>Knutsford and District Good Neighbours</td> <td>providing transport for patients and providing practical assistance to elderly, disabled and housebound people.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/87"> <td>71</td> <td>MOSAC</td> <td>providing support, education and advice to parents of abused children in Blackpool, Wyre and Fylde.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/88"> <td>72</td> <td>One Voice/Team 2000</td> <td>improving lives of local residents through urban regeneration, crime prevention and educating young people in community citizenship.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/89"> <td>73</td> <td>Rochdale Childer</td> <td>providing help and assistance for any Rochdale child in need.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/90"> <td>74</td> <td>South Lakeland Voluntary Society for the Blind</td> <td>providing practical support, information, advice and social activities to local people with sight problems.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/91"> <td>75</td> <td>St Rocco's Hospice Volunteers</td> <td>providing practical help and emotional support, transporting patients and helping with hospice events and fundraising.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/92"> <td>76</td> <td>The Blackbrook Group and Residents</td> <td>promoting community fire safety through young people in Warrington working with the Fire Service.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/93"> <td>77</td> <td>The Blackburn Breast Care Support Group</td> <td>providing support for women who have suffered from or have concerns about breast cancer.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/94"> <td>78</td> <td>The Friday Club</td> <td>providing holidays and social activities for adults with learning disabilities in Warrington and giving respite to their carers.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/95"> <td>79</td> <td>The Littleborough Coach House Trust</td> <td>maintaining a historic listed building for use by local groups and societies.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/96"> <td>80</td> <td>The Open Door</td> <td>providing facilities and resources to improve the quality of life for residents of Benchill and to regenerate the area.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/97"> <td>81</td> <td>The Salford Link Project</td> <td>providing links between ethnic communities and statutory and voluntary organisations, including promotion of advice and education programmes.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/98"> <td>82</td> <td>The Standish Friendly Visiting Group</td> <td>befriending elderly and housebound people and those living alone and arranging outings to places of interest.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/99"> <td>83</td> <td>The Volunteers of Drugline&mdash;Lancashire</td> <td>supporting people affected by drug use, directly or indirectly, by providing counselling and a telephone helpline.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/100"> <td>84</td> <td>Wirral and Chester Riding for the Disabled</td> <td>providing practical facilities for people with physical or learning difficulties to enjoy horse riding.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/101"> <td></td> <td>Northern Ireland</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/102"> <td>85</td> <td>Broughshane and District Community Association</td> <td>enhancing the sense of community ownership and responsibility.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/103"> <td>86</td> <td>Lynn Social Club</td> <td>providing meals on wheels and organising social and recreational activities for the community of Larne.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/104"> <td>87</td> <td>Newtownstewart Development Association</td> <td>promoting economic development through tourism and employment regeneration and providing social and recreational facilities.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/105"> <td>88</td> <td>St John Ambulance HQ Transport Division</td> <td>providing a volunteer first aid and ambulance service for the community of Northern Ireland.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/106"> <td>89</td> <td>The Lack Women's Group</td> <td>providing recreational classes and training for local women in Lack.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/107"> <td>90</td> <td>Samiritans&mdash;Belfast Branch</td> <td>providing a 24 hour confidential emotional support service for people experiencing distress or despair.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/108"> <td>91</td> <td>The Walkway Women's Group &amp; EBCEC</td> <td>providing educational, arts and environment opportunities for local women in Belfast</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/109"> <td>92</td> <td>Voluntary Service Bureau</td> <td>providing advice and practical fitting of security devices to older and vulnerable people.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/110"> <td></td> <td>Scotland</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/111"> <td>93</td> <td>Arran Lifeline</td> <td>providing and servicing a telephone activated push button service in elderly and disabled peoples' homes.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/112"> <td>94</td> <td>Canine Concern Scotland Trust&mdash;Therapet Scheme&mdash;Aberdeen</td> <td>providing 'Therapy Dogs' for people in hospitals, hospices and residential and nursing homes to help those devoid of animal contact.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/113"> <td>95</td> <td>Central Gurdware Singh Sabha, Glasgow</td> <td>managing a Sikh community place of worship and providing activities to promote Sikh culture.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/114"> <td>96</td> <td>Churches Action for the Homeless</td> <td>running a day centre, accommodation and training centre for the homeless or those at risk of homelessness in Perth and district.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/115"> <td>97</td> <td>Drug Initiative Group&mdash;Forfar</td> <td>running a cafe facility for young people and offering an alternative to drug use and misuse.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/116"> <td>98</td> <td>Eighteen and Under</td> <td>providing information and support to young people in Dundee who have been abused and researching ways of preventing abuse.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/117"> <td>99</td> <td>Fife Christian Counselling Centre</td> <td>providing support and counselling to members of the community.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/118"> <td>100</td> <td>Focus Youth Project Management Committee</td> <td>overseeing the running of the Youth Project in Viewpark.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/119"> <td>101</td> <td>Glasgow Association of Family Support Groups</td> <td>promoting the development of groups to support and advise parents of drug abusers.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/120"> <td>102</td> <td>Home Basics</td> <td>collecting and refurbishing donated furniture and household goods for disadvantaged people in Tweeddale.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/121"> <td>103</td> <td>Inverclyde Peace Initiative</td> <td>promoting conflict resolution within the community to make it cohesive and sustainable.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/122"> <td>104</td> <td>Islay Disabled Endeavours and Actions</td> <td>providing care, advocacy, craft working, training and health supervision for individuals with special needs.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/123"> <td>105</td> <td>Lanarkshire Cancer Care Trust (The Volunteer Driver Service)</td> <td>providing a personal hospital transport service for cancer sufferers.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/124"> <td>106</td> <td>McSence Limited</td> <td>creating sustainable community owned and run businesses, employing and training unemployed people of Dalkeith.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/125"> <td>107</td> <td>Portlethen &amp; District Community Ambulance Association</td> <td>providing transport for those unable to attend church, social or health facilities.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/126"> <td>108</td> <td>Red Star Athletics Club</td> <td>providing sporting, recreational and social opportunities for people with disabilities in Glasgow.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/127"> <td>109</td> <td>Roseberry Centre</td> <td>providing support, advisory and counselling services to people with dementia and their families in and around Livingston.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/128"> <td>110</td> <td>The Drop In</td> <td>providing social activities, meals and advice for pensioners in Irvine.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/129"> <td>111</td> <td>The Hit Squad</td> <td>improving the environement in Dawson by enabling elderly and infirm residents to undertake low maintenance gardening and run a community allotment.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/130"> <td>112</td> <td>The Moorpark Community Association</td> <td>providing social and educational opportunities and raising funds to improve the local environment.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/131"> <td></td> <td>South East</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/132"> <td>113</td> <td>777 Conservation Group</td> <td>conserving the environment of Buckinghamshire for the benefit of the public.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/133"> <td>114</td> <td>A New Start For Netherfield Partnership Board</td> <td>attracting and administering funds to transform Netherfield.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/134"> <td>115</td> <td>Berinsfield Information and Volunteer Centre</td> <td>providing advisory services for local people.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/135"> <td>116</td> <td>CHAIN</td> <td>providing practical help and information for the people of Hungerford.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/136"> <td>117</td> <td>Epsom &amp; Ewell Phab</td> <td>integrating young people with and without physical disabilities.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/137"> <td>118</td> <td>Fleet Pond Society</td> <td>promoting the preservation and maintenance of the Fleet Pond Nature Reserve.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/138"> <td>119</td> <td>Florence Nightingale House Volunteers</td> <td>enhancing the quality of hospice patients' care.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/139"> <td>120</td> <td>Folkestone Rainbow Centre</td> <td>supporting the community's needs physically, spiritually and emotionally.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/140"> <td>121</td> <td>Gatehouse</td> <td>a cafe for homeless people in Oxford.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/141"> <td>122</td> <td>Hampshire Association for the Care of the Blind</td> <td>supporting Hampshire people who have lost their sight.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/142"> <td>123</td> <td>Havant Area Bereavement Care Group</td> <td>providing help and comfort to bereaved people.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/143"> <td>124</td> <td>Katharine House Hospice</td> <td>enhancing the lives of hospice patients and their families.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/144"> <td>125</td> <td>Maidenhead Multiple Sclerosis Society</td> <td>providing a social venue and outings for MS patients.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/145"> <td>126</td> <td>Mytchett Community Association</td> <td>providing a community centre and playing fields to improve the quality of people's lives.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/146"> <td>127</td> <td>Oxford Samaritans</td> <td>offering year round confidential and emotional support for suicidal or desparate people.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/147"> <td>128</td> <td>Penrose Club for Adults with Special Needs</td> <td>providing leisure activities in Surrey and encouraging the independence of its members.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/148"> <td>129</td> <td>Phyllis Tuckwell Hospice Volunteers</td> <td>providing specialist activities and practical support for hospice patients.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/149"> <td>130</td> <td>SEBEV Search and Rescue</td> <td>assisting the authorities in the Thames Valley area, following reports of lost or missing persons.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/150"> <td>131</td> <td>Tandem</td> <td>providing a transport service and a weekly club for elderly and disabled people in Midhurst and Petworth.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/151"> <td>132</td> <td>The Leatherhead Swans Club</td> <td>helping to provide recreation and leisure facilities for disabled people.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/152"> <td>133</td> <td>The V Team</td> <td>enabling people in Maidstone who are ill or have support needs to be succesful volunteers.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/153"> <td>134</td> <td>The Wire</td> <td>providing programmes to enhance the lives of the people of Wick</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/154"> <td>135</td> <td>Working Hospice Volunteer Team</td> <td>helping to provide care for patients and their families</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/155"> <td>136</td> <td>Wokingham and West Berkshire Mind</td> <td>providing support for mental health service users and carers.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/156"> <td></td> <td>South West</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/157"> <td>137</td> <td>Blackdown Support Group</td> <td>supplementing health and social services in the Blackdown Hills by providing care and support services.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/158"> <td>138</td> <td>Burnham &amp; Highbridge Stroke Club</td> <td>a social club providing companionship and activities for people who have suffered strokes.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/159"> <td>139</td> <td>Cheltenham and District Sports Association for the Disabled</td> <td>providing swimming instruction and sailing opportunities for disabled people.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/160"> <td>140</td> <td>Downderry and District Community Bus Association</td> <td>providing accessible and inexpensive transport for all local residents and holiday-makers.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/161"> <td>141</td> <td>Gloucestershire Chinese Women's Guild</td> <td>providing services for socially excluded and isolated Chinese women and their families.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/162"> <td>142</td> <td>North Devon Display Gymnastics Club</td> <td>providing gymnastics and coaching opportunities for the people of North Devon.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/163"> <td>143</td> <td>Plymouth Musical Activities Club</td> <td>providing opportunities for young people to learn and perform music to support charitable organisations.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/164"> <td>144</td> <td>St Keverne Youth Band</td> <td>providing young people with the opportunity to play musical instruments and perform.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/165"> <td>145</td> <td>Swindon Children's Scrapstore</td> <td>promoting recycling by collecting useable waste and donating it to community organisations.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/166"> <td>146</td> <td>Talaton Village Community Shop &amp; Post Office</td> <td>providing service to the community and a focal point for village needs.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/167"> <td>147</td> <td>The Beacon Community Regeneration Partnership</td> <td>regenerating areas of Falmouth, alleviating disadvantage and social exclusion, and providing support services.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/168"> <td>148</td> <td>The Sheltered Work Opportunities Project</td> <td>providing horticultural work opportunities for people suffering from mental health problems in Bournemouth.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/169"> <td>149</td> <td>The Southmead Project Limited</td> <td>providing education, training, and counselling for individuals and families affected by drug misuse and historic abuse.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/170"> <td>150</td> <td>The St James Priory Project</td> <td>supporting homeless people in Bristol with addiction problems and facilitating their reintegration into society.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/171"> <td>151</td> <td>Trussell Trust</td> <td>providing food for people in crisis in Wiltshire and augmenting the work of other statutory and voluntary organisations.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/172"> <td>152</td> <td>Thorncombe First Responders</td> <td>pioneers of community life support between a '999' emergency call and the arrival of ambulance.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/173"> <td></td> <td>Wales</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/174"> <td>153</td> <td>Aberfan and Merthyr Vale Youth and Community Project</td> <td>providing activities for young and unemployed people.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/175"> <td>154</td> <td>Bush and Park Tenants and Residents' Association</td> <td>improving the lives of estate residents.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/176"> <td>155</td> <td>Grangetown Community Concern</td> <td>acting as an umbrella group for other voluntary organisations.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/177"> <td>156</td> <td>Gwynedd Hospice at Home</td> <td>enabling patients to use day Hospice facilities,and supporting Hospice Nurses.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/178"> <td>157</td> <td>North Wales Superkids</td> <td>providing family holidays and gifts for needy children and young people.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/179"> <td>158</td> <td>Ogmore Centre Trust</td> <td>providing residential courses for young people and a community life-long learning facility for rural residents.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/180"> <td>159</td> <td>Perthcelyn Tenants and Residents Association</td> <td>organising social activities and learning opportunities for residents of the Perthcelyn estate.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/181"> <td>160</td> <td>Swansea Old People's Welfare</td> <td>operating four day centres for elderly and housebound people.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/182"> <td>161</td> <td>The Clwyd Special Riding Trust</td> <td>enabling people with special needs to ride or carriage drive.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/183"> <td>162</td> <td>The Muslim Welfare Association of Vale of Glamorgan</td> <td>promoting education, art and culture among the ethnic minority community.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/184"> <td>163</td> <td>Treasure Trove</td> <td>providing a residential project for young people aged 16 to 25 years both with and without physical disabilities.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/185"> <td>164</td> <td>Tyddyn Bach Trust</td> <td>caring for and supporting those affected by HIV and Aids, and their families and carers in the UK.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/186"> <td></td> <td>West Midlands</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/187"> <td>165</td> <td>Harborne Carnival Association</td> <td>promoting and organising an annual carnival to improve community spirit and support local charities.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/188"> <td>166</td> <td>OSCA</td> <td>providing volunteers to support and represent people with learning difficulties throughout Shropshire.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/189"> <td>167</td> <td>Perry Hall Community Association</td> <td>providing entertainment, holidays and exercise for residents of Perry Barr, Birmingham.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/190"> <td>168</td> <td>Pershore Pathfinders</td> <td>providing social activities for blind and partially sighted people.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/191"> <td>169</td> <td>Rock Community Bus</td> <td>providing educational, leisure and play activities to socially and economically disadvantaged communities in Birmingham.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/192"> <td>170</td> <td>S.H.A.R.P. Peer Education</td> <td>informing young people in Sandwell and Dudley of the dangers of leaving home unplanned and how to access support.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/193"> <td>171</td> <td>The Shifnal Millennium Sensory Garden Committee</td> <td>creating and maintaining a sensory garden for the community, especially elderly and disabled people.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/194"> <td>172</td> <td>St Michael's Hospice</td> <td>providing specialist palliative care for people from Herefordshire and surrounding counties and support for family and friends.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/195"> <td>173</td> <td>Stepping Stones Support Limited</td> <td>providing support, advice and information to women experiencing domestic violence in Walsall.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/196"> <td>174</td> <td>Age Concern Stourbridge</td> <td>providing services for the elderly including day care facilities and transport.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/197"> <td>175</td> <td>T.S. Sutton Coldfield</td> <td>guiding young people towards responsible and confident adulthood by encouraging personal attributes and conduct.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/198"> <td>176</td> <td>The Asian Blind Association</td> <td>providing advice and counselling for blind and partially sighted people, and their carers, in Coventry.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/199"> <td>177</td> <td>The Rose Staner Friendship Club</td> <td>offering friendship and support to elderly visually impaired people living alone in Coventry.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/200"> <td>178</td> <td>The Royal Orthopaedic Hospital League of Friends Volunteers</td> <td>providing support to patients, hospital management and staff.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/201"> <td>179</td> <td>The Stonehouse Gang</td> <td>providing activities for pre-school and school children, youths and senior citizens in Selly Oak.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/202"> <td>180</td> <td>Watch Limited</td> <td>a community-led organisation, working to improve the quality of life for people in Hillfields.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/203"> <td>181</td> <td>Wetton and Alstonefield Community First Responders</td> <td>providing emergency medical aid in response to '999' calls from remote areas.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/204"> <td>182</td> <td>The Wolverhampton Asian Women and Diabetes Group</td> <td>providing support and information about diabetes to Asian women.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/205"> <td>183</td> <td>Wolverhampton Support for Deafened People</td> <td>providing a battery and repair service for hearing aid users.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/206"> <td>184</td> <td>The Wolverhampton Urdu Centre</td> <td>providing information, advice and linguistic services in Asian languages.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/207"> <td></td> <td>Yorkshire and the Humber</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/208"> <td>185</td> <td>The Crosby Community Association</td> <td>running a drop-in centre, neighbourhood watches, children's groups and an outreach service.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/209"> <td>186</td> <td>FLAG</td> <td>providing support and respite care to families of children with disabilities.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/210"> <td>187</td> <td>Friend to Friend</td> <td>providing activities for the elderly people of Holme Valley.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/211"> <td>188</td> <td>Hornsea Inshore Rescue</td> <td>rescuing those in difficulties at sea and promoting water safety.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/212"> <td>189</td> <td>Manor Young People's Health Project</td> <td>educating and advising the young in Sheffield on health issues.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/213"> <td>190</td> <td>Sheffield Cathedral Breakfast &amp; Archer Projects</td> <td>supporting the homeless by providing education, breakfasts, shower and laundry facilities.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/214"> <td>191</td> <td>The Community Care Association&ndash;Stokesley</td> <td>promoting voluntary action and developing projects with service users and carers.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/215"> <td>192</td> <td>The British Fishermen's Association</td> <td>achieved compensation for distant water trawler men in Hull.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/216"> <td>193</td> <td>The Friends of Paces</td> <td>supporting the local community of Sheffield and children with cerebral palsy by generating funds.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/217"> <td>194</td> <td>The Goodwill Motorists' Friendship Group</td> <td>organising year-round, fun-filled gatherings for housebound (infirm, blind and/or bereaved) people, sponsored and entertained by groups in North East Lincolnshire.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/218"> <td>195</td> <td>The Junction</td> <td>providing support, education and advice to people in Harrogate with a wide range of special needs.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/219"> <td>196</td> <td>The Longhill Link Up Trust</td> <td>providing services and activities for those living on the Longhill Housing Estate.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/220"> <td>197</td> <td>The Manor Farm, Monkswood, Thorogate Community Centre</td> <td>maintaining the community centre and providing activities for the local people.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/221"> <td>198</td> <td>The Safe Anchor Trust</td> <td>giving special needs groups free access to waterways, and maintaining the canal environment in West Yorkshire.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/222"> <td>199</td> <td>Upper Wharfedale Fell Rescue Association</td> <td>providing a rescue service for people and animals above and below ground in the Yorkshire Dales.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.160.5/223"> <td>200</td> <td>York Students in Schools</td> <td>introducing students from the University of York to classrooms in York to help teachers and children.</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn0">
	Race Relations Act Section 19D
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100179" speakername="Lord Dormand of Easington" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.161.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.1/2" qnum="HL3208">Whether they have plans to make any new ministerial authorisations under Section 19D(3)(a) of the Race Relations Act 1976, as amended by the Race Relations Act 1999.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100212" speakername="Lord Filkin" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.161.2/1">Beverley Hughes has made a new authorisation under section 19D of the Race Relations Act 1976 (as amended) to allow a certain proportion of the permits issued under the new sectors based schemes in the hospitality and food processing sectors to be available for issue only to nationals of countries who are due to accede to the European Union on <phrase class="date" code="2004-05-01">1 May 2004</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.2/2">This reflects the Government's commitment to these countries to give greater access to the UK labour markets in the period leading up to the date of their accession to the European Union.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.2/3">A copy of the new authorisation, which came into force on <phrase class="date" code="">30 May</phrase>, has been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn1">
	Parliamentary Commissioner for Administration
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100367" speakername="Lord Lester of Herne Hill" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.161.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.4/2" qnum="HL2942">What is the average amount of time, during the past five years, in which complaints of maladministration submitted by the Parliamentary Commissioner for Administration under the code of practice on access to government information have been dealt with, from the initial statement of the complaint to publication of the Parliamentary Commissioner's final determination.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.161.5/1">The conduct of her investigations and the timing of publication of her reports are matters for the Parliamentary Commissioner for Administration.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn2">
	Light Pollution
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100144" speakername="Lord Corbett of Castle Vale" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.161.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.7/2" qnum="HL3029">What steps they are taking to lessen light pollution.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.161.8/1">A number of Government initiatives in recent years have looked at the scope for mitigating the effects of light pollution.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.8/2">In 1997 the Government published Lighting in the Countryside: Towards good practice. This guide was aimed at minimising the intrusiveness of lighting in the countryside, but its advice applies equally to lighting in urban areas. Lighting in the Countryside advises local authorities to consider a policy in relation to lighting in their development plans, and for supplementary planning guidance to elucidate those policies.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.8/3">The 1998 Transport White Paper A New Deal for Transport&mdash;Better for Everyone states that, &quot;where lighting is essential, it should be designed in such a way that nuisance is reduced and the effect on the night sky in the countryside minimised&quot;. The Highways Agency when providing new lighting or renewing existing lighting systems installs modern low-spillage luminaires. The Government have made &pound;300 million in PFI credits available in 2003&ndash;04 to help local authorities in England (outside London) modernise their street lighting. In London a further &pound;85 million in PFI credits will be available for street lighting over the next three years. This support is additional to that through revenue support grant. Modernisation of street lighting should result in reduced light pollution compared with older systems.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.8/4">In October 2002 the Government issued a consultation paper entitled Living Places&mdash;Powers, Rights, Responsibilities. One of the issues the paper addresses is dealing with nuisance lighting, which it notes is a general contributor to light pollution. The paper sought opinions as to whether the Government should introduce new regulations for positioning of external lighting (other than street lights) and the powers to extend the statutory nuisance regime to include lighting. The paper also asked local authorities, householders and building developers whether they considered that the guidance in Lighting in the Countryside needed updating. The Government are currently considering the responses and are expecting to publish a summary document in the coming months. lynne</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.9" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn3">
	Light Pollution
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100469" speakername="Lord Oakeshott of Seagrove Bay" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.161.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.10/2" qnum="HL3040">Whether they will define light pollution as a statutory nuisance and introduce regulations to enable environmental health officers to take actions to stop outdoor lights shining into homes.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.11" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.161.11/1">In October 2002 the Government issued a consultation paper entitled Living Places&mdash;Powers, Rights, Responsibilities. One of the issues the paper addresses is dealing with nuisance lighting, which it notes is a general contributor to light pollution. The paper sought opinions as to whether the Government should introduce new regulations for positioning of external lighting (other than street lights) and the powers to extend the statutory nuisance regime to include lighting. The paper also asked local authorities, householders and building developers whether they considered that the guidance in Lighting in the Countryside needed updating. The Government are currently considering the responses and are expecting to publish a summary document in the coming months.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.12" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn4">
	Light Pollution
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.13" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100469" speakername="Lord Oakeshott of Seagrove Bay" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.161.13/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.13/2" qnum="HL3042">What evidence they have of the increase in light pollution in recent years; and how they intend to monitor it in the future.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.14" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.161.14/1">The Office of the Deputy Prime Minister does not currently monitor light pollution in England and we have no plans at present to do so.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.15" nospeaker="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn5">
	Local Government Bill Clause 71
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.16" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100112" speakername="Lord Carter" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.161.16/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.16/2" qnum="HL3145">Whether they have fulfilled their commitment made in the House of Commons during the Report stage of the Local Government Bill to make available a note on their broad policy intent with regard to Clause 71 of the Bill on the local retention of business rates.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.17" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.161.17/1">I can confirm that a note on the policy intent with regard to Clause 71 of the Local Government Bill was available in the Libraries of the House from <phrase class="date" code="2003-05-29">29 May 2003</phrase> in advance of Committee consideration of the Bill in another place. Copies were also sent to Baroness Hanham and Baroness Hamwee. In addition, copies of the revised draft regulations for Part of the Bill and the first draft of the regulations with regard to the 2004 local government elections provisions of the Bill, together with the draft guidance for the new charging provisions currently out to consultation.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.18" nospeaker="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn6">
	Armed Forces: Emergency Fire Cover
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.19" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100496" speakername="Lord Peston" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.161.19/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.19/2" qnum="HL3189">What is the current position on the provision of emergency fire cover by the Armed Forces.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.20" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.161.20/1">The Fire Brigades' Union executive council and the national employers have reached an agreement which will be put to a recall conference on <phrase class="date" code="">12 June</phrase>. As a result I am pleased to announce that the Armed Forces personnel deployed on firefighting duties have been stood down during the run-up to the conference.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.21" nospeaker="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn7">
	Medieval History
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.22" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100489" speakername="Lord Patten" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.161.22/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.22/2" qnum="HL2822">Whether medieval history should be supported by public funds in British universities; and</p>
	<p pid="a.161.22/3" qnum="HL2823">Following recent remarks by the Secretary of State of Education, Charles Clarke, concerning medieval history, what other subjects they consider are not worthy of study</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.23" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100024" speakername="Baroness Ashton of Upholland" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.161.23/1">The Government believe that a wide range of disciplines, including medieval history, are worthy of study and public support. That is why we are increasing the unit funding for higher education by 7 per cent in real terms between 2002&ndash;03 and 2005&ndash;06, compared with the 8 per cent real terms cut which took place between 1992&ndash;93 and 1994&ndash;95 when the noble Lord was Secretary of State for Education.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.24" nospeaker="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn8">
	Schools: Broadband Connection
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.25" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100465" speakername="The Earl of Northesk" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.161.25/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.25/2" qnum="HL2996">How they respond to the decision of Education Bradford to purchase high-speed internet access well in excess of the Department for Education and Skills' guidelines of a 2Mbps synchronous connection for primary schools and an 8Mbps synchronous connection for secondary schools.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.26" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100024" speakername="Baroness Ashton of Upholland" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w03.htm#30604w03_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.161.26/1">In November 2002, the Prime Minister announced all schools should be connected to broadband by 2006. Typically, it is hoped primary schools will be connected at a minimum of 2 megabits per second (Mbps) and secondary schools at a minimum on 8 Mbps.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.26/2">However, where higher capacity bandwidth is available and is cost effective, my department would encourage LEAs and schools to consider installing even faster internet connectivity. It is envisaged that the bandwidth schools require will increase over time as the availability and use of digitally rich resources, video conferencing and collaboration devices continue to grow.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.26/3">Education Bradford plans to connect all Bradford schools at 10Mbps using fibre optic cabling. This increased bandwidth will enable schools in Bradford to benefit considerably from the teaching and learning opportunities high-speed Internet access offers. In addition, the use of fibre optic technology will enable cost-effective and timely upgradeability to even higher bandwidths as schools' bandwidth requirements increase.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.26/4">My department supports LEAs in connecting schools at bandwidths higher than the recommended minimum where local conditions and infrastructure permit, providing local schools have been consulted and have agreed to this approach.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.27" nospeaker="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn0">
	Business: Information TechnologyPilot Projects
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.28" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100465" speakername="The Earl of Northesk" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.161.28/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.28/2" qnum="HL2947">In light of the recent survey from Intel Service Solutions indicating that 88 per cent of United Kingdom businesses experience significant barriers to implementing information technology pilot projects, what measures they are taking to encourage United Kingdom businesses to take appropriate advantage of such pilots.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.29" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.161.29/1">Through UK Online for Business, a DTI-led programme, the Government seek to support businesses in their use of information and communications technologies (ICTs). The delivery of the programme is built around raising awareness of the business case for adopting ICTs and providing independent and impartial advice and content in order to help companies develop their e-business strategies.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.29/2">DTI advisers, based in the Business Link Network, give ICT advice and assistance to over 100,000 businesses each year. These advisers are well placed to advise on issues such as whether and how a business might implement information technology initiatives, including pilot projects. Advisers can also propose ways of overcoming barriers to ICT adoption.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.29/3">The Government are working hard across the board to create the right conditions for ICT adoption. Last year's international benchmarking study by Booz Allen Hamilton showed the UK to have the second-best environment in the world for e-commerce.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.30" nospeaker="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn1">
	3.4GHz Fixed Wireless Access Licences
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.31" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100465" speakername="The Earl of Northesk" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.161.31/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.31/2" qnum="HL2943">What is their response to the applications received for the 3.4GHz broadband fixed wireless auction, with particular reference to the apparent involvement of the Hong Kong-based company, Pacific Century Cyberworks, in bids for all 15 regional licences.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.32" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.161.32/1">The Radiocommunications Agency received a number of applications on <phrase class="date" code="2006-04-14">14 April</phrase> to take part in the forthcoming auction of 3.4GHz fixed wireless access licences. All of the applicants have gone through the pre-qualification process and in accordance with paragraph 11.B.4.1 of the Wireless Telegraphy (Public Fixed Wireless Access Licences) Notice 2003 the names of the qualified bidders have now been published. The Government welcome the encouraging level of interest in bidding in the auction.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.33" nospeaker="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn2">
	e-Europe
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.34" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100465" speakername="The Earl of Northesk" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.161.34/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.34/2" qnum="HL2945">What is their response to recent comments by Andrea Servida, head of sector for the information society unit at the European Commission, that the two main enablers for guaranteeing delivery of European and national objectives for Information and Communications Technology by 2004 are broadband and security.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.35" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.161.35/1">The Seville European Council last June endorsed the objectives of the Commission's e-Europe 2005 Action Plan. This aims to &quot;stimulate secure services, applications and content based on a widely available broadband infrastructure&quot;. This February, the Commission produced a paper on addressing perceived weaknesses in the telecoms markets called The Road to Knowledge Economy. Its overall conclusion was that no new EU-level action is required, as long as there is full, timely and effective implementation of both the new regulatory framework and the e-Europe 2005 Action Plan, as well as the adoption by the end of 2003 of effective national strategies for broadband in each member state. The UK fully supports this position. The UK national strategy for broadband was first set out in UK online: the broadband future published in February 2001. Since that time it has continued to evolve, drawing on the advice of the Broadband Stakeholder Group. Security and broadband are key components to realising e-Europe and form an essential part to realising the Lisbon strategy of making the European Union the most competitive and dynamic knowledge-based economy with improved employment and social cohesion by 2010.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.36" nospeaker="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn3">
	Businesses : Data and Information Technology System Security
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.37" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100465" speakername="The Earl of Northesk" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.161.37/1">asked her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.37/2" qnum="HL2946">What assessment they have made of any regulatory and financial burdens to be placed on United Kingdom businesses in respect of data and information technology system security, given the coming into force of the Higgs Report on corporate governance on 1 July; and, if such an assessment has been made, what are their projections for increased costs per annum to business.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.38" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.161.38/1">The combined code is to be amended in the light of the recommendations in the report by Derek Higgs on the role and effectiveness of non-executive directors. The Financial Reporting Council is responsible for changes to the combined code.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.39" nospeaker="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn4">
	Olympic Games 2012
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.40" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100339" speakername="Lord Jopling" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.161.40/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.40/2" qnum="HL2971">In the event that London secures the 2012 Olympic Games, what preferential arrangements will be made to London residents, who have been surcharged to pay part of the costs of the games, to obtain tickets for various events.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.41" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.161.41/1">The ticketing policy, should London stage the Olympic and Paralympic Games in 2012, has not yet been determined. This will be a matter for the bid organisation to consider in due course, within the constraints of any relevant IOC criteria.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.42" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn5">
	Olympic Games 2012
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.43" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100339" speakername="Lord Jopling" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.161.43/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.43/2" qnum="HL2972">In the event that London secures the 2012 Olympic Games, whether a secure fence or wall will be constructed around the Olympic village to ensure the safety of competitors; and how long it will be.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.44" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.161.44/1">While the details of security arrangements in the event of a successful London Olympic bid are not yet known, security for competitors, officials and spectators will be of the highest priority. The Government, the bidding organisation and, in the event of hosting the games, the organising committee will ensure full attention is given to these matters, and that appropriate arrangements are in place.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.45" nospeaker="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn6">
	Overseas Commercial Industrial Investment
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.46" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100416" speakername="Lord Marlesford" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.161.46/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.46/2" qnum="HL3049">Whether they will estimate the value, at constant prices, of total overseas commercial industrial investment in the United Kingdom for each of the last 10 years, showing separately the investment from within the European Union and from outside the European Union.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.47" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.161.47/1">The information requested falls within the responsibility of the National Statistician, who has been asked to reply.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.47/2">Letter to Lord Marlesford from Karen Dunnell the Director of the Surveys and Administrative Sources Directorate, Office for National Statistics, dated <phrase class="date" code="2003-06-04">4 June 2003</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.47/3">The National Statistician has been asked to reply to your recent question asking about the estimated value, at constant prices, of total overseas commercial industrial investment in the United Kingdom for each of the last ten years, showing separately the investment from within the European Union and from outside the European Union. I am replying in his absence. (HL3049)</p>
	<p pid="a.161.47/4">The value of foreign direct investment in the UK is not estimated at constant prices. Current price estimates are published in the Office for National Statistics Monitor MA4 and are available on the National Statistics website at: <a href="http://www.statistics.gov.uk/CCI/SearchRes.asp?term=MA4&amp;x=21&amp;y=20">http://www.statistics. gov.uk/CCI/SearchRes.asp?term=MA4&amp;x=21&amp;y=20</a></p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.48" nospeaker="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn7">
	Greenhouse Gas Emissions
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.49" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100334" speakername="Lord Jenkin of Roding" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.161.49/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.49/2" qnum="HL3039">Why the figures for greenhouse gas emissions published by the Office for National Statistics are estimated on a basis which differs from that used to monitor progress against the Kyoto protocol target for the reduction of greenhouse gases; and whether they will now publish the latest figures for such emissions estimated on the Kyoto protocol target basis.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.50" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.161.50/1">The information requested falls within the responsibility of the National Statistician who has been asked to reply.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.50/2" class="letterfrom">Letter from John Pullinger, Executive Director, Office for National Statistics, dated <phrase class="date" code="2003-06-04">4 June 2003</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.50/3">The National Statistician has been asked to reply to your recent question concerning the ONS (Office for National Statistics) estimates of UK greenhouse gas emissions. I am replying in his absence. (HL3039)</p>
	<p pid="a.161.50/4">ONS publishes estimates of UK greenhouse gases emissions on a National Accounts basis i.e. it includes all emissions made by UK residents regardless of where the emissions take place and excludes emissions made in the UK by non-residents. The estimates published by the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (DEFRA), which are used for monitoring against the Kyoto protocol target, record all emissions taking place in the UK regardless of the nationality of the source and exclude emissions made by UK residents abroad.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.50/5">ONS will continue to publish green house gas emissions on a National Accounts consistent basis so that users can compare emissions by economic sector against sectoral breakdowns of measures such as gross output and gross value added.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.51" nospeaker="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn8">
	Hepatitis C
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.52" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100444" speakername="Lord Morris of Manchester" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.161.52/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.52/2" qnum="HL2982">What figures they have for the number of hepatitis C-infected people who entered the United Kingdom in each of the last three years as legal immigrants.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.53" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w04.htm#30604w04_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.161.53/1">We do not hold the information requested as immigrants to the United Kingdom are not routinely screened for hepatitis C infection.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.54" nospeaker="true" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w05.htm#30604w05_wqn0">
	NHS: Patient and Public Involvement
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.55" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100382" speakername="Baroness Lockwood" colon="" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w05.htm#30604w05_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.161.55/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.161.55/2" qnum="HL3186">What are the arrangements for the next phase of implementation of the new system of patient and public involvement in the National Health Service.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-06-04a.161.56" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="161"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030604/text/30604w05.htm#30604w05_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.161.56/1">The system of patient and public involvement in the National Health Service that will be in place from <phrase class="date" code="">1 September</phrase> will provide far greater support for patients than ever before.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.56/2">At <phrase class="date" code="">1 September</phrase> the programme of work to set up patients' forums will be well under way and the support for them will be in place to provide a one-stop shop for information and advice; the Commission for Patient and Public Involvement in Health (CPPIH) will be representing the patients' voice nationally; local authority overview and scrutiny committees will be scrutinising the NHS; the NHS itself will be carrying out its new duty to involve and consult the public; there will be independent support for complainants; there will be support for patients from PALS (Patient Advice and Liaison Service) in almost all trusts; there will be a national helpline set up by CPPIH that will provide advice, information and signposting for the public about where to get advice and support; and there will be monitoring of the NHS by the Commission for Health Improvement and by patient environment action teams.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.56/3">The Government have been consistent in their drive to ensure accessible and informed support for patients; provide for independent scrutiny by democratically elected representatives; and, ensure that the views and experiences of patients are fed into decisions affecting their health and health services. Massive progress has already been made.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.56/4">We have listened to parliamentarians and other stakeholders, including the CPPIH, and we are responding positively to comments around the specific issue of independent monitoring of the NHS during the transition period.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.56/5">We have therefore decided to make the position absolutely unassailable by retaining community health councils (CHCs) to continue their monitoring function until <phrase class="date" code="">1 December</phrase>, at which point all patient forums will be in place to take up this role.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.56/6">Sharon Grant, chair of CPPIH, has stated that this decision allows an important breathing space to help ensure a smooth handover to the new system of patient and public involvement forums in December.</p>
	<p pid="a.161.56/7">All CHC staff and members have been sent a letter advising them of the change of arrangements.</p>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

