<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.277.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="277"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000434">
	Abdul Baset Al Megrahi
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.277.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon=":" colnum="277"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000434">
	<p pid="a.277.1/1" qnum="HL12723">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether they will instruct the British Ambassador to Libya to visit Abdul Baset Al Megrahi in Tripoli and ascertain his state of health.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.277.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100308" speakername="Lord Howell of Guildford" colon=":" colnum="277"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000003">
	<p pid="a.277.2/1">The Scottish authorities are responsible for monitoring Mr Al Megrahi's health as a condition of his compassionate release licence. It is for the Scottish authorities to assess his state of health. As such, the Foreign and Commonwealth Office will not be instructing H.M. Ambassador in Libya to visit Abdul Baset al Megrahi.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.277.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="277"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000435">
	Abortion
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.277.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon=":" colnum="277"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000435">
	<p pid="a.277.4/1" qnum="HL12547">To ask Her Majesty's Government why they are pressing the Republic of Ireland, through the United Nations, to legalise abortion; and how this pressure is compatible with their commitment to respect the rights of sovereign democratic nations.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.277.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100308" speakername="Lord Howell of Guildford" colon=":" colnum="277"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000004">
	<p pid="a.277.5/1">We are not pressing the Republic of Ireland to legalise abortion. At the recent UN Human Right's Council's Universal Periodic Review (UPR) of Ireland the UK recommended that Ireland introduce legislation to implement the European Court of Human Rights (ECtHR) judgment in the A, B and C v Ireland case. It stated that Ireland had violated the convention by failing to provide an accessible and effective procedure by which a woman can have established whether she qualifies for a legal abortion under current Irish law. In its response to the UPR the Government of Ireland have committed to ensuring that this judgment is implemented expeditiously.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.277.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="277"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000436">
	Agriculture: Soil Management
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.277.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100427" speakername="Baroness Miller of Chilthorne Domer" colon=":" colnum="277"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000436">
	<p pid="a.277.7/1" qnum="HL12609">To ask Her Majesty's Government how they assess which areas of the country to prioritise for increased soil management regimes.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.277.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100908" speakername="Lord Taylor of Holbeach" colon=":" colnum="277"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000005">
	<p pid="a.277.8/1">The Government do not systematically prioritise different areas of the country for increased soil management regimes. However, through the cross-compliance requirements, all single payment scheme claimants are required to identify the risk of soil degradation on their holding and select appropriate management options to mitigate these risks.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.278.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="278"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000437">
	Agriculture: Soil Management
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.278.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100427" speakername="Baroness Miller of Chilthorne Domer" colon=":" colnum="278"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000437">
	<p pid="a.278.1/1" qnum="HL12613">To ask Her Majesty's Government, in the light of the Environment Agency advice that &quot;selenium is an essential element (micronutrient) for animals and humans&quot;, what assessment they have made of changes in uptake by plants of selenium; and whether this is likely to be as a result of changes in soil pH, or, if not, for what other reasons.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.278.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100908" speakername="Lord Taylor of Holbeach" colon=":" colnum="278"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000006">
	<p pid="a.278.2/1">The Environment Agency has reviewed selenium toxicity and environmental behaviour as part of its contaminated land exposure assessment (CLEA) programme. Although changes in soil pH over the past 40 years could result in an increase in selenium uptake by plants, the Environment Agency has no data to confirm this and consideration of selenium concentrations in soils in England and Wales suggests that any increase would be very small and probably insignificant.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.278.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="278"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000438">
	Arab Partnership
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.278.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100386" speakername="Lord Luce" colon=":" colnum="278"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000438">
	<p pid="a.278.4/1" qnum="HL12838">To ask Her Majesty's Government, in the light of the Arab Spring, what range of co-operation, advice and assistance they offer to countries in the Middle East through the Arab Partnership.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.278.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100308" speakername="Lord Howell of Guildford" colon=":" colnum="278"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000007">
	<p pid="a.278.5/1">Through the Arab Partnership, the UK has committed &#163;110 million over four years to support both political and economic reform across the Middle East and North Africa region. This includes up to &#163;40 million for political reform, to support not just free and fair elections, but stronger parliaments, media and judiciaries; and up to &#163;70 million to support inclusive economic growth. There are a number of areas where the UK has specific expertise and can make a distinct contribution to effective reform in the region. Arab Partnership projects are working with countries on issues such as tackling corruption, reinforcing the rule of law, enabling political participation, enhancing the public voice, creating jobs, accelerating economic growth, supporting economic and social inclusion and improving public sector accountability.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.278.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="278"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000439">
	Armed Forces: Aircraft
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.278.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100956" speakername="Lord West of Spithead" colon=":" colnum="278"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000439">
	<p pid="a.278.7/1" qnum="HL12847">To ask Her Majesty's Government how many Royal Air Force Nimrod aircrew were made redundant in the last round of redundancies; and how many are forecast to be made redundant in the next two rounds of redundancies.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.279.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100026" speakername="Lord Astor of Hever" colon=":" colnum="279"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000008">
	<p pid="a.279.0/1">The number of Royal Air Force Nimrod aircrew that were selected for redundancy in tranche 1 of the RAF redundancy programme is 64. No qualified pilots were selected for redundancy. A forecast of the number to be selected for redundancy in future tranches is not available as the redundancy fields have not yet been confirmed.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.279.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="279"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000440">
	Armed Forces: Litigation Costs
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.279.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon=":" colnum="279"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000440">
	<p pid="a.279.2/1" qnum="HL12722">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether they will take steps to recover the costs of the trial from the compensation paid to Aidan McKeever following his High Court case against the Ministry of Defence.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.279.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100026" speakername="Lord Astor of Hever" colon=":" colnum="279"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000009">
	<p pid="a.279.3/1">There is no legal basis on which to do so. The Government are studying the terms of the judgment with a view to deciding whether to appeal.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.279.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="279"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000441">
	Armed Forces: Staff
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.279.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100469" speakername="Lord Oakeshott of Seagrove Bay" colon=":" colnum="279"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000441">
	<p pid="a.279.5/1" qnum="HL12488">To ask Her Majesty's Government what level of security clearance is held by Mr Luke Coffey, Special Adviser to the Secretary of State for Defence; and what measures are in place to ensure that he does not face any conflict of loyalties arising from his past service as an officer in the United States Army.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.279.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100026" speakername="Lord Astor of Hever" colon=":" colnum="279"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000010">
	<p pid="a.279.6/1">Mr Coffey, who has now left the Ministry of Defence, had the appropriate level of security clearance when working in the department from May 2010 to October 2011 to permit him to have unescorted access to the building to undertake his duties as special adviser to the Defence Secretary, and to have access to information that his role required. Nationality is not a bar to holding a security clearance but may restrict access to certain types of sensitive information.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.279.7" nospeaker="true" colnum="279"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000442">
	Aviation
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.279.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100235" speakername="Baroness Gibson of Market Rasen" colon=":" colnum="279"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000442">
	<p pid="a.279.8/1" qnum="HL12889">To ask Her Majesty's Government what is their assessment of the contribution of airports to the United Kingdom's infrastructure and to economic growth.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.279.9" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100028" speakername="Earl Attlee" colon=":" colnum="279"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000011">
	<p pid="a.279.9/1">Aviation makes a significant contribution, both directly and indirectly, to the UK economy. We want to maximise this contribution in the future and explore how aviation growth can occur, while ensuring that it is genuinely sustainable.</p>
	<p pid="a.279.9/2">The air transport sector's turnover in 2009 was around &#163;26 billion; the sector directly generated around &#163;9 billion of economic output and directly provided 120,000 jobs in the UK, supporting many more indirectly. Aviation plays a crucial role in facilitating business and trade, for example, in 2010 goods worth &#163;113 billion were shipped by air freight between the UK and non-EU countries representing 38 per cent of total trade with those countries.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.280.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="280"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000443">
	Aviation
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.280.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100235" speakername="Baroness Gibson of Market Rasen" colon=":" colnum="280"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000443">
	<p pid="a.280.1/1" qnum="HL12891">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether, given the Department for Transport's assertion in the UK Aviation Forecast's report (August 2011) that &quot;The recent financial crisis and associated recession caused the biggest fall in activity at United Kingdom airports since 1950&quot;, they have plans to introduce measures to assist this sector pending the publication of the Sustainable Framework for UK Aviation in March 2013.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.280.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100028" speakername="Earl Attlee" colon=":" colnum="280"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000013">
	<p pid="a.280.2/1">The Government want to see a successful aviation sector which facilitates economic growth and addresses its environmental impacts. We will issue a sustainable framework for UK Aviation for public consultation in spring 2012. In the mean time, we are pursuing a number of measures to support the sector, including taking forward the recommendations of the South East Airports Taskforce, and reforming the economic regulation of airports to put passengers at the heart of the regulatory regime and to support investment in our airports.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.280.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="280"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000444">
	Banking
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.280.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100983" speakername="Lord Myners" colon=":" colnum="280"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000444">
	<p pid="a.280.4/1" qnum="HL12641">To ask Her Majesty's Government what assessment they have made of whether the increased use by banks of liquidity swaps represents a risk to financial stability.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.280.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/101012" speakername="Lord Sassoon" colon=":" colnum="280"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000014">
	<p pid="a.280.5/1">On <phrase class="date" code="2011-07-21">21 July</phrase>, the Financial Services Authority (FSA) issued proposed guidance on liquidity swaps, which refers to transactions that effect liquidity transformation, typically between an insurer and a bank.</p>
	<p pid="a.280.5/2">The bank can access liquidity embedded within asset portfolios held by an insurer and thereby improve its liquidity position. It does this by exchanging certain of its less liquid assets with high-quality, more liquid assets held by an insurer.</p>
	<p pid="a.280.5/3">The FSA's proposed guidance highlights evidence of significant demand for liquidity swaps, which creates the potential for a significant increase in the volume of trades. This would enhance the interconnectedness of the banking and insurance sectors, and therefore pose a greater risk to financial stability. It is therefore important that the potential risk of a significant increase in the volume of these trades could pose is carefully managed. Further details of the FSA's proposed guidance can be found at: <a href="http://www.fsa.gov.uk/pages/Library/Policy/guidance_consultations/2011/11_18.shtml">http://www.fsa.gov.uk/pages/Library/Policy/guidance_consultations/2011/11_18.shtml</a>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.281.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="281"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000445">
	Banks: Lending
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.281.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100983" speakername="Lord Myners" colon=":" colnum="281"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000445">
	<p pid="a.281.1/1" qnum="HL12683">To ask Her Majesty's Government what assessment they have made of the Eurostat statistical report on unsuccessful loan applications by small and medium-sized businesses to United Kingdom banks over the last four years, published on 3 October; and what assessment they have made of the possibility of this leading to further strengthening of Project Merlin.</p>
	<p pid="a.281.1/2" qnum="HL12781">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether data reported in the most recent Bank of England report <I>Trends in Lending</I> have contributed to their assessment of Project Merlin's performance.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.281.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/101012" speakername="Lord Sassoon" colon=":" colnum="281"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000017">
	<p pid="a.281.2/1">On <phrase class="date" code="2011-02-09">9 February</phrase>, the Chancellor announced a new commitment by the UK's biggest high street banks on lending expectations and capacity. As part of this commitment, the banks intend to make available appropriate capital and resources to support &#163;190 billion of new credit to businesses in 2011, up from &#163;179 billion in 2010. If demand exceeds this, the banks will lend more. &#163;76 billion of this lending will be to small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs). This is a 15 per cent increase on 2010 lending of &#163;66 billion.</p>
	<p pid="a.281.2/2">At the half-year point, the Bank of England has reported that the banks have loaned over &#163;100 billion to UK businesses. Over &#163;37 billion of this was to SMEs. The Government will use all of the tools available to it to ensure that the banks live up to their promises.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.281.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="281"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000446">
	Benefits
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.281.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/101046" speakername="Baroness Liddell of Coatdyke" colon=":" colnum="281"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000446">
	<p pid="a.281.4/1" qnum="HL12868">To ask Her Majesty's Government how much was paid in state pension payments to residents of Scotland in the 2010-11 tax year.</p>
	<p pid="a.281.4/2" qnum="HL12869">To ask Her Majesty's Government what they estimate will be the total value of state pension payments to residents of Scotland in 2015, 2020, 2025 and 2030.</p>
	<p pid="a.281.4/3" qnum="HL12870">To ask Her Majesty's Government what was the total amount paid to residents of Scotland in social security payments in the 2010-11 tax year.</p>
	<p pid="a.281.4/4" qnum="HL12871">To ask Her Majesty's Government what they estimate will be the total value of social security payments to residents of Scotland in 2015, 2020, 2025 and 2030.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.282.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100992" speakername="Lord Freud" colon=":" colnum="282"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000019">
	<p pid="a.282.0/1">The total amount paid in state pension to residents of Scotland for the 2010-11 financial year is an estimated &#163;6.0 billion.</p>
	<p pid="a.282.0/2">The information requested is not available. The department does not forecast below Great Britain level for social security payments. Forecasts for Great Britain for 2015 can be found on the DWP's website at: <a href="http://research.dwp.gov.uk/asd/asd4/index.php?paqe">http://research.dwp.gov.uk/asd/asd4/index.php?paqe</a> =expenditure.</p>
	<p pid="a.282.0/3">In the 2010-11 financial year the Department for Work and Pensions spent an estimated &#163;13.2 billion on its main benefits<sup>1</sup> in Scotland.</p>
	<p pid="a.282.0/4">The information requested is not available. The department does not forecast below Great Britain level for social security payments. Forecasts for Great Britain for 2015 can be found on the DWP's website at the address above.</p>
	<p pid="a.282.0/5" class="indent"><sup>1</sup> DWP figures include expenditure for attendance allowance, bereavement benefit/widows benefit, carer's allowance, disability living allowance, incapacity benefit/severe disablement allowance, income support, jobseekers allowance, pension credit, state pension, winter fuel payments, employment and support allowance and housing and council tax benefits.</p>
	<p pid="a.282.0/6" class="indent"><I>Source:</I></p>
	<p pid="a.282.0/7" class="indent">DWP statistical and accounting data, as published at: <a href="http://research.dwg.gov.uk/asd/asd4/all_tables_budget_2011_2.xls">http://research.dwg.gov.uk/asd/asd4/all_tables_budget_2011_2.xls</a> and at <a href="http://research.dwg.gov.uk/asd/asd4/PC_expenditure.xls">http://research.dwg.gov.uk/asd/asd4/PC_expenditure.xls</a></p>
	<p pid="a.282.0/8" class="indent"><I>Notes:</I></p>
	<p pid="a.282.0/9" class="indent">Figures are rounded to the nearest &#163;100 million.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.282.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="282"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000447">
	Children: Care
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.282.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100794" speakername="Lord Roberts of Llandudno" colon=":" colnum="282"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000447">
	<p pid="a.282.2/1" qnum="HL12644">To ask Her Majesty's Government, further to the Written Answer by Lord Hill of Oareford on 18 October (<I>WA 46</I>), what is the breakdown of the &#163;2,881 average cost per week of caring for a child in a local authority children's home.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.282.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/101010" speakername="Lord Hill of Oareford" colon=":" colnum="282"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000023">
	<p pid="a.282.3/1">The breakdown of the average cost per week of caring for a child in a local authority children's home is provided in the table below. This expands on information provided in a previous Written Answer and is derived from Table 6.2 in the University of Kent's publication <I>Unit costs of health and social care 2010</I>.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/4"> <td>Costs and unit estimation</td> <td>2009-10 value</td> <td>Notes</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/5"> <td>Capital costs (A, B &amp; C)</td> <td></td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/6"> <td>A. Buildings</td> <td>&#163;98 per resident week</td> <td>Based on the new build and land requirements for local authority children's homes. These allow for 59.95 square metres per person.<sup>2</sup> Capital costs are discounted at 3.5 per cent over 60 years.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/7"> <td>B. Land</td> <td>&#163;13 per resident week</td> <td>Based on statistics provided by the Department for Communities and Local Government. Land costs have been annuitised at 3.5 per cent over 60 years.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/8"> <td>C. Equipment</td> <td></td> <td>No information available.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/9"> <td>Revenue costs</td> <td></td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/10"> <td>D. Salary and other revenue costs</td> <td>&#163;2,578 per resident week</td> <td>Mean costs for children looked after in own provision children's homes are based on P55 EX1 returns for 2007/2008 uprated using the P55 Pay &amp; Prices Index.<sup>4</sup> Data have been adjusted to include respite and short-term placements. Capital charges based on the above estimate (&#163;98) have been deducted. The mean cost in the &quot;Leadership and Resources in Children's Homes&quot; study staff costs accounted for 65 per cent of the total cost of homes on average.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/11"> <td>E. Agency overheads</td> <td></td> <td>Agency overheads are excluded from this schema. However the &quot;Leadership and Resources in Children's Homes&quot; study imputed these costs at 10.6 per cent of total annual revenue costs.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/12"> <td>F. Other costs</td> <td></td> <td>Service use data taken from the &quot;Leadership and Resources in Children's Homes&quot; study and likely to be an underestimate as information on key services only was requested.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/13"> <td>External services</td> <td></td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/14"> <td>Health services</td> <td>5</td> <td>Costs of hospital services were taken from Trust Financial returns (CIPFA, 2001) and uprated to 2009/2010 prices using the HCHS Pay &amp; Prices Index.<sup>5</sup></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/15"> <td>Social services</td> <td>&#163;15</td> <td>Support provided by field social workers, leaving care workers and family support workers. Unit costs were taken from Netten et al, (2001) and uprated to 2009/2010 prices using the P55 Pay &amp; Prices Index<sup>7</sup></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/16"> <td>Youth justice sector</td> <td>&#163;2</td> <td>Costs for police contacts and youth custody were estimated using information contained in Finn et al. (2000) and uprated to 2009/2010 prices using the P55 Pay &amp; Prices Index.7 Costs estimated according to the location of the home using information contained in CIPFA (2001).<sup>5</sup></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/17"> <td>Education sector (excluding in-house education)</td> <td>170</td> <td>Home tuition costs were estimated using methodology reported by Berridge et al. (2002).<sup>8</sup> The mid-point of the pay scale for qualified teachers was used, including employers' National insurance and Superannuation contributions. A percentage (6S per cent) was added to cover 'other institutional' expenditure and LEA overheads.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/18"> <td>Use of facility by client</td> <td>52.18 weeks per annum</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/19"> <td>Occupancy</td> <td>84%</td> <td>Taken from the &quot;Leadership and Resources in Children's Homes&quot; study. Based on the occupancy rate for all Community Children's Homes.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/20"> <td>London multiplier</td> <td>1.06 x A: 2.52 x B: 1.01 x (D)</td> <td>Relative London costs are drawn from the same source as the base data for each cost element.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/21"> <td colspan="3">Unit costs available 2009-10</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.282.3/22"> <td colspan="3">&#163;2,689 establishment costs per resident week (includes A to E); &#163;2,881 care package costs per resident week (includes A to D and F).</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.282.3/25">More information on the above table and other costs is available at: <a href="http://www.pssru.ac.uk/pdf/uc/uc2010/uc2010.pdf">http://www.pssru.ac.uk/pdf/uc/uc2010/uc2010.pdf</a>).</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.284.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="284"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000448">
	Egypt
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.284.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100994" speakername="Baroness Kinnock of Holyhead" colon=":" colnum="284"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000448">
	<p pid="a.284.1/1" qnum="HL12810">To ask Her Majesty's Government to what extent the Arab Partnership Fund is being used to support women's rights and political participation in the forthcoming elections in Egypt; what percentage of the applications received by the fund to date were from women's organisations working in Egypt; and what proportion of grants awarded to date will support women's rights in Egypt.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.284.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100308" speakername="Lord Howell of Guildford" colon=":" colnum="284"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000065">
	<p pid="a.284.2/1">The Arab Partnership programme in Egypt is the largest country programme, worth almost &#163;1.7 million. Of this, &#163;842,000 will be spent on supporting enhanced political participation, including a &#163;500,000 package of support linked to the forthcoming elections. This additional package includes &#163;50,000 to support the increased participation of women in parliamentary elections through a pilot training academy led by a local non-governmental organisation. The academy is preparing women candidates and their campaigners with the skills they need to run effective campaigns. In our work supporting inclusive political dialogue we have ensured women are prominently represented and the UK is supporting the UN's focus on women and other marginalised groups in their voter education programme.</p>
	<p pid="a.284.2/2">Overall, around 5 per cent of the total bids to the Arab Partnership in 2011-12 were from women's organisations. Bids were received for projects in Egypt, Lebanon, Iraq and regional programmes.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.285.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="285"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000449">
	Employment
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.285.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/101044" speakername="Lord Wills" colon=":" colnum="285"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000449">
	<p pid="a.285.1/1" qnum="HL12740">To ask Her Majesty's Government what assessment they have made of the impact on jobs in each region of the United Kingdom of the United Kingdom leaving the European Union.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.285.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100684" speakername="Baroness Wilcox" colon=":" colnum="285"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000067">
	<p pid="a.285.2/1">There is no available estimate of the impact on jobs for the United Kingdom as a whole and in each of the regions of the United Kingdom of the United Kingdom leaving the EU. These estimates would be difficult and would therefore represent an important cost as the consequences on a wide range of issues would have to be considered. This would include among other things the impact on trade in goods and services, foreign investments of European Union and non-European Union origins, financial and banking relations, inward and outward flows of migrants, etc. The consequences would also depend on the type of relation the UK and the rest of the EU would be able to negotiate or not as an alternative to EU membership. The time length and the economic uncertainty created by that negotiation would influence the business environment in the UK. Many other details of such a scenario are unknown and would be extremely difficult to guess.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.285.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="285"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000450">
	European Union
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.285.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100994" speakername="Baroness Kinnock of Holyhead" colon=":" colnum="285"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000450">
	<p pid="a.285.4/1" qnum="HL12811">To ask Her Majesty's Government, further to the statement by the Prime Minister on 24 October (<I>Official Report</I>, col. 26-7), what are the European Union powers and competencies which they intend to &quot;bring back from Brussels&quot;; and what procedure they will use for accomplishing this repatriation.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.285.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100308" speakername="Lord Howell of Guildford" colon=":" colnum="285"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000068">
	<p pid="a.285.5/1">The Government's stated intention is to examine the balance of the EU's existing competences. We have made no commitment to a particular outcome from that review. Bringing back powers and competences can be done in a number of ways. For example, by repealing EU legislation or provisions in EU legislation, by getting agreement to no longer use a TEU Treaty provision in a particular way, or by changing the competences conferred upon the EU under the treaties.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.285.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="285"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000451">
	Export Control
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.285.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon=":" colnum="285"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000451">
	<p pid="a.285.7/1" qnum="HL12883">To ask Her Majesty's Government what were the meetings of the Wassenaar Arrangement on Export Controls for Conventional Arms and Dual-Use Goods and Technologies in each month since May 2010; who attended each meeting from the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills; where each meeting was held; on what dates; whether they will place in the Library of the House (a) the agenda, and (b) the minutes, of each such meeting; and whether they will publish the speaking notes of the United Kingdom representative at each such meeting.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.286.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100684" speakername="Baroness Wilcox" colon=":" colnum="286"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000069">
	<p pid="a.286.0/1">The United Kingdom is represented at Wassenaar Arrangement meetings held in Vienna by officials from those government departments with an interest in accordance with their policy responsibilities. This would include an official from the Export Control Organisation. The agenda and minutes of these meetings are not made publicly available in order to enable frank discussions of the issues by the participants.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.286.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="286"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000452">
	Family Income
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.286.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100489" speakername="Lord Patten" colon=":" colnum="286"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000452">
	<p pid="a.286.2/1" qnum="HL12795">To ask Her Majesty's Government (a) what was the median family income in 2008-09, 2009-10, and 2010-11; and (b) what was the percentage increase or decrease in income between each of those years.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.286.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100992" speakername="Lord Freud" colon=":" colnum="286"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000070">
	<p pid="a.286.3/1">Households below average income data can be used to provide estimates of median family incomes. Data are only available for 2008-09 and 2009-10. The 2010-11 Households Below Average Income publication will be published in May June 2012.</p>
	<p pid="a.286.3/2">The table below shows the median unequivalised gross and net family income for families for 2008-09 and 2009-10 and the percentage change between the two periods.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.286.3/5"> <td colspan="3"><I>Table 1: Median unequivalised gross and net family income, 2008-09 and 2009-10</I></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.286.3/6"> <td></td> <td colspan="2">Median unequivalised gross and net family income (&#163; per week, 2009-10 prices)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.286.3/7"> <td></td> <td>Gross family income</td> <td>Net family income</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.286.3/8"> <td>2008-09</td> <td>389</td> <td>318</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.286.3/9"> <td>2009-10</td> <td>392</td> <td>324</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.286.3/10"> <td>Percentage change between 2008-09 and 2009-10 (per cent)</td> <td>+1</td> <td>+2</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.286.3/13" class="indent"><I>Source:</I> Households Below Average Income (HBAI) 2008-09 and 2009-10.</p>
	<p pid="a.286.3/14" class="indent"><I>Notes</I></p>
	<p pid="a.286.3/15" class="indent">1. These statistics are based on households below average income (HBAI) data sourced from the Family Resources Survey (FRS).</p>
	<p pid="a.286.3/16" class="indent">2. For this analysis, unequivalised gross and net family income is used. Conventionally, HBAI analysis is based on equivalised disposable household income that is adjusted for household size and composition. This enables the total equivalised income of the household to be used as a proxy for the standard of living of each household member, but because incomes have not been equivalised, this is no longer true.</p>
	<p pid="a.286.3/17" class="indent">3. Gross and net family incomes have been used to answer the question. This includes earnings from employment and self-employment, state support, income from occupational and private pensions, investment income and other sources. Income tax, payments, national insurance contributions, council tax I domestic rates and some other payments are deducted from incomes to produce net incomes.</p>
	<p pid="a.286.3/18" class="indent">4. All estimates are based on survey data and are therefore subject to a degree of uncertainty. Small differences should be treated with caution as these will be affected by sampling error and variability in non-response.</p>
	<p pid="a.286.3/19" class="indent">5. The reference period for HBAI figures is the financial year.</p>
	<p pid="a.286.3/20" class="indent">6. Weekly incomes are presented in 2009-10 prices and have been rounded to the nearest pound. Percentage changes have been rounded to the nearest percentage point.</p>
	<p pid="a.286.3/21" class="indent">7. Families are defined as a single adult or couple living as married and any dependent children, including same sex couples (civil partnerships and cohabitees) from January 2006. A household is made up of one of more families and is defined as a single person or group of people living at the same address as their only or main residence, who either share one meal a day together or share the living accommodation (ie a living room). In line with the wording of the question, analysis has been carried out at the family level.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.287.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="287"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000453">
	Gendercide
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.287.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100489" speakername="Lord Patten" colon=":" colnum="287"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000453">
	<p pid="a.287.1/1" qnum="HL12730">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether the United Kingdom representative to the United Nations has raised the issue of gendercide in 2011 to date.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.287.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100308" speakername="Lord Howell of Guildford" colon=":" colnum="287"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000081">
	<p pid="a.287.2/1">The Government remain firmly committed to combating all forms of discrimination and violence against women and girls. We raise this issue both through bilateral dialogue and via mulitilateral fora. UK representatives have spoken out against such discrimination and violence on many occasions at the United Nations both in Geneva and New York, including in discussions at the Human Rights Council, the Commission on the Status of Women and the General Assembly.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/2">The UK Permanent Representative to the UN in New York has also raised the question of violence against women in a number of Security Council discussions, including on Libya, Somalia and Sudan. The Government's concern was reiterated by Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State Henry Bellingham during the UN summit on Preventing and Responding to Sexual Violence in Conflict in September.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.287.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="287"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000454">
	Gendercide
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.287.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100489" speakername="Lord Patten" colon=":" colnum="287"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000454">
	<p pid="a.287.4/1" qnum="HL12796">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether in 2011 to date the British High Commissioner in India and the British Ambassador in China have raised the issue of gendercide affecting female babies in those countries.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.287.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100308" speakername="Lord Howell of Guildford" colon=":" colnum="287"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000083">
	<p pid="a.287.5/1">The Government remain firmly committed to combating all forms of discrimination and violence against women and girls.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.5/2">Our High Commissioner in Delhi has not raised the issue of sex-selective abortion and female infanticide with the Indian Government in 2011. However, the UK Equalities Minister, my honourable friend Lynne Featherstone, discussed the problem of sex-selective abortion and female infanticide, as well as other issues affecting women in India, during meetings with the Indian Ministry for Women and Child Development and the Indian Parliamentary Committee for Women's Empowerment, when she visited India in June of this year.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.5/3">Additionally, through the Government of India's Reproductive and Child Health Programme the Department for International Development supports the Indian Government's efforts to implement its Pre-Conception and Pre-natal Diagnostic Techniques Regulation Act which outlaws the practice of sex-selective abortion.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.5/4">Our ambassador in Beijing has not raised the issue of female infanticide with the Chinese Government in 2011. However my noble friend Baroness Warsi raised China's one child policy earlier this year in a meeting with Madame Uyunqimg, vice-chair of the Standing Committee of the National People's Congress.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.5/5">We believe that it is important that family planning and its implementation meet international human rights standards.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.5/6">In his 2011 Work Report to the Nation, Premier Wen announced that China would progressively improve the basic state policy on family planning and promote balanced population growth. We welcome this announcement and would encourage the Chinese Government to ensure that the relevant domestic laws are properly enforced at local level.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.288.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="288"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000455">
	Government Departments: Official Receptions
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.288.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon=":" colnum="288"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000455">
	<p pid="a.288.1/1" qnum="HL12670">To ask Her Majesty's Government who represented the Foreign and Commonwealth Office at the recent Hillsborough reception which included the President of the Republic of Ireland.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.288.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100308" speakername="Lord Howell of Guildford" colon=":" colnum="288"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000089">
	<p pid="a.288.2/1">His Excellency Julian King, the British Ambassador to Ireland attended the reception and dinner at Hillsborough Castle at the invitation of the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland the right honourable Owen Paterson. Both events were attended by President McAleese as the guest of honour.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.288.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="288"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000456">
	Government Departments: Staff
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.288.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100021" speakername="Lord Ashcroft" colon=":" colnum="288"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000456">
	<p pid="a.288.4/1" qnum="HL12357">To ask Her Majesty's Government how many staff have been employed by the Department for International Development in each year since 1997.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.289.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100467" speakername="Baroness Northover" colon=":" colnum="289"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000090">
	<p pid="a.289.0/1">The numbers of staff employed by the Department for International Development in each year since 1997 are shown in the table below.</p>
	<p pid="a.289.0/2">The figures show our Home Civil Servant (HCS) staff and our Staff Appointed in Country (SAIC).</p>
	<p pid="a.289.0/3">SAIC are employed locally overseas on local terms and conditions, in support of our in-country development activity.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.289.0/6"> <td>Year</td> <td>No. of HCS employees</td> <td>No. of SAIC employees</td> <td>Total</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.0/7"> <td>1997</td> <td>1,714</td> <td>330</td> <td>2,044</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.0/8"> <td>1998</td> <td>1,690</td> <td>356</td> <td>2,046</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.0/9"> <td>1999</td> <td>1,822</td> <td>457</td> <td>2,279</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.0/10"> <td>2000</td> <td>1,896</td> <td>404</td> <td>2,300</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.0/11"> <td>2001</td> <td>1,884</td> <td>424</td> <td>2,298</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.0/12"> <td>2002</td> <td>1,956</td> <td>739</td> <td>2,695</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.0/13"> <td>2003</td> <td>1,933</td> <td>874</td> <td>2,807</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.0/14"> <td>2004</td> <td>1,949</td> <td>918</td> <td>2,867</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.0/15"> <td>2005</td> <td>1,928</td> <td>989</td> <td>2,917</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.0/16"> <td>2006</td> <td>1,847</td> <td>932</td> <td>2,779</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.0/17"> <td>2007</td> <td>1,765</td> <td>874</td> <td>2,639</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.0/18"> <td>2008</td> <td>1,658</td> <td>843</td> <td>2,501</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.0/19"> <td>2009</td> <td>1,647</td> <td>763</td> <td>2,410</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.0/20"> <td>2010</td> <td>1,619</td> <td>766</td> <td>2,385</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.0/21"> <td>2011</td> <td>1,609</td> <td>760</td> <td>2,369</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.289.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="289"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000457">
	Government: Official Photographs
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.289.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/101021" speakername="Lord Kennedy of Southwark" colon=":" colnum="289"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000457">
	<p pid="a.289.2/1" qnum="HL12802">To ask Her Majesty's Government at what events in the past six months they have taken official photographs of the Foreign Secretary.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.289.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100308" speakername="Lord Howell of Guildford" colon=":" colnum="289"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000153">
	<p pid="a.289.3/1">The Foreign Secretary is regularly photographed. Photographs are an element of his official duties, but they are also used as part of the FCO's strategy of explaining more clearly its work to the public.</p>
	<p pid="a.289.3/2">In the past six months, the following official photographs have been taken of the Foreign Secretary:</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/5"> <td>Date</td> <td>Official photographs of the Foreign Secretary</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/6"> <td>30-Mar-</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Turkish Foreign Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/7"> <td>04-Apr-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Chair of the African Union Commission</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/8"> <td>11-Apr-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Commander NATO Training Mission Afghanistan</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/9"> <td>11-Apr-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with former Libya UN Permanent Representative</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/10"> <td>11-Apr-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Italian Foreign Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/11"> <td>11-Apr- 11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Italian Foreign Minister press conference</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/12"> <td>27-Apr-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Australian Foreign Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/13"> <td>28-Apr-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with US Senator John McCain</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/14"> <td>03-May-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Japanese Foreign Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/15"> <td>10-May-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Maltese Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/16"> <td>12-May-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Chairman of the Libyan Transnational National Council</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/17"> <td>16-May-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Romanian Foreign Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/18"> <td>23-May-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with US Secretary of State</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/19"> <td>06-Jun-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Sudanese Foreign Minister Karti</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/20"> <td>07-Jun-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Secretary General Council of Europe</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/21"> <td>08-Jun-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Ethiopian Foreign Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/22"> <td>08-Jun-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Georgian Speaker</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/23"> <td>27-Jun-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary meeting on British Indian Ocean Territory</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/24"> <td>27-Jun-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Premier of Qu&#233;bec</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/25"> <td>29-Jun-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary Twitter picture</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/26"> <td>30-Jun-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Indian Foreign Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/27"> <td>30-Jun-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Mexican Foreign Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/28"> <td>30-Jun-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with President of Pakistan</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/29"> <td>13-Jul-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Colombian Foreign Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/30"> <td>14-Jul-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Malaysian Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/31"> <td>19-Jul-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Kazakh Foreign Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/32"> <td>19-Jul-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with President of the Bharatiya Janata Party of India</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/33"> <td>21-Jul-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Kuwaiti Minister of Foreign Affairs</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/34"> <td>25-Jul-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with French Foreign Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/35"> <td>26-Jul-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary in Milton Keynes</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/36"> <td>27-Jul-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary Libya Statement</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/37"> <td>27-Jul-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Polish Foreign Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/38"> <td>27-Jul-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Yemen Foreign Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/39"> <td>08-Aug-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with German Foreign Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/40"> <td>24-Aug-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary Libya Statement</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/41"> <td>06-Sep-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with President Elect UN General Assembly</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/42"> <td>07-Sep-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Nigerian Foreign Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/43"> <td>07-Sep-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Minister for Foreign Affairs &amp; European Integration for Moldova</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/44"> <td>08-Sep-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary speech at the FCO</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/45"> <td>08-Sep-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary speech</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/46"> <td>29-Sep-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary &amp; Minister Burt with Syrian Human Rights activists</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/47"> <td>06-Oct-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Commonwealth Secretary-General</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/48"> <td>06-Oct-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Israeli leader of the opposition</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/49"> <td>12-Oct-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Iraqi Speaker</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/50"> <td>12-Oct-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Malawi Foreign Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/51"> <td>12-Oct-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Portuguese Foreign Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.289.3/52"> <td>20-Oct-11</td> <td>Foreign Secretary with Macedonia Prime Minister</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.291.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="291"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000458">
	House of Lords: Catering
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.291.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100481" speakername="Lord Palmer" colon=":" colnum="291"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000458">
	<p pid="a.291.1/1" qnum="HL12787">To ask the Chairman of Committees what is the outstanding debt to the House of Lords Catering and Retail Services beyond the 30-day limit; and how much of that is owed by (a) members of the House of Lords, and (b) members of staff employed by the House of Lords.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.291.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100067" speakername="Lord Brabazon of Tara" colon=":" colnum="291"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000249">
	<p pid="a.291.2/1">As at the end of <phrase class="date" code="2011-10-25">25 October 2011</phrase> the total outstanding debt to the House of Lords Catering and Retail Services owed for more than 30 days was &#163;38,916.63, made up of the following amounts:</p>
	<p pid="a.291.2/2">&#163;31,578.90 owed for banqueting functions and other events, sponsored by Members of the House of Lords;&#163;2,067.38 owed by Members of the House of Lords for food and drink in House outlets; and&#163;5,270.35 owed by a member of staff employed by the House of Lords.</p>
	<p pid="a.291.2/3">Accounts are always reviewed at the end of every month and, as at the end of <phrase class="date" code="2011-10-31">31 October</phrase>, &#163;2,705.00 of these banqueting debts, &#163;745.04 of these Members' debts, and the full amount owed by staff had been paid.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.291.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="291"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000459">
	House of Lords: Oral Statements
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.291.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100616" speakername="Lord Stoddart of Swindon" colon=":" colnum="291"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000459">
	<p pid="a.291.4/1" qnum="HL12951">To ask the Leader of the House, further to the Statement he repeated on 24 October concerning Libya and the European Council meeting (<I>Official Report</I>, cols. 550-3), whether in the future when two important and separate subjects are contained in one Statement they will arrange that forty minutes are available for back-bench questions.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.291.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100621" speakername="Lord Strathclyde" colon=":" colnum="291"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000251">
	<p pid="a.291.5/1">Ministerial Oral Statements are made &quot;for the information of the House&quot; and &quot;should not be made the occasion for immediate debate&quot; (Companion 6.07). Twenty minutes is appropriate for backbench interventions on Statements, given the Companion guidance and the necessary balance between interest in a Statement and inconvenience to those Members who have come prepared for the day's expected business. In exceptional circumstances, however, the Usual Channels can agree to extend the time allocated to back-bench interventions on Statements, and have done ,so on several occasions this session.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.291.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="291"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000460">
	Housing
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.291.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon=":" colnum="291"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000460">
	<p pid="a.291.7/1" qnum="HL12637">To ask Her Majesty's Government what assessment they have made of the Intergenerational Foundation's report <I>Hoarding of Housing</I>.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.292.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100269" speakername="Baroness Hanham" colon=":" colnum="292"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000252">
	<p pid="a.292.0/1">People who have worked hard and paid their taxes all their lives should not be taxed or bullied out of their homes. Many people will rightly want to stay in their homes for as long as possible. Homes can provide a secure asset for the future, they provide bedrooms for visiting family and friends, and homes have an important emotional value and attachment. State interventions in private property should be limited, and the right to own property is a fundamental human right that should be respected.</p>
	<p pid="a.292.0/2">In this context, we disagree with many of the suggestions in the independent report, such as its calls to abolish the single person council tax discount and to increase taxes on family homes.</p>
	<p pid="a.292.0/3">Instead, it is the approach of this Government to work with local communities to build more homes and increase choice. For example, we have provided &#163;13 million for councils to make it easier for tenants who actively want to move from larger family homes to smaller, more manageable homes. We have abolished arbitrary Whitehall density targets to encourage the building of new family homes. Our FirstBuy scheme is helping first time buyers get on the housing ladder, and our National Home Swap initiative will allow social tenants to move home without losing their security of tenure.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.292.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="292"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000461">
	Libya
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.292.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/101102" speakername="Lord Empey" colon=":" colnum="292"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000461">
	<p pid="a.292.2/1" qnum="HL12732">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether they will lead negotiations with the National Transitional Council in Libya to secure compensation for the victims of IRA violence.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.292.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100308" speakername="Lord Howell of Guildford" colon=":" colnum="292"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000255">
	<p pid="a.292.3/1">We are looking at all possible options to secure the resolution of legacy issues including those relating to Qadhafi's support of IRA violence. When the National Transitional Council appoints the new Transitional Government, this will be one of HM Government's priorities. As my right honourable friend the Prime Minister has said in another place, this will be an important bilateral issue between Britain and the new Libyan authorities.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.292.4" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="292"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000462">
	Libya
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.292.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/101102" speakername="Lord Empey" colon=":" colnum="292"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000462">
	<p pid="a.292.5/1" qnum="HL12733">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether negotiations with the National Transitional Council in Libya to secure compensation for victims of IRA violence will be left to private individuals or their legal representatives to initiate.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.292.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100308" speakername="Lord Howell of Guildford" colon=":" colnum="292"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000256">
	<p pid="a.292.6/1">We are looking at all possible options to secure the resolution of legacy issues including those relating to Qadhafi's support of IRA violence. When the National Transitional Council appoints the new Transitional Government, this will be one of the Government's priorities. As my right honourable friend the Prime Minister has said in another place, this will be an important bilateral issue between Britain and the new Libyan authorities.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.293.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="293"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000463">
	Local Authorities: Expenditure
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.293.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/101021" speakername="Lord Kennedy of Southwark" colon=":" colnum="293"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000463">
	<p pid="a.293.1/1" qnum="HL12693">To ask Her Majesty's Government what estimate they have made of changes in per capita spending in local authorities following the 2011-12 local government settlement.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.293.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100269" speakername="Baroness Hanham" colon=":" colnum="293"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000257">
	<p pid="a.293.2/1">Local authority revenue expenditure in England in 2010-11 is estimated at &#163;1,998 per capita. Budgeted revenue expenditure for 2011-12 is &#163;1,951 per capita. This is a change of just 2.4 per cent, before adjusting for differences in responsibilities between years.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.293.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="293"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000464">
	Northern Ireland Office: Bonuses
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.293.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon=":" colnum="293"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000464">
	<p pid="a.293.4/1" qnum="HL12697">To ask Her Majesty's Government what plans they have to award bonus payments to staff of the Northern Ireland Office; and how much such payments would be.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.293.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100028" speakername="Earl Attlee" colon=":" colnum="293"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000258">
	<p pid="a.293.5/1">The Northern Ireland Office has adopted Ministry of Justice terms and conditions for its staff who are Home Civil Servants. The Ministry of Justice operates a reward and recognition scheme, which the NIO has adopted, for staff below the senior civil service. This provides for non-cash awards (gift vouchers) of up to &#163;50 and special cash bonuses up to &#163;500 for staff who have made a particularly outstanding contribution. Pay arrangements for 2011-12 are yet to be determined but will, as in 2010-11, reflect the current two-year pay freeze.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.293.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="293"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000465">
	Pensions
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.293.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100983" speakername="Lord Myners" colon=":" colnum="293"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000465">
	<p pid="a.293.7/1" qnum="HL12805">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether the Pension Regulator will be instructed to take into account the impact of quantitative easing when directing that action should be taken to accelerate the reduction of scheme deficits.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.293.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100992" speakername="Lord Freud" colon=":" colnum="293"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000259">
	<p pid="a.293.8/1">The Pensions Act 2004 introduced a scheme-specific approach to regulating pension scheme funding. The Pensions Regulator, which is operationally independent of Ministers, has made it clear that funding objectives must be set prudently, to uphold stability during various economic climates. The scheme funding regime is sufficiently flexible to support pension schemes through fluctuations in the economic cycle, and allows trustees the flexibility to develop prudent funding strategies which take account of the particular circumstances of their particular scheme.</p>
	<p pid="a.293.8/2">Pension scheme funding strategies are designed to deliver members' benefits over the long-term, during which time there will inevitably be fluctuations in the economic cycle. I understand that the Regulator will continue to apply the system pragmatically, looking for outcomes in the best interests of the scheme and sponsor.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.294.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="294"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000466">
	Protests
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.294.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100489" speakername="Lord Patten" colon=":" colnum="294"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000466">
	<p pid="a.294.1/1" qnum="HL12731">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether they are (a) considering availability for work surveys amongst those presently camping in support of the Occupy the Stock Exchange protests by St Paul's Cathedral and Finsbury Square, City of London, and (b) making special arrangements for the payment of social benefits to those persons.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.294.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100992" speakername="Lord Freud" colon=":" colnum="294"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000261">
	<p pid="a.294.2/1">The benefit entitlement rules encourage claimants to meet their responsibilities. Those people claiming jobseeker's allowance are expected to attend their Jobcentre Plus Office fortnightly, where they are asked to confirm that they are available for and actively seeking work. Failure to attend, or to comply with these requirements could result in their benefit being sanctioned, or terminated. As those claiming jobseeker's allowance have their continued entitlement assessed frequently, there are no plans to carry out a more general &quot;availability for work&quot; survey.</p>
	<p pid="a.294.2/2">No special arrangements have been made for the payment of benefits to claimants camping at the Occupy the Stock Exchange protests.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.294.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="294"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000467">
	Shipping: Towing Vessels
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.294.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100403" speakername="Lord MacKenzie of Culkein" colon=":" colnum="294"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000467">
	<p pid="a.294.4/1" qnum="HL12666">To ask Her Majesty's Government what discussions have taken place with the Government of France in relation to the withdrawal of the coastguard's emergency towing vessels from their stations in Dover and Falmouth; and whether the Government of France has made any representations on this matter.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.294.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100028" speakername="Earl Attlee" colon=":" colnum="294"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000263">
	<p pid="a.294.5/1">The cost and operation of the Dover emergency towing vessel (ETV) was shared with the French Government. The Falmouth ETV was funded solely from UK Government funds and was operated by the Maritime and Coastguard Agency (MCA). Following the comprehensive spending review announcement concerning the withdrawal of UK ETVs, MCA officials wrote to the French Directorate of Maritime Affairs formally to advise them of the withdrawal of the Dover ETV. MCA officials also met with their opposite numbers at the French embassy. The French Government have since announced their intention to reposition one of their ETVs from the Bay of Biscay area to the area off Calais.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.295.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="295"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000468">
	South Sudan
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.295.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon=":" colnum="295"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000468">
	<p pid="a.295.1/1" qnum="HL12633">To ask Her Majesty's Government what support they are giving to the Government of South Sudan in expediting their application to join the Commonwealth; and what timetable has been established for completing the admission process.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.295.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100308" speakername="Lord Howell of Guildford" colon=":" colnum="295"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000264">
	<p pid="a.295.2/1">We fully support South Sudan's application to join the Commonwealth. If possible, we would like to see South Sudan join by 2013 as long as it meets the relevant criteria, especially those relating to the core values of democracy, human rights and the rule of law. Ultimately it will be for all member states to agree on whether to admit South Sudan to the Commonwealth.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.295.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="295"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000469">
	Transport: Funding
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.295.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/101021" speakername="Lord Kennedy of Southwark" colon=":" colnum="295"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000469">
	<p pid="a.295.4/1" qnum="HL12545">To ask Her Majesty's Government what capital and revenue funding for local transport schemes has been provided to each of the London Boroughs and the City of London in each year since 1996.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.295.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100028" speakername="Earl Attlee" colon=":" colnum="295"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000265">
	<p pid="a.295.5/1">Since 2001-02 funding for local transport schemes has been provided to the London boroughs and the City of London by Transport for London, with the exception of specific grant payments made direct from the Department for Transport.</p>
	<p pid="a.295.5/2">These payments by the department include exceptional funding to cover damage to local road networks caused by the severe winter weather. They also include funding for street lighting projects delivered through the private finance initiative to boroughs including Croydon and Lewisham, Brent, Ealing, Enfield, Lambeth and Islington.</p>
	<p pid="a.295.5/3">Transport for London (TfL) receives funding in the form of a block grant from the department to deliver transport services. Under devolution it is for the Mayor of London and TfL to decide transport priorities in London and to allocate their budget accordingly. However, as part of the spending review settlement, a list of major investment and upgrade schemes was agreed with the department to ensure delivery of key projects. Before 2001-02 funding was provided directly to London boroughs and the City of London by Government.</p>
	<p pid="a.295.5/4">Information on the overall sums that were paid to local authorities nationally under different schemes is available in the departmental reports for those years; copies of these reports are in the House Library. However, details of specific amounts paid to each borough during the period in question cannot be provided without incurring disproportionate cost.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.296.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="296"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000470">
	Unemployment: Under 25s
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.296.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100794" speakername="Lord Roberts of Llandudno" colon=":" colnum="296"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000470">
	<p pid="a.296.1/1" qnum="HL12860">To ask Her Majesty's Government what financial support they make available to unemployed persons between (a) 16 and 18 years old, and (b) 18 and 25 years old.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.296.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100992" speakername="Lord Freud" colon=":" colnum="296"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000269">
	<p pid="a.296.2/1">Financial support for all unemployed people depends upon their particular circumstances. Benefits that may be available are jobseeker's allowance (JSA), income support (IS), employment and support allowance (ESA) and housing benefit.</p>
	<p pid="a.296.2/2">For jobseekers who have paid sufficient national insurance contributions in the relevant income tax years, contribution-based JSA is available. Eligibility for income-based JSA for under 18s is restricted to prescribed circumstances or where the Secretary of State makes a severe hardship direction. Prescribed circumstances include care leavers, those who are forced to live away from their parents or another person acting in place of their parents and those released from custody. People aged 18 or over may receive JSA if they meet the standard eligibility criteria.</p>
	<p pid="a.296.2/3">Income support is available to people aged 16 or over who fall into a prescribed category. Those in prescribed categories usually have obstacles to employment that means they are not expected to be available for work. Examples include young people who are estranged from their parents and in non-advanced education, lone parents and carers.</p>
	<p pid="a.296.2/4">People aged 16 or over may be able to receive ESA if they have an illness or disability that limits their ability to work.</p>
	<p pid="a.296.2/5">Any award of a DWP benefit for a person aged 16 to 25 is subject to their meeting the normal conditions of entitlement, such as the income, capital and earnings rules. Where the conditions are met and an income-related benefit is awarded, or the young person is on a low income, housing benefit may also be available. Council tax benefit may also be available to those aged over 18.</p>
	<p pid="a.296.2/6">The rates of benefits payable to 16 to 25 year-olds in 2011-12 are available in the annual uprating statement in the (<phrase class="offrep" id="wms/2010-12-09.38"><I>Official Report</I>, 9 December 2010, col. WS 38</phrase>).</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.296.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="296"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000471">
	Universal Credit
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.296.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/101027" speakername="Lord Touhig" colon=":" colnum="296"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000471">
	<p pid="a.296.4/1" qnum="HL12656">To ask Her Majesty's Government what is the estimated cost of the computer system that will be established to run the universal credit.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.296.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100992" speakername="Lord Freud" colon=":" colnum="296"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000275">
	<p pid="a.296.5/1">The Treasury has allocated &#163;2 billion investment funding to the Department of Work and Pensions for universal credit over the current spending review period. Plans on the allocation of funding are currently under review as part of work to produce an outline business case for next-stage approval. This funding will cover all aspects of implementation.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.297.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="297"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000472">
	Universal Credit
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.297.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/101027" speakername="Lord Touhig" colon=":" colnum="297"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000472">
	<p pid="a.297.1/1" qnum="HL12658">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether the National Audit Office has been consulted about the development and planning of the computer system that will be established to run the universal credit.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2011-11-03a.298.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100992" speakername="Lord Freud" colon=":" colnum="298"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/111103w0001.htm#11110390000276">
	<p pid="a.298.0/1">The department has been working with NAO, to help support it with the methodology of assessing and auditing an agile programme.</p>
	<p pid="a.298.0/2">As part of the Integrated Approvals and Assurance Group that has oversight of assurance activity relating to universal credit, the NAO has put proposals to that group detailing a series of reviews to examine how universal credit will deliver anticipated outcomes and objectives.</p>
	<p pid="a.298.0/3">Planning for the review of the technical assurance of proposed IT system is expected to start in November with field work planned to take place in the new year, leading to the anticipated publication of a value for money report in 2012.</p>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

