<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.127.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn0">
	School Standards and Framework Act 1998: Adherence
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.127.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100162" speakername="Baroness David" colon="" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.127.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/2" qnum="0">What action has been taken to ensure that Section 131 of the School Standards and Framework Act 1998 is complied with--</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/3" qnum="0">(a) by all independent schools, day and boarding; and</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/4" qnum="HL3069">(b) by all those working in nursery education as defined by the Act.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.127.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.127.2/1">It is the responsibility of Ofsted, in the case of independent schools, and local education authorities, in the case of nursery education providers, to ensure that the law is adhered to.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.127.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn1">
	English Literature: Teaching in Schools
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.127.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100016" speakername="Baroness Anelay of St Johns" colon="" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.127.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/2" qnum="HL3080">What measures they are taking to ensure that children leave school with a knowledge of the core texts of English Literature.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.127.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100052" speakername="Baroness Blackstone" colon=":" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.127.5/1">The revised National Curriculum, to be introduced from September 2000, sets out the requirements for teaching English in both primary and secondary schools. In primary schools the range of literature should include works by significant children's authors and long established children's fiction. Since January 1998, primary schools have received on average &pound;5,000 each for the purchase of books.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.5/2">Children between the ages of 11 and 16 are required to study the works of a range of major writers and poets, both classic and modern. The range should include plays, novels, short stories and poetry from the English literary heritage. Classical authors represented include Jane Austen, Charles Dickens, John Milton and William Wordsworth. Two plays by William Shakespeare must also be studied.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.127.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn2">
	Sierra Leone Diamonds
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.127.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.127.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.127.7/2" qnum="HL2991">Whether they have evidence that diamonds are being exported illegally from Sierra Leone via Liberia; and what means exist for identifying such diamonds when offered on world markets.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.128.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="128"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.128.0/1">There is considerable evidence of the illegal export of Sierra Leone diamonds via Liberia. At present there are no established means for identifying such diamonds when offered on world markets. The UK is pressing for a UN Security Council ban on the import of all Sierra Leone diamonds except those accompanied by a certificate of origin issued by the Government of Sierra Leone and for an exploratory hearing of the UN Sanctions Committee, which would involve other countries in the region, to assess the role of diamonds in the Sierra Leone conflict.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.128.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="128"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn3">
	Exports to India and Pakistan: Controls
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.128.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100374" speakername="Lord Lipsey" colon="" colnum="128"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.128.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.128.2/2" qnum="HL3120">In what circumstances a licence is required to export strategic goods or technology to India or Pakistan; and what is their current policy regarding exports to nuclear or nuclear-related end-users in India and Pakistan.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.128.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="128"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.128.3/1">A licence is required to export to India or Pakistan any goods or technology that are listed as subject to control in the legislation under which strategic export controls are implemented or any goods or technology subject to the Weapons of Mass Destruction (WMD) end-use controls set out in Article 4 of Council Regulation (EC) 3381/94 and Regulations 4(1) and 4(2)(b) and (c) of the Dual-Use and Related Goods (Export Control) Regulations 1996.</p>
	<p pid="a.128.3/2">Where a licence is required, then, as my honourable friend the then Minister of State, Tony Lloyd, said in a Written Answer to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/347" name="Stephen Ladyman">the Member for Thanet South (Dr Stephen Ladyman)</phrase> on <phrase class="date" code="1998-07-10">10 July 1998</phrase> in another place, we will not allow the export of items listed in the Nuclear Suppliers Group Dual-Use List to nuclear or nuclear-related end-users in India or Pakistan, nor any other goods to these end-users which could contribute to the Indian and Pakistani nuclear programmes. The exception is equipment which would not normally require an export licence but is deemed licensable under the WMD end-use controls and where the initial concerns about WMD end-use are not subsequently substantiated.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.128.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="128"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn4">
	Sudan: Ceasefire Violations
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.128.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100525" speakername="Lord Rea" colon="" colnum="128"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.128.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.128.5/2" qnum="HL3123">What they are doing about the most recent SPLA violations of the ceasefire in Bahr al-Ghazal, Sudan.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.128.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="128"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.128.6/1">We have been following with grave concern reports of violations by the SPLA of the humanitarian ceasefire in Bahr al-Ghazal and in particular the attack on the town of Gogrial. We call on the SPLA and the Sudanese Government to exercise restraint, to respect humanitarian principles and the agreed ceasefire in that region and to work to negotiate a comprehensive, permanent, effectively-monitored ceasefire throughout Sudan. We reaffirm our support for the peace efforts being made under the auspices of the Intergovernmental Authority on Development (IGAD) and firmly believe that only a negotiated settlement can bring all the people of Sudan the peace and stability they deserve.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.129.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="129"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn5">
	BBC Agreement
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.129.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100296" speakername="Lord Hogg of Cumbernauld" colon="" colnum="129"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.129.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.129.1/2" qnum="HL3178">When they will amend the BBC Agreement to enable the Department of Social Security to make certain payments to the BBC in recognition of the fact that, from 1st November, people aged 75 or over will become entitled to free television licences.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.129.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="129"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.129.2/1">The Amendment to the BBC Agreement [Command 4797] has been laid before the House of Commons today. Copies have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses and the Printed Paper Office.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.129.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="129"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn6">
	Public Service Pension Schemes
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.129.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100053" speakername="Lord Blackwell" colon="" colnum="129"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.129.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.129.4/2" qnum="HL3034">Which pension schemes are in place for public sector employees; and what additional capital sum would need to be provided for each scheme if current liabilities for future pension payments were to be fully funded out of invested capital.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.129.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="129"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.129.5/1">There are several hundred public sector schemes. Such information for all public sector pension scheme arrangements is not held centrally and could be obtained only at disproportionate cost. The only major funded schemes are those for local government employees and public corporations.</p>
	<p pid="a.129.5/2">If capital sums were to be provided to buy out existing unfunded liabilities the sum required would depend on prevailing investment market conditions. Estimates by the Government Actuary's Department of the long-term liabilities for the main unfunded public service pension schemes suggest that liabilities for future pensions in respect of active and former members--including allowances for anticipated future salary and pension increases--total approximately &pound;295 billion as at <phrase class="date" code="1998-03-31">31 March 1998</phrase>. This is made up of:</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.129.5/5"> <td></td> <td>&pound;billion</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.129.5/6"> <td>NHS Pension Scheme</td> <td>70</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.129.5/7"> <td>Teachers Pension Scheme</td> <td>95</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.129.5/8"> <td>Prinicipal Civil Service Pension Scheme</td> <td>50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.129.5/9"> <td>Armed Forces Pension Scheme</td> <td>45</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.129.5/10"> <td>Police and Fire Pension Schemes</td> <td>35</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.129.5/11"> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.129.5/12"> <td>Total</td> <td>295</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.129.5/15">Some more recent figures will appear in an annual actuary's report appended to the pension schemes equivalent of resource accounts later in the year.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.130.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="130"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn7">
	Labour Market Flexibility andthe Global Economy
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.130.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100341" speakername="Lord Judd" colon="" colnum="130"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.130.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.130.1/2" qnum="HL2970">What studies they are making of the consequences of increasing commitment to a global market economy in the absence of the free international movement of labour; and what policies they are pursuing to meet the economic and social challenges flowing from this.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.130.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="130"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.130.2/1">The Government are committed to a more integrated world economy as the foundation for global prosperity, and are pursuing policies to encourage a more flexible labour market, including through membership of the EU. The European Single Market has removed all formal barriers to labour mobility between the 15 EU Member States. Budget 2000 went further and introduced changes to the work permit system to attract highly skilled overseas workers where there are skills shortages. These changes followed a thorough review of the work permits system, and are aimed at contributing to the Government's objective of achieving high and stable levels of growth and employment, and prosperity for all.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.130.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="130"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn8">
	Political Parties, Elections andReferendums Bill
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.130.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100223" speakername="Lord Fraser of Carmyllie" colon="" colnum="130"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.130.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.130.4/2" qnum="HL2993">Whether it is their intention to amend Part XI and Schedule 18 of the Political Parties and Referendums Bill to ensure that the activities of all-party parliamentary groups and associate parliamentary groups are excluded from the definition of political activities.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.130.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="130"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w01.htm#00704w01_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.130.5/1">The Political Parties, Elections and Referendums Bill will, in line with the Neill Committee's recommendation, require companies to seek prior shareholder authorisation for donations to a political party or organisation. The Bill currently defines a &quot;political organisation&quot; as a registered party or any other organisation which carries on, or proposes to carry on, activities of any political nature in the United Kingdom or any other EU member state. The Government accept that this is a very broad definition, and have undertaken to consider it further. Ministers fully recognise the contribution which parliamentary all-party groups make to political life in this country.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.131.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="131"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w02.htm#00704w02_wqn0">
	Oil Production Equipment Exports to Sudan
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.131.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="131"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w02.htm#00704w02_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.131.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.131.1/2" qnum="HL3074">Whether they have received applications for Export Credits Guarantee Department cover in respect of exports to the Sudan related to the development and production of oil; if so, for what amounts; and whether such cover can be made conditional on the making and implementation of an internal peace agreement.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.131.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="131"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w02.htm#00704w02_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.131.2/1">One application was received in 1997 but no ECGD cover was provided.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.131.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="131"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w02.htm#00704w02_wqn1">
	British Telecom
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.131.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100465" speakername="The Earl of Northesk" colon="" colnum="131"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w02.htm#00704w02_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.131.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.131.4/2" qnum="HL3046">What consultations, if any, they have had with British Telecom in respect of the forthcoming rollout of ADSL (Asymmetric Digital Subcriber Line), particularly in terms of the service's availability and affordability to home-users and single-user businesses.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.131.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="131"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w02.htm#00704w02_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.131.5/1">DTI officials have discussed BT's plans for its ADSL rollout with it on a number of occasions, but the details of the rollout are a commercial matter for BT. The independent telecommunications regulator, OFTEL, has been working to ensure effective competition in the provision of ADSL and other broadband services. Once BT has installed ADSL on local lines, it will be required to give service providers access to its upgraded system on non-discriminatory terms. OFTEL is also requiring BT to open up its local loop to other operators so that they can compete in the provision of broadband access. The Government believe that competition, both from other ADSL providers and other high speed services such as broadband cable, is the best way to ensure that access to broadband services is affordable for both consumers and small businesses.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.131.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="131"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w02.htm#00704w02_wqn2">
	British Telecom
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.131.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100465" speakername="The Earl of Northesk" colon="" colnum="131"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w02.htm#00704w02_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.131.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.131.7/2" qnum="HL3047">Whether they consider that British Telecom's proposal to enforce a patent on the concept of &quot;hyperlinks&quot; is consistent with the Government's strategy for access to the Internet; and, if not, what action they are proposing to take to remedy the situation.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.131.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="131"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w02.htm#00704w02_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.131.8/1">Companies are entitled to seek to establish and enforce patent rights in the interests of their shareholders. British Telecom is a private company and its actions in this area are a matter for itself.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.132.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="132"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w02.htm#00704w02_wqn3">
	Factortame Judgment: Payment of Claims
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.132.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100424" speakername="Lord Merlyn-Rees" colon="" colnum="132"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w02.htm#00704w02_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.132.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.132.1/2" qnum="HL3160">How they intend to meet expenditure relating to payment of claims following judgment against the UK in the Factortame case.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.132.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100284" speakername="Baroness Hayman" colon=":" colnum="132"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w02.htm#00704w02_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.132.2/1">Parliamentary approval to expenditure arising from the Factortame case is being sought in the Main Estimate for the Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food (Class X, Vote 2). Pending that approval, urgent expenditure estimated at &pound;9,735 million is being met by repayable advances from the Contingencies Fund.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.132.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="132"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w02.htm#00704w02_wqn4">
	Tuberculosis Cases in London
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.132.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100275" speakername="Lord Harris of Haringey" colon="" colnum="132"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w02.htm#00704w02_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.132.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.132.4/2" qnum="HL2981">What were the numbers of cases of tuberculosis notified in each of the London health authorities in each of the last five years.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2000-07-04a.132.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="132"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/vo000704/text/00704w02.htm#00704w02_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.132.5/1">The information requested is provided in the table.</p>
	<table>
		<caption>Communicable Disease Surveillance Centre--London Tuberculosis Notifications 1995-1999</caption>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/5"> <td>District Health Authority</td> <td>1995</td> <td>1996</td> <td>1997</td> <td>1998</td> <td>1999</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/6"> <td>Barking and Havering</td> <td>43</td> <td>30</td> <td>41</td> <td>43</td> <td>44</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/7"> <td>Barnet</td> <td>66</td> <td>57</td> <td>63</td> <td>77</td> <td>50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/8"> <td>Bexley and Greenwich</td> <td>43</td> <td>59</td> <td>72</td> <td>87</td> <td>81</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/9"> <td>Brent and Harrow</td> <td>272</td> <td>257</td> <td>259</td> <td>236</td> <td>286</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/10"> <td>Bromley</td> <td>13</td> <td>12</td> <td>21</td> <td>13</td> <td>26</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/11"> <td>Camden and Islington</td> <td>135</td> <td>138</td> <td>182</td> <td>187</td> <td>171</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/12"> <td>Croydon</td> <td>47</td> <td>60</td> <td>64</td> <td>83</td> <td>87</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/13"> <td>Ealing, Hammersmith  and Hounslow</td> <td>241</td> <td>287</td> <td>290</td> <td>350</td> <td>351</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/14"> <td>East London and  The City</td> <td>398</td> <td>402</td> <td>427</td> <td>438</td> <td>442</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/15"> <td>Enfield and Haringey</td> <td>140</td> <td>154</td> <td>190</td> <td>167</td> <td>198</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/16"> <td>Hillingdon</td> <td>56</td> <td>78</td> <td>75</td> <td>98</td> <td>79</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/17"> <td>Kensington, Chelsea  and Westminster</td> <td>128</td> <td>162</td> <td>156</td> <td>124</td> <td>153</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/18"> <td>Kingston and  Richmond</td> <td>27</td> <td>25</td> <td>19</td> <td>31</td> <td>31</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/19"> <td>Lambeth, Southwark  and Lewisham</td> <td>198</td> <td>235</td> <td>226</td> <td>241</td> <td>242</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/20"> <td>Merton, Sutton and  Wandsworth</td> <td>104</td> <td>103</td> <td>132</td> <td>106</td> <td>104</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/21"> <td>Redbridge and  Waltham Forest</td> <td>131</td> <td>131</td> <td>194</td> <td>163</td> <td>164</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/22"> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.132.5/23"> <td>London Region Total</td> <td>2,042</td> <td>2,190</td> <td>2,411</td> <td>2,444</td> <td>2,509</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.132.5/26">Source:</p>
	<p pid="a.132.5/27">Public Health Laboratory Service.</p>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

