<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;" >
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;" >
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;" >
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;" >
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;" >

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="c" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.1.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="1"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_wqn0">
	Afghanistan
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.1.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100026" speakername="Lord Astor of Hever" colon="" colnum="1"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.1.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.1.1/2" qnum="HL3894">What is the nature of the recent security incidents in the Helmand Province of Afghanistan.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.1.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="1"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.1.2/1">On <phrase class="date" code="2006-02-03">3 February 2006</phrase>, insurgents in Helmand Province mounted a series of attacks against both Afghan security forces and government offices. The Afghan national police and a small number of US forces were deployed to reinforce the staff of the deputy governor of Helmand Province. By <phrase class="date" code="2007-02-04">4 February</phrase>, the insurgents had dispersed from the area and following further reinforcement from the Afghanistan national army the affected areas are now under the control of Afghan forces.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.1.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="1"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_wqn1">
	Afghanistan
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.1.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100026" speakername="Lord Astor of Hever" colon="" colnum="1"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.1.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.1.4/2" qnum="HL3895">What arrangements are in hand to ensure co-ordinated action on security matters between the United Kingdom contingent to be deployed to the Helmand Province of Afghanistan and the authorities in adjacent provinces such as Kandahar.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.1.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="1"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.1.5/1">There are a number of measures in place to ensure co-ordinated action on security matters in southern Afghanistan, including the sharing of intelligence with coalition partners and the co-ordination of military plans.</p>
	<p pid="c.1.5/2">The lead nation to command southern Afghanistan will be Canada, followed on current plans by the Dutch in November 2006 and the UK in May 2007. The regional commander will ensure that NATO forces deployed to southern Afghanistan operate in a co-ordinated manner and have access to relevant information on operations in other provinces. In addition, the UK will have liaison officers in the regional command office to ensure a joined-up approach with our operations in Helmand.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.1.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="1"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_wqn2">
	Armed Forces: Defence Aviation Repair Agency
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.1.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100028" speakername="Earl Attlee" colon="" colnum="1"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.1.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.1.7/2" qnum="HL3933">Where the work on fast jets will be undertaken following the closure of the Defence Aviation Repair Agency's fast jet business at St Athan, Glamorgan.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.1.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="1"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.1.8/1">Harrier GR7 combined maintenance and upgrade has been undertaken at the main operating base (MOB) at RAF Cottesmore, Rutland since November 2004. Depth on-aircraft maintenance for the Tornado GR4 will concentrate forward to the MOB at RAF Marham in Norfolk. Depth on-aircraft maintenance for the Tornado F3 is currently undertaken at both DARA St Athan and the MOB at RAF Leuchars. From March 2006 this work will be done solely at RAF Leuchars until the aircraft's out-of-service date.</p>
	<p pid="c.1.8/2">All depth on-aircraft maintenance work required for the Jaguar and Hawk aircraft to meet their respective out-of-service dates will be completed at DARA St Athan prior to closure.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.2.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="2"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_wqn3">
	Armed Forces: Defence Aviation Repair Agency
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.2.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100028" speakername="Earl Attlee" colon="" colnum="2"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.2.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.2.1/2" qnum="HL3934">Where relevant engine maintenance work will be undertaken following the closure of the Defence Aviation Repair Agency's engine maintenance business at Fleetlands, Hampshire.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.2.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="2"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_spnew1">
	<p pid="c.2.2/1">Engine maintenance for the Tornado GR4/F3, Hawk, Lynx and Sea King will be undertaken by Rolls-Royce Defence Aerospace at a number of different locations. Engine support for the Gazelle will be initially contracted with Turbomeca, the original equipment manufacturer for the engine. The work is likely to be undertaken in the UK; however, contractual arrangements are still being negotiated. The Chinook engines are currently supported by Honeywell Engines &amp; Systems under a prime contract, sub-contracted to DARA Fleetlands. Upon site closure engine support will continue to be the responsibility of Honeywell Engines &amp; Systems.</p>
	<p pid="c.2.2/2">All engine maintenance work required for the Jaguar to meet its out-of-service date will be completed at DARA Fleetlands prior to closure.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.2.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="2"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_wqn4">
	Armed Forces: Joint Strike Fighter
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.2.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100804" speakername="Lord Dykes" colon="" colnum="2"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.2.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.2.4/2" qnum="HL3900">What additional representations they will make to the Government of the United States following the decision to drop the Rolls-Royce option for the second Joint Strike Fighter aircraft engine project.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.2.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="2"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_spmin2">
	<p pid="c.2.5/1">Harrier GR7 combined maintenance and upgrade has been undertaken at the main operating base (MOB) at RAF Cottesmore, Rutland, since November 2004. Depth on-aircraft maintenance for the Tornado GR4 will concentrate forward to the MOB at RAF Marham in Norfolk. Depth on-aircraft maintenance for the Tornado F3 is currently undertaken at both DARA St Athan and the MOB at RAF Leuchars. From March 2006 this work will be done solely at RAF Leuchars until the aircraft's out-of-service date.</p>
	<p pid="c.2.5/2">All depth on-aircraft maintenance work required for the Jaguar and Hawk aircraft to meet their respective out-of-service dates will be completed at DARA St Athan prior to closure.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.3.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="3"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_wqn5">
	Arms Control
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.3.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="3"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_wqn5">
	<p pid="c.3.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.3.1/2" qnum="HL4097">What plans they have for closing any existing loopholes in arms control for all kinds of military equipment which occur through brokering and licensing agreements.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.3.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="3"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_spmin3">
	<p pid="c.3.2/1">The Government do not accept that any such loopholes exist. None the less, DTI is monitoring the impact of the legislation and will review it in three years' time, in line with the Cabinet Office guidance on better regulation.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.3.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="3"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_wqn6">
	Arms Control
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.3.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="3"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_wqn6">
	<p pid="c.3.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.3.4/2" qnum="HL4098">How they are developing end-use monitoring of exports of British arms and military equipment; and whether United Kingdom military attach&eacute;s overseas are assisting in this work.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.3.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="3"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_spmin4">
	<p pid="c.3.5/1">The Government are committed to carrying out post-export monitoring of strategic exports from the UK where such monitoring is feasible and would make a genuine contribution to our efforts to prevent their diversion or misuse. The possibility of such monitoring cannot, however, override the need for a thorough risk assessment before the issue of any licence. If a licence application is not consistent with the consolidated EU and national export licensing criteria it will be refused. Our overseas posts watch carefully for reports about the possible misuse of UK-exported equipment in the countries that they cover. Defence and military attach&eacute;s, where available, are a valuable resource in this regard and in the rigorous assessment of export licence applications themselves.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.3.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="3"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_wqn7">
	Autism
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.3.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100414" speakername="The Countess of Mar" colon="" colnum="3"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_wqn7">
	<p pid="c.3.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.3.7/2" qnum="HL4116">What planning provisions are made by the Department for Education and Skills for each stage of education for children with autistic spectrum disorders.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.3.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100839" speakername="Lord Adonis" colon=":" colnum="3"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w01.htm#60227w01_spmin5">
	<p pid="c.3.8/1">The Government, through legislation and guidance, set the framework for planning and making provision for all children with special educational needs (SEN), including those with autistic spectrum disorders (ASDs), and it is for local agencies to develop arrangements within that framework.</p>
	<p pid="c.3.8/2">The Education Act 1996 and associated regulations lay duties on local authorities to publish information on their SEN arrangements, including any plans to develop provision, and to keep those arrangements under review. The SEN code of practice gives statutory guidance to schools, local authorities and others on making provision in the early years and during the primary and secondary phases. The Disability Discrimination Act 1995 lays a duty on schools and local authorities to plan to increase access to both premises and the curriculum for disabled children, including many children with ASDs.</p>
	<p pid="c.3.8/3">For ASDs, in particular, we have published non-statutory guidance. The autism exemplar under the National Service Framework for Children, Young People and Maternity Services, aimed at professionals in education, health and social services and the voluntary sector, illustrates optimal provision for a child with autism from the age of three through to 16. The ASDs good practice guidance, which the Department for Education and Skills and the Department of Health published in 2002, makes &quot;policy and planning&quot; one of the key principles for good autism provision and advises that education, health and social services should work together to arrive at a clear picture of the size of the cohort of children with ASD and plan to meet future demand.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.4.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="4"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn0">
	Bosnia and Herzegovina
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.4.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100804" speakername="Lord Dykes" colon="" colnum="4"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.4.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.4.1/2" qnum="HL4064">What progress has been made by the European Union Council of Ministers in concluding a stabilisation and association agreement with Bosnia and Herzegovina following the European Commission's communication of October 2005.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.4.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="4"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.4.2/1">Negotiations on a stabilisation and association agreement between the EU and Bosnia and Herzegovina were officially opened on <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-25">25 November 2005</phrase>. The first round of talks, which began on <phrase class="date" code="2006-01-25">25 January 2006</phrase>, went well. Successive rounds of negotiations will continue until at least November 2006. As the EU has made clear, the pace and conclusion of these negotiations will depend on continued progress in key areas of reform, such as police restructuring and, in particular, full co-operation with the International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.4.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="4"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn1">
	Broadband
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.4.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100489" speakername="Lord Patten" colon="" colnum="4"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.4.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.4.4/2" qnum="HL4005">Whether businesses in rural areas are disadvantaged by delays in the development of rural broadband infrastructure; and whether they are discussing this issue with the communications regulator, Ofcom.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.4.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="4"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.4.5/1">The UK was listed as first for extensiveness, with coverage at 99.7 per cent in September 2005 <sup>1</sup> , which reflects the successful delivery on the target set in 2001 of having the most extensive broadband market in the G7 by the end of 2005.</p>
	<p pid="c.4.5/2"><sup>1</sup> Ovum <i>International Broadband Market Comparisons Update January 2006.</i></p>
	<p pid="c.4.5/3">Through <i>Connecting the UK: The Digital Strategy</i> the Government have made a commitment to address the so-called digital divide so that all citizens can take advantage of the digital world. Although fixed broadband connections will play a major role in delivery of digital media, mobile devices will also have a significant impact.</p>
	<p pid="c.4.5/4">As the development of broadband continues toward next-generation access in the UK, the Government are actively working to bring together private and public sectors, in addition to Ofcom, to gain effective dialogue across the value chain.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.5.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="5"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn2">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.5.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="5"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.5.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.5.1/2" qnum="HL3964">When they first became aware that Sir John Chisholm might profit by some &pound;20 million from the arrangements for the privatisation of QinetiQ.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.5.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="5"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_spmin2">
	<p pid="c.5.2/1">Sir John Chisholm invested in QinetiQ at the time of the PPP transaction in February 2003 on the terms offered and agreed by the shareholders, the Ministry of Defence and Carlyle. Any gains he makes on this investment are linked directly to the growth in value of the business, which in turn is driven by the performance of the company and the value attributed by investors. As a significant shareholder, MOD has kept the performance of the company under regular review, although the value attributed by investors could only really be tested in the preparation work leading up to the Intention to Float announcement (<phrase class="date" code="2006-01-12">12 January 2006</phrase>) and in the IPO itself (<phrase class="date" code="2006-02-10">10 February 2006</phrase>).</p>
	<p pid="c.5.2/2">The shareholdings of Sir John Chisholm and other senior management are subject to a lock-up agreement, which restricts the proportion of shares they are able to sell for the three years after the IPO, and hence provides an ongoing incentive on senior management to continue to create value for the company and the shareholders. Sir John Chisholm sold no shares at IPO.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.5.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="5"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn3">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.5.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="5"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.5.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.5.4/2" qnum="HL3965">Whether the post of chairman of QinetiQ was advertised before Sir John Chisholm was appointed.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.5.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="5"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.5.5/1">Under the terms of the PPP transaction in February 2003, decisions on the appointment of the chairman of QinetiQ are a matter for Carlyle.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.6.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="6"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn4">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.6.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="6"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.6.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.6.1/2" qnum="HL3966">Whether the post of chief executive of QinetiQ was advertised before Sir John Chisholm was appointed.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.6.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="6"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_spnew1">
	<p pid="c.6.2/1">Sir John Chisholm was appointed in 1991 as chief executive of the Defence Research Agency (which subsequently became the Defence Evaluation and Research Agency in 1993) following an open competition and continued as chief executive of QinetiQ, steering the organisation through its transition from a government agency to a Companies Act company.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.6.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="6"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn5">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.6.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="6"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn5">
	<p pid="c.6.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.6.4/2" qnum="HL3968">Whether the post of finance director of QinetiQ was advertised before Mr Love was appointed.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.6.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="6"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_spnew2">
	<p pid="c.6.5/1">Graham Love was appointed as chief financial officer of the Defence Evaluation and Research Agency (DERA) in 2001 following an open competition and continued in this role in QinetiQ, steering the organisation through its transition from a government agency to a Companies Act company.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.6.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="6"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn6">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.6.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="6"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn6">
	<p pid="c.6.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.6.7/2" qnum="HL3969">Which Minister was responsible for the appointment of Sir John Chisholm and Mr Love to the posts they hold in QinetiQ.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.6.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="6"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_spnew3">
	<p pid="c.6.8/1">Under the terms of the PPP transaction in February 2003, decisions on the appointment of the chairman of QinetiQ are a matter for Carlyle and those on the chief executive appointment are a matter for the QinetiQ board.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.6.9" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="6"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn7">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.6.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="6"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn7">
	<p pid="c.6.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.6.10/2" qnum="HL4016">When Sir John Chisholm was first appointed managing director of the Defence Evaluation and Research Agency.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.6.11" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="6"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_spnew4">
	<p pid="c.6.11/1">Sir John Chisholm was appointed in 1991 as chief executive of the Defence Research Agency, which subsequently became the Defence Evaluation and Research Agency (DERA) in 1995.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.6.12" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="6"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn8">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.6.13" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="6"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn8">
	<p pid="c.6.13/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.6.13/2" qnum="HL4017">Which Minister approved the stock option plan that would have enabled Sir John Chisholm and Mr Love to gain more than they were originally due to derive from the QinetiQ flotation.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.6.14" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="6"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_spnew5">
	<p pid="c.6.14/1">There is no such stock option plan that would have enabled Sir John Chisholm and Graham Love to gain more than they were originally due to derive from the QinetiQ flotation.</p>
	<p pid="c.6.14/2">All QinetiQ employees including them received &pound;500 of shares at the IPO. This was approved by Lord Drayson as the Minister responsible for the QinetiQ IPO.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.7.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="7"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn9">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.7.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="7"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn9">
	<p pid="c.7.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.7.1/2" qnum="HL4019">Whether the head of the civil service was consulted on the extent to which individual former public servants would benefit financially from the flotation of QinetiQ.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.7.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="7"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_spnew6">
	<p pid="c.7.2/1">No, the head of the civil service was not consulted, as it was not considered necessary to do so. All QinetiQ employees ceased to be public servants on vesting of the company on <phrase class="date" code="2001-07-01">1 July 2001</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.7.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="7"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn10">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.7.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="7"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn10">
	<p pid="c.7.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.7.4/2" qnum="HL4020">Whether Sir John Chisholm will be invited to enter into a binding agreement not to make any use of the stock option plan still available to him; and, if so, what form this agreement will take.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.7.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="7"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_spnew7">
	<p pid="c.7.5/1">Sir John Chisholm, along with certain other senior executives, has entered into a lock-up agreement, which restricts his ability to sell his QinetiQ shares during the three-year period following the IPO. The details of this agreement are set out in the QinetiQ IPO prospectus, a copy of which was placed in the Library of the House on <phrase class="date" code="2007-01-26">26 January</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.7.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="7"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn11">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.7.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="7"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_wqn11">
	<p pid="c.7.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.7.7/2" qnum="HL4021">What has been the sum of the contributions from public funds to Sir John Chisholm's public service pension since he was appointed as managing director of the Defence Evaluation and Research Agency.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.7.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="7"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w02.htm#60227w02_spnew8">
	<p pid="c.7.8/1">Sir John Chisholm was a civil servant from 1991 to 2001. Throughout this period he was a member of both the Principal Civil Service Pension Scheme and the Civil Service Supplementary Earnings Pension Scheme, and the contributions made from public funds were made in accordance with the rules of these schemes and on the same basis as other civil servants. Details of his pension arrangements since he was appointed as chief executive of the Defence Evaluation and Research Agency are available in the annual reports published by the agency since it was established in 1995, which were placed in the Library at the time of publication. That information relating to the period between the end of the financial year 2000&ndash;01 and the establishment of QinetiQ on <phrase class="date" code="2001-07-01">1 July 2001</phrase> can be found in the Defence Science and Technology Laboratory annual report for 2001&ndash;02.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.7.9" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="7"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn0">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.7.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="7"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.7.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.7.10/2" qnum="HL4042">What is the sum of the private contributions that Sir John Chisholm made to his public service pension while he was managing director of the Defence Evaluation and Research Agency.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.7.11" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="7"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.7.11/1">Sir John Chisholm was a civil servant between 1991 and 2001. During this period he was a member of the Principal Civil Service Pension Scheme and the Civil Service Supplementary Earnings Pension Scheme. As with other civil servants, Sir John would have been entitled to make additional voluntary contributions to purchase extra years of reckonable service in order to enhance his entitlement and final pension. However, further such detail on his pension arrangements is a private matter for Sir John.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.8.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="8"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn1">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.8.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="8"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.8.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.8.1/2" qnum="HL4043">When (a) Sir John Chisholm, and (b) Mr Graham Love might expect to be able to draw their pensions acquired as a result of working for the Defence Evaluation and Research Agency.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.8.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="8"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_spnew1">
	<p pid="c.8.2/1">Both Sir John Chisholm and Graham Love are entitled to draw their accrued pensions acquired as a result of working for DERA from age 60.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.8.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="8"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn2">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.8.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="8"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.8.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.8.4/2" qnum="HL4045">How much (a) Sir John Chisholm, and (b) Mr Graham Love have drawn in each financial year since the establishment of QinetiQ by way of emoluments as a result of working for the Defence Evaluation and Research Agency.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.8.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="8"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_spnew2">
	<p pid="c.8.5/1">The Defence Evaluation and Research Agency ceased to exist from <phrase class="date" code="2001-07-01">1 July 2001</phrase>, at which time QinetiQ was vested as a company. Since this point, the emoluments drawn by Sir John Chisholm and Graham Love relate to their employment by QinetiQ and as such are disclosed in QinetiQ's annual report and accounts.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.8.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="8"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn3">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.8.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="8"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.8.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.8.7/2" qnum="HL4046">How much (a) Sir John Chisholm, and (b) Mr Graham Love drew by way of emoluments in each of the last three financial years that they worked for the Defence Evaluation and Research Agency.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.8.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="8"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_spnew3">
	<p pid="c.8.8/1">Information on the emoluments drawn by Sir John Chisholm and Graham Love in the last three financial years that they worked for the Defence Evaluation and Research Agency is contained in the agency's annual reports which were placed in the Library at the time of publication. That information relating to the period between the end of the financial year 2000&ndash;01 and the establishment of QinetiQ on <phrase class="date" code="2001-07-01">1 July 2001</phrase> can be found in the Defence Science and Technology Laboratory annual report for 2001&ndash;02.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.8.9" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="8"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn4">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.8.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="8"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.8.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.8.10/2" qnum="HL4047">To what risks the investments in QinetiQ of (a) Sir John Chisholm, and (b) Mr Graham Love were exposed before the company's shares started to be traded on the Stock Exchange.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.8.11" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="8"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_spnew4">
	<p pid="c.8.11/1">Sir John Chisholm's and Graham Love's investments were exposed to the risk that the equity value of the company, on which their investments were based, declined after the PPP.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.8.12" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="8"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn5">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.8.13" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="8"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn5">
	<p pid="c.8.13/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.8.13/2" qnum="HL4188">Which Minister gave final approval to the arrangements by which Sir John Chisholm was able to benefit by over &pound;20 million from the QinetiQ flotation.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.9.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_spnew5">
	<p pid="c.9.0/1">Sir John Chisholm, Graham Love and other QinetiQ senior management invested in the company at the time of the PPP transaction in February 2003 on the terms offered and agreed by the shareholders, MoD and Carlyle, at this time. Any gains senior management make on their investments are linked directly to the growth in value of the business, which in turn is driven by the performance of the company, and the value attributed by investors. The Minister responsible for approving all aspects of the PPP transaction, including this senior management incentive scheme, was the former Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence, now my noble friend Lord Moonie. Details of the employee share schemes included in the IPO, and the company's plans for share schemes after the IPO, are set out in the QinetiQ IPO prospectus, which was placed in the Library of the House on <phrase class="date" code="2007-01-26">26 January</phrase>. I am the Minister responsible for the IPO of QinetiQ.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.9.1" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn6">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.9.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn6">
	<p pid="c.9.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.9.2/2" qnum="HL4189">Whether any former employees of the Ministry of Defence have benefited from the arrangements surrounding the flotation of QinetiQ that accrued to the benefit of Sir John Chisholm; and, if so, which former employees; and</p>
	<p pid="c.9.2/3" qnum="HL4190">How many employees of QinetiQ have not had access to the arrangements that benefited Sir John Chisholm on the flotation of QinetiQ; and what proportion of the total employees they represent.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.9.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_spnew6">
	<p pid="c.9.3/1">The share schemes that apply to Sir John Chisholm and other employees in QinetiQ are set out in detail in the QinetiQ IPO prospectus, a copy of which was placed in the Library of the House on <phrase class="date" code="2007-01-26">26 January</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.9.4" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn7">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.9.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn7">
	<p pid="c.9.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.9.5/2" qnum="HL4192">What rate of return on total investment in the Defence Evaluation and Research Agency by its publicly owned predecessors they calculate was achieved as a result of the flotation of QinetiQ.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.9.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_spnew7">
	<p pid="c.9.6/1">Prior to the IPO, the only previous market valuation of the MoD's investment in QinetiQ was through the public-private partnership in February 2003. That process valued the MoD's majority equity stake at &pound;78 million. Since then, the Government have received &pound;82 million from the repayment of preference shares, and &pound;347 million of net proceeds from the initial public offering. The MoD continues to own a 19 per cent stake in QinetiQ, which was worth &pound;250 million at the IPO issue price. Overall, this provides an annualised rate of return of 119.7 per cent.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.9.7" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn8">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.9.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="9"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn8">
	<p pid="c.9.8/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.9.8/2" qnum="HL3967">What representations Ministers have made to Sir John Chisholm with respect to his occupying simultaneously the posts of chairman and chief executive of QinetiQ.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.10.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_spnew8">
	<p pid="c.10.0/1">Sir John Chisholm has never occupied simultaneously the posts of chairman and chief executive of QinetiQ.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.10.1" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn9">
	Defence Research: QinetiQ
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.10.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100236" speakername="Lord Gilbert" colon="" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn9">
	<p pid="c.10.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.10.2/2" qnum="HL4044">How much (a) Sir John Chisholm, and (b) Mr Graham Love might expect to be able to draw in pension as a result of working for the Defence Evaluation and Research Agency.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.10.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_spnew9">
	<p pid="c.10.3/1">The accrued pension benefits as a result of working for DERA of Sir John Chisholm will be in line with those of all other participants in the Principal Civil Service Pension Scheme and the Civil Service Supplementary Earnings Pension Scheme, and those of Graham Love will be in line with those of all other participants in the Principal Civil Service Pension Scheme. Under the principal scheme, members are, broadly speaking, entitled to a pension of 1/80th of their pay in their last year of service, for each year of service, plus a tax-free lump sum of three times the annual pension. The Supplementary Earnings Scheme allows extra pension provision for certain senior appointees.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.10.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn10">
	Department of Trade and Industry: BAA
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.10.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100271" speakername="Lord Hanningfield" colon="" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn10">
	<p pid="c.10.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.10.5/2" qnum="HL4065">Whether Ministers or officials from the Department of Trade and Industry have had contact with representatives of BAA regarding a possible takeover of the company; and, if so, (a) on what dates the contact occurred; (b) what was the nature of the communication; (c) which Ministers or officials were involved; and (d) which representatives from BAA were involved.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.10.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.10.6/1">There has been no contact with Ministers or officials from the DTI with BAA regarding the possible takeover of the company.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.10.7" nospeaker="true" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn11">
	Disability: Safeguarding Children
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.10.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100685" speakername="Baroness Wilkins" colon="" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_wqn11">
	<p pid="c.10.8/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.10.8/2" qnum="HL3881">When they will publish and distribute the work on safeguarding disabled children, commissioned from the Council for Disabled Children.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.10.9" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100839" speakername="Lord Adonis" colon=":" colnum="10"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w03.htm#60227w03_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.10.9/1"><i>Safeguarding Disabled Children: the Resource for Local Safeguarding Children Boards</i>, commissioned by the Government from the Council for Disabled Children, will be published on the Every Child Matters website by the end of February 2006.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.11.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="11"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_wqn0">
	Energy: Renewable
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.11.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100427" speakername="Baroness Miller of Chilthorne Domer" colon="" colnum="11"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.11.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.11.1/2" qnum="HL4123">What is their assessment of the equivalent annual cost figures for tidal lagoons given in the report by the Office of Gas and Electricity Markets (Ofgem) <i>Assessment of the benefits from large scale deployment of certain renewable technologies</i>.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.11.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="11"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.11.2/1">The DTI has previously commissioned an independent assessment of a proposed tidal lagoon scheme in Swansea Bay. That assessment shows the unit cost of power to be around &pound;160/MWh using an 8 per cent discount rate.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.11.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="11"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_wqn1">
	Energy: Renewable
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.11.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100427" speakername="Baroness Miller of Chilthorne Domer" colon="" colnum="11"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.11.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.11.4/2" qnum="HL4124">Further to the answer by the Lord Sainsbury of Turville on 8 February (col. 656) that &quot;Photovoltaics is still by a long way the most expensive kind of energy, so to put that into building regulations would build a huge cost into our energy bills&quot;, whether this statement represents government policy.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.11.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="11"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.11.5/1">The use of solar photovoltaics is one of the more expensive means of generating electricity. The Energy Saving Trust report on microgeneration states that a typical domestic installation costs around &pound;12,500.</p>
	<p pid="c.11.5/2">However, the Government recognise that there are circumstances where photovoltaics could become more economic; for example, where the cost of connecting to the grid is particularly high, or where they are being used instead of a premium building cladding. There are also a range of non-cost values and attributes that make photovoltaics an attractive option, which is why the number of installations has grown substantially in recent years (from 589kWp in 1997 to around 8,164kWp in 2004).</p>
	<p pid="c.11.5/3">Part L of the Building Regulations sets levels for energy performance in ways that offer designers the flexibility to choose solutions that best meet their needs, are cost-effective and practical, and enable innovation. Without prescribing solutions this enables builders to take up the benefits of renewable and other &quot;low and zero-carbon&quot; technologies.</p>
	<p pid="c.11.5/4">In September 2005, the Office of the Deputy Prime Minister announced further improvements to these energy efficiency requirements that will come into effect in April 2006 that will encourage greater take-up of renewable and other low-carbon systems. The overall package of proposed changes, including the further encouragement of low and zero-carbon systems will save around 0.9 million tonnes of carbon per year by 2010 and help to combat climate change.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.12.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="12"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_wqn2">
	Energy: Wind Turbines
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.12.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100541" speakername="Lord Roberts of Conwy" colon="" colnum="12"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.12.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.12.1/2" qnum="HL4199">How many applications for wind turbine installations have been made for Liverpool Bay; and</p>
	<p pid="c.12.1/3" qnum="HL4200">How many applications for wind turbine installations (a) have been granted; and (b) are under consideration for Liverpool Bay; and</p>
	<p pid="c.12.1/4" qnum="HL4201">What is the size and extent of (a) granted applications, and (b) applications under consideration for wind turbine installations in Liverpool Bay.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.12.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="12"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.12.2/1">The following table gives details of applications under Section 36 of the Electricity Act 1989 for the development of wind farms in the Liverpool Bay area (ie from the north Wales coast to a line of latitude of 53&deg; 40' N).</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="c.12.2/4"> <td>    <br/>    Wind farm<br/>    site</td> <td>    <br/>    Number of<br/>    turbines</td> <td>Generating<br/>    capacity (as<br/>    applied for or<br/>    consented)</td> <td>    <br/>    <br/>    Area</td> <td>    <br/>    <br/>    Status</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.12.2/5"> <td>North Hoyle</td> <td>30</td> <td>90MW</td> <td>10 sq kms</td> <td>Consented. Wind farm operational</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.12.2/6"> <td>Rhyl Flats</td> <td>30</td> <td>150MW</td> <td>10 sq kms</td> <td>Consented</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.12.2/7"> <td>Burbo Bank</td> <td>30</td> <td>90MW</td> <td>10 sq kms</td> <td>Consented</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.12.2/8"> <td>Gwynt y Mor</td> <td>Up to 250</td> <td>750MW</td> <td>124 sq kms</td> <td>Under consideration</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.12.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="12"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_wqn3">
	EU: Anti-Fraud Office
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.12.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100616" speakername="Lord Stoddart of Swindon" colon="" colnum="12"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.12.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.12.4/2" qnum="HL4164">In the light of the recommendations from the European Parliament's Budgetary Control Committee that Franz-Hermann Br&uuml;ner should not be reappointed as director general of the European Anti-Fraud Office, what representations they have made to the relevant European Union authorities.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.12.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="12"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_spmin2">
	<p pid="c.12.5/1">The director of the European Union Anti-Fraud Office is appointed by the Commission, taking account of the opinions of the Council and the European Parliament, following an open competition. The Council and the Parliament recommended various candidates and the Commission chose to appoint Mr Br&uuml;ner, who was one of the candidates common to both the Council and the Parliament's recommendations.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.13.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="13"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_wqn4">
	EU: Constitution
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.13.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100345" speakername="Lord Kilclooney" colon="" colnum="13"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.13.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.13.1/2" qnum="HL3960">Whether the Governments of France and the Netherlands have confirmed to the Government their support for the programmes of the Austrian presidency of the European Union to re-launch the treaty for a constitution for the European Union.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.13.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="13"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_spmin3">
	<p pid="c.13.2/1">All member states customarily welcome an incoming presidency's work programme in outline terms. The Government do not explore the detail of other member states' views on an incoming presidency's work programme. The issue of the treaty will be discussed in more detail during the rest of the Austrian presidency, notably in the run-up to the June European Council's discussion on the period of reflection agreed last year.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.13.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="13"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_wqn5">
	EU: Constitution
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.13.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100656" speakername="Lord Vinson" colon="" colnum="13"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_wqn5">
	<p pid="c.13.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.13.4/2" qnum="HL4030">Further to the Written Statement by the Lord Triesman on 6 February (<i>WS 31&ndash;34</i>) on the European Union General Affairs and External Relations Council, why the constitutional treaty is the first priority area under the work programme for 2006; what such work involves; and what input the Government will make to it.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.13.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="13"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_spnew1">
	<p pid="c.13.5/1">In June 2005, the European Council agreed on the need for a period of reflection as the right response to the No votes on the treaty in France and the Netherlands and to come back to the matter in the first half of 2006. It is therefore natural that the Council cites the treaty as one of its priorities in its annual operational programme for 2006. We will participate constructively in these discussions.</p>
	<p pid="c.13.5/2">This June, the Council will make an overall assessment of the national debates in member states, which formed part of the period of reflection, and agree on how to proceed. The Government are committed to engaging and informing the UK public on the future of Europe and, since the June 2005 Council declaration on the treaty, have undertaken a range of activities to generate debate about the future direction of the EU.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.13.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="13"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_wqn6">
	EU: UK Membership
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.13.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100491" speakername="Lord Pearson of Rannoch" colon="" colnum="13"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_wqn6">
	<p pid="c.13.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.13.7/2" qnum="HL4033">Further to the Answer by the Lord Triesman on 25 January (<i>Official Report</i>, col. 1181), what, in their view, are realistic and credible economic extrapolations which are appropriate in conducting analyses of the costs and benefits to the United Kingdom of European Union membership.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.13.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="13"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_spmin4">
	<p pid="c.13.8/1">A credible analysis of the costs and benefits of EU membership must take account of all dimensions of that relationship. Membership of the European Union has brought significant benefits to the United Kingdom, in terms of wealth, jobs, peace and security. Some benefits, such as the 3 million British jobs linked to exports to the EU, can be quantified; others, such as the UK's strengthened ability to deal with global issues, such as the environment and to tackle problems such as crime, illegal immigration and terrorism, are harder to measure.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.14.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_wqn7">
	Extradition: Mr Manzarpour
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.14.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100028" speakername="Earl Attlee" colon="" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_wqn7">
	<p pid="c.14.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.14.1/2" qnum="HL3979">What are the current circumstances of Mr Manzarpour, a British citizen, in connection with his extradition to the United States.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.14.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w04.htm#60227w04_spmin5">
	<p pid="c.14.2/1">Mr Ali Manzarpour, a British/Iranian dual national, remains in prison in Poland awaiting the outcome of legal proceedings concerning his extradition to the US. Following a number of hearings, the Polish court decided on <phrase class="date" code="2007-02-02">2 February</phrase> that it was legal to extradite Mr Manzarpour to the US. The verdict is subject to appeal. The final decision on extradition rests with the Polish Minister of Justice.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.14.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn0">
	Extradition: Mr Manzarpour
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.14.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100246" speakername="Lord Goodhart" colon="" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.14.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.14.4/2" qnum="HL4031">Whether they will take steps to secure the release of Mr Ali Manzarpour, a British citizen, following the decision of a Polish court to extradite him to the United States.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.14.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.14.5/1">Mr Ali Manzarpour, a British/Iranian dual national, remains in detention in Poland awaiting the outcome of legal proceedings concerning a US extradition request. Following a number of hearings, the court decided on <phrase class="date" code="2007-02-02">2 February</phrase> that it is legal to extradite Mr Manzarpour to the US. The verdict is subject to appeal. The final decision on extradition rests with the Polish Minister of Justice.</p>
	<p pid="c.14.5/2">We have been monitoring Mr Mazarpour's case closely. Our embassy in Warsaw has previously registered our interest in the case with the Ministry of Justice. A senior official called on the ministry again on <phrase class="date" code="2007-02-14">14 February</phrase> to highlight our continuing interest. Consular staff have visited Mr Manzarpour five times in prison since he was arrested in February 2005&mdash;most recently in December. Staff in Warsaw and London remain in regular contact with Mr Manzarpour's lawyer and his family and friends.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.14.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn1">
	Foot and Mouth Disease
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.14.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100414" speakername="The Countess of Mar" colon="" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.14.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.14.7/2" qnum="HL4087">How many human poisoning incidents were recorded by the Health and Safety Executive during the 2001 foot and mouth disease epidemic due to exposure to FAM30 disinfectant.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.14.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.14.8/1">The Health and Safety Executive recorded one complaint of possible poisoning linked to exposure of FAM30 disinfectant during the 2001 foot and mouth disease epidemic.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.15.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn2">
	Government Computer Systems: Department for Constitutional Affairs
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.15.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100275" speakername="Lord Harris of Haringey" colon="" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.15.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.15.1/2" qnum="HL3936">On how many occasions in each of the past two years malicious programs have compromised computer systems in the Department for Constitutional Affairs; and for each such occasion (a) how many machines were affected; (b) how long it took to remove the programs from the system; and (c) what the impact was on the activities of the department.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.15.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100024" speakername="Baroness Ashton of Upholland" colon=":" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.15.2/1">In the past two years, computer equipment at the Department for Constitutional Affairs has been compromised by malicious programs (such as worms, viruses, Trojans) on 216 separate occasions. In 2004, there were 135 attacks, affecting 184 machines. In 2005, there were 81 attacks, affecting 87 machines. This is out of a total number of approximately 26,000 machines in the department. The malicious programs were removed as soon as practicable, and had minimal impact on the day-to-day running of the department's operations. None of the department's key operational computer systems was compromised by these incidents.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.15.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn3">
	Government Computer Systems: Department for Education and Skills
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.15.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100275" speakername="Lord Harris of Haringey" colon="" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.15.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.15.4/2" qnum="HL3938">On how many occasions in each of the past two years malicious programs have compromised computer systems in the Department for Education and Skills; and for each such occasion (a) how many machines were affected; (b) how long it took to remove the programs from the system; and (c) what the impact was on the activities of the department.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.15.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100839" speakername="Lord Adonis" colon=":" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_spmin2">
	<p pid="c.15.5/1">In the past two years, no computer systems at the Department for Education and Skills have been compromised by malicious programs.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.15.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn4">
	Government Computer Systems: Department for Work and Pensions
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.15.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100275" speakername="Lord Harris of Haringey" colon="" colnum="15"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.15.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.15.7/2" qnum="HL3973">On how many occasions in each of the past two years malicious programs have compromised computer systems in the Department for Work and Pensions; and for each such occasion (a) how many machines were affected; (b) how long it took to remove the programs from the system; and (c) what the impact was on the activities of the department.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.16.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_spmin3">
	<p pid="c.16.0/1">In the past two years, the computer systems at Department for Work and Pensions (DWP) have been compromised by malicious programs (such as worms, viruses, etc) on 22 separate occasions.</p>
	<p pid="c.16.0/2">On four occasions, networked machines were affected. On the first occasion 75,000 machines were affected; on the second 200 machines were affected; on the third 20 machines were affected; on the fourth 25 machines were affected. On the remaining 18 occasions only a single machine was affected in each case.</p>
	<p pid="c.16.0/3">The malicious programs were removed as soon as practicable, and did not have a significant impact on the day-to-day running of DWP operations.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.16.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn5">
	Government Computer Systems: Department of Trade and Industry
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.16.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100275" speakername="Lord Harris of Haringey" colon="" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn5">
	<p pid="c.16.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.16.2/2" qnum="HL3975">On how many occasions in each of the past two years malicious programs have compromised computer systems in the Department for Trade and Industry; and for each such occasion (a) how many machines were affected; (b) how long it took to remove the programs from the system; and (c) what the impact was on the activities of the department.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.16.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_spmin4">
	<p pid="c.16.3/1">In the past two years: one Internet facing server has been compromised by malicious software; the server was rebuilt by the company providing that service to DTI. Total loss of service from that server was four days, and the impact on the department's activities was negligible.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.16.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn6">
	Government Computer Systems: Foreign and Commonwealth Office
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.16.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100275" speakername="Lord Harris of Haringey" colon="" colnum="16"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn6">
	<p pid="c.16.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.16.5/2" qnum="HL3976">On how many occasions in each of the past two years malicious programs have compromised computer systems in the Foreign and Commonwealth Office; and for each such occasion (a) how many machines were affected; (b) how long it took to remove the programs from the system; and (c) what the impact was on the activities of the department.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.17.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_spmin5">
	<p pid="c.17.0/1">On average 6.4 per cent. of e-mails received in the Foreign and Commonwealth Office (FCO) contain a virus. In the past two years there is no evidence that the FCO's strategic system has been compromised. In September 2005, however, an attack was so severe that the system was taken down for 10 hours so that the malicious software could be contained and eradicated. During that period some 14,000 users had restricted availability of applications.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.17.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn7">
	Government Computer Systems: Ministry of Defence
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.17.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100275" speakername="Lord Harris of Haringey" colon="" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn7">
	<p pid="c.17.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.17.2/2" qnum="HL4022">On how many occasions in each of the past two years malicious programs have compromised computer systems in the Ministry of Defence; and for each such occasion (a) how many machines were affected; (b) how long it took to remove the programs from the system; and (c) what the impact was on the activities of the department.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.17.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_spmin6">
	<p pid="c.17.3/1">During 2004 and 2005, Ministry of Defence computers are known or suspected to have been infected by malicious software on 47 and 57 occasions respectively. The number of computers infected on each occasion was typically only one but ranged up to a maximum of 40 during one event. A total of 225 machines were infected over the two-year period. On each occasion the malicious software was removed as soon as practicable. The time taken to restore affected systems to normal operations ranged from a few minutes to two to three days. There was no identified degradation of UK military readiness as a result of the infections. The MoD system and network infrastructure is continuously monitored, with defence in depth at key points to prevent cross-infection.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.17.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn8">
	Guantanamo Bay
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.17.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100804" speakername="Lord Dykes" colon="" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_wqn8">
	<p pid="c.17.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.17.5/2" qnum="HL4167">What representations they will make to the United States military authorities about closing the Guantanamo Bay detention facility in the light of the recent United Nations Commission on Human Rights report.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.17.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w05.htm#60227w05_spmin7">
	<p pid="c.17.6/1">We have made clear publicly and privately that we regard the circumstances under which detainees continue to be held at Guantanamo Bay as unacceptable, and that the current use of the Guantanamo Bay detention facility is an anomaly that should be brought to an end. We will continue to do so.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.18.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_wqn0">
	House of Lords: Smoking
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.18.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100481" speakername="Lord Palmer" colon="" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.18.1/1">asked the Chairman of Committees:</p>
	<p pid="c.18.1/2" qnum="HL4154">Whether the Refreshment Committee had the power to prohibit smoking in the banqueting facilities of the House of Lords without referring the matter for decision on the Floor of the House.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.18.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100067" speakername="Lord Brabazon of Tara" colon=":" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.18.2/1">Yes. It is normal for domestic committees to refer to the House major strategic changes affecting Members, but they retain the discretion to make changes within their terms of reference.</p>
	<p pid="c.18.2/2">On <phrase class="date" code="2004-12-21">21 December 2004</phrase>, the House agreed the First Report from the Administration and Works Committee on Smoking (HL Paper 209, Session 2004&ndash;05). That report contained two statements of principle, that: staff should be entitled to work in a smoke-free environment; and it is extremely desirable that smoking should not be permitted where food is being served.</p>
	<p pid="c.18.2/3">Given that these decisions of principle had already been agreed by the House, the Refreshment Committee was acting within its powers in agreeing to make this change.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.18.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_wqn1">
	Housing
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.18.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.18.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.18.4/2" qnum="HL3941">What measures they have taken in the past two years, or will shortly take, to increase the supply of affordable housing for people on average or below average earnings in (a) urban; and (b) rural areas.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.18.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.18.5/1">The Government are investing around &pound;3 billion through the Housing Corporation for the provision of affordable housing for those on average or below average earnings in urban and rural areas in 2004&ndash;06. This level of investment is set to increase to &pound;3.9 billion in 2006&ndash;08 including key worker living. Priorities for this funding have been drawn from the regional housing strategies produced by regional housing boards.</p>
	<p pid="c.18.5/2">In 2004&ndash;05 through the Housing Corporation's approved development programme 16,000 homes for social rent have been delivered. Of these around 1,180 were in small rural settlements of fewer than 3,000 homes. More than 11,900 were provided through low-cost home ownership schemes, including 4,800 for key workers, and 460 in small rural settlements.</p>
	<p pid="c.18.5/3">The Government set a target of providing 75,000 social rented homes from 2005&ndash;06 to 2007&ndash;08. That is an additional 10,000 homes, a 50 per cent. increase on 2004&ndash;05. In addition, the Government aim to help around 100,000 households into home ownership between 2005&ndash;06 and 2009&ndash;10.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.19.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_wqn2">
	Immigration: EU Expansion
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.19.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100804" speakername="Lord Dykes" colon="" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.19.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.19.1/2" qnum="HL4061">What conclusions have been reached on future policy on immigration from the European Union's 10 new member states and Romania and Bulgaria, in respect of admissions over the transitional period, following the conclusions of the report from Commissioner Vladimir Spidla on the numbers of new entrants so far recorded.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.19.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_spmin2">
	<p pid="c.19.2/1">On <phrase class="date" code="2007-02-08">8 February</phrase>, the European Commission adopted Vladimir Spidla's report on the effect of member states' use, since May 2004, of transitional arrangements for the free movement of workers from central and eastern Europe. The report supports the decision of the UK to open its labour markets and the Government welcome this endorsement of their decision. Nationals from the new member states are making a welcome contribution to our economy and society. They are taking employment in sectors where hard-to-fill vacancies exist and in many cases are supporting the provision of public services in communities across the UK. The evidence does not suggest that there has been an adverse impact on the labour market. Given the success of this decision, there are currently no plans to reverse it. The UK is required to inform the Commission by the end of April 2006 whether we intend to maintain transitional measures.</p>
	<p pid="c.19.2/2">As I set out during the EU (Accessions) Bill's passage through Parliament, no decision has been taken yet on what level of access to grant Bulgarian and Romanian workers following accession. That decision will be made closer to the date of accession, after full consideration of the state of the domestic labour market, other member states' decisions, and further analysis of our own experience with the previous enlargement.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.19.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_wqn3">
	India: Religious Discrimination
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.19.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100489" speakername="Lord Patten" colon="" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.19.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.19.4/2" qnum="HL3928">Whether they will make representations to the Government of India regarding the extension to Dalit Christians of protection against discrimination already afforded to Dalits of Buddhist, Hindu and Sikh background.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.19.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_spmin3">
	<p pid="c.19.5/1">Our High Commission in New Delhi has indeed raised this with the Indian Minorities Commission, drawing its attention to British parliamentary and public concern. The UK, as presidency of the European Union, also raised this issue during a human rights dialogue with Indian government officials in Delhi on <phrase class="date" code="2005-12-01">1 December 2005</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="c.19.5/2">We remain concerned by reports of discrimination towards the Dalit Christian and Muslim communities in India. It is worrying that both these communities are still excluded from the quota system of jobs that have been set aside for Dalit and other tribal groups to bring them into the political and social mainstream.</p>
	<p pid="c.19.5/3">Our High Commission in Delhi has reported that a petition was filed by the Centre for Public Interest with the Indian Supreme Court to argue that excluding Christians from quotas is unconstitutional. This case is now due to be heard at the end of February. We are awaiting the court's decision before deciding the nature of any further representations. Our High Commission in New Delhi is continuing to monitor the situation closely.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.20.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_wqn4">
	Influenza Pandemic
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.20.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100334" speakername="Lord Jenkin of Roding" colon="" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.20.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.20.1/2" qnum="HL3708">Who is responsible in Government for encouraging and advising the business community to plan for the possible eventuality of an influenza pandemic; and what information is available to advise the business community on this matter.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.20.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100670" speakername="Lord Warner" colon=":" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_spmin4">
	<p pid="c.20.2/1">As the lead department on pandemic influenza planning, the Department of Health has published all information relating to pandemic influenza on its website, <a href="http://www.dh.gov.uk/pandemicflu">www.dh.gov.uk/pandemicflu</a>. Our <i>UK Influenza Pandemic Contingency Plan</i>, available in the Library, sets out the importance of maintaining business continuity as far as is possible and reducing the general disruption to society that a pandemic is likely to cause.</p>
	<p pid="c.20.2/2">We are working, with the support of the Civil Contingencies Secretariat in the Cabinet Office, to engage a wide range of stakeholders in the critical national infrastructure and more widely, to encourage them to develop robust business continuity plans appropriate for a flu pandemic. In doing so, we are drawing on a wide range of guidance, including the UK influenza plan, other material published on the Department of Health and UK Resilience websites, Health and Safety Executive's guidance to employers (on the HSE website), and material provided through a range of non-governmental channels. Working with other departments, we will continue to keep that material up-to-date as planning progresses.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.20.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_wqn5">
	Influenza Pandemic
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.20.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100807" speakername="Lord Broers" colon="" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_wqn5">
	<p pid="c.20.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.20.4/2" qnum="HL3715">Whether officials from the Department of Health held meetings in 2005 with the British Retail Consortium or the major food retailers regarding preparations for a possible influenza pandemic; if so, on what dates these meetings were held; and who attended; and</p>
	<p pid="c.20.4/3" qnum="HL3716">Whether the Department of Health or the Health Protection Agency have issued advice to either the British Retail Consortium or the major food retailers regarding preparations for a possible influenza pandemic; and</p>
	<p pid="c.20.4/4" qnum="HL3717">How many meetings were held in 2005 between officials and the British Retail Consortium or the major food retailers to discuss preparations for a possible influenza pandemic; when the first such meeting was held; who initiated this meeting; and who attended.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.21.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100670" speakername="Lord Warner" colon=":" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w06.htm#60227w06_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.21.0/1">Pandemic influenza was discussed at meetings of the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Defra) food chain emergency liaison group on <phrase class="date" code="">21 October</phrase> and <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-28">28 November 2005</phrase>, at which officials from the Department of Health were present.</p>
	<p pid="c.21.0/2">Defra's food chain emergency liaison group meets regularly to discuss emergency planning for dealing with disruptions to food supplies as well as food chain resilience issues. The group comprises representatives from all key sectors in the food chain, including the British Retail Consortium, which represents food retailers. A review of food chain resilience was initiated with food retailers and other stakeholders back in June 2005.</p>
	<p pid="c.21.0/3">The Government have not produced specific guidance to the British Retail Consortium. However, generic advice regarding business continuity has been published as Annexe J of the <i>UK Influenza Pandemic Contingency Plan </i>(available in the Library and on the Department of Health website at <a href="http://www.dh.gov.uk/pandemicflu">www.dh.gov.uk/pandemicflu</a>). The Civil Contingencies Secretariat has also produced information for organisations and businesses available on its website at <a href="http://www.ukresilience.info">www.ukresilience.info</a>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.21.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_wqn0">
	International Stability: Strategy Unit Report
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.21.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100680" speakername="Baroness Whitaker" colon="" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.21.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.21.2/2" qnum="HL3962">What is the outcome of their consideration of the report by the Prime Minister's Strategy Unit <i>Investing in Prevention</i>, published in February 2005.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.21.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.21.3/1">Preventing conflict and building stability are fundamental to the Government's foreign policy. The Prime Minister's Strategy Unit (PMSU) report <i>Investing in Prevention</i> underlines the importance of continued government effort to make the international response to instability and conflict more effective. The report's recommendations are broadly consistent with government policy. The role played by the UK's EU and G8 presidencies in building international commitment to tackle instability and improve crisis response, particularly in Africa, is one example; UK efforts in support of the successful establishment of the UN Peacebuilding Commission, alongside our contribution in helping to build UN and regional organisations' peacekeeping capacity, is another.</p>
	<p pid="c.21.3/2">The Government will continue to work on a broad front to strengthen international capacity to prevent conflict.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.22.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_wqn1">
	Iran: Nuclear Programme
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.22.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100804" speakername="Lord Dykes" colon="" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.22.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.22.1/2" qnum="HL4029">Whether they will make a renewed approach linking the European Union Group of the United Kingdom, France and Germany with the current Austrian European Union presidency to pursue a co-ordinated approach in the United Nations Security Council on moves seeking Iran's adherence to its non-proliferation treaty obligations.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.22.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.22.2/1">The UK, France and Germany have been, and will continue to be, in constant and close contact with the Austrian presidency and other European Union partners over Iran's nuclear programme and the European Union's approach towards it.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.22.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_wqn2">
	Iran: Nuclear Programme
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.22.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100804" speakername="Lord Dykes" colon="" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.22.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.22.4/2" qnum="HL4059">Whether they will use the EU3 mechanism to examine ways in which the terms of the Paris agreement of 15 November 2004 with Iran, on the suspension of enrichment and reprocessing activity, can be revived in advance of the United Nations Security Council's deliberations in March 2006.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.22.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.22.5/1">We have urged Iran on many occasions to reinstate and maintain a full suspension of all enrichment-related and reprocessing activities, which they agreed to in the Paris agreement, and which has been requested many times by the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) board of governors as an essential confidence-building measure.</p>
	<p pid="c.22.5/2">Iran's resumption of uranium conversion last August violated its commitments in the Paris agreement and was a rejection of the process of negotiations under that agreement. Despite this, the E3/EU held exploratory discussions with Iran on <phrase class="date" code="2005-12-21">21 December 2005</phrase> to see whether it was possible to agree a basis for resuming negotiations. The E3/EU made clear that for any resumption of negotiations to be possible it would be essential for Iran to refrain from any further erosion of the suspension. In full knowledge of this, Iran resumed enrichment-related activity on <phrase class="date" code="2006-01-10">10 January 2006</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="c.22.5/3">The E3/EU have been flexible, twice last autumn delaying involving the Security Council to leave more time for diplomacy and for Iran to address international concerns. Iran has responded by hardening its position and further disregarding IAEA board resolutions. On <phrase class="date" code="2007-02-04">4 February</phrase>, the IAEA board decided with an overwhelming majority to ask the IAEA director-general to report to the Security Council the steps required of Iran by the board. The onus is now on Iran to reinstate a full suspension without delay.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.23.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_wqn3">
	Israel and Palestine: Military Actions
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.23.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100804" speakername="Lord Dykes" colon="" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.23.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.23.1/2" qnum="HL4028">Whether they will make representations to the Government of Israel following the deaths of Palestinian individuals caused by the Israel defence forces' military actions in Gaza and the West Bank since the Palestinian elections.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.23.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_spmin2">
	<p pid="c.23.2/1">We remain concerned by the Israel defence forces' action in Gaza and the West Bank and call upon Israel to act with restraint. Our ambassador in Tel Aviv last raised the deaths of Palestinian individuals as a result of Israel defence force activities in the Occupied Territories with Israeli Foreign Minister Tzipi Livni on <phrase class="date" code="2007-01-30">30 January</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.23.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_wqn4">
	Israel and Palestine: Road Map
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.23.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100804" speakername="Lord Dykes" colon="" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.23.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.23.4/2" qnum="HL4027">Whether they will make representations to the Government of the United States on the agreement at Sharm-el-Sheikh which indicated that quartet countries, including the United States, need to maintain neutrality between Israel and the Palestinian Authority in the road map procedures.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.23.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_spmin3">
	<p pid="c.23.5/1">All quartet members seek to act as dependable intermediaries in the peace process, encouraging both parties to implement previous agreements towards a lasting two-state solution. We work closely with all the quartet members and consult regularly on matters relating to the Middle East peace process.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.23.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_wqn5">
	Land Army
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.23.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100420" speakername="Lord Mason of Barnsley" colon="" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_wqn5">
	<p pid="c.23.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.23.7/2" qnum="HL3763">What recognition they will afford to members of the Land Army and the conscripted Bevin Boys for their services during the years of 1943 to 1948.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.23.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_spmin4">
	<p pid="c.23.8/1">The work of the Bevin Boys, the Land Army, air raid wardens, munitions workers and so many others was vital to Britain's survival during World War Two and it is therefore entirely appropriate that such groups have been, and will continue to be, included in commemorative events. I also welcome the representation of groups who played a key role in the war effort at the Cenotaph on Remembrance Day.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.24.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_wqn6">
	Maldives: Human Rights
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.24.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100026" speakername="Lord Astor of Hever" colon="" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_wqn6">
	<p pid="c.24.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.24.1/2" qnum="HL3995">What representations they are making to the Government of the Republic of Maldives concerning alleged human rights abuses in that country in the light of the September 2005 report of the United Kingdom lawyers' delegation to the republic on the prospects of fair trial for persons facing prosecution for terrorism and crimes against the state.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.24.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_spmin5">
	<p pid="c.24.2/1">We are concerned about the human rights situation in the Maldives, including freedom of expression and association and the right to fair trials conducted with due legal process. We share the view that some recent trials of political activists appear to have political motivations. We noted the contents and recommendations of the UK lawyers' report and those of the Attorney-General of the Maldives in his open letter in response, which acknowledged that a number of fundamental reforms to the Maldivian justice system were necessary.</p>
	<p pid="c.24.2/2">We monitor developments in the Maldives closely, regularly making clear, both bilaterally and with EU partners, to the Government of the Maldives our concerns about the need for democratic reform and improved human rights. An EU statement in September 2005 raised concerns about the arrests, trials, and the need for democratic reform. The full text of the statement can be found at: <a href="http://ue.eu.int/ueDocs/cms-Data/docs/pressData/en/cfsp/86111.pdf">http://ue.eu.int/ueDocs/cms&ndash;Data/docs/pressData/en/cfsp/86111.pdf</a>.</p>
	<p pid="c.24.2/3">Most recently in December 2005, the British High Commissioner led a delegation of European Union Heads of Mission from Colombo (accredited to the Maldives) which underlined our concerns to President Gayoom and to Maldivian Government Ministers. The High Commissioner also visited the Maldives in late January, when he had discussions with representatives of the Government and the Maldivian Democratic Party.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.24.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_wqn7">
	Medical Practitioners: Regulation
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.24.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100305" speakername="Earl Howe" colon="" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_wqn7">
	<p pid="c.24.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.24.4/2" qnum="HL4011">What are their plans for the future regulation of (a) herbalists; (b) acupuncturists; and (c) osteopaths; whether those plans will require legislation; and within what timescale they anticipate that progress being made.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.24.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100670" speakername="Lord Warner" colon=":" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w07.htm#60227w07_spmin6">
	<p pid="c.24.5/1">Osteopaths are already subject to statutory regulation and must register with the General Osteopathic Council.</p>
	<p pid="c.24.5/2">The Government are committed to legislate for statutory regulation of acupuncture and herbal medicine. We are in the process of setting up a stakeholder working group to take forward preparations for regulation.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.25.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w08.htm#60227w08_wqn0">
	Mental Health: Bournewood Judgment
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.25.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100791" speakername="Baroness Murphy" colon="" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w08.htm#60227w08_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.25.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.25.1/2" qnum="HL4071">When they intend to publish the results of their consultations on the approach to be taken in response to the judgment of the European Court of Human Rights in the Bournewood case.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.25.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100670" speakername="Lord Warner" colon=":" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w08.htm#60227w08_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.25.2/1">We are finalising the details of our response to the judgment of the European Court of Human Rights in the case of <i>HL </i>v <i>UK</i> (the Bournewood case). We are grateful to the many individuals and organisations who commented on the consultation document published last year. We plan to publish our formal response to that consultation in the near future.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.25.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w08.htm#60227w08_wqn1">
	Mental Health: Residential Services
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.25.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w08.htm#60227w08_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.25.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.25.4/2" qnum="HL3596">What steps they are taking to ensure that secure residential services for persons with serious mental health or substance misuse problems are properly resourced; and whether courts have the power to send offenders to institutions providing those services instead of sending them to prison.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.25.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w08.htm#60227w08_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.25.5/1">Responsibility for the funding of secure psychiatric services rests with primary care trusts, which are required to identify the needs of their population and develop integrated local secure services accordingly. There is, however, central oversight of the arrangements for the commissioning of high-security psychiatric services, and the funding for these services is effectively ring-fenced. The Government are undertaking a capacity review of high- and medium-security services with a view to ensuring that they are of a level and quality to meet current and future requirements, and that they sit within an integrated network of wider mental health services. Courts have the power to refer offenders to the Criminal Justice Liaison Scheme (CJLS)&mdash;sometimes referred to as the Court Diversion Scheme.</p>
	<p pid="c.25.5/2">There are currently 139 local schemes that allow mental health assessments of offenders to be undertaken in order to provide the court with information about the offender's mental condition and any treatment that may be appropriate. This enables the courts to refer offenders to mental health services, where their mental condition warrants this, rather than to proceed automatically with a prosecution. Where a prosecution is appropriate, courts have the power to order the admission of a convicted offender to hospital for treatment or to add a treatment requirement to a community order or suspended sentence order instead of passing a prison sentence.</p>
	<p pid="c.25.5/3">Residential rehabilitation services are provided by a range of providers from the statutory, voluntary and private sectors. Funding for residential drug treatment can come via local authority community care budgets and the pooled treatment budget. The pooled treatment budget has increased significantly from &pound;191 million in 2002&ndash;03 to &pound;299 million in 2005&ndash;06. Attendance at residential rehabilitation services is voluntary, with some clients consenting to attend as part of a community sentence through the provision of a drug treatment and testing order, or from April 2005, a drug rehabilitation requirement of the community order. Residential rehabilitation services are not provided within a secure environment.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.26.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w08.htm#60227w08_wqn2">
	NHS: Contaminated Blood Products
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.26.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100444" speakername="Lord Morris of Manchester" colon="" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w08.htm#60227w08_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.26.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.26.1/2" qnum="HL3732">Further to the answer by the Lord Warner on 12 January (<i>Official Report</i>, col. 300) about documents dealing with contaminated National Health Service blood products that were destroyed in error by the Department of Health in the early 1990s, on what date or dates they were destroyed; by whose decision they were destroyed; and whether it is only documents on these products that have been destroyed in error by the department.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.26.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100670" speakername="Lord Warner" colon=":" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w08.htm#60227w08_spmin2">
	<p pid="c.26.2/1">My noble friend is aware that during the HIV litigation many papers were recalled. We understand that papers were not adequately archived and were unfortunately destroyed in the early 1990s.</p>
	<p pid="c.26.2/2">My noble friend is also aware that further documents were destroyed in the 1990s. Officials at the Department of Health have established that these documents related to the minutes and papers of the Advisory Committee on the Virological Safety of Blood between 1989 and 1992. These papers were destroyed between July 1994 and March 1998. A decision, most probably made by an inexperienced member of staff, was responsible for the destruction of these files.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.26.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w08.htm#60227w08_wqn3">
	NHS: Dentistry
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.26.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100104" speakername="Lord Campbell-Savours" colon="" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w08.htm#60227w08_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.26.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.26.4/2" qnum="HL3868">What is their assessment of the reasons provided by National Health Service dentists for terminating their National Health Service contracts and entering private practice.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.26.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100670" speakername="Lord Warner" colon=":" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w08.htm#60227w08_spmin3">
	<p pid="c.26.5/1">Very few dentists provide exclusively private care and where dentists engage in private practice, they typically provide a mix of private and National Health Service services.</p>
	<p pid="c.26.5/2">The main reason cited by the British Dental Association (BDA) and individual dentists for increasing the proportion of work done privately has been concern that the current fee-per-item system of remuneration in the General Dental Services (GDS) creates a &quot;treadmill&quot; effect that leads to excessive workload and insufficient time for preventative care. The new GDS contracts, being implemented from April, abolish the fee-per-item system and provide for dentists to receive a fixed annual NHS income (which will typically give a net income of around &pound;80,000 on average) in return for providing an agreed level of courses of treatment. This is designed to address the long-standing concerns expressed by the BDA and the profession, as well as promoting a more preventive approach that will have benefits for patients.</p>
	<p pid="c.26.5/3">In addition, over the past 10 years there has also been a significant increase in demand for private cosmetic treatment, which is, quite rightly, outside the scope of the NHS. However, this has contributed to an increase in the range of private treatments offered by dentists.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.27.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="27"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w08.htm#60227w08_wqn4">
	NHS: Heart Disease
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.27.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100855" speakername="Lord Jones of Cheltenham" colon="" colnum="27"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w08.htm#60227w08_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.27.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.27.1/2" qnum="HL4179">(a) how many National Health Service patients have been treated with arterial stents in each year since 1997 for which figures are available; (b) how many of these patients are still alive; and (c) how many have required stent replacement due to stent failure.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.27.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100670" speakername="Lord Warner" colon=":" colnum="27"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w08.htm#60227w08_spmin4">
	<p pid="c.27.2/1">The number of National Health Service patients who have been treated with arterial stents in each year since 1997 for which figures are available is detailed as follows.</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/2">Data on how many of these patients are still alive and how many have required stent replacement due to stent failure are not collected centrally.</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/3">Count of finished consultant episodes and patients for selected procedures for arterial stents.</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/4">NHS patients treated in NHS Hospitals.</p>
	<table>
		<caption>NHS Hospitals, England 1997&ndash;98 to 2004&ndash;05</caption>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="c.27.2/8"> <td>Year</td> <td>Finished Consultant Episodes</td> <td>Patient Counts</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.27.2/9"> <td>1997-98</td> <td>5,234</td> <td>4,943</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.27.2/10"> <td>1998-99</td> <td>7,042</td> <td>6,689</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.27.2/11"> <td>1999-2000</td> <td>9,359</td> <td>8,945</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.27.2/12"> <td>2000-01</td> <td>12,983</td> <td>12,206</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.27.2/13"> <td>2001-02</td> <td>17,524</td> <td>16,702</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.27.2/14"> <td>2002-03</td> <td>22,881</td> <td>23,936</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.27.2/15"> <td>2003-04</td> <td>29,340</td> <td>28,285</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.27.2/16"> <td>2004-05</td> <td>36,086</td> <td>34,796</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="c.27.2/19" class="italic">Footnotes:</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/20">Finished consultant episode (FCE) and patient counts</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/21">Available data for NHS patients treated in NHS hospitals shows information for those treated with arterial stents since 1997 in two forms: finished consultant episodes and patient counts. Finished consultant episodes refer to a period of care under which a patient is admitted under one consultant and an arterial stent is used as the main form of treatment. Therefore a patient may have more than one FCE per year. Patient counts data refer to individual patients; however, there are validation and data completeness issues with this data.</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/22">These data includes stents used in arteries in the heart, neck, head, leg and kidney.</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/23" class="italic">Finished Consultant Episode (FCE)</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/24">An FCE is defined as a period of admitted patient care under one consultant within one healthcare provider.</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/25" class="italic">Patient counts</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/26">Patient counts are based on the unique patient identifier HESID. This identifier is based on patients' date of birth, postcode, sex, local patient identifier and NHS number, using an agreed algorithm. Where data are incomplete, HESID might erroneously link episodes or fail to recognise episodes for the same patient. Care is therefore needed, especially where duplicate records persist in the data. The patient count cannot be summed across a table where patients may have episodes in more than one cell.</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/27" class="italic">Definition of Arterial Stent Procedures:</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/28">Main Operation is one of the following codes:</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/29">K48 Other open operations on coronary artery</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/30">K49 Transluminal balloon angioplasty of coronary artery</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/31">K50 Other therapeutic transluminal operations on coronary artery</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/32">L13.8 Other specified transluminal operations on pulmonary artery</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/33">L26.1 Percutaneous transluminal balloon angioplasty of aorta</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/34">L26.2 Percutaneous transluminal angioplasty of aorta nec</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/35">L31.1 Percutaneous transluminal angioplasty of carotid artery</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/36">L35.8 Other specified transluminal operations on cerebral artery</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/37">L39.1 Percutaneous transluminal angioplasty of subclavian artery</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/38">L43.1 Percutaneous transluminal angioplasty of renal artery</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/39">L47.1 Percutaneous transluminal angioplasty of visceral branch of abdominal aorta nec</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/40">L54.1 Percutaneous transluminal angioplasty of iliac artery</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/41">L63.1 Percutaneous transluminal angioplasty of femoral artery</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/42">L71.1 Percutaneous transluminal angioplasty of artery nec</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/43" class="italic">Secondary Procedure.</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/44">All of the above must occur with a code of Y02.2 insertion of prosthesis into organ noc in any of the secondary positions.</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/45" class="italic">Main Operation</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/46">The main operation is the first recorded operation in the hospital episode statistics (HES) data set and is usually the most resource-intensive procedure performed during the episode. It is appropriate to use main operation when looking at admission details&mdash;for example, time waited&mdash;but the figures for &quot;all operations count of episodes&quot; give a more complete count of episodes with an operation.</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/47" class="italic">Secondary Procedure</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/48">As well as the main operative procedure, there are up to 11 (three prior to 2002&ndash;03) secondary operation fields in hospital episode statistics (HES) that show secondary or additional procedures performed on the patient during the episode of care.</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/49" class="italic">Grossing (Finished Consultant Episodes)</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/50">Figures are grossed for both coverage and missing/invalid clinical data, except for 2003&ndash;04 and 2004&ndash;05, which are not yet adjusted for shortfalls.</p>
	<p pid="c.27.2/51"><i>Source:</i> Hospital Episode Statistics, Health and Social Care Information Centre.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.29.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn0">
	NHS: Sex Discrimination
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.29.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100213" speakername="Baroness Finlay of Llandaff" colon="" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.29.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.29.1/2" qnum="HL3896">What action is being taken, in the light of recent research, to ensure that discrimination against female physicians in the promotion process to consultant grade is detected and addressed.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.29.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100670" speakername="Lord Warner" colon=":" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.29.2/1">In January 2005, the Department of Health published good practice guidance on the National Health Service (Appointment of Consultants) Regulations 1996 for use by NHS trusts, primary care trusts and strategic health authorities when making appointments to consultant posts. The guidance includes an annexe on equal opportunities issues. Copies are available in the Library.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.29.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn1">
	Planning
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.29.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon="" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.29.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.29.4/2" qnum="HL3425">In what circumstance planning procedures for district councils allow a planning decision to which objections have been received to be determined by reference to the ward councillor alone.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.29.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.29.5/1">It is for the local planning authority to decide whether a planning application is decided by the planning committee or delegated to officers and, where delegation operates, the level of member involvement. Unless debarred by having lobbied for or against the proposal (or for some other reason of propriety), any ward councillor could contribute opinion and local knowledge to the committee's deliberations.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.30.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn2">
	Planning: Public Inquiries
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.30.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100576" speakername="Baroness Scott of Needham Market" colon="" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.30.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.30.1/2" qnum="HL3709">What is the average length of time for a planning public inquiry, using 1997 as a baseline.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.30.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_spmin2">
	<p pid="c.30.2/1">Records do not go back as far as 1997. The earliest year available is 2001 when the average length of a planning inquiry was 2.16 days. In 2005 it was 2.35 days.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.30.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn3">
	Planning: Public Inquiries
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.30.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100576" speakername="Baroness Scott of Needham Market" colon="" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.30.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.30.4/2" qnum="HL3710">How many public inquiries for national scale projects since 1997 have taken longer than three months.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.30.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.30.5/1">Since November 2001 the Planning Inspectorate has held 14 inquiries on national scale projects which have lasted longer than three months. Information earlier than this is not held centrally.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.30.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn4">
	Planning: Public Inquiries
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.30.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100576" speakername="Baroness Scott of Needham Market" colon="" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.30.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.30.7/2" qnum="HL3711">What planning public inquiries have been held since 2000; and in each case what length of time elapsed between the opening of the inquiry and submission of the report.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.30.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_spnew1">
	<p pid="c.30.8/1">Since 2000 approximately 400 appeals were held by inquiry by the Planning Inspectorate and a report subsequently submitted to the First Secretary of State, my right honourable friend the Deputy Prime Minister. A list of these appeals to show the elapsed time between the opening of the inquiry and the submission of the report is currently being collated and a copy will be made available to the Library of the House.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.30.9" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn5">
	Planning: Public Inquiries
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.30.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100576" speakername="Baroness Scott of Needham Market" colon="" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn5">
	<p pid="c.30.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.30.10/2" qnum="HL3712">What were the last 10 applications for planning permission involving a public inquiry; and what was the length of time taken between receipt of the inspector's report and the ministerial announcement.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.30.11" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_spnew2">
	<p pid="c.30.11/1">The last 10 planning cases decided by the First Secretary of State, my right honourable friend the Deputy Prime Minister, after a public inquiry are tabled below. They include both called-in applications and recovered appeals.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="c.30.11/4"> <td>    <br/>    Case name</td> <td>    Number of decisions</td> <td>    Inquiry closing date</td> <td>    Date received by ODPM</td> <td>    Date of Secretary of State's decision</td> <td>Weeks &amp; days from receipt of report to decision</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.30.11/5"> <td>Bedfont Lakes Site, Bedfont Green Close, Feltham</td> <td>2</td> <td>06/10/05</td> <td>04/11/05</td> <td>29/12/05</td> <td>7 weeks, 6 days</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.30.11/6"> <td>Land at Green Lane and Church Road, Christchurch,    Cambridgeshire</td> <td>1</td> <td>21/09/05</td> <td>14/10/05</td> <td>29/12/05</td> <td>10 weeks, 6 days</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.30.11/7"> <td>Hop Farm Country Park, Beltring, East Peckham, Kent</td> <td>1</td> <td>21/09/05</td> <td>19/10/05</td> <td>30/12/05</td> <td>10 weeks, 2 days</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.30.11/8"> <td>Former Warrant Distribution Depot, Argyle Street,    Hebburn, South Tyneside</td> <td>1</td> <td>20/10/05</td> <td>17/11/05</td> <td>12/01/06</td> <td>8 weeks</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.30.11/9"> <td>Land off Countesthorpe Road, Whetstone, Leicestershire</td> <td>2</td> <td>29/09/05</td> <td>04/11/05</td> <td>18/01/06</td> <td>10 weeks, 5 days</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.30.11/10"> <td>Land off Stadium Way, Rayleigh Weir Industrial Estate,    Benfleet, Essex</td> <td>1</td> <td>11/08/05</td> <td>29/09/05</td> <td>Minded to decision<br/>    30/11/05 Final<br/>    decision 23/01/06</td> <td>8 weeks, 6 days;<br/>    16 weeks, 4 days</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.30.11/11"> <td>Evesham Rd, Cleeve Prior, Worcestershire</td> <td>1</td> <td>11/10/05</td> <td>10/11/05</td> <td>26/01/06</td> <td>11 weeks</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.30.11/12"> <td>Lots Road Power Station, Lots Road &amp; Land to the south    of Chelsea Creek, Chelsea Harbour Drive, London</td> <td>2</td> <td>26/04/05</td> <td>19/08/05</td> <td>30/01/06</td> <td>23 weeks, 3 days</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.30.11/13"> <td>Land at Hovefields Drive, Wickford, Essex</td> <td>10</td> <td>12/10/05</td> <td>28/11/05</td> <td>01/02/06</td> <td>9    weeks, 2 days</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.30.11/14"> <td>Land at and in the vicinity of Landguard Terminal, Port of    Felixstowe, Suffolk</td> <td>1</td> <td>02/12/04</td> <td>04/05/05</td> <td>01/02/06</td> <td>38 weeks</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.31.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn6">
	Prisoners: Secure Psychiatric Hospitals
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.31.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn6">
	<p pid="c.31.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.31.1/2" qnum="HL4085">How many prisoners have been transferred to secure psychiatric hospital wards, or to other National Health Service treatment outside prisons, in each of the past three years; and whether any young offenders have been so transferred.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.31.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_spmin3">
	<p pid="c.31.2/1">The information available is that the number of prisoners transferred to hospital under Section 47 and Section 48 of the Mental Health Act 1983 is 644 for 2002, 721 for 2003 and 831 in 2004. The number of young offenders under the age of 18 so transferred is 26 in 2002; 20 in 2003 and 34 in 2004.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.31.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn7">
	Probation Service: Early Retirement
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.31.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100632" speakername="Viscount Tenby" colon="" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn7">
	<p pid="c.31.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.31.4/2" qnum="HL4128">Whether, when the Probation Service was restructured into its present areas, any of the chief probation officers of the pre-existing service retired; and, if so, whether any of these officers were awarded additional years to enhance their pension benefits.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.31.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_spmin4">
	<p pid="c.31.5/1">As a result of the radical restructuring of the Probation Service in 2001, which included making local areas coterminous with current police forces, all chief probation officers who took early retirement did so on terms which gave additional added years to their reckonable service.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.31.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn8">
	Royal Mail
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.31.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100435" speakername="Lord Monson" colon="" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn8">
	<p pid="c.31.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.31.7/2" qnum="HL4106">What proportion of the &pound;11.7 million fine recently levied on Royal Mail for poor performance will be met by (a) taxpayers; (b) Royal Mail customers; and (c) Royal Mail managers.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.32.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_spmin5">
	<p pid="c.32.0/1">The decision to impose this penalty was taken by Postcomm. Royal Mail has the right to apply to the courts to appeal against this decision. Penalties would be paid from Royal Mail's revenues.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.32.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn9">
	Social Security: New Deal
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.32.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100112" speakername="Lord Carter" colon="" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_wqn9">
	<p pid="c.32.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.32.2/2" qnum="HL3782">When an accessible version of the Green Paper <i>A new deal for welfare</i> will be published; whether there will be an extension to the consultation deadline for those requiring the accessible version; and whether the non-availability of an accessible version constitutes discrimination.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.32.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w09.htm#60227w09_spmin6">
	<p pid="c.32.3/1">We launched our welfare reform Green Paper, <i>A new deal for welfare: Empowering people to work</i>, on <phrase class="date" code="2007-01-24">24 January</phrase>. Since then, more than 2,500 copies have been distributed.</p>
	<p pid="c.32.3/2">We are also producing alternative versions of the Green Paper&mdash;Word, Braille, audio, large print, easy-read and Welsh language. People can request copies of these via our e-mail and telephone contact points. The Braille, audio and large print versions have already been distributed, and we took delivery of the Welsh language version on <phrase class="date" code="2007-02-15">15 February</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="c.32.3/3">It does take time to prepare the easy-read version in a properly accessible format, with appropriate illustrations. The first draft of that version has been approved and the final version will be with us on <phrase class="date" code="2006-02-27">27 February 2006</phrase>. Given this delay, we will respond sensibly and sensitively to individuals who require additional time to make their response. We also have a telephone helpline to provide one-to-one advice to</p>
	<p pid="c.32.3/4">individuals and organisations in understanding our proposals.</p>
	<p pid="c.32.3/5">Ministers and officials worked closely with the stakeholder community over the past year in developing our proposals. We will continue to do so.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.33.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w10.htm#60227w10_wqn0">
	Sudan: Darfur
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.33.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w10.htm#60227w10_wqn0">
	<p pid="c.33.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.33.1/2" qnum="HL4025">Whether they intend to refer to the United Nations Security Council the recent attacks by militias from Darfur into Chad and by Chadian rebels using Darfur as a base.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.33.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w10.htm#60227w10_spmin0">
	<p pid="c.33.2/1">We deplore the recent militia and rebel attacks in both Chad and Darfur. Stability in both countries is vital for the region and we therefore welcome the peace agreement signed by the Presidents of both Sudan and Chad in Libya on <phrase class="date" code="2007-02-08">8 February</phrase>. We expect the parties to honour it.</p>
	<p pid="c.33.2/2">Cross-border security issues have been discussed on several occasions by the Security Council in its efforts to find a lasting solution to the widespread conflict and humanitarian crisis in Darfur. In addition, my right honourable friend the Foreign Secretary and I met the Sudanese Foreign Minister, Dr Lam Akol, on <phrase class="date" code="2007-02-03">3 February</phrase> and impressed upon him the need to find a peaceful solution. Our permanent representative to the United Nations in New York has also discussed the issue with the Foreign Minister of Chad.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.33.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w10.htm#60227w10_wqn1">
	Sudan: Darfur
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.33.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100026" speakername="Lord Astor of Hever" colon="" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w10.htm#60227w10_wqn1">
	<p pid="c.33.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.33.4/2" qnum="HL4076">What equipment is being provided by the United Kingdom in support of, and for the use of, the African Union Mission and the proposed United Nations Mission to the Sudan.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.33.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w10.htm#60227w10_spnew0">
	<p pid="c.33.5/1">The UK has committed &pound;19 million of funding this financial year to the African Union Mission in Sudan (AMIS). This brings our total contribution to AMIS, since its inception, to almost &pound;32 million. We are using the majority of our contribution to provide equipment. We have purchased more than 900 vehicles and are funding the airlift of troops into Darfur. We have contributed rapid deployment kits for the troops as well as ration kits. We are also providing military and civilian policing advice, expertise and training.</p>
	<p pid="c.33.5/2">The existing United Nations Mission in the Sudan (UNMIS), which operates outside Darfur, is supplied by the UN and therefore does not need bilateral grants of equipment. The proposed UN successor mission to AMIS will be in a similar position.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.34.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w10.htm#60227w10_wqn2">
	Sudan: Darfur
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.34.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100026" speakername="Lord Astor of Hever" colon="" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w10.htm#60227w10_wqn2">
	<p pid="c.34.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.34.1/2" qnum="HL4075">How many (a) military, and (b) police service personnel are being provided by the United Kingdom in advisory support to the African Union Mission and the proposed United Nations Mission to the Sudan; and</p>
	<p pid="c.34.1/3" qnum="HL4077">What is the estimated annual cost of military and police service advisory support provided by the United Kingdom in advisory support to the African Union Mission and the proposed United Nations Mission to the Sudan; and</p>
	<p pid="c.34.1/4" qnum="HL4078">What estimate they have formed of the overall financial cost of military and police service advisory support being provided by the United Kingdom in advisory support to the African Union Mission and the proposed United Nations Mission to the Sudan in comparison with the value of similar contributions made by other donors.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.34.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w10.htm#60227w10_spnew1">
	<p pid="c.34.2/1">The UK provides one officer through the EU as an adviser to the Joint Logistics Organisation in the African Union Mission (AMIS) in El Fashir, Darfur, at an annual estimated cost of &pound;150,000. The UK also provides a military observer at an estimated annual cost of &pound;70,000. We have contributed six police experts to the EU's civilian policing mission to AMIS, at an annual cost of approximately &pound;280,000. The UK also contributes indirectly to common costs of the EU's policing mission through its contribution to the EU's common foreign and security policy budget. We estimate the UK's share of these annual costs at &pound;400,000. Canada, US and EU member states have also provided a number of military and police advisers, whose numbers have fluctuated, and for whom we do not have cost details.</p>
	<p pid="c.34.2/2">The UK has played a leading role in establishing AMIS. Since its inception we have provided &pound;32 million of financial assistance. We are also a key supporter of AMIS through our efforts to engage other donors. We welcome the AU (African Union) Peace and Security Council's decision in principle to hand over the mission to the UN, and urge the AU and UN to agree the final decision as soon as possible. The UK will continue to support AMIS during its deployment.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.34.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w10.htm#60227w10_wqn3">
	Syria: Middle East Peace Process
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.34.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100804" speakername="Lord Dykes" colon="" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w10.htm#60227w10_wqn3">
	<p pid="c.34.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.34.4/2" qnum="HL4063">Whether they will propose that the European Union Council of Ministers withhold its signature from the European Union-Syria Association Agreement pending the conclusions of the United Nations IIIC investigation, under United Nations Security Council Resolution 1559, on political murders and their effects on the Middle East peace process.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.35.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w10.htm#60227w10_spmin1">
	<p pid="c.35.0/1">A decision on signature of the EU-Syria Association Agreement will be sought from the Council only once technical procedures relating to the agreement have been finalised. Our view on whether the Council should sign will be influenced by the situation in the region at the time a decision is sought, including progress of the UN International Independent Investigation Commission.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.35.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w10.htm#60227w10_wqn4">
	US Government Aircraft: Use of Military Airbases
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.35.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100367" speakername="Lord Lester of Herne Hill" colon="" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w10.htm#60227w10_wqn4">
	<p pid="c.35.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.35.2/2" qnum="HL3386">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Drayson on 9 January (<i>WA 28</i>), whether they will publish the terms of the reciprocal arrangement giving United States military and state aircraft clearance to land at military airfields in the United Kingdom.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-02-27c.36.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo060227/text/60227w10.htm#60227w10_spmin2">
	<p pid="c.36.0/1">The arrangements are that no individual clearance is required for US military and state aircraft wishing to land at military airfields in the UK; flight plans must be filed in accordance with normal air traffic control procedures; and aircraft carrying dangerous air cargo or VIPs must notify the Ministry of Defence prior to arrival. The aircraft registration number, the names of pilot and owner, the date of departure and the outbound destination will be recorded. No information is required about the purpose of flights, nor about passengers where they are not to enter the UK. Where passengers enter the UK, their details will be passed to the Immigration Service and HM Revenue and Customs.</p>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

