<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.69.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn0">
	The first Written Answer should have been printed in the Official Report of Monday, 30th June.Fire Service College Task Group
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.69.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100519" speakername="Baroness Ramsay of Cartvale" colon="" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.69.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.69.1/2" qnum="HL3674">When the final report of the Fire Service College task group will be published.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.69.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.69.2/1">In May 2002 Alan Whitehead MP announced the creation of a task group to look into the future of the Fire Service College. The group has now reported, and I have arranged for copies of its report to be placed in the House Libraries today.</p>
	<p pid="a.69.2/2">The task group concluded that there was a need for a central Fire Service training facility to serve as a centre of intellectual leadership for the Fire Service. It should take forward work on vocational development through the integrated personal development system, the civil contingency response arising from the events of September 11, and the modernisation agenda opened up by the Bain report. It recommended that a national workforce development/training strategy should be drawn up, which would define the role of the college in relation to other providers. It also recommended that there should be a long-term plan for improving the college's infrastructure and services.</p>
	<p pid="a.69.2/3">I have accepted these and other recommendations of the report. I have agreed that the college should be given a &pound;5 million grant to invest in its infrastructure this financial year, plus &pound;2.5 million to invest in urban search and rescue facilities; and that it should actively examine ways of involving the private sector in its future development. This investment in the college should enable it to develop as a centre of excellence, and play a key role in the modernisation of the fire service.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.69.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn1">
	Disabled Facilities Grant: Gypsy Sites
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.69.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.69.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.69.4/2" qnum="HL3835">What steps they are taking to ensure that the disabled facilities grant is extended to people who live on gypsy sites run by local authorities or registered social landlords, and not only to those who live in &quot;qualifying park homes&quot;.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.69.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="69"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.69.5/1">The Office of the Deputy Prime Minister will be writing shortly to key interested parties, including the noble Lord, setting out proposals for amending the definition of a qualifying park home in relation to eligibility for disabled facililties grant to include all occupiers of caravans.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.70.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn2">
	Northern Ireland: Morning-after Pill
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.70.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100419" speakername="Baroness Masham of Ilton" colon="" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.70.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.70.1/2" qnum="HL3308">What surveys they have carried out to indicate (a) support; and (b) opposition to the widespread use of the morning-after pill in Northern Ireland; and whether they will place in the Library of the House the results of any such survey.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.70.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.70.2/1">No such surveys have been carried out.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.70.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn3">
	Alastair Campbell: Accountability
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.70.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100408" speakername="Lord McNally" colon="" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.70.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.70.4/2" qnum="HL3713">Which Minister accepts overall responsibility for Alastair Campbell's department.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.70.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.70.5/1">Alastair Campbell is the Director of Communications and Strategy at No. 10. He is appointed by the Prime Minister under terms and conditions set out in the Model Contract for Special Advisers. He is accountable to the Prime Minister.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.70.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn4">
	Ministerial Responsibilities: Publication of Changes
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.70.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100468" speakername="Lord Norton of Louth" colon="" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.70.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.70.7/2" qnum="HL3812">What were the dates on which final lists of ministerial responsibilities were published by each of the departments affected by the ministerial changes announced on 12 and 13 June.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.70.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100688" speakername="Lord Williams of Mostyn" colon=":" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.70.8/1">A full list of Ministers was placed on the No. 10 and Cabinet Office websites on <phrase class="date" code="2003-06-17">Tuesday 17 June</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.70.8/2">The revised list of ministerial responsibilities, which provides a detailed breakdown of individual ministerial portfolios, will be published shortly in both electronic and paper form.</p>
	<p pid="a.70.8/3">The dates on which individual departments published details of their Ministers' responsibilities are not held centrally.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.70.9" nospeaker="true" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn5">
	British Overseas Territories
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.70.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100444" speakername="Lord Morris of Manchester" colon="" colnum="70"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.70.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.70.10/2" qnum="HL3448">What arrangements are being made to provide technical and financial assistance to reduce the impact of the trading arrangements of the World Trade Organisation and the Free Trade Area of the Americas on British Overseas Territories in terms of adjustment periods, special and deferential treatment and resource needs.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.71.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.71.0/1">The provisions of the World Trade Organisation do not apply to the British Overseas Territories, with the exception of Gibraltar, which is covered by the EC's membership to the extent that the EC Treaty applies to Gibraltar. Negotiations for the Free Trade Area of the Americas (FTAA) are at an early stage and it remains unclear what, if any, implications the FTAA might have for the Overseas Territories. We will keep this under close review.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.71.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn6">
	Montserrat: CARICOM and OECS
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.71.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100444" speakername="Lord Morris of Manchester" colon="" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.71.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.71.2/2" qnum="HL3450">Whether there would be implications for the United Kingdom as a result of Montserrat's participation in the proposed CARICOM single market and economy and the Caribbean Court of Justice.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.71.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.71.3/1">The British Government encourage Montserrat to play a full role in regional affairs, including through its membership of CARICOM and the Organisation of Eastern Caribbean States (OECS). The British Overseas Territories require prior British Government approval, in the form of an entrustment, before undertaking international commitments. We hope to work together with the Government of Montserrat and the CARICOM Secretariat to assess the implications of Montserrat's full participation in the CARICOM single market and economy (CSME) and the Caribbean Court of Justice (CCJ) for Montserrat and the United Kingdom. Her Majesty's Government have already issued several entrustments to the Government of Montserrat to sign various protocols pertaining to CSME, but further entrustments will be required for full participation. The Government of Montserrat have not yet requested entrustments in relation to the CCJ.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.71.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn7">
	Burma
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.71.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.71.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.71.5/2" qnum="HL3649">Whether they have any plans to raise the issue of atrocities by the Burmese military against the Karen, Karenni and Shan people in Burma at the United Nations Security Council</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.71.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="71"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.71.6/1">The United Nations Security Council has not formally considered the issue of Burma. However, we are in discussions with Security Council partners to help to bring this about. Should Burma feature on the Security Council agenda, the Government would ensure that the plight of Burma's ethnic minority groups was taken fully into account.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.72.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn8">
	Burma
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.72.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.72.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.72.1/2" qnum="HL3650">Whether they will lobby the United Nations Security Council for a global arms and investment embargo against Burma.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.72.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.72.2/1">We are in discussions with partners in the Security Council to determine whether the Security Council can consider the issue of Burma. The Government are encouraging all the appropriate bodies of the UN to tackle the issue of helping to bring about national reconciliation, respect for human rights and democracy in Burma. Despite our efforts, there is currently no consensus for Security Council action for a global arms and investment embargo against Burma.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.72.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn9">
	Burma
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.72.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn9">
	<p pid="a.72.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.72.4/2" qnum="HL3651">Whether they will lobby at the United Nations Security Council for the setting up of an international criminal tribunal on Burma to try members of the Burmese military regime for alleged atrocities against the Karen, Karenni and Shan people.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.72.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.72.5/1">The UK is one of the strongest critics of the Burmese regime's violations of human rights. There has been a consistent pattern of serious violations over many years in Burma, particularly against ethnic minorities. These have been highlighted in UK co-sponsored resolutions on Burma in both the United Nations General Assembly and the United Nations Commission on Human Rights. There is currently no international criminal tribunal with jurisdiction over Burma; and ultimately, it will be for the people of Burma to decide how they view this period of their history. The UK is against impunity for breaches of international law. That is why it is one of the strongest supporters of the International Criminal Court (ICC) which is able to try cases of genocide, war crimes and crimes against humanity.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.72.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn10">
	Burma
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.72.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_wqn10">
	<p pid="a.72.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.72.7/2" qnum="HL3653">Since the beginning of 2003, on how many occasions the British Ambassador in Rangoon raised concerns with the Burmese military regime regarding atrocities against the Karen, Karenni and Shan people; and what response the Ambassador received on each occasion.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.72.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="72"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w01.htm#30714w01_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.72.8/1">The UK has been at the forefront of international action to bring pressure to bear on the Burmese regime to improve the human rights situation and restore democracy. Our Ambassador and other UK Government representatives regularly raise a wide range of human rights abuses including those against ethnic minorities, in their contacts with senior regime figures. However, these contacts are limited in view of the current state of relations between the United Kingdom and the Burmese regime. Responses have so far been unsatisfactory.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.73.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="73"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn0">
	Burma
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.73.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="73"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.73.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.73.1/2" qnum="HL3654">Since the beginning of 2003, on how many occasions they have participated in a European Union demarche to the Burmese regime regarding atrocities against the Karen, Karenni and Shan people.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.73.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="73"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.73.2/1">The UK has been instrumental in pressing for and supporting demarches against the Burmese regime, including on human rights abuses against the ethnic groups. The EU has made numerous statements and demarches covering a wide range of human rights abuses including those inflicted on the Karen, Karenni and Shan people. The most recent EU demarche was made on <phrase class="date" code="2003-06-09">9 June</phrase>. These have been conveyed to the regime by the local presidency in Rangoon.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.73.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="73"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn1">
	Jamil Bassam and Ibrahim Khodebandeh
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.73.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="73"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.73.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.73.4/2" qnum="HL3690">(a) what representations they have made to the Syrian authorities on behalf of Mr Jamil Bassam and Mr Ibrahim Khodebandeh, refugees from Iran who were resident in the United Kingdom for more than 20 years and who were arrested during a visit to Syria in April and were returned to Iran on 12 June; and (b) whether, during his forthcoming visit to Iran, the Foreign Secretary will inquire about the health and location of these two persons.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.73.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="73"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.73.5/1">Our embassy in Damascus repeatedly asked the Syrian authorities for information on Jamil Bassam and Ibrahim Khodebandeh following their detention. The Syrian authorities did not respond to any of the embassy's four formal notes before the men were deported. We have taken this matter up with the Syrian Government and our embassy in Tehran has made it clear to the Iranian Government that we are taking a keen interest in the human rights of these two men.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.73.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="73"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn2">
	Indonesia
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.73.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="73"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.73.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.73.7/2" qnum="HL3704">Whether they consider that an independent organisation or supranational body can be found to mediate in the conflict concerning Aceh in Indonesia; and, if so, which.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.73.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="73"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.73.8/1">The Centre for Humanitarian Dialogue (HDC) brokered the Cessation of Hostilities Agreement (COHA) agreed on <phrase class="date" code="2002-12-09">9 December 2002</phrase> between the Indonesian Government and the Free Aceh Movement (GAM). To monitor the peace agreement in Aceh both sides agreed to international observers from Thailand and the Philippines. The observers were removed in April 2003 following attacks on their offices.</p>
	<p pid="a.73.8/2">We remain convinced that a long-term solution to the Aceh problem can only be achieved through political negotiation and consultation between the Indonesian Government and the Acehenese people. We support the statements issued by the EU, US, Japan and the World Bank, as co-chairs of the Tokyo Preparatory Conference on Peace and Reconstruction in Aceh, urging both sides to resume political dialogue. The UK, and the international community, support Indonesia's territorial integrity. We see no scope, at the moment, for a supranational body to become involved in the conflict in Aceh.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.74.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="74"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn3">
	Congo
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.74.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100341" speakername="Lord Judd" colon="" colnum="74"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.74.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.74.1/2" qnum="HL3738">In the light of the political and operational arrangements for the European Union military force in the Democratic Republic of the Congo, what is their policy towards the respective responsibilities of the United Nations Security Councils and the European Council when intervention by European Union forces outside the European Union is being planned or undertaken.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.74.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="74"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.74.2/1">Under the UN charter, the Security Council has primary responsibility for the maintenance of international peace and security. The EU's security and defence policy can be used to support the UN. This is the case in the operation in the Democratic Republic of Congo, where the EU is operating under a UN Security Council Resolution (UNSCR) mandate. In this case, the UNSCR sets out the mandate for the force and authorises the deployment of the force under that mandate. But the political control and strategic direction of the EU operation within the mandate is a matter for the EU.</p>
	<p pid="a.74.2/2">The EU can also conduct crisis management operations without requiring a specific UNSCR to authorise the mission; for example, when the EU is operating at the request of the country concerned, as is the case for the EU's mission in Macedonia.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.74.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="74"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn4">
	Guantanamo Bay: UK Nationals
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.74.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100469" speakername="Lord Oakeshott of Seagrove Bay" colon="" colnum="74"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.74.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.74.4/2" qnum="HL3798">Further to the Written Answer by the Baroness Amos on 8 April (WA 19), whether they have asked the United States authorities to give the Government access to all the facts of the nine individual cases of the British subjects held at Guantanamo Bay, which are necessary to determine their status; and, if not, why not.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.74.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="74"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.74.5/1">The assessment of the status of the detainees is a matter for the US, as the detaining power. We have, however, discussed the detainees' status with the US authorities. They have told us that they do not consider any of the British detainees to be entitled to prisoner of war status. The US authorities have assured us that the detainees are being treated humanely and consistently with the principles of the Geneva Conventions.</p>
	<p pid="a.74.5/2">Whatever their status, the detainees are entitled to humane treatment and if prosecuted, a fair trial.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.75.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="75"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn5">
	Guantanamo Bay: UK Nationals
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.75.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100469" speakername="Lord Oakeshott of Seagrove Bay" colon="" colnum="75"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.75.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.75.1/2" qnum="HL3799">Further to the Written Answer by the Baroness Amos on 28 April (WA 61), what is the current response of the United States authorities to the Government's continuing pressure on them to make decisions on the future of the British detainees at Guantanamo Bay; and for how long the Government are prepared to tolerate their detention without trial.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.75.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="75"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.75.2/1">I refer the noble Lord to the Statement I made on <phrase class="date" code="2003-07-07">7 July</phrase> (Official Report, col. 27).</p>
	<p pid="a.75.2/2">We continue to press the US to resolve the position of the detainees in Guantanamo Bay.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.75.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="75"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn6">
	Guantanamo Bay: UK Nationals
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.75.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100469" speakername="Lord Oakeshott of Seagrove Bay" colon="" colnum="75"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.75.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.75.4/2" qnum="HL3800">Whether, in their view, the national security of either the United States or the United Kingdom would be put at risk if the nine British subjects held at Guantanamo Bay were now to be transferred to United Kingdom custody.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.75.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="75"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.75.5/1">We understand that the United States authorities have not made a decision to transfer any of the British nationals held at Guantanamo Bay to the UK. The impact on US and UK security would be taken into account by the Government in their approach to any potential transfer of the detainees to the UK.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.75.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="75"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn7">
	Sexual Offences Legislation: Sado- masochistic Activity
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.75.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100667" speakername="Baroness Walmsley" colon="" colnum="75"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.75.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.75.7/2" qnum="HL3416">How they plan to amend sexual offences and offences against the person legislation to end the criminalisation of consenting adults who engage in sado-masochistic sexual activity when that activity results in no lasting harm or injury.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.75.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="75"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.75.8/1">We have no current plans to amend the sexual offences and offences against the person legislation to take account of this issue.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.76.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="76"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn8">
	Race Relations Act 1976 (Amendment) Regulations 2003
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.76.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100476" speakername="Lord Ouseley" colon="" colnum="76"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn8">
	<p pid="a.76.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.76.1/2" qnum="HL3432">Why they have allowed a colour bar to be prevalent in anti-discrimination legislation by excluding &quot;colour&quot; discrimination from protection in the Race Relations Act 1976 (Amendment) Regulations 2003.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.76.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="76"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.76.2/1">We do not accept that we have allowed a colour bar to be prevalent in anti-discrimination legislation by excluding &quot;colour&quot; discrimination from protection in the Race Relations Act 1976 (Amendment) Regulations 2003. Most of the 1976 Act, which lists colour as one of the grounds of unlawful racial discrimination, was already more than compliant with the directive. The changes introduced by the regulations to ensure full compliance with the directive and are relatively few in number. Furthermore one of these changes, namely the definition of harassment, reflects current case law (which will continue to apply in cases involving harassment on grounds of colour).</p>
	<p pid="a.76.2/2">&quot;Colour&quot; discrimination has been excluded from the Race Relations Act 1976 (Amendment) Regulations 2003 because we consider that the power conferred by the European Communities Act 1972 would confer authority to combat discrimination on grounds of colour, in the course of grounds of colour, in the course of implementing the Race Directive (Council Directive 2000/43/EC), if it had not already been used to make good any shortfall in Community competence in certain areas of the 1976 Act corresponding to those mentioned in the directive (in order to deal with the limitation in Article 3.1 of the directive).</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.76.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="76"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn9">
	Trespassers
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.76.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="76"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_wqn9">
	<p pid="a.76.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.76.4/2" qnum="HL3741">Which persons or organisations they have consulted about the provisions of Clause 61 of the Anti-social Behaviour Bill.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.76.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="76"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w02.htm#30714w02_spnew8">
	<p pid="a.76.5/1">The Government signalled their intention to introduce new measures to extend police powers when dealing with trespassers in a guidance document Managing Unauthorised Camping published by the Home Office and Office of the Deputy Prime Minister (ODPM). Responses to these new measures were received from a number of respondents including local authorities, the National Farmers Union and the police.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.76.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="76"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_wqn0">
	Civil Partnerships
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.76.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100367" speakername="Lord Lester of Herne Hill" colon="" colnum="76"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.76.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.76.7/2" qnum="HL3751">Whether they are willing to permit the public to express views during the consultation period for the White Paper, Civil Partnership: a framework for the legal recognition of same-sex couples, on their decision to exclude opposite-sex couples from the benefits of the scheme.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.77.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="77"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.77.0/1">The consultation paper on civil partnership asks the public to comment on a series of questions relating to specific areas of the Government's proposals, together with the more general question &quot;Do you have any other comments?&quot;. Members of the public are entitled, in any event, to comment on whichever aspect of the proposed scheme they choose. The Government encourage them to do so.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.77.1" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="77"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_wqn1">
	Civil Partnerships
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.77.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100367" speakername="Lord Lester of Herne Hill" colon="" colnum="77"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.77.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.77.2/2" qnum="HL3752">What is the justification for proposing to treat opposite-sex cohabitants less favourably than same-sex cohabitants as regards claims for financial loss under the Fatal Accidents Act 1976 and fatal injury applications under the criminal injuries compensation scheme.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.77.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="77"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.77.3/1">The Government do not propose to treat opposite-sex cohabitants less favourably than same-sex cohabitants as regards either claims under the Fatal Accidents Act or applications under the criminal industries compensation scheme.</p>
	<p pid="a.77.3/2">The Government's consultation paper Civil Partnership: a framework for the legal recognition of same-sex couples, would enable same-sex partners, for the first time, to gain legal recognition for their relationships. Opposite-sex couples already have this opportunity. Those same-sex couples who choose not to register will not gain the package of rights and responsibilities proposed, as is the case for those opposite-sex couples who choose not to marry.</p>
	<p pid="a.77.3/3">The Government therefore propose that registered partners should be allowed to make a claim for financial loss under the Fatal Accidents Act, in the same way that spouses can.</p>
	<p pid="a.77.3/4">In March 2001, the Government amended the Criminal Injuries Compensation Scheme to allow same-sex cohabitants the same rights as opposite-sex cohabitants to make a fatal injury application in the event of a partner's death. Under the Government's new proposals, same-sex registered partners, like opposite-sex married partners, will not have to demonstrate that they have been cohabitants for two years prior to the death.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.77.4" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="77"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_wqn2">
	Civil Partnerships
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.77.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100367" speakername="Lord Lester of Herne Hill" colon="" colnum="77"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.77.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.77.5/2" qnum="HL3753">What solution they propose for opposite-sex couples who choose not to marry and are vulnerable in the way described in paragraph 2.8 of the White Paper on civil partnership.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.77.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="77"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.77.6/1">As the Government make clear in their consultation paper, opposite-sex couples who become vulnerable in the way described already have the opportunity to secure legal recognition for their partnerships through the option of marriage. The Government do recognise, however, that many couples mistakenly believe that there is such a thing as &quot;common-law marriage&quot;. The Department of Constitutional Affairs will be leading a cross-government working group to explore how best to raise public awareness about the rights and responsibilities of cohabitees and to dispel the myths around &quot;common law marriage&quot;.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.78.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="78"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_wqn3">
	Homicide
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.78.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100629" speakername="Lord Tebbit" colon="" colnum="78"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.78.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.78.1/2" qnum="HL3755">How many people have died since 1963 in England and Wales at the hands of persons previously convicted of homicide.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.78.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="78"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.78.2/1">During the period 1963 to date, a total of 105 persons in England and Wales are known to have been killed by persons who had been previously convicted of homicide in England and Wales.</p>
	<p pid="a.78.2/2">As with previous answers, the figure excludes persons who have been killed by those who may have been convicted outside England and Wales (for whom there is incomplete information), and persons who have been killed by those not previously convicted of homicide by reason of their mental state.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.78.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="78"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_wqn4">
	Wildlife and Countryside Act 2000: Prosecutions under Section 14
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.78.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100244" speakername="Baroness Golding" colon="" colnum="78"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.78.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.78.4/2" qnum="HL3773">How many prosecutions there have been under the Wildlife and Countryside Act 2000 relating to the prohibition of release of non-native species of animals; and what were the animals to which the prosecutions referred.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.78.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="78"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.78.5/1">Information reported to the Home Office shows that 10 persons have been proceeded against under the Wildlife and Countryside Act 1981, Section 14, by the end of 2001, and in each case the offence related to an animal. Records held centrally do not allow the identification of the animal(s).</p>
	<p pid="a.78.5/2">Statistics for 2002 will be published in the autumn.</p>
	<p pid="a.78.5/3">Figures for Scotland are a matter for the Scotland Office and those for Northern Ireland for the Northern Ireland Office.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.78.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="78"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_wqn5">
	Biometric Identification
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.78.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100403" speakername="Lord MacKenzie of Culkein" colon="" colnum="78"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.78.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.78.7/2" qnum="HL3818">What progress has been made towards the incorporation of biometric identification into British passports.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.79.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="79"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.79.0/1">Specifications for the deployment of biometrics in passports were agreed and endorsed by the International Civil Aviation Organisation (ICAO) in May 2003. The UK Passport Service (UKPS) actively supported the development of these specifications.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.0/2">The specifications call for a high resolution portrait image stored on a contactless chip embedded in passports and other travel documents. As optional additions, images of fingerprints or irises can be added. The ICAO specifications are designed to ensure interoperability of biometric information.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.0/3">The UKPS is developing implementation plans compliant with ICAO specification for electronically stored portrait images in British passports. As indicated in its 2003&ndash;08 corporate and business plan published on <phrase class="date" code="2003-04-23">23 April</phrase>, the UKPS is aiming to commence production of these passports in early 2005.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.79.1" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="79"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_wqn6">
	Biometric Identification
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.79.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100403" speakername="Lord MacKenzie of Culkein" colon="" colnum="79"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.79.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/2" qnum="HL3819">Whether they have plans to introduce iris, fingerprint and facial recognition systems at British airports.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.79.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="79"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.79.3/1">As part of the drive to modernise and improve the effectiveness of the United Kingdom's borders, the Immigration and Nationality Directorate is undertaking a project to implement an automated border entry system using iris recognition technology. A notice inviting expressions of interest from potential technology suppliers has been issued recently in the Official Journal of the European Communities.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.3/2">Passengers in certain eligible categories, details of which have yet to be finalised, who volunteer to enrol in the system will be able to gain entry to the United Kingdom via an automated border entry system that can recognise their iris pattern. This will provide a fast, fraud-resistant way to pass through immigration controls and allow immigration control staff to concentrate on other priorities. The system will not be operational until 2004.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.3/3">The permanent implementation of automated iris recognition barriers at United Kingdom ports of entry follows a successful trial with frequent travellers conducted at Heathrow last year.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.3/4">Fingerprints have been taken routinely from asylum seekers at airports (as well as other places where they are encountered) since 1993. In 2001 the Immigration and Asylum Fingerprint System (IAFS) was introduced to ports of entry and provided a fast result service. In April 2002 the IAFS was expanded to allow, at Heathrow and Gatwick (in addition to other locations), the production of application registration cards (ARCs) for asylum applicants. These cards include fingerprint data, which are stored in an attached microchip.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.3/5">We are currently conducting a pilot concentrating on verifying passengers' identities before they embark on flights to the UK. Part of that pilot will examine the extent to which facial recognition might assist in confirming identity.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.80.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="80"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_wqn7">
	United States: Extradition Treaty
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.80.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100367" speakername="Lord Lester of Herne Hill" colon="" colnum="80"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.80.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.80.1/2" qnum="HL3845">Whether they consider that the judicial and administrative authorities of the United Kingdom will be entitled to refuse to sanction the extradition of individuals to the United States, under the new United States-United Kingdom Extradition Treaty, in the event that extradition would be incompatible with United Kingdom constitutional principles or with the rights protected by the European Convention on Human Rights, or the common law; and</p>
	<p pid="a.80.1/3" qnum="HL3858">Whether they will ensure that no-one is extradited from the United Kingdom to the United States, or any place over which the United States exercises effective control, under the new bilateral and European Extradition Treaties with the United States, to face a trial before a special military commission or other court or tribunal that does not comply with the requirements of fairness contained in the European Convention on Human Rights and the International Covenant on Civil Political Rights.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.80.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="80"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w03.htm#30714w03_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.80.2/1">Extradition to the United States will in future be governed by Part 2 of the Extradition Bill, if it is enacted.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.2/2">The Extradition Bill sets out clearly the circumstances in which extradition cannot take place. One of the bars to extradition&mdash;contained in Clause 86 of the Bill&mdash;provides that extradition cannot take place where it would be incompatible with the ECHR rights of the person.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.80.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="80"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w04.htm#30714w04_wqn0">
	Immigration Detention Centres: Religious Affairs
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.80.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="80"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w04.htm#30714w04_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.80.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.80.4/2" qnum="HL3861">What are the existing chaplaincy arrangements for all faiths at immigration detention centres; and whether there are plans for any improvements.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.80.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="80"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w04.htm#30714w04_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.80.5/1">In accordance with the Detention Centre Rules 2001 every removal centre must appoint a manager of religious affairs. The religious affairs manager's task is to facilitate religious observance and the provision of pastoral care for detained persons with the assistance of suitably qualified staff, including ministers of religion. The performance of the religious affairs office in each removal centre is monitored continually and improvements will be made whenever the need arises.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.81.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="81"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w04.htm#30714w04_wqn1">
	Criminal Records Bureau: Review
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.81.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100519" speakername="Baroness Ramsay of Cartvale" colon="" colnum="81"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w04.htm#30714w04_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.81.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.81.1/2" qnum="HL3959">What changes have taken place as a result of the independent review of the Criminal Records Bureau.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.81.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="81"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w04.htm#30714w04_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.81.2/1">The Government, in their response on <phrase class="date" code="2003-02-27">27 February 2003</phrase> to the independent review team's recommendations for changes to the way in which the Criminal Records Bureau (CRB) is managed and operates (Official Report, Commons, cols. 32&ndash;36WS), agreed that the CRB should be reconstituted as a free-standing executive agency within the Home Office as soon as practicable.</p>
	<p pid="a.81.2/2">Vince Gaskell has been appointed to lead the new agency which will be launched on <phrase class="date" code="2003-09-01">1 September</phrase>. I have today placed in the Library of the House a copy of its framework document which sets out its role and functions and makes provision for its governance. A copy of its corporate and business plan including the targets set for the current financial year was placed in the Library of the House on <phrase class="date" code="2003-06-05">5 June</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.81.2/3">Much has been done to strengthen and improve the CRB's performance and significant improvements in output volume and turnaround times have already been achieved. Since October the CRB has been issuing an average of 40,000 disclosures a week compared with 24,500 a week last August and the bureau is now meeting its service standards for turnaround times. Once the provisions in the Criminal Justice Bill to implement a number of the independent review team's recommendations are in force, further improvements can be made to the efficiency and effectiveness of the CRB's services. We will consult further with registered bodies and others on the terms of the regulations to be made under the legislation before they are brought into force.</p>
	<p pid="a.81.2/4">The establishment of the CRB as a separate agency will enable its senior management team under the leadership of Vince Gaskell to focus exclusively on the delivery of the CRB's changing and increasingly demanding functions and ensure that its customers receive the quality of service they have the right to expect.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.81.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="81"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w04.htm#30714w04_wqn2">
	Riot (Damages) Act 1886: Review
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.81.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100172" speakername="Lord Desai" colon="" colnum="81"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w04.htm#30714w04_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.81.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.81.4/2" qnum="HL3978">When they plan to publish a review of the Riot (Damages) Act 1886.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.81.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="81"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w04.htm#30714w04_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.81.5/1">We have today published a consultation paper that looks at the origin and past operation of the Riot (Damages) Act 1886 (RDA) and seeks the views of stakeholders on the future of the RDA.</p>
	<p pid="a.81.5/2">The RDA is more than 100 years old. Both society and the nature of policing have changed dramatically in that time. In particular, in the light of our radical police reform programme, we need to look at whether the Act is still appropriate in the 21st century.</p>
	<p pid="a.81.5/3">Currently the RDA makes a police authority in England and Wales liable to pay for damages to buildings and their contents when a riot has taken place. Police authorities, the police service and others have argued for some time that the principle underpinning the RDA&mdash;that a riot presents a culpable failure to provide adequate policing&mdash;is no longer appropriate to modern conditions. There is also concern that police authorities are subject to unlimited liability for riot damage under the RDA.</p>
	<p pid="a.81.5/4">It is also argued that the RDA provides a safety net for businesses and households&mdash;particularly in inner-city areas, which have traditionally been more at risk of civil disturbances&mdash;and where property owners may have difficulties obtaining insurance, at least at affordable rates. Without the protection provided by the RDA, vulnerable communities could be at risk of further economic decline.</p>
	<p pid="a.81.5/5">At a time when the police service is engaged in a programme of major reform it seems appropriate to consider whether the RDA remains appropriate to 21st century needs. We are therefore inviting views on the future of the RDA and, specifically, whether the RDA should be retained as it stands; repealed entirely; or reformed to limit liability for claims.</p>
	<p pid="a.81.5/6">Comments and suggestions are requested on these specific issues but any alternative approaches or views to those outlined would be welcome.</p>
	<p pid="a.81.5/7">The Government have an open mind on the options and look forward to hearing the views of interested parties.</p>
	<p pid="a.81.5/8">We hope that the consultation will improve the evidence base to help develop a more detailed impact assessment.</p>
	<p pid="a.81.5/9">Options 2 and 3 would require primary legislation.</p>
	<p pid="a.81.5/10">Responses to the consultation paper are requested by <phrase class="date" code="2003-10-09">9 October 2003</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.81.5/11">A copy of the document has been placed in the Library and is available at <a href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/inside/consults/current/index.html">http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/inside/consults/current/index.html</a>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.82.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="82"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w04.htm#30714w04_wqn3">
	Shipman Inquiry: Second and Third Reports
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.82.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100112" speakername="Lord Carter" colon="" colnum="82"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w04.htm#30714w04_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.82.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.82.1/2" qnum="HL3979">When they plan to publish the second and third reports of the Shipman inquiry.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.82.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="82"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w04.htm#30714w04_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.82.2/1">This morning, the Home Secretary and the Secretary of State for Health are publishing and laying before Parliament the Shipman inquiry's second and third reports: The Police Investigation of March 1998, and Death Certification and the Investigation of Deaths by Coroners. These follow the publication, last year, of the first report, Death Disguised, which established the extent of Harold Shipman's activities. The inquiry's final reports, on controlled drugs, and disciplinary systems and complaints, are expected next year.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/2">We would like to thank Dame Janet Smith for the considerable work, and care and attention that have obviously gone into the preparation of these reports. We also wish to reiterate our sympathy to the relatives and friends of Shipman's victims. For their sake and in the wider interest of the community, it is essential that lessons are learned from these dreadful events.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/3">The second report covers the investigation conducted by the Greater Manchester Police in March and April 1998; five months before Harold Shipman was arrested. It makes it clear that, while the inquiry does not blame police management systems, the conduct of those officers involved in this specific investigation fell below the standard which the community is entitled to expect of public servants in their position. There was a subsequent internal inquiry by Greater Manchester Police into the failure of the March 1998 investigation. In the words of Dame Janet this inquiry was &quot;quite inadequate&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/4">We take the judgment of the Shipman inquiry on the Greater Manchester Police extremely seriously. For the initial investigation to have failed is severe enough, but for the subsequent investigation into its handling to have been so flawed requires the most urgent and strenuous efforts to ensure that such an event could never recur. It is for Greater Manchester Police to investigate but we await its report, and will expect rapid and effective action as well as lessons to be learnt by other forces in response.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/5">We have asked our officials to work closely with the Greater Manchester Police to establish what can usefully be drawn from the report and to offer appropriate support and advice. We will help Greater Manchester Police to move forward. Through the Home Office Police Standards Unit and Her Majesty's Inspectorate of Constabulary we are already working with the force to deliver performance improvements for the benefit of those living and working in the force area.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/6">It will also be for Greater Manchester Police to decide what action may be appropriate in relation to any individual police officer. The Home Secretary has written to the Chief Constable to ask to be kept informed of how the criticism against individuals in the force is being addressed.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/7">The report recommends that guidance should be issued to those detective officers who have to undertake investigations into allegations of wrongdoing by health professionals. Work on this is already under way. The Association of Chief Police Officers and the Department of Health, with the advice of the Health and Safety Executive, are jointly developing a memorandum of understanding. This sets out the roles and responsibilities of both organisations when a serious incident takes place or is suspected of occurring, and principles for effective liaison when criminal investigations may be needed into such incidents involving NHS patients. The memorandum will also refer to other guidance on incidents of this type; for example, guidance to police senior investigating officers, which the report identified as being developed.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/8">The third report found systemic shortcomings within the cremation arrangements and coroner system. The report of the Fundamental Review of Coroner Services and Death Certification, published on <phrase class="date" code="2003-06-04">4 June</phrase>, identified similar inadequacies, although the solutions proposed are slightly different.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/9">As we announced when the earlier report was published, in order to assist the Government to develop a coherent long-term strategy for the future of our death investigation processes, we have asked the chair of the fundamental review, Mr Tom Luce, to conduct some further work to link the review's recommendations to the findings of the Shipman inquiry. This will enable us to formulate a comprehensive programme of reform later this year, taking into account both sets of observations and recommendations.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/10">Dame Janet makes two recommendations for short-term improvement: that cremation certification procedures should be strengthened and that practices in coroners' offices should be improved. As a matter of urgency, our officials are discussing these proposals with the relevant agencies as part of our existing programme to take forward interim measures to improve these services. We shall ensure that guidance to deliver more robust procedures and practices is issued as soon as possible.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/11">The Financial Secretary to the Treasury last week published a consultation document on modernisation of the civil registration service, including death certification. Like the Fundamental Review of Coroner Services and Death Certification, this also presents an opportunity for comprehensive reform, this time specifically of the registration service and its interaction with related services.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.84.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="84"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_wqn0">
	Meat Hygiene Service: Annual Report and Accounts 2002&ndash;03
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.84.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100172" speakername="Lord Desai" colon="" colnum="84"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.84.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.84.1/2" qnum="HL3980">When the 2002&ndash;03 annual report and accounts for the Meat Hygiene Service will be laid before Parliament.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.84.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100670" speakername="Lord Warner" colon=":" colnum="84"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.84.2/1">The 2002&ndash;03 annual report and accounts for the Meat Hygiene Service was laid before Parliament today. Copies will be placed in the Library, but formal printing and publication will not occur for another six to eight weeks, pending preparation of a version in Welsh as required by the Welsh Language Act.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.85.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="85"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_wqn1">
	Wanless Review on Prevention and the Wider Determinants of Health
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.85.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon="" colnum="85"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.85.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.85.1/2" qnum="HL3708">Whether the review by Derek Wanless into the prevention and the wider determinants of health will be open to public comment and engagement; and</p>
	<p pid="a.85.1/3" qnum="HL3709">Which external organisations have been invited or commissioned to submit evidence to the Derek Wanless review on prevention and the wider determinants of health.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.85.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="85"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.85.2/1">The review will be open to public comment and engagement and will seek to take views and the submission of evidence from a wide range of experts. An invitation to submit comments and evidence will be available on the review's webpage on the HM Treasury website shortly.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.85.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="85"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_wqn2">
	Pensions Protection Fund
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.85.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100289" speakername="Lord Higgins" colon="" colnum="85"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_wqn2">
	<p pid="a.85.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.85.4/2" qnum="HL3776">Further to the Written Answer by the Baroness Hollis of Heigham on 24 June (WA 13)&mdash; (a) for what reason the cost of liabilities for the Pensions Protection Fund was taken as being less than the full insurance buy-out cost; (b) what was the ratio of the full buy-out cost to the MFR for the sample examined; (c) whether the benefits costed included a full allowance for pensions to increase in accordance with the normal rules of the scheme; and (d) whether any allowance was made for there to be a correlation between the size of a pension deficit and the probability of the insolvency of the sponsoring company.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.85.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100298" speakername="Baroness Hollis of Heigham" colon=":" colnum="85"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.85.5/1">Full insurance buy out costs are based on the yields of government and corporate bonds, and reflect the full costs of the Financial Services Authority's solvency requirements, as well as incorporating profit margins for the insurance company concerned. Not all of these elements will be relevant for the proposed Pension Protection Fund (PPF). We propose that the PPF will take in the assets of eligible pension schemes as well as any necessary levy. We do not intend for the PPF to be constrained by a legislative requirement to invest solely in gilts and corporate bonds, and over the medium to longer term, corporate bonds and equities have generally provided higher returns than conventional and indexed-linked gilts.</p>
	<p pid="a.85.5/2">The full buy-out costs were estimated by rating up MFR liabilities separately for pensioners, non-pensioners within 10 years of retirement age and others, and in aggregate were estimated to be 50 per cent higher than the liabilities measured on the MFR basis.</p>
	<p pid="a.85.5/3">The benefits costed included increases to pensions consistent with those included in the MFR valuations, and therefore only allow for guaranteed increases.</p>
	<p pid="a.85.5/4">Allowance was made for there to be a correlation between the size of the pension scheme and the probability of the insolvency of the sponsoring company, but no specific allowance was made for a correlation between the size of a pension deficit and the probability of employer insolvency.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.86.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="86"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_wqn3">
	Microchips
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.86.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100659" speakername="Lord Wade of Chorlton" colon="" colnum="86"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_wqn3">
	<p pid="a.86.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.86.1/2" qnum="HL3732">Whether they have consulted the Information Age Partnership about the recommendations in the Science and Technology Committee's December 2002 report, Chips for Everything: Britain's opportunities in a key global market, and, if so, when they did so and what practical actions have resulted.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.86.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="86"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_spmin3">
	<p pid="a.86.2/1">The Information Age Partnership (IAP) has not been consulted on the Science and Technology Committee's December 2002 report, Chips for Everything: Britain's opportunities in a key global market.</p>
	<p pid="a.86.2/2">The IAP identifies the key issues across the IT communications, electronics and content sectors, where partnership between government and industry can make a difference. The IAP is orientated to rapid action, and work is driven forward through industry-led and resourced working groups with government participation.</p>
	<p pid="a.86.2/3">As regards the whole area of electronics, from design through manufacture, these issues are being addressed by the recently announced Electronics Innovation and Growth Team (EIGT) which has some common membership with the IAP and which will no doubt wish to consider issues raised in Chips for Everything.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.86.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="86"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_wqn4">
	Iraq: Oil and Petroleum
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.86.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon="" colnum="86"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_wqn4">
	<p pid="a.86.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.86.4/2" qnum="HL3768">How many oil wells, refineries and related facilities are now functioning in Iraq; whether Iraq is now self-sufficient in petroleum products; and when they expect it to be producing for export.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.86.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="86"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.86.5/1">As at February 2003 there were approximately 1,500 to 1,700 wells in Iraq producing oil and 10 operating refineries. (Source US Dept of Energy, Energy Information Administration). No comparable statistics have been made available since the end of the hostilities.</p>
	<p pid="a.86.5/2">Current Iraqi oil production is estimated to be 800,000 to 900,000 barrels per day. This compares to production of 2.5 million barrels per day in February 2003 (Source Platts Analytics Service).</p>
	<p pid="a.86.5/3">Iraq is still importing some petroleum products to meet domestic demand.</p>
	<p pid="a.86.5/4">The first tender for Iraq oil produced since the end of hostilities was issued on <phrase class="date" code="2003-07-03">3 July 2003</phrase> for the sale of 8 million barrels of Basra crude. 9.5 million barrels of Iraqi crude were successfully tendered in June. This was oil produced pre-war and stored during the hostilities.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.87.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="87"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_wqn5">
	Broadband
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.87.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100465" speakername="The Earl of Northesk" colon="" colnum="87"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_wqn5">
	<p pid="a.87.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/2" qnum="HL3796">What consideration they are giving to the call from the Broadband Stakeholder Group that more spectrum, specifically frequencies at 2.4GHz and 5.8GHz and above, should be released for the purposes of establishing wireless broadband services.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.87.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="87"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.87.2/1">It is the intention of Her Majesty's Government that 105 MHz of spectrum at 5.8 GHz (known as band C) will be made available for broadband fixed wireless access services by the end of summer 2003 on a light licensed basis.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.2/2">The existing licence exempt 2.4 GHz frequency band may already be used for fixed wireless access services.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.2/3">Broadband services have also been made available at 3.4 GHz and 28 GHz.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.2/4">We are planning further access to other bands, in particular 3.6&ndash;4.2 GHz and 2.010&ndash;2.025 GHz, and their use for broadband applications will be considered.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.2/5">Officials in my department and the Radiocommunications Agency are working with the Broadband Stakeholders Group to explore the need for the release of further spectrum to help to achieve the Government's broadband target.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.87.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="87"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_wqn6">
	E-commerce
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.87.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100465" speakername="The Earl of Northesk" colon="" colnum="87"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_wqn6">
	<p pid="a.87.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.87.4/2" qnum="HL3797">How they responded to the 2003 IDC/World Times Information Society Index indicating that the United Kingdom has slipped out of the 10 top-performing countries from its seventh place of last year.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.87.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="87"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.87.5/1">It is disappointing to see that the United Kingdom has fallen from seventh position to eleventh in the 2003 IDC/World Times Information Society Index. However, of the G7 countries only the USA in eighth position and Canada, 10th, rank higher than the UK in the index. In other recent international surveys the UK has performed well, ranking second in the world for its environment for e-commerce in the 2002 Booz Allen Hamilton Study on the World's Most Effective Policies for the e-Economy, and joint third in the Economist Intelligence Unit's 2003 e-Readiness rankings, which looks at the extent to which a market is conducive to Internet-based opportunities in the world's sixty largest economies. The Government are continuing to pursue a range of policies with the aim of making the UK a world leader in take up and usage of information and communication technologies and we will look at the findings of the Information Society Index to see what lessons can be learned.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.88.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="88"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_wqn7">
	Competition Commission (Penalties) Order 2003
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.88.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100293" speakername="Lord Hodgson of Astley Abbotts" colon="" colnum="88"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_wqn7">
	<p pid="a.88.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.88.1/2" qnum="HL3852">To which government department are fees imposed under the Competition Commission (Penalties) Order 2003 payable.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.88.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="88"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w05.htm#30714w05_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.88.2/1">The Commission is empowered by Section 110 of the Enterprise Act 2002 to impose penalties for failure to comply with notices relating to the exercise of its investigation powers under the Act. The Competition Commission (Penalties) Order 2003 specifies the maximum penalties that may be imposed. By virtue of Section 113 of the Act, such penalties must be paid into the Consolidated Fund.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.88.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="88"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w06.htm#30714w06_wqn0">
	CAP Reform: Single Payment Scheme
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.88.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100492" speakername="Earl Peel" colon="" colnum="88"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w06.htm#30714w06_wqn0">
	<p pid="a.88.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.88.4/2" qnum="HL3782">What discretion they have secured under the reform of the common agricultural policy to introduce regulations on the single farm payment (SFP) to deal with the problem that SFP may be stripped from land by outgoers; and</p>
	<p pid="a.88.4/3" qnum="HL3784">Whether, in the light of their objective for the Tenancy Reform Industry Group &quot;to maintain the area of let land&quot;, they will consider regulations to ensure that transferability of single farm payment without land is managed in a way that is equitable as between the owner and the tenant.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.88.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="88"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w06.htm#30714w06_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.88.5/1">Under the agreement reached at the Agriculture and Fisheries Council on <phrase class="date" code="2003-06-26">26 June</phrase>, entitlements to new single payment will be allocated to farmers, irrespective of whether they are owner/occupiers or tenants, who claimed under existing CAP subsidy schemes during a historical reference period. We recognise that the option for those entitlements to transfer without land has implications for the contractual relationships between landlords and tenants. However, it should be noted that entitlements to the single payment will only be exercisable by individuals farming the corresponding areas of eligible land. It is therefore to be expected that there will be markets for land with and without entitlement in which there will be buyers and sellers, and this will be just one factor to be reflected in rents agreed between landlords and tenants. It is against that background that we shall be seeking stakeholders' views on a draft EU Commission regulation setting detailed rules for the single payment scheme, which we expect to issue in the autumn.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.89.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="89"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w06.htm#30714w06_wqn1">
	CAP Reform: Single Payment Scheme
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.89.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100492" speakername="Earl Peel" colon="" colnum="89"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w06.htm#30714w06_wqn1">
	<p pid="a.89.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="a.89.1/2" qnum="HL3783">What researchers have advised, and what representations they have received, about potential problems with regard to environmental degradation and new lettings, arising from transferability of single farm payment without land.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2003-07-14a.90.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon=":" colnum="90"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200203/ldhansrd/vo030714/text/30714w06.htm#30714w06_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.90.0/1">The Government have yet to receive the final report they commissioned on the potential environmental impacts of the European Commission's CAP reform proposals. However, it is expected that this will cover, amongst other things, the transferability of the new single payment without land. Tenant representatives supported this aspect of the Commission's proposals, while landowner representatives, with some support from the environmental community, favoured a system where the single payment could only be transferred with the land that gave rise to it. The Government remain to be convinced by the environmental arguments advanced in support of the latter view; nor do we expect transferability of entitlements to be a significant factor inhibiting new lettings.</p>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

