<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.107.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="107"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000462">
	Abortion
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.107.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100419" speakername="Baroness Masham of Ilton" colon=":" colnum="107"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000462">
	<p pid="a.107.1/1" qnum="HL2277">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether they are taking steps to reduce the number of abortions in the United Kingdom; and, if so, what form these take.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.107.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="107"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000003">
	<p pid="a.107.2/1">One of the aims of the Government's Sexual Health and HIV Strategy for England is to reduce the number of unintended pregnancies. From <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-01">1 April 2009</phrase>, the standard National Health Service contract will include the requirement that abortion service providers should provide advice, supply and fitting of the full range of methods of contraception for women undergoing abortion.</p>
	<p pid="a.107.2/2">We have invested &pound;26.8 million in 2008-09 to improve access to contraception to improve all women's knowledge of, and access to, the full range of contraception and help reduce the number of unintended pregnancies, abortion and repeat abortions. An extra &pound;20.5 million will be invested during 2009-10 for this purpose, including &pound;7 million for a contraceptive choices media campaign and a further &pound;10 million to strategic health authorities for local action.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.107.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="107"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000463">
	Abortion
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.107.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100419" speakername="Baroness Masham of Ilton" colon=":" colnum="107"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000463">
	<p pid="a.107.4/1" qnum="HL2278">To ask Her Majesty's Government how many women in Scotland aged (a) 18, (b) 17, (c) 16, (d) 15, (e) 14, (f) 13 and (g) 12 years who had an abortion in (1) 2006 and (2) 2007 had (i) one, (ii) two, (iii) three, (iv) four, and (v) five or more previous abortions.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.107.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="107"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000005">
	<p pid="a.107.5/1">This is a matter for the Scottish Government.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.107.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="107"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000464">
	Armed Forces: Urgent Operational Requirements
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.107.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100861" speakername="Lord Moonie" colon=":" colnum="107"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000464">
	<p pid="a.107.7/1" qnum="HL1901">To ask Her Majesty's Government what was the annual amount spent on urgent operational requirements by the Ministry of Defence in each year since 2002&mdash;03; in each case, how much of that amount was funded from the Ministry of Defence budget and how much was funded from HM Treasury's contingency reserve.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.107.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100844" speakername="Baroness Taylor of Bolton" colon=":" colnum="107"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000006">
	<p pid="a.107.8/1">The approval cost of urgent operational requirements (UOR) per year is shown in the table below:</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.107.8/4"> <td>Financial Year</td> <td>Approval cost</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.107.8/5"> <td>2002-03</td> <td>&pound;500 million</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.107.8/6"> <td>2003-04</td> <td>&pound;180 million</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.107.8/7"> <td>2004-05</td> <td>&pound;130 million</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.107.8/8"> <td>2005-06</td> <td>&pound;260 million</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.107.8/9"> <td>2006-07</td> <td>&pound;790 million</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.107.8/10"> <td>2007-08</td> <td>&pound;1,550 million</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.107.8/11"> <td>2008-09</td> <td>&pound;800 million</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.107.8/14">For FY2008-09, the figure given is the anticipated approval for the financial year, noting that the financial year is not yet complete.</p>
	<p pid="a.107.8/15">UOR figures are collated as approvals rather than expenditure; the answer is therefore couched in those terms. We do not have robust information on previous UOR expenditure, because these figures have not been collated centrally.</p>
	<p pid="a.107.8/16">UORs are normally funded from the reserve and not subject to repayment. There are however occasions when an urgent capability will also bring long-term benefit to the MoD, and it is therefore appropriate for the MoD to contribute to the cost of the UOR. Equally, existing funded programmes in the MoD's forward equipment plan may be brought forward for urgent operational reasons, and if reserve funding is provided to meet the urgent requirement, it may be subject to repayment.</p>
	<p pid="a.107.8/17">Exact proportions of any cost-share will vary according to the particular projects and final costs and are not held centrally. An exact breakdown of costs to the MoD and the reserve for all UORs could only be provided at disproportionate cost.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.108.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="108"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000465">
	Asylum Seekers
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.108.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon=":" colnum="108"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000465">
	<p pid="a.108.1/1" qnum="HL2149">To ask Her Majesty's Government what steps they are taking to reduce the number of asylum applicants who are detained on arrival in the United Kingdom; and whether they will review the quality of decision making under the fast-track procedure.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.108.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100956" speakername="Lord West of Spithead" colon=":" colnum="108"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000025">
	<p pid="a.108.2/1">The majority of asylum applicants are not detained while their applications are under consideration. The decision as to whether or not to detain will be made on a case-by-case basis and a person will only go into the detained fast-track process where they meet the criteria set out in the published guidance manual which can be found on the following website at <a href="http://www.homeoffice.gsi.gov.uk/IND/Manuals/Asylum/resources/Asylum_Processes_&amp;_">www.homeoffice.gsi.gov.uk/IND/Manuals/Asylum/resources/Asylum_Processes_&amp;_</a> Guidance/Detention/Guidance/DFT_DNSA_intake_ selection.doc.</p>
	<p pid="a.108.2/2">A copy of this document will be placed in the Library of the House of Commons.</p>
	<p pid="a.108.2/3">All case owners dealing with cases in the detained fast-track (DFT) process have been fully trained and give each case full and careful consideration. Each case refused asylum within the DFT process has the same avenue of appeal as for other asylum decisions. The Asylum and Immigration Tribunal upholds the case owner's decision in 97 per cent of the cases that go before it. The UK Border Agency is taking steps to further improve decision quality. The Quality Assurance Team quality assesses 10 per cent of asylum decisions, including those taken in the DFT process, per month. In addition to this, each DFT decision is reviewed by line managers or senior caseworkers.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.109.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="109"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000466">
	Asylum Seekers: Congo
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.109.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100794" speakername="Lord Roberts of Llandudno" colon=":" colnum="109"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000466">
	<p pid="a.109.1/1" qnum="HL2115">To ask Her Majesty's Government how many asylum seekers from the Congo were granted leave to remain in the United Kingdom between 2005 and 2008.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.109.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100956" speakername="Lord West of Spithead" colon=":" colnum="109"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000028">
	<p pid="a.109.2/1">Information on the number of asylum seekers, excluding dependants, from the Congo who were granted leave to remain in the United Kingdom between 2005 and 2007 is published annually in table 4.1 in the annual <I>Home Office Statistical Bulletin&mdash;Asylum Statistics United Kingdom.</I></p>
	<p pid="a.109.2/2">Statistics for 2008 are published in the table B of the supplementary web tables published with the <I>Control of Immigration: Quarterly Statistical Summary&mdash;Fourth Quarter 2008</I>. This table shows applications received for asylum in the UK (excluding dependants) and initial decisions broken down by country of nationality.</p>
	<p pid="a.109.2/3">2007 and 2008 figures are provisional and may be subject to change. These publications are available from the Library of the House and from the Home Office Research, Development and Statistics Directorate website at <a href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/immigration-asylum-stats.html">www.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/immigration-asylum-stats.html</a>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.109.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="109"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000467">
	British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.109.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon=":" colnum="109"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000467">
	<p pid="a.109.4/1" qnum="HL2258">To ask Her Majesty's Government how much they paid to the British-Irish Inter-Parliamentary Body in each year from 2003 to 2008.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.109.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100955" speakername="Lord Malloch-Brown" colon=":" colnum="109"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000031">
	<p pid="a.109.5/1">The following information about grant in aid is drawn from the accounts of the British-Irish Inter-Parliamentary Body. These payments are made in the form of grant-in-aid payments from central government.</p>
	<p pid="a.109.5/2">2001-02&mdash;&pound;95,000;</p>
	<p pid="a.109.5/3">2002-03&mdash;no grant in aid received in order to allow the body to reduce its reserves;</p>
	<p pid="a.109.5/4">2003-04&mdash;&pound;252,500;</p>
	<p pid="a.109.5/5">2004-05&mdash;&pound;210,000;</p>
	<p pid="a.109.5/6">2005-06&mdash;&pound;170,000;</p>
	<p pid="a.109.5/7">2006-07&mdash;&pound;180,000; and</p>
	<p pid="a.109.5/8">2007-08&mdash;&pound;204,300.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.110.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="110"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000468">
	Crown Prosecution Service
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.110.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100629" speakername="Lord Tebbit" colon=":" colnum="110"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000468">
	<p pid="a.110.1/1" qnum="HL2092">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Answer by Baroness Scotland of Asthal on 4 March (<I>WA 158</I>), whether in making appointments to the Crown Prosecution Service they disregard the gender, sexual orientation and ethnic origins of applicants.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.110.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="110"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000039">
	<p pid="a.110.2/1">The Crown Prosecution Service (CPS) operates under the Civil Service Commissioners' recruitment code, which upholds the principles of recruitment on the basis of fair and open competition and selection on merit.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.2/2">The CPS does not take into consideration gender, sexual orientation and ethnic origins in ensuring the most suitable candidate is appointed.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.110.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="110"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000469">
	Equality: Race
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.110.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon=":" colnum="110"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000469">
	<p pid="a.110.4/1" qnum="HL2139">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Answer by Baroness Andrews on 10 March (<I>WA 228&mdash;29</I>), how they define minority ethnic people.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.110.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="110"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000041">
	<p pid="a.110.5/1">In our discussion paper <I>Tackling Race Inequalities</I>, to which I referred in my reply to the noble Lord Ouseley on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-10">10 March</phrase> (<phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2009-03-10.229"><I>Official Report</I>, col. WA 229</phrase>), we use the term &quot;Black, Asian and minority ethnic&quot; to mean people from &quot;visible&quot; ethnic groups such as Black, South Asian and Chinese people and also Gypsies and Travellers. However, the Government are not prescriptive in their wider use of the term &quot;minority ethnic&quot; and use the terms &quot;Black and minority ethnic&quot;, &quot;Black, Asian and minority ethnic&quot;, &quot;ethnic minority&quot; and &quot;minority ethnic&quot; interchangeably.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.110.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="110"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000470">
	G20: Conference
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.110.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100341" speakername="Lord Judd" colon=":" colnum="110"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000470">
	<p pid="a.110.7/1" qnum="HL1973">To ask Her Majesty's Government what proposals they will discuss at the G20 meeting in London on 2 April to ensure that poor countries play a full part in shaping the agendas of multilateral institutions and meetings.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.110.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100955" speakername="Lord Malloch-Brown" colon=":" colnum="110"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000042">
	<p pid="a.110.8/1">We are keen to ensure that the voices of developing regions are heard at the London Summit of G20 leaders. That is why we invited Prime Minister Meles of Ethiopia as chair of the New Economic Partnership for African Development and Prime Minister Abhisit in his capacity as the chair of the Association of South East Asian Nations (ASEAN). Jean Ping, of the African Union (AU) Commission, and Dr Surin, the Secretary General of ASEAN, will also attend to further extend the representation from developing regions.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.8/2">I attended the AU Summit at the end of January 2009 and the ASEAN summit at the end of February 2009 to seek views from African and Asian leaders directly. I have also held consultations at the UN with member states, the Secretariat and specialised agencies in New York and Geneva. And on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-16">16 March 2009</phrase>, my right honourable friend the Prime Minister hosted a discussion with African leaders in London.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.8/3">We recognise the importance of protecting the poorest during the economic downturn. We will therefore be seeking action from the multilateral development banks to take immediate steps to help countries cope with the impact of the crisis on the poorest people.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.8/4">Further, as well as seeking to ensure that fiscal support is available from the International Monetary Fund on an affordable, flexible basis, we need to agree the principles for governance reform of the international financial institutions to make them more effective and legitimate. Actions at the London G20 summit to stabilise the financial system and build foundations for sustaining and strengthening global growth are essential in order to achieve this. It will be more important to ensure that growth during the economic recovery helps the poor as well as helping more developed countries.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.111.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="111"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000471">
	G20: Smoking
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.111.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100616" speakername="Lord Stoddart of Swindon" colon=":" colnum="111"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000471">
	<p pid="a.111.1/1" qnum="HL2228">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether they intend to allow smoking booths to be provided at the venue for the G20 summit in April; and, if so, whether they will amend the law to allow public houses, clubs, restaurants and employers to provide separate smoking rooms for their customers and employees.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.111.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="111"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000046">
	<p pid="a.111.2/1">Smoking booths will not be provided. The Government have no plans to amend the smokefree legislation.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.111.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="111"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000472">
	Gaza
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.111.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100467" speakername="Baroness Northover" colon=":" colnum="111"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000472">
	<p pid="a.111.4/1" qnum="HL1856">To ask Her Majesty's Government what is their response to Amnesty International's recent report, <I>Fuelling conflict: Foreign arms supplies to Israel/Gaza</I>, on the use of foreign-supplied weaponry during the recent Gaza conflict.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.111.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100955" speakername="Lord Malloch-Brown" colon=":" colnum="111"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000047">
	<p pid="a.111.5/1">I would like to reiterate what my honourable friend Bill Rammell said during the Foreign Affairs Committee evidence on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-04">4 March 2009</phrase> that it has not been clear what equipment was used by the Israeli Defence Forces in Gaza. We have therefore been undertaking our own assessment based upon a variety of sources. The Amnesty International report is a helpful contributor to that. When that process is complete we will make the information available to Parliament.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.112.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="112"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000473">
	Gaza
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.112.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100804" speakername="Lord Dykes" colon=":" colnum="112"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000473">
	<p pid="a.112.1/1" qnum="HL2181">To ask Her Majesty's Government what assessment they have made of the conclusion of Human Rights Watch that Hamas did not use civilians as human shields during the recent military action in Gaza.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.112.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100955" speakername="Lord Malloch-Brown" colon=":" colnum="112"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000048">
	<p pid="a.112.2/1">According to the Human Rights Watch letter to Foreign Ministers of <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-16">16 March 2009</phrase>, it has clearly stated that it has documented cases in which Hamas has fired rockets from very near populated homes or other civilian objects. The letter also states that launching rockets from within densely populated areas&mdash;thus making civilians in the vicinity vulnerable to counterattacks&mdash;violates the requirement to take all feasible precautions to protect civilians from harm.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.112.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="112"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000474">
	Government Buildings: Security
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.112.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100962" speakername="Baroness Neville-Jones" colon=":" colnum="112"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000474">
	<p pid="a.112.4/1" qnum="HL1929">To ask Her Majesty's Government how many breaches of physical security occurred at government buildings in each year for which figures are available; and where those breaches occurred.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.112.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100926" speakername="Lord Patel of Bradford" colon=":" colnum="112"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000049">
	<p pid="a.112.5/1">The information requested is not held centrally and can only be provided at disproportionate cost.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.112.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="112"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000475">
	Government Departments: Data Security
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.112.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100962" speakername="Baroness Neville-Jones" colon=":" colnum="112"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000475">
	<p pid="a.112.7/1" qnum="HL1930">To ask Her Majesty's Government in each year for which figures are available, how many breaches of data security involving Ministers or civil servants occurred; and in which departments those Ministers or civil servants were based.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.112.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100926" speakername="Lord Patel of Bradford" colon=":" colnum="112"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000050">
	<p pid="a.112.8/1">The reporting of data security breaches is the individual responsibility of government departments. Following the publication of the data handling report on <phrase class="date" code="2008-06-25">25 June 2008</phrase>, there is a requirement on departments to report on information risk in their annual resource accounts and this includes reporting on data security incidents. The first such reports were published by departments following the end of the 2008-09 reporting year.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.8/2">Comprehensive information on the numbers and nature of data security breaches by departments is not held centrally.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.8/3">Copies of the data handling report are available in the Library.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.113.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="113"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000476">
	Government: Ministerial Visits
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.113.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100255" speakername="Lord Greaves" colon=":" colnum="113"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000476">
	<p pid="a.113.1/1" qnum="HL2245">To ask Her Majesty's Government what were the dates and purposes of visits to the north-west that the Minister for the north-west has made in that capacity since her appointment.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.114.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="114"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0001.htm#09032440000053">
	<p pid="a.114.0/1">The information has been placed in the Library of the House.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/4"> <td>Date</td> <td>Visit</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/5"> <td>30 July 2007</td> <td>Greater Manchester sub-regional visit, incorporating:</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/6"> <td></td> <td>Meeting with GONW directors</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/7"> <td></td> <td>Meeting with SHA/NHS directors</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/8"> <td></td> <td>Meeting with GNN</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/9"> <td></td> <td>1. Meeting with representatives from Greater Manchester Local Authorities and Chamber of Commerce</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/10"> <td></td> <td>2. Visit to Salford Quays Media City with representatives from RDA, URC and English Partnerships</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/11"> <td>7 August 2007</td> <td>Meeting with farmers in Cumbria regarding foot and mouth</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/12"> <td>23 August 2007</td> <td>Merseyside sub-regional visit incorporating:</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/13"> <td></td> <td>1. Merseyside Local Authority Chief Executives</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/14"> <td></td> <td>2. Visit to Croxteth, Liverpool with Merseyside Police following the Rhys Jones shooting (visited the incident advisory group and primary school where held a press conference)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/15"> <td></td> <td>3. Mike Shields, economic regeneration consultant</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/16"> <td>6 September 2007</td> <td>Cumbria sub-regional visit incorporating:</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/17"> <td></td> <td>1. Meeting to discuss sub-regional overview set by the Sustainable Community Strategy.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/18"> <td></td> <td>2. Meeting to discuss West Cumbria Strategic Masterplan</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/19"> <td></td> <td>3. Affordable housing, Staveley</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/20"> <td></td> <td>4. Lake District National Park Authority representatives</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/21"> <td></td> <td>5. Meeting with Cumbria PCT</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/22"> <td></td> <td>6. Wash-up session&mdash;(David Higham, GONW, Peter Stybelski, Chief Executive, Cumbria County Council, Dave Harrison, NWDA, Bill Lowther, Chair of Cumbria Strategic Partnership)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/23"> <td>1 October 2007</td> <td>North West Universities Association Board Meeting &amp; Dinner, Preston</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/24"> <td>2 October 2007</td> <td>Merseyside sub-regional visit incorporating:</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/25"> <td></td> <td>1. Meeting with representatives from Knowsley Local Authority, New Deal for Communities and Housing Market Renewal</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/26"> <td></td> <td>2. Meeting with Liverpool 1</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/27"> <td></td> <td>3. Meeting with Capital Culture Company</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/28"> <td></td> <td>4. Meeting with Chief Executive of Liverpool City Council</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/29"> <td></td> <td>5. Meeting with Liverpool MPs, Deputy Chair of Culture Board and Radio Merseyside Presenter</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/30"> <td>8 October 2007</td> <td>Draft Legislative Breakfast Event, Haydock Park</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/31"> <td>18 October 2007</td> <td>1. Regional Development Agency Annual Conference, Manchester Central Convention Complex</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/32"> <td></td> <td>2. BERR consultation event (with John Hutton) for NW small and medium enterprises</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/33"> <td>29 October</td> <td>All-day visit to Lancashire:</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/34"> <td></td> <td>1. Burnley Wood</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/35"> <td></td> <td>2. Bank Top Community Centre, Blackburn</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/36"> <td></td> <td>3. Opening of Wensley Fold Children's Centre, Blackburn</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/37"> <td></td> <td>4. City Employment Strategy Meeting, Blackburn</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/38"> <td></td> <td>5. Lancashire Economic Partnership Meeting, Preston</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/39"> <td></td> <td>6. Blackpool Partners Meeting, Preston</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/40"> <td>2 November 2007</td> <td>Speech at NW Stakeholder event&mdash;Towards a Tobacco Free Future, Salford</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/41"> <td>5 November 2007</td> <td>315-degrees interview With Trevor Bates, NWDA</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/42"> <td>16 November 2007</td> <td>Speech at &quot;Make your Mark&quot; Liverpool Enterprise Week event</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/43"> <td>19 November 2007</td> <td>Cheshire sub-regional visit:</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/44"> <td></td> <td>1. Tour of Ellesmere Port Waterfront and Overpool housing and employment areas</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/45"> <td></td> <td>2. Interview with Ellesmere Port Pioneer</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/46"> <td></td> <td>3. Meeting with West Cheshire Local Authorities (Ellesmere Port and Neston Borough Council, Vale Royal Borough Council, Chester City Council and Cheshire County Council) to discuss their combined Growth Point Bid</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/47"> <td></td> <td>4. Meeting with Cheshire and Warrington Economic Alliance to discuss their strategy for economic growth in the region</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/48"> <td></td> <td>5. Meeting with Warrington Borough Council to discuss economic growth in Warrington</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/49"> <td>23 November 2007</td> <td>Speech at NW Charter Awards event, for NW local authorities, Salford</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/50"> <td>3 December 2007</td> <td>Visit to Bolton Hospital to open a children's ward; discussion of child dedicated A&amp;E provision, improving performance to reduce health inequalities</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/51"> <td>14 January 2008</td> <td>1. Meeting with GONW regional minister team</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/52"> <td></td> <td>2. Meeting with CEMVO (Council of Ethnic Minority and Voluntary organisations)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/53"> <td>28 January 2008</td> <td>1. Business breakfast with attendees from NW business community</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/54"> <td></td> <td>2. &quot;Coffee with Editors&quot; meeting with representatives from the NW media</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/55"> <td></td> <td>3. Meeting with Susan Woodward, ITV, to discuss Liverpool City Region Health is Wealth Commission</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/56"> <td>21 February 2008</td> <td>Interview with Party People as regional Minister for the north-west</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/57"> <td>25 February 2008</td> <td>Lancashire sub-regional visit incorporating:</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/58"> <td></td> <td>1. Meeting with Hazel Harding to discuss Lancashire County Council's relationship with district councils. Also to discuss Building Schools for the Future participation in Lancashire.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/59"> <td></td> <td>2. Coffee with Lancashire editors.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/60"> <td></td> <td>3. Visit to Preston Restorative Justice Centre</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/61"> <td>31 March 2008</td> <td>Launch of National Concessionary Bus Travel (Manchester)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/62"> <td>4 April 2008</td> <td>Speaking at Protecting Your Business Seminar&mdash;Business Continuity, Trafford</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/63"> <td>17 April 2008</td> <td>Meeting with Neville Chamberlain, Chair of the Northern Way (Manchester)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/64"> <td>2 June 2008</td> <td>1. Meeting with Merseyside editors</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/65"> <td></td> <td>2. Meeting with volunteers and apprentices involved in the Capital of Culture</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/66"> <td>19 June 2008</td> <td>Draft Legislative Programme Consultation event at Stretford High School, Trafford&mdash;involving parents, teachers, pupils and governors</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/67"> <td>23 June 2008</td> <td>1. Business breakfast with CBI members to discuss NW issues and DLP</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/68"> <td></td> <td>2. Speech at CLES</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/69"> <td></td> <td>3. Meeting with Sir Richard Leese&mdash;GMC, Manchester PIB, SNR, MAAs</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/70"> <td></td> <td>4. Meeting with Geoff Muirhead (MAG)&mdash;Aviation Duty and Manchester Airport</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/71"> <td></td> <td>5. Meeting with regional director, GONW</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/72"> <td>14 July 2008</td> <td>DLP consultation event in Liverpool with representatives from the equality and diversity, and 3rd sectors (Liverpool)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/73"> <td>7 August 2008</td> <td>West Cumbria sub-regional visit:</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/74"> <td></td> <td>1. Green Apprenticeships and Integrated Family Support Project</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/75"> <td></td> <td>2. Wheels to Work</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/76"> <td></td> <td>3. Meeting with Jack Ellerby and NW RAF members (2)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/77"> <td></td> <td>4. Meeting with Peter Stybelski, Cumbria CC</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/78"> <td></td> <td>5. Meeting with Richard Waite, NDA</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/79"> <td>4 September 2008</td> <td>Attendance and speech at Econ Regional Economic Framework event</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/80"> <td>20 October 2008</td> <td>Meeting with Liz Meek, GONW regional director to discuss regional issues, Manchester</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/81"> <td>21 October 2008</td> <td>Economic Development and Enterprise dinner (Manchester)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/82"> <td>22 October 2008</td> <td>Economic Development and Enterprise breakfast (Manchester)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/83"> <td>24 October 2008</td> <td>BBC NW lunch-time news interview (appearance)&mdash;government and NW response to current economic climate (Liverpool)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/84"> <td>24 October 2008</td> <td>Attendance at the signing ceremony of Merseyside Skills Pledge (Liverpool)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/85"> <td>26 October 2008</td> <td>Interview on &quot;Politics Show&quot;&mdash;government and NW response to current economic climate, Manchester</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/86"> <td>3 November 2008</td> <td>Chaired first meeting of the Joint Economic Commission for the North West (Manchester)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/87"> <td>6 November 2008</td> <td>Speech at Regional Talent Debate, Manchester</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/88"> <td>21 November 2008</td> <td>Presentations at NW Charter Awards, The Lowry</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/89"> <td>27 November 08</td> <td>Attendance at the CBI Regional Council's meeting, Liverpool</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/90"> <td>27 November 08</td> <td>Interview on &quot;Party People&quot;, ITV</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/91"> <td>4 December 08</td> <td>NW Worklessness dinner</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/92"> <td>8 December 08</td> <td>Chaired the second meeting of the Joint Economic Commission for the North West with media interviews</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/93"> <td>15 December 08</td> <td>Child Poverty Conference and sub-regional meeting with GM LA leaders and chief executives to discuss the economic downturn and sub-regional governance</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/94"> <td>08 January 09</td> <td>Regional Cabinet, Liverpool</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/95"> <td>16 January 09</td> <td>Opening of Greater Manchester SkillCentre including launch of Social Mobility White Paper</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/96"> <td>19 January 09</td> <td>Sub-regional meeting with Cheshire LA leaders and chief executives to discuss the economic downturn, sub-regional governance and alcohol harm</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/97"> <td>02 February</td> <td>Third meeting of the Joint Economic Commission for the North West, followed by chairing a public sector as employers supporting the north-west economy meeting. Media visit to JCP to promote the key messages from the morning's JEC meeting, primarily around action to help the unemployed get back in to work, also an opportunity to meet with operational managers, staff and customers of JC+ to discuss impact of current economic situation and help available</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/98"> <td>9 February 09</td> <td>Meeting with Merseyside leaders and chief executives to discuss the economic downturn, City Region and MAAs, meeting Creative Apprentices and also coffee with Merseyside editors</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/99"> <td>13 February</td> <td>Meeting with Jim Cumbes to discuss Lancashire Cricket Club</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/100"> <td>23 February</td> <td>Visit to the proposed site of '&quot;he Sharp Project&quot;; a former electronics factory in East Manchester that is being converted into a digital media production centre</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/101"> <td>2 March</td> <td>Meeting with Cheshire West and Chester Shadow Authority</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/102"> <td>16 March</td> <td>Chaired the fourth meeting of the Joint Economic Commission for the North West and a visit to Eastserve to officially announce the partnership, expansion and benefit of the project for the local community; it was also an opportunity to communicate the key messages from the JEC, East Manchester</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.114.0/103"> <td>19 March</td> <td>Attendance at the NWDA board meeting, Warrington</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.118.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="118"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000477">
	Health: GPs
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.118.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100338" speakername="Lord Jones" colon=":" colnum="118"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000477">
	<p pid="a.118.1/1" qnum="HL2110">To ask Her Majesty's Government how many general practitioners there were in the National Health Service in (a) 1998, and (b) 2008.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.118.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="118"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000205">
	<p pid="a.118.2/1">Figures for the number of general practitioners employed by the National Health Service in England in 2008 will be available when the new NHS workforce census is published on the <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-25">25 March 2009</phrase>. The table below gives the number employed in the NHS in England in 1998 and the available figure from the last workforce census which was published in April 2008.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.118.2/4"> <td colspan="3"><I>General Practitioners in England (Excluding GP Retainers andGP Registrars)</I></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.118.2/5"> <td></td> <td>Headcount</td> <td>Full-Time Equivalent (FTE)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.118.2/6"> <td>1998</td> <td>28,251</td> <td>26,455</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.118.2/7"> <td>2007</td> <td>33,364</td> <td>30,936</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.118.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="118"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000478">
	Health: Nurses
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.118.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100338" speakername="Lord Jones" colon=":" colnum="118"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000478">
	<p pid="a.118.4/1" qnum="HL2111">To ask Her Majesty's Government how many nurses there were in the National Health Service in (a) 1998, and (b) 2008.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.118.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="118"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000212">
	<p pid="a.118.5/1">Figures for the number of nurses employed by the National Health Service in England in 2008 will be available when the new NHS workforce census is published on the <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-25">25 March 2009</phrase>. The table below gives the number of nurses employed in the NHS in England in 1998 and the available figure from the last workforce census which was published in April 2008.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.118.5/4"> <td colspan="3"><I>All Qualified Nursing. Midwifery and Health Visiting Staff in England</I></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.118.5/5"> <td></td> <td>Headcount</td> <td>Full-Time Equivalent (FTE)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.118.5/6"> <td>1998</td> <td>304,563</td> <td>247,238</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.118.5/7"> <td>2007</td> <td>376,737</td> <td>307,628</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.118.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="118"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000479">
	Health: Pharmaceutical Services
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.118.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100305" speakername="Earl Howe" colon=":" colnum="118"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000479">
	<p pid="a.118.7/1" qnum="HL2176">To ask Her Majesty's Government when they expect to publish the findings of the White Paper consultation, <I>Pharmacy in England: Building on strengths&mdash;delivering the future: proposals for legislative change</I>, which closed in November 2008, in particular with regard to the market entry arrangements for community pharmacies open at least 100 hours per week.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.118.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="118"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000219">
	<p pid="a.118.8/1">Following the consultation which began on <phrase class="date" code="2008-08-27">27 August 2008</phrase> and ended on <phrase class="date" code="2008-11-20">20 November 2008</phrase>, a summary report relating to proposals for primary legislation was published on <phrase class="date" code="2009-01-16">16 January</phrase> on the department's website alongside the Health Bill. A copy of the report has been placed in the Library and it is available at <a href="http://www.dh.gov.uk/en/Consultations/Responsestoconsultations">www.dh.gov.uk/en/Consultations/Responsestoconsultations</a>.</p>
	<p pid="a.118.8/2">We are considering the responses to the consultation in respect of pharmacies opening at least 100 hours per week. A full report of the consultation will be published in due course. In the mean time, the current system remains in place.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.118.9" nospeaker="true" colnum="118"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000480">
	Houses of Parliament: Copyright
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.118.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100367" speakername="Lord Lester of Herne Hill" colon=":" colnum="118"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000480">
	<p pid="a.118.10/1" qnum="HL2382">To ask the Chairman of Committees who receives the income generated from the sale of House of Lords papers protected by parliamentary copyright; and what is the annual net profit derived from such sales in each of the last five years.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.118.11" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100067" speakername="Lord Brabazon of Tara" colon=":" colnum="118"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000221">
	<p pid="a.118.11/1">Parliamentary copyright has no bearing on the arrangements for the sale of parliamentary papers: all House of Lords parliamentary copyright publications are available free of charge online. The distribution of printed parliamentary publications is managed as a public service concession contract, which means that the supplier, The Stationery Office (TSO), does not charge the House of Lords for the service of distributing publications to the public, but keeps the revenue from any sales. In the absence of such an arrangement, any shortfall in TSO's revenue would necessarily be met, under the terms of a revised contract, from the public purse. The amount of revenue generated from sales is a matter for TSO.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.119.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="119"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000481">
	Houses of Parliament: Interns
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.119.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon=":" colnum="119"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000481">
	<p pid="a.119.1/1" qnum="HL1978">To ask Her Majesty's Government what arrangements they have made to ensure that university students from the United States can obtain permission to work as interns during the summer of 2009, in particular in the Houses of Parliament.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.119.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100956" speakername="Lord West of Spithead" colon=":" colnum="119"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000222">
	<p pid="a.119.2/1">The Government's new points-based system for managing migration provides a number of routes which could be used by students from the United States wishing to undertake internships in the UK.</p>
	<p pid="a.119.2/2">Under tier 4, the rules for which were laid before Parliament on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-09">9 March</phrase> (HC 314) and which are due to take effect from <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-31">31 March</phrase>, students on overseas degree courses may undertake a course-related internship placement provided they also spend some time studying in the UK and provided that the length of internship does not exceed the time spent studying in this country.</p>
	<p pid="a.119.2/3">Under tier 5, temporary workers, there is a sub-category for government-authorised exchange (GAE) schemes. A GAE requires the support of a government department and would need to be compliant with all relevant UK laws, including national minimum wage legislation but one could be created to accommodate internship exchanges for those interns interested purely in taking a work placement in the UK. UKBA officials are currently discussing options for such a scheme with interested departments.</p>
	<p pid="a.119.2/4">The tier 5 youth mobility scheme (YMS), which allows young participants to do most work of choice during their stay in the UK, could also be used to provide a route for US interns if the USA decides to join the scheme and is able to meet the qualifying criteria.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.119.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="119"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000482">
	Housing
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.119.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100255" speakername="Lord Greaves" colon=":" colnum="119"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000482">
	<p pid="a.119.4/1" qnum="HL2146">To ask Her Majesty's Government what assessment they have made of the extent to which investment in labour-intensive housing and infrastructure schemes can contribute towards both alleviating the current economic situation and increasing employment levels; and whether they took that into account when announcing on 28 February funding levels for the housing market renewal pathfinder schemes which will reduce funding by approximately 9 per cent between 2008&mdash;09 and 2009&mdash;10 and between 2009&mdash;10 and 2010&mdash;11.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.119.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="119"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000226">
	<p pid="a.119.5/1">Decisions to grant funding to the housing market renewal programme for 2008-11 were taken as part of allocations within the Department of Communities and Local Government following the Comprehensive Spending Review 2007.</p>
	<p pid="a.119.5/2">The funding reflects in part the initial success of the programme in narrowing the gaps in house prices and vacancies between pathfinders and their regions. It also recognises the need to tackle problems of deep-seated structural need and to ensure that the housing market renewal and growth programmes can be taken forward together where appropriate. The total of approximately &pound;2.2 billion invested since 2002 represents a very substantial local economic stimulus and the programme is bringing back confidence to areas that have been neglected for too long, something that is particularly important in times of economic uncertainty. The announcement on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-10">10 March 2009</phrase> confirming funding allocations for 2009-10, gives further incentive to pathfinders to focus on outcomes precisely to help stimulate local economic activity.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.120.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="120"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000483">
	Ibrahim Moussawi
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.120.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100944" speakername="Lord Pearson of Rannoch" colon=":" colnum="120"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000483">
	<p pid="a.120.1/1" qnum="HL2147">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether they intend to allow Dr Ibrahim Moussawi to visit the United Kingdom; and whether they will use the same criteria in reaching that decision as were used in refusing entry to Mr Geert Wilders in February.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.120.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100956" speakername="Lord West of Spithead" colon=":" colnum="120"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000228">
	<p pid="a.120.2/1">Dr Moussawi has been refused a visa under paragraph 320(19) of the Immigration Rules on the grounds that his presence in the UK would not be conducive to the public good.</p>
	<p pid="a.120.2/2">Geert Wilders was refused admission to the UK under regulation 19 of the Immigration (European Economic Area) Regulations 2006 because, in accordance with regulation 21 of the same regulations, an immigration officer was satisfied that his exclusion was justified on grounds of public policy and/or public security.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.120.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="120"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000484">
	Immigration: Detention Centres
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.120.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon=":" colnum="120"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000484">
	<p pid="a.120.4/1" qnum="HL2150">To ask Her Majesty's Government how they will reduce the length of time that individuals are held in immigration and asylum detention centres; and how many people are detained for more than one year.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.120.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100956" speakername="Lord West of Spithead" colon=":" colnum="120"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000230">
	<p pid="a.120.5/1">It is important that those who apply for asylum in the UK have their application processed as quickly, as possible and that is why we have set a target to conclude 90 per cent of asylum applications within six months by December 2011. In order to effect removal of those who have committed crimes in the UK at the earliest opportunity, the early removal scheme and the facilitated returns scheme are available specifically for foreign national prisoners who meet the qualifying criteria. Under these incentives removals take place considerably more quickly decreasing pressures on prisons and the UK Border Agency's detention estate.</p>
	<p pid="a.120.5/2">Detention will always be for as short a time as possible and for no longer than is necessary. However, detention is often prolonged by individuals and families with no right to be here refusing to leave voluntarily and frustrating our attempts to remove them. They can voluntarily leave the UK at any point.</p>
	<p pid="a.120.5/3">Published management information indicates that as at <phrase class="date" code="2008-12-27">27 December 2008</phrase>, a total of 150 persons were recorded as being detained within the UK Border Agency's detention estate solely under Immigration Act powers for one year or more. This figure is rounded to the nearest five, has not been quality-assured under National Statistics protocols, is subject to change and should be treated as provisional. This is the latest date for which published statistics are available.</p>
	<p pid="a.120.5/4">National statistics on persons detained solely under Immigration Act powers on a snapshot basis are published quarterly. This information is published in tables 9-11 of the <I>Control of Immigration: Quarterly Statistical Summary</I>, United Kingdom bulletins, which are available from the Library of the House and from the Home Office's Research, Development and Statistics website at <a href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/immigration-asylum-stats.html">www.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/immigration-asylum-stats.html</a>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.121.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="121"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000485">
	Immigration: Detention Centres
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.121.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon=":" colnum="121"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000485">
	<p pid="a.121.1/1" qnum="HL2189">To ask Her Majesty's Government why (a) Mr Ahmed Abu Bakar Hassam has been held at Oakington detention centre for 28 months; and (b) Mr Ali Saifi has been held at Colnbrook detention centre for 22 months.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.121.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100956" speakername="Lord West of Spithead" colon=":" colnum="121"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000234">
	<p pid="a.121.2/1">Information contained in individual records held by the UK Border Agency is treated as being confidential and is not normally disclosed to third parties.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/2">This is, of course, unless they are authorised representatives of the individual concerned. This is not a question of secrecy for its own sake but simply a matter of protecting the privacy of the individual.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.121.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="121"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000486">
	International Festivals and Competitions
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.121.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100794" speakername="Lord Roberts of Llandudno" colon=":" colnum="121"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000486">
	<p pid="a.121.4/1" qnum="HL2174">To ask Her Majesty's Government what guidelines are provided to competitors from overseas to enable them to enter the United Kingdom and participate in international festivals and competitions.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.121.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100956" speakername="Lord West of Spithead" colon=":" colnum="121"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000236">
	<p pid="a.121.5/1">Those seeking entry to the United Kingdom in order to take part in international festivals and competitions may, depending on circumstances, seek entry as either sports or entertainer visitors.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.5/2">Full guidance on whether participants would qualify as visitors or whether they would be required to seek entry under the points-based system is publicly available on both the UKBA and visa services websites.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.122.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="122"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000487">
	Licensing Act
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.122.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100130" speakername="Lord Clement-Jones" colon=":" colnum="122"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000487">
	<p pid="a.122.1/1" qnum="HL2235">To ask Her Majesty's Government what is the current status of their review of the live music provisions of the Licensing Act 2003.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.122.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100164" speakername="Lord Davies of Oldham" colon=":" colnum="122"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000238">
	<p pid="a.122.2/1">There is no formal review of the live music provisions of the Licensing Act 2003. However, the Department for Culture, Media and Sport continues to discuss the effect of the Licensing Act 2003 on live music with representatives of musicians and local government. These discussions include consideration of how low impact live music events might be further encouraged.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.122.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="122"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000488">
	Migrant Workers: Employment
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.122.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100804" speakername="Lord Dykes" colon=":" colnum="122"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000488">
	<p pid="a.122.4/1" qnum="HL2180">To ask Her Majesty's Government what results they expect from the European Union blue card entry system for highly skilled entrants from third countries, and what proportion of entrants they expect to apply to be United Kingdom entry under the new tier two provisions.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.122.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100956" speakername="Lord West of Spithead" colon=":" colnum="122"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000239">
	<p pid="a.122.5/1">The United Kingdom has not opted into the directive on the entry and residence of third country nationals for the purpose of highly qualified employment. It is not possible for the Government to reliably predict how many of those admitted onto the territory of another member state as the holder of a blue card issued under the terms of the directive will subsequently apply for admission to the United Kingdom under the points-based system, or which tier of the points-based system they would seek to access. However, since the UK has not opted into the directive, any such worker would need to meet the full criteria of the points-based system in the same way as a person seeking admission from outside the European Union.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.122.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="122"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000489">
	NHS: Hospital Referral
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.122.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100130" speakername="Lord Clement-Jones" colon=":" colnum="122"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000489">
	<p pid="a.122.7/1" qnum="HL2282">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether, in circumstances where the general practitioner and the patient agree on the hospital to which the patient will be referred, primary care trusts can override their wishes and deny access to the relevant hospital.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.122.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="122"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000240">
	<p pid="a.122.8/1">From <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-01">1 April 2009</phrase> patients will have a legal right to choose the organisation that provides their treatment when they are referred to a consultant-led service for their first outpatient appointment, and to information to support that choice. The right to choice will develop as choice is extended into other areas. The right is underpinned by legally binding directions from the Secretary of State to primary care trusts (PCTs).</p>
	<p pid="a.122.8/2">The standard National Health Service contract for acute services says &quot;the provider shall accept all clinically appropriate referrals of patients&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.122.8/3">Under Free Choice, patients are able to choose from a national menu of services provided by National Health Service and nationally appointed independent sector providers. General practitioners (GPs) will be able to refer to any clinically appropriate provider and it will be for the referring clinician to guide the patient through the clinical aspects of their options as appropriate. GPs referral will continue to constitute authority to treat on behalf of the PCT. PCTs commissioning arrangements will not restrict where patients are offered choice.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.123.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="123"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000490">
	Northern Ireland Office: Bonuses
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.123.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon=":" colnum="123"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000490">
	<p pid="a.123.1/1" qnum="HL2218">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Answer by Baroness Royall of Blaisdon on 24 February (<I>WA 60&mdash;61</I>) concerning bonus payments to the Northern Ireland Office, when was the last time a review of the administrative budget led to a reduction in that budget.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.123.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100828" speakername="Baroness Royall of Blaisdon" colon=":" colnum="123"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000243">
	<p pid="a.123.2/1">The Northern Ireland Office reviews all budgets, including administration budgets, on an ongoing basis.</p>
	<p pid="a.123.2/2">As part of the 2007 Comprehensive Spending Review settlement, the department was required to make 5 per cent per annum savings in administration costs which were recycled to front line programmes.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.123.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="123"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000491">
	Northern Ireland Office: Electricity
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.123.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon=":" colnum="123"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000491">
	<p pid="a.123.4/1" qnum="HL1822">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Answer by Baroness Royall of Blaisdon on 24 February (<I>WA 61</I>) concerning the cost of electricity for the Northern Ireland Office, why the cost rose 61 per cent between 2003&mdash;04 and 2007&mdash;08.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.123.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100828" speakername="Baroness Royall of Blaisdon" colon=":" colnum="123"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0003.htm#09032440000245">
	<p pid="a.123.5/1">An analysis of the costs has shown that there are two main reasons for the increase in the department's (excluding agencies and Executive NDPBs) electricity expenditure between 2003-04 and 2007-08.</p>
	<p pid="a.123.5/2">an increase in charges from approximately &pound;0.085 to &pound;0.113 per unit consumed. This is equivalent to a 33 per cent price rise. The department does not hold details of the units of electricity consumed in 2003-04, so it is not possible to compare consumption totals; andan increase in staff numbers from 1,032 to 1,251 (a 21 per cent rise). This has resulted in increased accommodation costs, including electricity. During this period the Public Prosecution Service (PPS)&mdash;whose staff are included in these numbers&mdash;have increased from 237 to 546 staff (an increase of 309). The PPS was established in June 2005 by the Justice (NI) Act 2002 and is now responsible for all criminal cases previously prosecuted by the Department of the Director of Public Prosecutions (DPPNI) and the Police Service of Northern Ireland (PSNI). The PPS has been implemented over a number of phases from 2003 onwards and staffing levels have increased accordingly. Excluding the Public Prosecution Service, the department's staff numbers have actually decreased over the period.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.124.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="124"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000492">
	Northern Ireland Office: Staff
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.124.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon=":" colnum="124"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000492">
	<p pid="a.124.1/1" qnum="HL1535">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Answer by Baroness Royall of Blaisdon on 9 February (<I>WA 166</I>), why salary and pension costs for Northern Ireland Office staff have risen 78 per cent in the six years to 2007&mdash;08 from &pound;29.532 million to &pound;51.636 million; and what were the numeric and percentage increases in staff in those years.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.124.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100828" speakername="Baroness Royall of Blaisdon" colon=":" colnum="124"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000246">
	<p pid="a.124.2/1">There are three main reasons for the department's salary and pension costs increasing from &pound;29.532 million to &pound;51.636 million in the sixyears to 2007-08:</p>
	<p pid="a.124.2/2"><I>Increase in staff numbers</I></p>
	<p pid="a.124.2/3">The staff numbers for the Northern Ireland Office, excluding its agencies and Executive NDPBs, since 2001-02 are shown in the following table.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.124.2/6"> <td>Financial Year</td> <td>Staff Numbers</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.124.2/7"> <td>2001-02</td> <td>886</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.124.2/8"> <td>2002-03</td> <td>926</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.124.2/9"> <td>2003-04</td> <td>1,032</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.124.2/10"> <td>2004-05</td> <td>1,091</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.124.2/11"> <td>2005-06</td> <td>1,191</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.124.2/12"> <td>2006-07</td> <td>1,233</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.124.2/13"> <td>2007-08</td> <td>1,251</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.124.2/16">This represents an increase 365 staff in the six-year period which equates to a percentage increase of 41.2 per cent.</p>
	<p pid="a.124.2/17">However, during this period the Public Prosecution Service (PPS)&mdash;whose staff are included in these numbers&mdash;has increased from 159 to 546 staff (an increase of 387). The PPS was established in June 2005 by the Justice (NI) Act 2002 and is now responsible for all criminal cases previously prosecuted by the Department of the Director of Public Prosecutions (DPPNI) and the Police Service of Northern Ireland (PSNI). The PPS has been implemented over a number of phases from 2003 onwards and staffing levels have increased accordingly.</p>
	<p pid="a.124.2/18">Excluding the Public Prosecution Service, the department's staff numbers have actually decreased over the period.</p>
	<p pid="a.124.2/19"><I>Annual pay increases</I></p>
	<p pid="a.124.2/20">The average annual pay increases for Northern Ireland Office staff, excluding its agencies and Executive NDPBs, since 2001-02 have also affected the total cost. The average increase has been 3.78 per cent per annum during this period.</p>
	<p pid="a.124.2/21"><I>Superannuation Increases</I></p>
	<p pid="a.124.2/22">The majority of staff belong to the PCSPS or PCSPS(NI) schemes. The employers accruing superannuation liability charges (ASLCs) for these schemes have risen over the period since 2001-02.</p>
	<p pid="a.124.2/23">In 2001-02, the ASLC rates ranged between 12.0 per cent and 20.5 per cent of pensionable pay, depending on pensionable salary. The rates in 2007-08 ranged between 16.5 per cent and 23.5 per cent, also depending on pensionable salary.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.125.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="125"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000493">
	Nuclear Plants: Security
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.125.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100275" speakername="Lord Harris of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="125"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000493">
	<p pid="a.125.1/1" qnum="HL2100">To ask Her Majesty's Government who is responsible for assessing the security risks associated with the protection of (a) the Sellafield nuclear reprocessing plant, and (b) Dounreay nuclear establishment; and how that risk assessment is fed into the funding and support for the Civil Nuclear Constabulary.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.125.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="125"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000271">
	<p pid="a.125.2/1">The Office for Civil Nuclear Security (OCNS) is the security regulator for the civil nuclear industry. It regulates security arrangements for the protection of nuclear and radioactive material on licensed civil nuclear sites, nuclear transports and sensitive information under the Nuclear Industries Security Regulations 2003. The OCNS is part of the Health and Safety Executive and conducts its regulatory activities on behalf of the Secretary of State for Energy and Climate Change.</p>
	<p pid="a.125.2/2">The Civil Nuclear Constabulary is administered by the Civil Nuclear Police Authority (CNPA), a non-departmental public body set up by the Energy Act 2004. Under this Act, the director of Civil Nuclear Security, who has formal links with the national intelligence services, directs the CNPA on security matters including which sites require an armed response and minimum police numbers required to fulfil this.</p>
	<p pid="a.125.2/3">The CNPA is part of central government accounts, but they are expected to recover their full economic costs each year from those to whom they provide services, although not to make a profit. Those receiving statutory services from the CNPA are under a statutory obligation to pay the associated costs. Chiefly, these are the nuclear operators whose sites the CNC police.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.125.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="125"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000494">
	Nuclear Plants: Security
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.125.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100275" speakername="Lord Harris of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="125"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000494">
	<p pid="a.125.4/1" qnum="HL2101">To ask Her Majesty's Government who is responsible for assessing whether the arrangements to protect civil nuclear establishments are adequate.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.126.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="126"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000274">
	<p pid="a.126.0/1">The Office for Civil Nuclear Security (OCNS) is the security regulator for the UK's civil nuclear industry. It regulates security arrangements for the protection of nuclear and radioactive material on licensed civil nuclear sites, nuclear transports and sensitive information under the Nuclear Industries Security Regulations 2003. The OCNS is part of the Health and Safety Executive and conducts its regulatory activities on behalf of the Secretary of State for Energy and Climate Change.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.126.1" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="126"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000495">
	Nuclear Plants: Security
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.126.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100275" speakername="Lord Harris of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="126"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000495">
	<p pid="a.126.2/1" qnum="HL2102">To ask Her Majesty's Government who is responsible for assessing whether the support available to the Civil Nuclear Constabulary from other police forces is adequate.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.126.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="126"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000275">
	<p pid="a.126.3/1">The chief constable, having operational command of the constabulary, works closely with other police forces to ensure that effective support is available to the Civil Nuclear Constabulary (CNC). Such support is the subject of a separate Memorandum of Understanding between the CNC and each territorial force in whose operational area the CNC is deployed. The extent and the nature of the support is an operational policing matter.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.126.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="126"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000496">
	Ofcom
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.126.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100427" speakername="Baroness Miller of Chilthorne Domer" colon=":" colnum="126"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000496">
	<p pid="a.126.5/1" qnum="HL2156">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether they will divide the functions of Ofcom into separate regulators for telecommunications and media in order to avoid potential conflicts of interest within Ofcom.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.126.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100982" speakername="Lord Carter of Barnes" colon=":" colnum="126"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000276">
	<p pid="a.126.6/1">In 2003, the Office of Communications (Ofcom) replaced the functions and duties of five separate regulatory bodies&mdash;the Broadcasting Standards Commission, the Independent Television Commission, the Office of Telecommunications, the Radio Authority, and the Radiocommunications Agency. This was done in response to convergence in the telecoms, broadcasting and radio spectrum markets and the need for joined-up regulation in those markets. After five years there are no plans to reintroduce separation.</p>
	<p pid="a.126.6/2">Under the Communications Act 2003, Ofcom has the power to regulate the UK's broadcasting, telecommunications and wireless communications sectors. It also allows Ofcom to set and enforce rules on fair competition between companies in these industries.</p>
	<p pid="a.126.6/3">Procedures have been put in place to deal with potential conflicts of interest. These are that in general no member of Ofcom may have interests in companies where a significant part of their activities are those of an Ofcom-regulated company. If a member is in a position where they do have a conflict of interest, then such member will be advised by the corporation secretary on appropriate action to take. This can include a redaction from part of a meeting, disposal of an interest or resigning from a role. A register of all members' interests is available and published on Ofcom's website at <a href="http://www.ofcom.org.uk/about/csg/">www.ofcom.org.uk/about/csg/</a>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.127.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000497">
	Pakistan
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.127.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100489" speakername="Lord Patten" colon=":" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000497">
	<p pid="a.127.1/1" qnum="HL2050">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether they have made or intend to make representations to the Government of Pakistan about allegations that religious minorities were denied full participation in the Senate election held on 4 March.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.127.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100955" speakername="Lord Malloch-Brown" colon=":" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000279">
	<p pid="a.127.2/1">Representatives from religious minorities were unable to participate in the Senate election held on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-04">4 March 2009</phrase> because legislation to reserve Senate seats for minorities has yet to be passed. On <phrase class="date" code="2008-12-16">16 December 2008</phrase>, Prime Minister Gilani announced that five seats would be set aside in the Senate for minorities and the recently appointed Minister for Minorities has committed to take this forward through the National Assembly.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.2/2">Following Pakistan's parliamentary elections in February 2008, the EU Election Observation Mission issued a report which stressed the need for increased participation of minorities in the election process. We have endorsed these recommendations and are working with the EU to identify ways to support the strengthening of democratic institutions including by encouraging the participation of minorities in the election process.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.127.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000498">
	People Trafficking
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.127.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100321" speakername="Lord Hylton" colon=":" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000498">
	<p pid="a.127.4/1" qnum="HL2256">To ask Her Majesty's Government how the UK Border Agency will alter its advice and support for victims of trafficking following the requests made by the chief executive of the Immigration Advisory Service.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.127.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100956" speakername="Lord West of Spithead" colon=":" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000281">
	<p pid="a.127.5/1">We are giving due consideration to the views put forward by the chief executive of the Immigration Advisory Service. A number of them are reflected in the plans we have in place for identifying and supporting victims of trafficking under the Council of Europe Convention on Action against Trafficking in Human Beings, which will improve significantly our ability to identify and protect victims of trafficking. We are committed to keeping the new arrangements under review as part of our long-term trafficking strategy.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.127.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000499">
	Petitions
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.127.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100255" speakername="Lord Greaves" colon=":" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000499">
	<p pid="a.127.7/1" qnum="HL2077">To ask Her Majesty's Government how many petitions the Cabinet Office received in (a) 2007 and (b) 2008; what steps the office has taken to publicise them; and whether they will place the text of the petitions received and the number of signatures in the Library of the House.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.7/2" qnum="HL2078">To ask Her Majesty's Government what procedures the Cabinet Office has for receiving, acknowledging, dealing with and responding to petitions that it receives from members of the public.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.128.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100828" speakername="Baroness Royall of Blaisdon" colon=":" colnum="128"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000282">
	<p pid="a.128.0/1">Records show the Cabinet Office did not receive any petitions in 2007. In 2008, one petition was received. Once petitions are received they are recorded and handled in the same way as correspondence from the public which would involve sending an acknowledgement followed by a substantive reply. There are no plans to publish petitions or place them in the Library of the House.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.128.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="128"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000500">
	Retail Developments
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.128.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100907" speakername="Lord Cotter" colon=":" colnum="128"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000500">
	<p pid="a.128.2/1" qnum="HL2131">To ask Her Majesty's Government what measures they are taking to allow councils to protect local businesses and town centres from large out-of-town retail developments.</p>
	<p pid="a.128.2/2" qnum="HL2132">To ask Her Majesty's Government what steps they will take to ensure local authorities have the power to determine what retail developments best address their communities' needs.</p>
	<p pid="a.128.2/3" qnum="HL2133">To ask Her Majesty's Government what measures they are taking to sustain local town centres in the current economic climate.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.128.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="128"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000283">
	<p pid="a.128.3/1">The Government have put in place strong policies in Planning Policy Statement 6: <I>Planning for Town Centres </I>(PPS6), to allow local authorities to sustain and enhance their town centres. PPS6 asks local planning authorities to plan positively and proactively for their town centres with growth focused in existing centres in order to strengthen them, and where appropriate, regenerate them.</p>
	<p pid="a.128.3/2">PPS6 asks local planning authorities, in conjunction with stakeholders and the community, to assess the need for new retail development and identify deficiencies in provision. They should then put in place strong policies based on strategies that reflect their local vision and which are supported by a good evidence base.</p>
	<p pid="a.128.3/3">We will shortly be publishing revised planning policy for town centres in which the need and impact tests in PPS6, published in March 2005, will be replaced by a more effective and enhanced assessment of the impacts of new proposals outside town centres. Practice guidance on assessing need, impact and the sequential approach will be published at the same time to ensure that the town-centre first policy is implemented consistently.</p>
	<p pid="a.128.3/4">The Government have developed various policies and tools to promote vibrant and attractive town centres. We are considering what further steps might be taken to assist town centres in the current economic climate.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.129.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="129"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000501">
	Smoking
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.129.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon=":" colnum="129"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000501">
	<p pid="a.129.1/1" qnum="HL2321">To ask Her Majesty's Government how many people died in England and Wales as a result of smoking-related illnesses from 2005 to date.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.129.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100926" speakername="Lord Patel of Bradford" colon=":" colnum="129"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000287">
	<p pid="a.129.2/1">The information requested falls within the responsibility of the UK Statistics Authority. I have asked the authority to reply.</p>
	<p pid="a.129.2/2"><I>Letter from Karen Dunnell, National Statistician, to Lord Laird, dated March 2009.</I></p>
	<p pid="a.129.2/3">As National Statistician, I have been asked to reply to your recent Question asking how many people died in England and Wales as a result of smoking-related illnesses from 2005 to date. (HL2321)</p>
	<p pid="a.129.2/4">Deaths due to smoking-related illness cannot be directly estimated, as smoking status is not included on the death certificate. However, research published by the then Health Development Agency in 2004 suggested that, in the period 1998 to 2002, an annual average of 92,500 deaths were attributable to smoking in England and Wales.<sup>1</sup></p>
	<p pid="a.129.2/5" class="indent">1. Twigg L, Moon G, Walker S (2004) <I>The smoking epidemic in England</I>. London; Health Development Agency</p>
	<p pid="a.129.2/6" class="indent">Background note</p>
	<p pid="a.129.2/7" class="indent">1. A consultation document on premature and avoidable mortality, which included a section on smoking-related deaths, was published on the ONS website in November 2005. A response to this consultation was published on <phrase class="date" code="2006-09-15">15 September 2006</phrase>, which stated that although the consultation revealed support for an indicator of smoking-related deaths, ONS did not have the resources available at that time to take forward this development.</p>
	<p pid="a.129.2/8" class="indent">2. The report published by the Health Development Agency in 2004 is available at <a href="http://www.nice.org.uk/aboutnice/whoweare/aboutthehda/">www.nice.org.uk/aboutnice/whoweare/aboutthehda/</a> hdapublications/smoking_epidemic_in_england.jsp.</p>
	<p pid="a.129.2/9" class="indent">3. In 2007, the NHS Information Centre (IC) published a report, &quot;Statistics on Smoking: England, 2007&quot;, in which an estimated figure of 81,900 was presented for the number of deaths caused by smoking in England, 2005. This figure was not used in the Answer, since although it is for a more recent year, it relates to England only. The number is very similar to that stated for England only in the HPA report (86,500 deaths). The IC report is available at <a href="http://www.ic.nhs.uk/webfiles/publications/Smoking%20">www.ic.nhs.uk/webfiles/publications/Smoking%20</a> bulletin/Smoking%202007/Statistics%20on%20Smoking%20 England%202007%20with%20links%20with%20buttons.pdf.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.129.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="129"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000502">
	Sport: Funding
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.129.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100130" speakername="Lord Clement-Jones" colon=":" colnum="129"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000502">
	<p pid="a.129.4/1" qnum="HL1829">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Answer by Lord Carter of Barnes on 27 February (<I>WA 114</I>) on funding systems for sports and leisure projects, to what extent the Answer was informed by or took account of the conclusions of the Audit Commission report of January 2009, <I>Tired of Hanging Around</I>.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.130.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100164" speakername="Lord Davies of Oldham" colon=":" colnum="130"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0004.htm#09032440000291">
	<p pid="a.130.0/1">The Written Answer of <phrase class="date" code="2009-02-27">27 February</phrase> provided a response based on efficiency savings that are currently being made within sport and leisure at a national level.</p>
	<p pid="a.130.0/2">The Audit Commission's <I>Tired of Hanging Around</I> report highlighted the benefits of sport and leisure activities and their role in preventing anti-social behaviour. The report did not take into account the successes of the PE and Sport Strategy for Young People, through which the Department for Children Schools and Families and Culture Media and Sport has increased the quantity and quality of the sport offer for all young people.</p>
	<p pid="a.130.0/3">The report examined projects delivered predominantly with local funding, and while my department welcomes the report's focus on the importance of positive activities for young people, it does not recognise the report's presentation of the funding system for sports and leisure projects. We believe the current system continues to provide opportunities for those suffering from social exclusion in an effective and streamlined way.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.130.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="130"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0005.htm#09032440000503">
	Terrorism
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.130.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100489" speakername="Lord Patten" colon=":" colnum="130"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0005.htm#09032440000503">
	<p pid="a.130.2/1" qnum="HL2051">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether they have made or intend to make representations to the Government of Pakistan concerning threats made to the defence lawyer representing Mr Hector Aleem, who is charged in the terrorist court with making blasphemous telephone calls.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-03-24a.130.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100955" speakername="Lord Malloch-Brown" colon=":" colnum="130"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90324w0005.htm#09032440000294">
	<p pid="a.130.3/1">We are aware of Mr Aleem's detention and are concerned about the reports of threats that his lawyer has received. Officials in our High Commission in Islamabad have established that Pakistan's Ministry for Human Rights is already engaged in Mr Aleem's case and will monitor developments in this case through the Government of Pakistan.</p>
	<p pid="a.130.3/2">Through the EU and UN Human Rights Council we regularly raise with the Government of Pakistan the need to ensure protection for human rights defenders such as lawyers acting in blasphemy cases. Through programme and project work, we also support the work of human rights defenders and civil society enhancing their capacity to act as advocates and support our human rights objectives.</p>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

