<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.219.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="219"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000716">
	Afghanistan
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.219.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100341" speakername="Lord Judd" colon=":" colnum="219"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000716">
	<p pid="a.219.1/1" qnum="HL4242">To ask Her Majesty's Government what is their latest assessment of the effectiveness of co-operation between the Department for International Development and the Ministry of Defence in the more unstable parts of Afghanistan.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.219.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100072" speakername="Lord Brett" colon=":" colnum="219"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000003">
	<p pid="a.219.2/1">Civilian and military co-operation is vital to the success of the international effort in Afghanistan. Staff from the Department for International Development (DfID), the Ministry of Defence (MoD) and the Foreign and Commonwealth Office (FCO) work together in the Helmand Provincial Reconstruction Team (PRT) to deliver the activities guided by the Helmand road map, a shared single plan of action. The joint effort of the PRT has ensured that significant progress has been made to meet the needs of the local population and build the capacity and capability of the Afghanistan Government to deliver security, governance and development to the people of Helmand.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.219.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="219"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000717">
	Armed Forces: Compensation Scheme
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.219.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100444" speakername="Lord Morris of Manchester" colon=":" colnum="219"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000717">
	<p pid="a.219.4/1" qnum="HL4187">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether they plan to return the burden of proof under the Armed Forces compensation scheme to the Secretary of State for Defence.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.219.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100844" speakername="Baroness Taylor of Bolton" colon=":" colnum="219"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000004">
	<p pid="a.219.5/1">We have no plans to change the burden of proof, nor remove the time limit for claims made under the Armed Forces compensation scheme.</p>
	<p pid="a.219.5/2">The standard of proof used in the Armed Forces compensation scheme is based on the balance of probabilities. This is the accepted approach in other schemes, such as the criminal injuries compensation scheme, and in the civil courts. No case should fail where there is reasonable, reliable evidence that injury is due to service and the department is not aware of any examples to date of anyone who deserves an award being denied it due to the burden of proof.</p>
	<p pid="a.219.5/3">The Service Personnel Command Paper, <I>The Nation's Commitment: Cross-Government Support to </I><I>O</I><I>ur Armed Forces, </I><I>T</I><I>heir families and </I><I>V</I><I>eterans</I>, laid out our commitment to double the tax-free lump sum for the most serious injuries, raising the maximum lump sum payment to &pound;570,000. All recipients, according to the severity of their injuries, were entitled to an uplift of between 10 and 100 per cent in their upfront lump sum payment. Together with the index-linked, tax-free, annual guaranteed payment, this means the maximum total compensation is now in excess of &pound;1.5 million. All those who have received awards since the start of the scheme in 2005 have benefited from these changes, and all additional payments have now been actioned and paid, meeting the April 2009 deadline.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.220.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="220"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000718">
	Armed Forces: Severely Wounded
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.220.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100444" speakername="Lord Morris of Manchester" colon=":" colnum="220"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000718">
	<p pid="a.220.1/1" qnum="HL4189">To ask Her Majesty's Government what action they are taking to ensure a seamless transition from military to civilian healthcare and ongoing care for severely injured or disabled service personnel.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.220.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100844" speakername="Baroness Taylor of Bolton" colon=":" colnum="220"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000007">
	<p pid="a.220.2/1">The majority of personnel who suffer serious injuries, including those who do not return to full fitness, who wish to continue in-service are able to do so, provided that there are worthwhile military roles for them to fulfil. Such cases will continue to receive treatment and rehabilitation from the Defence Medical Services (DMS) for as long as they remain in the Armed Forces.</p>
	<p pid="a.220.2/2">In those cases where a decision has to be taken medically to discharge an individual, the specific DMS team which has been caring for that individual will begin a liaison with appropriate civilian healthcare providers (eg the general practitioner, primary care trust, civilian mental health team or NHS trust) to ensure the transfer of care and the patient's records takes place. In addition, we have specialist health social workers who manage the individual's wider resettlement issues, liaising with relevant civil agencies such as local housing authorities, financial authorities, service welfare and charitable organisations with the aim of ensuring that the individual's transfer into the civilian environment is as smooth and as seamless as possible.</p>
	<p pid="a.220.2/3">In particular, arrangements have been put in place to ensure that amputees who have been fitted with high-quality prosthetics while in service will continue to receive the same level of limb-fitting support from the NHS when the individual leaves the service, be it on medical discharge or after completion of their engagement. MoD and UK health departments have agreed protocols to ensure the transfer of clinical care and financial responsibility from the MoD to the NHS.</p>
	<p pid="a.220.2/4">Since 1953, when Ministry of Pensions hospitals were transferred to the NHS, war pensioners, and more recently recipients of Armed Forces compensation scheme awards, have been entitled to receive priority treatment at NHS hospitals for conditions accepted as due to service, subject to clinical need. In 2007, this entitlement was extended to all veterans who are assessed by their GP to have a condition related to their military service. War pensioners under both schemes may also be entitled to other benefits including free NHS prescriptions and aids or appliances if they are prescribed for the accepted disablement.</p>
	<p pid="a.220.2/5">For veterans who may develop a mental health condition after their discharge, we are currently piloting new models of community-based mental healthcare that will address assessment and treatment of veterans' mental health problems in the long term. The pilots are NHS-led and reflect NHS best practice. Two-year pilots are running at six NHS sites in England, Scotland and Wales. Evaluation of the pilot areas is now underway, and if they prove successful will be rolled out across the UK.</p>
	<p pid="a.220.2/6">In the interim, for areas not yet involved in the pilots, veterans with operational service after 1982 who are concerned about their mental health can attend our medical assessment programme (MAP) based at St Thomas's Hospital, London. The MAP offers assessment by an expert in mental health issues in military service and will include, where appropriate, a recommendation to the individual and their GP for treatment. MoD also provides assessment and treatment for demobilised reservists with operational service since 2003 following an overseas operational deployment as a reservist, and who believes that the deployment may have adversely affected their mental health. Details are available at the following link: <a href="http://www.army.mod.uk/welfare-support/family/13672.aspx">http://www.army.mod.uk/welfare-support/family/13672.aspx</a>. MoD is also the major donor to the charity Combat Stress, which offers care to ex-service personnel suffering from service-related post-traumatic stress disorder.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.221.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="221"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000719">
	Civil Service: Performance Pay
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.221.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100469" speakername="Lord Oakeshott of Seagrove Bay" colon=":" colnum="221"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000719">
	<p pid="a.221.1/1" qnum="HL3639">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Answer by Baroness Vadera on 11 May (<I>WA 156</I>) concerning the amount of funding for senior civil servants' performance-related pay, what were the figures requested.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.221.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100958" speakername="Baroness Vadera" colon=":" colnum="221"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000013">
	<p pid="a.221.2/1">I provided a breakdown for senior civil servants' performance-related pay in my Answer to the noble Lord on <phrase class="date" code="2009-06-08">8 June 2009</phrase> (<I>Official Report</I>, col. <I>WA</I><I></I><I>116</I>).</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.221.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="221"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000720">
	Constitutional Renewal Bill
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.221.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100367" speakername="Lord Lester of Herne Hill" colon=":" colnum="221"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000720">
	<p pid="a.221.4/1" qnum="HL3848">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether they intend to introduce the Constitutional Renewal Bill before the Summer Recess.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.222.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100030" speakername="Lord Bach" colon=":" colnum="222"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000014">
	<p pid="a.222.0/1">We anticipate that the Constitutional Renewal Bill will be introduced before the Summer Recess for carry-over into the next parliamentary Session.</p>
	<p pid="a.222.0/2">In addition, the Government intend to bring forward a Bill to create an Independent Parliamentary Standards Authority before the House rises for the summer.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.222.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="222"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000699">
	Counterterrorism
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.222.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100962" speakername="Baroness Neville-Jones" colon=":" colnum="222"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000699">
	<p pid="a.222.2/1" qnum="HL4278">To ask Her Majesty's Government what was the budget for the Centre for the Protection of National Infrastructure for 2008&mdash;09; what it is for 2009&mdash;10; and what is the planned budget for 2010&mdash;11.</p>
	<p pid="a.222.2/2" qnum="HL4279">To ask Her Majesty's Government what was the expenditure on the National Counter Terrorism Security Office in 2008&mdash;09; what will be the expenditure in 2009&mdash;10; and what is the planned expenditure in 2010&mdash;11.</p>
	<p pid="a.222.2/3" qnum="HL4280">To ask Her Majesty's Government what was the expenditure on activity under the PROTECT strand of the counterterrorism strategy in 2008&mdash;09; what will be the expenditure in 2009&mdash;10; and what is the planned expenditure in 2010&mdash;11.</p>
	<p pid="a.222.2/4" qnum="HL4281">To ask Her Majesty's Government what was the expenditure on activity under the PREPARE strand of the counterterrorism strategy in 2008&mdash;09; what will be the expenditure in 2009&mdash;10; and what is the planned expenditure in 2010&mdash;11.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.222.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100956" speakername="Lord West of Spithead" colon=":" colnum="222"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000016">
	<p pid="a.222.3/1">The United Kingdom's strategy for countering international terrorism set out details of government spending on counterterrorism and intelligence. It is forecast to rise from &pound;2.5 billion in 2008-09 to &pound;3.5 billion in 2010-11. This budget is wider than just expenditure on the Government's counterterrorism strategy, CONTEST.</p>
	<p pid="a.222.3/2">Breaking down this budget by specific counterterrorism and intelligence activities, beyond what is published already, would reveal our capabilities and details of the security and intelligence agencies' spending. It has been the policy of successive governments not to reveal these details.</p>
	<p pid="a.222.3/3">The Centre for the Protection of National Infrastructure is funded from the Single Intelligence Account (SIA) which carries the budget provision for all three security and intelligence agencies (the Security Service, SIS and GCHQ). Detailed breakdowns showing the division of funding between the three agencies are not published for security reasons.</p>
	<p pid="a.222.3/4">However, some information is already made publicly available. This includes:</p>
	<p pid="a.222.3/5">&pound;1.2 billion e-Borders system which has screened over 80 million passengers travelling to the UK, using data received from approximately 105 carriers on over 185 routes; assistance worth &pound;4.7 million was approved in 2008 and focused on overseas aviation and maritime security;&pound;5 million for 2009-10 to support regional and local delivery of work in England and Wales to improve the protection of crowded places as set out in the Government's consultation document <I>Working Together to Protect Crowded Places</I>; and&pound;2.7 million for the period 2007-08 to 2008-09 to increase the size of the National Barrier Asset.</p>
	<p pid="a.222.3/6">More than &pound;1.5 million in 2008-09 to support additional counterterrorist security advisers posts.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.223.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="223"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000721">
	Counterterrorism
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.223.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100962" speakername="Baroness Neville-Jones" colon=":" colnum="223"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000721">
	<p pid="a.223.1/1" qnum="HL4282">To ask Her Majesty's Government what new money has been allocated in the revised counterterrorism strategy to (a) pursue, (b) prevent, (c) protect, and (d) prepare.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.223.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100956" speakername="Lord West of Spithead" colon=":" colnum="223"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000021">
	<p pid="a.223.2/1">The single security and intelligence budget, which includes government spending on counterterrorism and intelligence, was announced as part of the 2007 Comprehensive Spending Review. It is forecast to rise from &pound;2.5 billion in 2008-09 to &pound;3.5 billion in 2010-11. The new version of the United Kingdom's strategy for countering international terrorism will be delivered within this envelope.</p>
	<p pid="a.223.2/2">Breaking down this budget by specific counterterrorism and intelligence activities, beyond what is published already, would reveal our capabilities and details of the security and intelligence agencies spending. It has been the policy of successive governments not to reveal these details.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.223.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="223"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000722">
	Cycling
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.223.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100042" speakername="Lord Berkeley" colon=":" colnum="223"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000722">
	<p pid="a.223.4/1" qnum="HL4116">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether the Department of Health is implementing the Government's cycle-to-work scheme.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.223.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="223"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000023">
	<p pid="a.223.5/1">The department implemented the cycle-to-work scheme on <phrase class="date" code="2008-06-02">2 June 2008</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.223.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="223"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000723">
	Cycling
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.223.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100042" speakername="Lord Berkeley" colon=":" colnum="223"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000723">
	<p pid="a.223.7/1" qnum="HL4268">To ask Her Majesty's Government how they ensure that highway authorities undertake cycle audits on proposed new road schemes in accordance with Department for Transport best practice guidelines.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.223.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100839" speakername="Lord Adonis" colon=":" colnum="223"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000024">
	<p pid="a.223.8/1">There is no mandatory requirement for local highway authorities to undertake cycle audits. Highway authorities have a duty to ensure that new road schemes are safe for all users, and it is for them to determine whether a cycle audit is required to achieve this.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.224.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="224"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000724">
	Cyprus: Property
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.224.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100855" speakername="Lord Jones of Cheltenham" colon=":" colnum="224"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000724">
	<p pid="a.224.1/1" qnum="HL4262">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Answer by Lord Malloch-Brown on 8 June (<I>WA 117</I>), what steps they will take to warn those contemplating buying property in Cyprus of the risk of losing their homes when developers who have retained title deeds in order to raise further loans default on those loans.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.224.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100072" speakername="Lord Brett" colon=":" colnum="224"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000025">
	<p pid="a.224.2/1">The travel advice on the Foreign and Commonwealth Office website (<a href="http://www.fco.gov.uk">www.fco.gov.uk</a>) advises those contemplating buying property in Cyprus to proceed with caution and to seek qualified legal advice from a source that is independent from anyone else involved in the transaction. It refers to the problems with obtaining title deeds and the risks which this causes.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.224.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="224"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000725">
	Cyprus: Property
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.224.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100855" speakername="Lord Jones of Cheltenham" colon=":" colnum="224"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000725">
	<p pid="a.224.4/1" qnum="HL4264">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Answer by Lord Malloch-Brown on 8 June (<I>WA 117</I>), whether they will work with other European countries to urge the Government of Cyprus to prosecute individuals who have retained title deeds after completion of property sales in Cyprus to United Kingdom and other European citizens.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.224.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100072" speakername="Lord Brett" colon=":" colnum="224"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000026">
	<p pid="a.224.5/1">The issue of whether or not to prosecute individuals who have retained title deeds after completion of property sales in Cyprus to UK and other European citizens is a matter of Cypriot law and therefore a decision for the Cypriot authorities.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.224.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="224"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000726">
	Economic Partnership Agreements: ACP Countries
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.224.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100569" speakername="The Earl of Sandwich" colon=":" colnum="224"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000726">
	<p pid="a.224.7/1" qnum="HL4204">To ask Her Majesty's Government which African, Caribbean and Pacific countries have not yet accepted an interim national or regional economic partnership agreement with the European Union; and what transitional assistance and advice is being given to them by the Department for International Development.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.224.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100072" speakername="Lord Brett" colon=":" colnum="224"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000027">
	<p pid="a.224.8/1">The following 41 African Caribbean and Pacific (ACP) countries have not as yet signed an economic partnership agreement (EPA) with the European Union (EU):</p>
	<p pid="a.224.8/2">Gabon, Republic of Congo-(Brazzaville), the Cook Islands, Tonga, Marshall Islands, Niue, Micronesia, Palau, Nauru, Nigeria, Central African Republic, DR Congo, Chad, Equatorial Guinea, Sao Tome, Djibouti, Eritrea, Ethiopia, Malawi, Somalia, Sudan, East Timor, Kiribati, Samoa, Solomon Islands, Tuvalu, Vanuatu, Benin, Burkina Faso, Cape Verde, Gambia, Guinea, Guinea Bissau, Liberia, Mali, Mauritania, Niger, Senegal, Sierra Leone, Togo and Angola.</p>
	<p pid="a.224.8/3">The Department for International Development's (DfID) assistance is not linked to signing of EPAs. However, DfID provides significant support through such measures as aid for trade to help ACP countries, as well as other developing countries, to increase their trading capacity and to help them integrate further into regional and global markets.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.225.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="225"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000727">
	Embryology
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.225.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon=":" colnum="225"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000727">
	<p pid="a.225.1/1" qnum="HL4181">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Answers by Lord Darzi of Denham on 3 June (<I>WA 87&mdash;8</I>), whether outgrowing embryos could not be used to derive embryonic stem cells by Roslin Cells Limited if the latest inspection report for that centre does not contain details of the embryo culture method used, and if no licence permits the culture of a &quot;live human embryo&quot; beyond 14 days or the appearance of the primitive streak (whichever comes first).</p>
	<p pid="a.225.1/2" qnum="HL4183">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Answers by Baroness Thornton on 20 April 2009 (<I>WA 329</I>) and by Lord Darzi of Denham on 24 June 2008 (<I>WA 227</I>) and 3 June 2009 (<I>WA 87&mdash;8</I>), how the Human Fertilisation and Embryology Authority determines a centre's compliance with the Human Fertilisation and Embryology Act 1990 in relation to embryo culture when the method used for embryo culture is not described.</p>
	<p pid="a.225.1/3" qnum="HL4184">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Answer by Lord Darzi of Denham on 20 January (<I>WA 196&mdash;7</I>) and 3 June (<I>WA 87&mdash;8</I>), if inspection reports of research centres licensed by the Human Fertilisation and Embryology Authority (HFEA) indicate that no embryonic stem cell lines have been derived from cytoplasmic hybrid embryos, and if the HFEA monitors both the use of embryos in research and the culture of their cells as part of its research inspection process, why an inspection report does not indicate whether a stem cell line has been derived using a method for which stem cell derivation is the stated aim when the method entails culture of outgrowing embryos beyond 14 days.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.225.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="225"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0001.htm#09061858000030">
	<p pid="a.225.2/1">The Human Fertilisation and Embryology Authority (HFEA) has advised that at all inspections, the authority's inspectors are required to check that there is a procedure in place to ensure that embryos are not cultured for longer than 14 days or after the appearance of the primitive streak.</p>
	<p pid="a.225.2/2">In respect of the culturing of embryos and stem cell derivation, the HEFA has confirmed that it has nothing further to add to the responses given to the noble Lord on <phrase class="date" code="2009-06-03">3 June 2009</phrase> <I>(WA</I><I></I><I>87-8) </I>and <phrase class="date" code="2008-06-24">24 June 2008</phrase> <I>(WA</I><I></I><I>227).</I></p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.226.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="226"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000728">
	Embryology
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.226.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon=":" colnum="226"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000728">
	<p pid="a.226.1/1" qnum="HL4185">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Answers by Lord Darzi of Denham on 10 January 2008 (<I>WA 216</I>) and by Lord Drayson on 19 May 2009 (<I>WA 290</I>), when the Newcastle primary care trust will offer more than one cycle of initial vitro fertilisation in accordance with the February 2004 National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence guidelines; and whether it will take place before the end of 2009.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.226.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="226"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000032">
	<p pid="a.226.2/1">Newcastle Primary Care Trust has advised that it currently commissions three cycles of in vitro fertilisation for eligible patients.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.226.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="226"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000729">
	Gulf War Illnesses
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.226.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100070" speakername="Lord Bramall" colon=":" colnum="226"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000729">
	<p pid="a.226.4/1" qnum="HL4180">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Answer by Baroness Taylor of Bolton on 19 May (<I>WA 295</I>) on the report of the Congressionally-mandated United States Research Advisory Committee's Inquiry into Gulf War illnesses, whether they have now checked the accuracy of Lord Tunnicliffe's Statement on 27 April (<I>Official Report</I>, House of Lords, cols. 8&mdash;10) that the US Institute of Medicine was then reviewing the report; and whether they will amend the statement.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.226.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100844" speakername="Baroness Taylor of Bolton" colon=":" colnum="226"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000033">
	<p pid="a.226.5/1">Government answers on the US Research Advisory Committee report have been accurate and reflect what the US authorities have publicly stated. There is no requirement for an amendment taking into account the information that has currently been made available to the Government. We have not seen the letter dated <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-24">24 April</phrase> referred to by Lord Morris during the Answer given by Lord Tunnicliffe on <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-27">27 April</phrase> (<phrase class="offrep" id="debates/2009-04-27.8"><I>Official Report</I>, col. 8-10</phrase>) but we have requested a copy. If the letter dated <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-24">24 April</phrase> provides further information on the Institute of Medicine (IOM) review then we will take this into account. However, we do not believe that this will alter the position that the IOM is due to publish its findings in February 2010, having been asked to review the report and make recommendations. Further information on the IOM review, provided by the US Department of Veterans Affairs (DVA), can be found by accessing the US House Committee on Veterans Affairs website at <a href="http://veterans.house.gov/hearings/hearing.aspx?NewsID=394">http://veterans.house.gov/hearings/hearing.aspx?NewsID=394</a>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.227.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="227"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000730">
	Health: Contaminated Blood Products
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.227.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100444" speakername="Lord Morris of Manchester" colon=":" colnum="227"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000730">
	<p pid="a.227.1/1" qnum="HL4131">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Statement by Lord Darzi of Denham on 20 May (<I>WS 121&mdash;22</I>), how the average annual payment of &pound;6,400 for the Macfarlane Trust's beneficiaries was determined; and whether any meetings between officials at the Department of Health and the trust have demonstrated that the sum may need adjusting.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.227.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="227"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000034">
	<p pid="a.227.2/1">A broad indicator of the annual level of benefit currently available through the Macfarlane Trust was calculated by dividing the total number of beneficiaries into the total expenditure of the trusts, the result being an overall average of &pound;6,400. Officials also referred to information from the trust about the amounts payable to individuals. There is no reason to adjust the &pound;6,400 figure as the Government's response to Lord Archer's recommendations makes clear that in future all infected beneficiaries will receive &pound;12,800 per annum.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.227.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="227"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000731">
	Health: Contaminated Blood Products
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.227.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100444" speakername="Lord Morris of Manchester" colon=":" colnum="227"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000731">
	<p pid="a.227.4/1" qnum="HL4134">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Statement by Lord Darzi of Denham on 20 May (<I>WS 121&mdash;22</I>), when the average annual payment made to the Macfarlane Trust's beneficiaries will be increased; whether payments will be back-dated to 20 May; and whether any payments made between 20 May and the date the new level is introduced will be discounted.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.227.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="227"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000035">
	<p pid="a.227.5/1">The Macfarlane Trust will be enabled to make flat rate payments to all infected beneficiaries of &pound;12,800 per year with effect from <phrase class="date" code="2009-05-20">20 May 2009</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.227.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="227"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000732">
	Health: Contaminated Blood Products
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.227.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100444" speakername="Lord Morris of Manchester" colon=":" colnum="227"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000732">
	<p pid="a.227.7/1" qnum="HL4186">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Answer by Lord Darzi of Denham on 5 May (WA <I>100&mdash;01</I>), whether Lord Darzi of Denham will now act on the assurance given to him by Mrs Harriet Bullock, the widow of a haemophilia patient contaminated by National Health Service blood products, that she has no objection to the text of the letter referred to in the question by Lord Roberts of Conwy being published in full in the <I>Official Report</I>.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.227.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="227"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000036">
	<p pid="a.227.8/1">The department received an assurance from Mrs Bullock on <phrase class="date" code="2009-05-11">11 May 2009</phrase> that she had no objection to the text of her letter referred to in the Question by Lord Roberts of Conwy being published in full. The date of that letter was <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-09">9 March 2009</phrase> and a reply was sent on <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-21">21 April 2009</phrase>, and copies of both of these are being placed in the Library.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.228.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="228"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000733">
	Health: Contaminated Blood Products
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.228.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100950" speakername="Baroness Campbell of Surbiton" colon=":" colnum="228"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000733">
	<p pid="a.228.1/1" qnum="HL4227">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Statement by Lord Darzi of Denham on 20 May (<I>WS 122</I>), why they did not respond nor refer to the Archer report's recommendation (at page 109) calling for action to end the anomaly of basing entitlement to financial help of the widow of a fatally-infected haemophilia patient on the date of his death; and whether they will now respond to the recommendation.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.228.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="228"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000037">
	<p pid="a.228.2/1">The purpose of the Written Ministerial Statement on <phrase class="date" code="2009-05-20">20 May 2009</phrase> (<I>WS 122</I>) was to inform the House of the publication of the Government's response to the Archer report. The Government's response contains a commitment to review the Skipton Fund in 2014.</p>
	<p pid="a.228.2/2">The Macfarlane and Eileen Trusts have always been able to make payments on a case by case basis to dependents of those entitled to financial relief, and that will remain the case.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.228.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="228"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000734">
	Health: Drugs
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.228.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100451" speakername="Lord Naseby" colon=":" colnum="228"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000734">
	<p pid="a.228.4/1" qnum="HL4178">To ask Her Majesty's Government further to the Written Answer by Lord Darzi of Denham on 20 May (<I>WA 338</I>), when they will place in the Library of the House their response regarding the supply of anti-viral drugs to the overseas territories.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.228.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="228"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000039">
	<p pid="a.228.5/1">All the overseas territories have pandemic preparedness plans, which have now been activated. However, if any of the overseas territories is not able to access antivirals or vaccine (when it becomes available), we will support it by providing access to the United Kingdom (UK) stockpile. This access would be up to the equivalent level of provision as the UK and would generally be on a repayment basis. In addition, we would seek to replace any antiviral or vaccines that were taken from the UK stockpile.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.228.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="228"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000735">
	Healthcare: Funding
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.228.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100851" speakername="Baroness Tonge" colon=":" colnum="228"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000735">
	<p pid="a.228.7/1" qnum="HL4234">To ask Her Majesty's Government how they monitor the levels of funding for healthcare necessary to deal with infections in primary and community care.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.228.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="228"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000040">
	<p pid="a.228.8/1">Primary care trusts are responsible for commissioning services that improve the health and well-being of the population, and are fair, personalised, effective and safe. To do this, they assess the needs of their population, prioritise investment, contract with providers and monitor the quality of services. Consequently, all decisions on funding for services relating to infectious diseases and healthcare acquired infections are taken locally, and the department does not hold relevant data centrally.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.229.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="229"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000736">
	Healthcare: Secondary Infection
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.229.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100851" speakername="Baroness Tonge" colon=":" colnum="229"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000736">
	<p pid="a.229.1/1" qnum="HL4205">To ask Her Majesty's Government what assessment they have made of the factors that increase healthcare-associated infections in secondary care.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.229.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="229"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000041">
	<p pid="a.229.2/1">We have based our infection control advice for secondary care on the best available evidence. There are a range of important factors that if not addressed will lead to increased rates of infection.</p>
	<p pid="a.229.2/2">The EPIC evidence-based guidelines for the prevention of healthcare acquired infections (HCAIs), which has already been placed in the library, set out the personal actions required to prevent HCAIs. Important factors are hand hygiene, environmental hygiene, correct antimicrobial prescribing, safe disposal of sharps, and correct aseptic technique.</p>
	<p pid="a.229.2/3">Organisational measures needed to prevent infections are detailed in the code of practice for the prevention and control of HCAIs, which has also already been placed in the Library. These include appropriate surveillance, clear antibiotic prescribing policies, board-level assurances for HCAI performance, adequate training for all staff in infection control and co-ordination between organisations.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.229.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="229"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000737">
	Healthcare: Secondary Infection
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.229.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100851" speakername="Baroness Tonge" colon=":" colnum="229"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000737">
	<p pid="a.229.4/1" qnum="HL4206">To ask Her Majesty's Government what measures they have taken to ensure a co-ordinated approach to tackling healthcare-associated infections between healthcare professionals, patients and officials.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.229.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="229"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000044">
	<p pid="a.229.5/1">We take a number of measures to ensure a co-ordinated approach between the parties mentioned.</p>
	<p pid="a.229.5/2">Development and review of policies and guidance take account of views from both healthcare professionals and patient groups. Significant pieces of work, such as the <I>Code of Practice for the Prevention and Control of Healthcare Associated Infections</I>, are formally consulted on, and views of healthcare professionals and patients are being sought in the development of a new minimum standard for methicillin-resistant staphylococcus aureus<I></I>(M RSA).</p>
	<p pid="a.229.5/3">Our advisory committee on antimicrobial resistance and healthcare associated infection (ARHAI) membership includes academics, healthcare professionals and a lay member. We also provide targeted support directly to trusts on healthcare associated infections and use this experience of the front line to inform other activities.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.230.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="230"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000738">
	Human Rights
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.230.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100341" speakername="Lord Judd" colon=":" colnum="230"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000738">
	<p pid="a.230.1/1" qnum="HL4244">To ask Her Majesty's Government what part human rights play in the sector reform programmes they are supporting in Iraq, Afghanistan and developing countries in general.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.230.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100072" speakername="Lord Brett" colon=":" colnum="230"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000047">
	<p pid="a.230.2/1">Human rights principles underpin the UK Government's work in developing countries. The policy of the Department for International Development (DfID) is to put people, their rights and social justice at the heart of its development work and to mainstream human rights in development programmes. This approach is reinforced by the conditionality policy which bases UK aid partnerships on a shared commitment to respect human rights. DfID policy is to take partner Governments' commitment to human rights into account when decisions are made about development partnership agreements, country strategies, and providing aid.</p>
	<p pid="a.230.2/2">The UK Government are committed to working with the Iraqi and Afghan Governments to ensure that the basic human rights of the peoples of those countries are protected. In Iraq, DfID is supporting key international agencies to ensure the provision of human rights&mdash;especially those related to freedom from hunger, violence and forced displacement&mdash;for vulnerable groups, including those displaced internally and in neighbouring countries. In Afghanistan the UK is working with the Afghan justice institutions to develop a national policy on non-state justice mechanisms.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.230.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="230"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000739">
	Lisbon Treaty
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.230.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100675" speakername="Viscount Waverley" colon=":" colnum="230"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000739">
	<p pid="a.230.4/1" qnum="HL4162">To ask Her Majesty's Government what is their assessment of whether the Lisbon treaty represents a mechanism for deeper integration or administers the European Union more effectively.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.230.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100072" speakername="Lord Brett" colon=":" colnum="230"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000049">
	<p pid="a.230.5/1">The Lisbon treaty will help the enlarged EU work more effectively by streamlining the institutions and decision-making processes, creating a single set of clear, coherent objectives for EU activity in Europe and around the world, and by making the EU more accountable to member states and national parliaments.</p>
	<p pid="a.230.5/2">Parliament has decided on the Lisbon treaty. The treaty was debated in detail in Parliament over 25 days; both Houses voted strongly in favour at every stage.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.231.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="231"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000740">
	Marine and Coastal Access Bill [HL]
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.231.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100871" speakername="Lord Goodlad" colon=":" colnum="231"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000740">
	<p pid="a.231.1/1" qnum="HL4193">To ask Her Majesty's Government what discussions they have had with the Planning Inspectorate about the proposed appellate functions in the Marine and Coastal Access Bill; and what was the outcome.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.231.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100164" speakername="Lord Davies of Oldham" colon=":" colnum="231"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000051">
	<p pid="a.231.2/1">We held detailed discussions with the Planning Inspectorate in developing the objection procedure in Schedule 1A to the National Parks and Access to the Countryside Act 1949 which has been inserted in the Marine and Coastal Access Bill. The schedule provides a process in which objections to Natural England's coastal access proposals made by a person with a relevant interest in affected land may be referred to an appointed person. We envisage that the appointed person will be an inspector from the Planning Inspectorate.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.231.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="231"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000741">
	Migrant Workers: Romania and Bulgaria
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.231.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon=":" colnum="231"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000741">
	<p pid="a.231.4/1" qnum="HL4176">To ask Her Majesty's Government how many (a) Romanian, and (b) Bulgarian, nationals have registered as workers and entered the United Kingdom in each year since the accession of those countries to the European Union; how many of their family members have entered the United Kingdom; and how many are claiming social security benefits.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.231.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100956" speakername="Lord West of Spithead" colon=":" colnum="231"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000052">
	<p pid="a.231.5/1">Information relating to the number of Romanian and Bulgarian nationals who have registered as workers is published in the Bulgarian and Romanian Accession Statistics which are published quarterly and are available in the Libraries of the House.</p>
	<p pid="a.231.5/2">Information on the number of family members who have entered in the UK is not available centrally and could be obtained only at disproportionate costs.</p>
	<p pid="a.231.5/3">The Department for Work and Pensions has advised that information on the number of Romanian and Bulgarian nationals in receipt of social security benefits is not available.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.231.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="231"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000742">
	Smoking
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.231.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon=":" colnum="231"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000742">
	<p pid="a.231.7/1" qnum="HL4225">To ask Her Majesty's Government whether they will bring forward proposals to ban or restrict smoking in public locations which are in the open.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.232.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="232"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000055">
	<p pid="a.232.0/1">There is no intention at this time to extend the smoke free law to any outdoor places.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.232.1" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="232"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000743">
	Smoking
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.232.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon=":" colnum="232"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000743">
	<p pid="a.232.2/1" qnum="HL4259">To ask Her Majesty's Government how much it cost to provide health services to those with smoking-related conditions in 2006&mdash;07.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.232.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100960" speakername="Lord Darzi of Denham" colon=":" colnum="232"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000056">
	<p pid="a.232.3/1">In 1998 the Government's White Paper, <I>Smoking Kills</I>, estimated that the cost to the National Health Service of treating illness and disease caused by smoking was &pound;1.7 billion every year.</p>
	<p pid="a.232.3/2">In October 2008, Action on Smoking and Health published a report called <I>Beyond Smoking Kills</I>, which estimated that the costs of smoking to the NHS had risen to &pound;2.7 billion a year.</p>
	<p pid="a.232.3/3">The latest research published in the Journal of Tobacco Control in June 2009, by researchers from the University of Oxford Department of Public Health, estimates the costs of smoking to the NHS at &pound;5.2 billion.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.232.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="232"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000744">
	Turks and Caicos Islands
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.232.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100855" speakername="Lord Jones of Cheltenham" colon=":" colnum="232"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000744">
	<p pid="a.232.5/1" qnum="HL4266">To ask Her Majesty's Government what assessment they have made of progress made by the new Government of the Turks and Caicos Islands in implementing recommendations made in Sir Robin Auld's preliminary report on that country; and whether they will work with the new Government to implement all of the recommendations in the final report.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.232.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100072" speakername="Lord Brett" colon=":" colnum="232"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000059">
	<p pid="a.232.6/1">We welcome the Turks and Caicos Islands Government's efforts to begin to resolve the issues highlighted in Sir Robin Auld's interim report. Once we have considered the commission's final report in detail, we will set out the steps needed to address the commissioners' recommendations. We hope that the Turks and Caicos Islands Government will continue to support the governor in order to restore good governance and sound financial management to the Turks and Caicos Islands.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.232.7" nospeaker="true" colnum="232"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000745">
	UK Border Agency: Staff
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.232.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100666" speakername="Lord Wallace of Saltaire" colon=":" colnum="232"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000745">
	<p pid="a.232.8/1" qnum="HL4207">To ask Her Majesty's Government how many staff of the UK Border Agency are posted abroad; and in which countries.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2009-06-18a.233.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100956" speakername="Lord West of Spithead" colon=":" colnum="233"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90618w0002.htm#09061858000060">
	<p pid="a.233.0/1">The number of staff working for the UK Border Agency posted abroad are shown in the attached table, as at <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-01">1 April 2009</phrase>.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/4"> <td>Country</td> <td>UK Based, posted abroad as at 1 April 2009</td> <td>Locally Engaged</td> <td>Total</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/5"> <td>Albania</td> <td>3</td> <td>6</td> <td>9</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/6"> <td>Algeria</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> <td>5</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/7"> <td>Angola</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/8"> <td>Argentina</td> <td>0</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/9"> <td>Armenia</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/10"> <td>Australia</td> <td>1</td> <td>29</td> <td>30</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/11"> <td>Austria</td> <td>0</td> <td>4</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/12"> <td>Azerbaijan</td> <td>2</td> <td>5</td> <td>7</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/13"> <td>Bangladesh</td> <td>12</td> <td>56</td> <td>68</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/14"> <td>Barbados</td> <td>0</td> <td>3</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/15"> <td>Belarus</td> <td>2</td> <td>4</td> <td>6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/16"> <td>Belgium</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/17"> <td>Belize</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/18"> <td>Bolivia</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/19"> <td>Bosnia and Herzegovinia</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/20"> <td>Botswana</td> <td>2</td> <td>4</td> <td>6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/21"> <td>Brazil</td> <td>3</td> <td>10</td> <td>13</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/22"> <td>Brunei</td> <td>4</td> <td>2</td> <td>6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/23"> <td>Bulgaria</td> <td>0</td> <td>3</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/24"> <td>Burma</td> <td>3</td> <td>3</td> <td>6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/25"> <td>Cambodia</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/26"> <td>Cameroon</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/27"> <td>Canada</td> <td>4</td> <td>11</td> <td>15</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/28"> <td>Chile</td> <td>0</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/29"> <td>China</td> <td>47</td> <td>92</td> <td>139</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/30"> <td>Colombia</td> <td>4</td> <td>10</td> <td>14</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/31"> <td>Congo (Dem. Rep.)</td> <td>3</td> <td>3</td> <td>6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/32"> <td>Croatia</td> <td>1</td> <td>3</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/33"> <td>Cuba</td> <td>3</td> <td>3</td> <td>6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/34"> <td>Cyprus</td> <td>3</td> <td>7</td> <td>10</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/35"> <td>Czech Republic</td> <td>0</td> <td>4</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/36"> <td>Denmark</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> <td>5</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/37"> <td>Dominican Republic</td> <td>1</td> <td>3</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/38"> <td>Ecuador</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/39"> <td>Egypt</td> <td>12</td> <td>10</td> <td>22</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/40"> <td>Eritrea</td> <td>2</td> <td>1</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/41"> <td>Estonia</td> <td>0</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/42"> <td>Ethiopia</td> <td>6</td> <td>7</td> <td>13</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/43"> <td>Fiji</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/44"> <td>Finland</td> <td>1</td> <td>3</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/45"> <td>France</td> <td>2</td> <td>16</td> <td>18</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/46"> <td>Gambia, The</td> <td>4</td> <td>9</td> <td>13</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/47"> <td>Georgia</td> <td>3</td> <td>2</td> <td>5</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/48"> <td>Germany</td> <td>2</td> <td>17</td> <td>19</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/49"> <td>Ghana</td> <td>16</td> <td>31</td> <td>47</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/50"> <td>Greece</td> <td>2</td> <td>4</td> <td>6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/51"> <td>Guatemala</td> <td>1</td> <td>3</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/52"> <td>Guyana</td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/53"> <td>Hungary</td> <td>0</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/54"> <td>Iceland</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/55"> <td>India</td> <td>73</td> <td>213</td> <td>286</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/56"> <td>Indonesia</td> <td>5</td> <td>4</td> <td>9</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/57"> <td>Iran</td> <td>5</td> <td>21</td> <td>26</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/58"> <td>Iraq</td> <td>2</td> <td>1</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/59"> <td>Irish Republic</td> <td>2</td> <td>10</td> <td>12</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/60"> <td>Israel</td> <td>2</td> <td>9</td> <td>11</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/61"> <td>Italy</td> <td>3</td> <td>9</td> <td>12</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/62"> <td>Jamaica</td> <td>8</td> <td>16</td> <td>24</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/63"> <td>Japan</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/64"> <td>Jordan</td> <td>6</td> <td>11</td> <td>17</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/65"> <td>Kazakhstan</td> <td>4</td> <td>4</td> <td>8</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/66"> <td>Kenya</td> <td>11</td> <td>25</td> <td>36</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/67"> <td>Korea</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/68"> <td>Kuwait</td> <td>5</td> <td>9</td> <td>14</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/69"> <td>Latvia</td> <td>0</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/70"> <td>Lebanon</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> <td>5</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/71"> <td>Libya</td> <td>7</td> <td>7</td> <td>14</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/72"> <td>Lithuania</td> <td>0</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/73"> <td>Macedonia</td> <td>3</td> <td>7</td> <td>10</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/74"> <td>Malawi</td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/75"> <td>Malaysia</td> <td>5</td> <td>10</td> <td>15</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/76"> <td>Malta</td> <td>0</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/77"> <td>Mauritius</td> <td>3</td> <td>5</td> <td>8</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/78"> <td>Mexico</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/79"> <td>Moldova</td> <td>1</td> <td>5</td> <td>6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/80"> <td>Mongolia</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/81"> <td>Montenegro</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/82"> <td>Morocco</td> <td>3</td> <td>9</td> <td>12</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/83"> <td>Mozambique</td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/84"> <td>Namibia</td> <td>1</td> <td>0</td> <td>1</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/85"> <td>Nepal</td> <td>0</td> <td>3</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/86"> <td>Netherlands</td> <td>1</td> <td>5</td> <td>6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/87"> <td>New Zealand</td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/88"> <td>Nigeria</td> <td>66</td> <td>132</td> <td>198</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/89"> <td>North Korea</td> <td>3</td> <td>0</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/90"> <td>Norway</td> <td>2</td> <td>4</td> <td>6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/91"> <td>Oman</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> <td>5</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/92"> <td>Pakistan</td> <td>29</td> <td>126</td> <td>155</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/93"> <td>Panama</td> <td>1</td> <td>3</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/94"> <td>Papua New Guinea</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/95"> <td>Peru</td> <td>0</td> <td>3</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/96"> <td>Philippines</td> <td>15</td> <td>26</td> <td>41</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/97"> <td>Poland</td> <td>4</td> <td>5</td> <td>9</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/98"> <td>Portugal</td> <td>0</td> <td>4</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/99"> <td>Qatar</td> <td>3</td> <td>5</td> <td>8</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/100"> <td>Romania</td> <td>5</td> <td>5</td> <td>10</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/101"> <td>Russian Federation</td> <td>22</td> <td>40</td> <td>62</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/102"> <td>Rwanda</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/103"> <td>Saint Lucia</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/104"> <td>Saudi Arabia</td> <td>5</td> <td>10</td> <td>15</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/105"> <td>Senegal</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/106"> <td>Seychelles</td> <td>0</td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/107"> <td>Sierra Leone</td> <td>2</td> <td>4</td> <td>6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/108"> <td>Singapore</td> <td>0</td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/109"> <td>Slovakia</td> <td>0</td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/110"> <td>South Africa</td> <td>17</td> <td>35</td> <td>52</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/111"> <td>Spain</td> <td>3</td> <td>12</td> <td>15</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/112"> <td>Sri Lanka</td> <td>4</td> <td>6</td> <td>10</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/113"> <td>Sudan</td> <td>3</td> <td>3</td> <td>6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/114"> <td>Sweden</td> <td>0</td> <td>7</td> <td>7</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/115"> <td>Switzerland</td> <td>1</td> <td>6</td> <td>7</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/116"> <td>Syria .</td> <td>2</td> <td>1</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/117"> <td>Taiwan (China)</td> <td>4</td> <td>8</td> <td>12</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/118"> <td>Tajikistan</td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/119"> <td>Tanzania</td> <td>4</td> <td>3</td> <td>7</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/120"> <td>Thailand</td> <td>11</td> <td>24</td> <td>35</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/121"> <td>Trinidad and Tobago</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> <td>5</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/122"> <td>Tunisia</td> <td>2</td> <td>4</td> <td>6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/123"> <td>Turkey</td> <td>17</td> <td>35</td> <td>52</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/124"> <td>Turkmenistan</td> <td>3</td> <td>2</td> <td>5</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/125"> <td>Uganda</td> <td>4</td> <td>2</td> <td>6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/126"> <td>Ukraine</td> <td>6</td> <td>12</td> <td>18</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/127"> <td>United Arab Emirates</td> <td>23</td> <td>56</td> <td>79</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/128"> <td>United States</td> <td>7</td> <td>68</td> <td>75</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/129"> <td>Unknown</td> <td>3</td> <td>0</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/130"> <td>Uruguay</td> <td>1</td> <td>0</td> <td>1</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/131"> <td>Uzbekistan</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/132"> <td>Venezuela</td> <td>0</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/133"> <td>Vietnam</td> <td>2</td> <td>8</td> <td>10</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/134"> <td>Yemen</td> <td>3</td> <td>2</td> <td>5</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/135"> <td>Yugoslavia</td> <td>4</td> <td>7</td> <td>11</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/136"> <td>Zambia</td> <td>2</td> <td>2</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/137"> <td>Zimbabwe</td> <td>3</td> <td>5</td> <td>8</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.233.0/138"> <td></td> <td>629</td> <td>1507</td> <td>2136</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.233.0/141">The proposed answer amalgamates the available data and gives countries only where more than five UK based staff have been posted. This is in accordance with long standing practice that we do not disclose information on small numbers of staff which could identify individuals.</p>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

