<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="c" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000019">
	Avian Flu
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100650" speakername="Lord Turnberg" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000019">
	<p pid="c.177.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.1/2" qnum="HL7434">Whether the Department of Health has examined the potential for passive antibodies to attenuate the disease in those exposed to avian flu; and</p>
	<p pid="c.177.1/3" qnum="HL7435">Whether any progress has been made in the deployment and use of passive antibodies in preventing the human spread of avian flu.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100670" speakername="Lord Warner" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000020">
	<p pid="c.177.2/1">The Department of Health has been advised by the Health Protection Agency that passive immunisation for avian flu would require the supply of human immunoglobulin with high levels of antibodies against avian flu. The effectiveness of passive immunisation to treat or prevent the spread of avian flu virus from person to person or to reduce the severity of illness in those infected with avian flu is not known.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000021">
	Benefits: Single Parents
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100823" speakername="Lord Steinberg" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000021">
	<p pid="c.177.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.4/2" qnum="HL7455">Whether, in light of recent research by Dr Libertad Gonzalez which suggested a direct link between the welfare system and the number of one parent families, they propose to change the level of benefits available to single mothers.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100314" speakername="Lord Hunt of Kings Heath" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000022">
	<p pid="c.177.5/1">We have no such plans.</p>
	<p pid="c.177.5/2">There are now around a million lone parents in work and the lone parent employment rate is up 11.3 percentage points since 1997. Our New Deal for Lone Parents programme has helped nearly 458,000 lone parents into work and the success of the programme has been a major contributing factor to the increase in lone parent employment in every region, the reduction in the number of children in workless households, and the reduction in child poverty.</p>
	<p pid="c.177.5/3">From next April we will be piloting a scheme to provide additional help to lone parents whose youngest child is aged 11 or over. Together with quarterly work-focused interviews, eligible lone parents in the pilot will be paid a work-related activity premium of an additional &pound;20 a week for up to six months if they agree to take active steps to return to the labour market.</p>
	<p pid="c.177.5/4">Paid employment helps families and individuals and improves life chances for children and we are determined to break into the cycle of intergenerational poverty by giving all children better opportunities.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000026">
	Compensation
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100246" speakername="Lord Goodhart" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000026">
	<p pid="c.177.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.7/2" qnum="HL7498">Whether they intend to make any contribution to the costs incurred by the parties in the case of Barker (Respondent) v Corus (UK) plc (Appellants) (formerly Barker (Respondent) v Saint Gobain Pipelines plc (Appellants)), following the retrospective reversal by the Compensation Act 2006 of the decision of the House of Lords in that case.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100024" speakername="Baroness Ashton of Upholland" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000027">
	<p pid="c.177.8/1">The Government remain ready to consider the proposal that they should make a contribution towards any costs reasonably incurred by the parties to this case in connection with the appeal to the House of Lords, where the Government's action reversed the relevant aspect of the appeal. Further consideration will be given to the matter once an order for costs has been made in the case.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.9" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000028">
	Electoral Law
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100255" speakername="Lord Greaves" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000028">
	<p pid="c.177.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.10/2" qnum="HL7427">Whether it is possible to hold two separate elections on the same day for vacancies in the same ward or division rather than a joint election for two vacancies; if so, what is their assessment of the advantages and disadvantages of this procedure; in how many cases it has happened in recent years; and what advice they give to local returning officers regarding this procedure.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.11" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100024" speakername="Baroness Ashton of Upholland" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000029">
	<p pid="c.177.11/1">It is possible for separate elections to be held on the same day for more than one vacancy in the same ward or division of the same local authority or parish council, as electoral law does not require that a combined election be held in these circumstances. It would be for the returning officer to decide how the elections are run. We have not carried out a formal assessment of holding such elections separately. An advantage might be that it would be clear to electors that there was more than one vacancy to be filled. The disadvantages would be that there would be duplication of election processes, such as printing of separate ballot papers for each vacancy, which would add to the cost of running the elections and make the procedure more complicated for electoral administrators and electors. Information is not recorded on cases where such elections have been held separately. The Government have not issued any advice to local returning officers concerning this procedure.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.12" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000030">
	Israel and Palestine: Borders
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.13" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100804" speakername="Lord Dykes" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000030">
	<p pid="c.177.13/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.13/2" qnum="HL7506">Whether they will make further representations to persuade Hamas ministers to recognise the state of Israel within the boundaries established prior to the Six-Day War in 1967.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.14" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000031">
	<p pid="c.177.14/1">We remain deeply concerned that neither the Hamas-led Palestinian Authority, nor Hamas as a movement, has committed to the quartet's (EU, US, UN and Russia) three principles: to renounce violence, recognise Israel; and accept all previous agreements and obligations. We have no plans to make any representations to the Hamas-led Palestinian Authority. We have suspended all political contacts with it since June 2005.</p>
	<p pid="c.177.14/2">As my right honourable friend the Prime Minister made clear during his visit to the region on9-<phrase class="date" code="2006-09-11">11 September</phrase>, we would be ready to re-engage with a Palestinian Government who are based on the quartet principles.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.15" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000033">
	Israel and Palestine: Gaza
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.16" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100804" speakername="Lord Dykes" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000033">
	<p pid="c.177.16/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.16/2" qnum="HL7505">Whether they will make representations to the Government of Israel regarding the legality of the economic blockade of the Gaza Strip under international law.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.17" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000034">
	<p pid="c.177.17/1">We, along with our EU partners, continue to call on Israel to resume transfers of withheld Palestinian tax and customs revenues which are essential in averting a crisis in the Palestinian territories. Israel collects customs revenues for the Palestinian Authority under the terms of the 1994 Paris protocols. Israel suspended these payments after the opening of the Palestinian Legislative Council on <phrase class="date" code="2006-02-18">18 February</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="c.177.17/2">We also continue to make representations to the Israeli Government regarding the closure of the Gaza crossing points, in particular Karni. Our ambassador in Tel Aviv last raised this issue with the Israeli Prime Minister's foreign policy adviser on <phrase class="date" code="2006-10-05">5 October</phrase>. The closure of the crossing points, especially around the agricultural seasons, has a detrimental effect on the Palestinian economy. We hope that both parties will act on their commitments under the November 2005 movement and access agreement.</p>
	<p pid="c.177.17/3">We have no plans to make representations to the Israeli Government regarding the legality of these matters.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.18" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000037">
	Ministry of Defence: Property
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.19" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100681" speakername="Lord Whitty" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000037">
	<p pid="c.177.19/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.19/2" qnum="HL7339">Further to the Written Answer by the Baroness Andrews on 24 October 2005 (<I>WA 160</I>) on Ministry of Defence property, why the document DAO (GEN) (07/05) contains no reference to affordable housing; and where is their policy on provision of affordable housing in public asset disposals set out.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.20" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100015" speakername="Baroness Andrews" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000038">
	<p pid="c.177.20/1">The primary purpose of HM Treasury's DAO (GEN) (07/05) is to update government accounting users on the application of clawback requirements on the disposal of publicly funded assets. This policy exists to safeguard the disposing body's financial interest and helps to ensure value for money for taxpayers. The Ministry of Defence, in common with all other central government bodies, follows government accounting rules which require disposing bodies to obtain market value when disposing of surplus assets. The Ministry of Defence will work in liaison with local authorities when considering its disposal strategies for surplus sites, including the provision of affordable housing.</p>
	<p pid="c.177.20/2">Defence Estates has a framework agreement with English Partnerships (November 2004) to facilitate the reuse of former defence sites. The agreement sets out how the agencies will work together to maximise the potential of surplus Ministry of Defence property to help deliver the objectives of the Government's Sustainable Communities Plan (February 2003).</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.21" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000040">
	NHS: Compensation and Legal Costs
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.22" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100823" speakername="Lord Steinberg" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000040">
	<p pid="c.177.22/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.22/2" qnum="HL7454">Whether the cost to the National Health Service of &pound;175 million for compensation and legal costs as stated by the National Health Service Litigation Authority includes all outstanding cases to the end of the past financial year.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.23" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100670" speakername="Lord Warner" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000041">
	<p pid="c.177.23/1">The NHS Litigation Authority 2005-06 accounts report expenditure of &pound;591,586,000 on clinical and non-clinical negligence claims in the past financial year. The accounts include a provision, as at <phrase class="date" code="2006-03-31">31 March 2006</phrase>, of &pound;8,344,980,000 for all outstanding cases including an estimate for incidents that have occurred but not been reported.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.24" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000042">
	Palestine: Hamas and Fatah
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.25" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100804" speakername="Lord Dykes" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000042">
	<p pid="c.177.25/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.25/2" qnum="HL7507">Whether they will take steps to promote the resumption of peace talks and co-operation between Hamas and Fatah in Palestine; and, if so, whether such steps would include easing European Union restrictions on aid disbursements.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.26" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000043">
	<p pid="c.177.26/1">We welcome Palestinian President Abbas's efforts to form a national unity government to end the division which has led to violence in Gaza. My right honourable friend the Prime Minister discussed the formation of a national unity government with President Abbas during his recent visit on9-<phrase class="date" code="2006-09-11">11 September</phrase>. We want to see a Palestinian Government with whom we can engage and do business with, which means one with a programme based on the three quartet (EU, US, UN and Russia) principles: renunciation of violence; recognition of Israel; and acceptance of previous agreements and obligations, including the road map. Although we support a resumption of talks between Hamas and Fatah, we will continue to disburse aid to the Palestinian people through the &quot;temporary international mechanism&quot; until the Palestinian Authority moves towards accepting the quartet's three principles. The UK is providing aid to the Palestinian people at the same level as in 2005. The EU has significantly increased its financial support to the Palestinian people compared to 2005. As my right honourable friend the Prime Minister has made clear, if the Palestinian Government are based on the quartet's three principles, we will engage.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.27" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000044">
	Prisoners: Foreign Nationals
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.28" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100476" speakername="Lord Ouseley" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000044">
	<p pid="c.177.28/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.28/2" qnum="HL7565">Further to the Written Answer by the Baroness Scotland of Asthal on 21 July (<I>WA 48-9</I>), whether the review of the failings which led to the release of 1,013 foreign national prisoners without consideration of possible deportation has commenced; whether conclusions have been reached to indicate which individuals were responsible for the failings; and whether action has been taken against those found culpable.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.29" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000045">
	<p pid="c.177.29/1">The Secretary of State for the Home Department explained in his Oral Statement of <phrase class="date" code="2006-10-09">9 October</phrase> on the prison estate that the Director General of the Immigration and Nationality Directorate had written to the Home Affairs Committee on the same day. This letter contains a progress update on the 1,013 cases released without deportation consideration and also further information on the review which is taking place into how this occurred.</p>
	<p pid="c.177.29/2">A copy of this letter has been made available in the Library of the House.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.30" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000047">
	Public Expenditure: Scotland
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.31" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100037" speakername="Lord Barnett" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000047">
	<p pid="c.177.31/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.31/2" qnum="HL7609">Whether they will provide a detailed analysis of public expenditure in Scotland, excluding locally financed local government expenditure.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.32" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100802" speakername="Lord McKenzie of Luton" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000048">
	<p pid="c.177.32/1">Table 7.17 of the publication<I> Public Expenditure Statistical Analyses 2006</I> (Cm 6811) breaks down identifiable public spending in Scotland by function for 2004-05 and shows the contributions made by devolved administrations, local authorities and UK government departments.</p>
	<p pid="c.177.32/2">Details of local authority spending in each of the countries of the United Kingdom by function are shown in Tables 5.7 and 5.8 of <I>Public Expenditure Statistical Analyses 2006</I> (Cm 6811).</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.33" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000050">
	Railways: Community Railways
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.34" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100068" speakername="Lord Bradshaw" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000050">
	<p pid="c.177.34/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.34/2" qnum="HL7566">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Davies of Oldham on 10 October (<I>WA 140</I>), whether they intend to commit resources to the Development Strategy for Community Railways.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.35" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100164" speakername="Lord Davies of Oldham" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000051">
	<p pid="c.177.35/1">The Government plan to continue to commit support to community rail as at present. They would consider specific proposals for specific developments on community railways on their merits.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.36" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000052">
	Railways: NAO Report
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.37" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100068" speakername="Lord Bradshaw" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000052">
	<p pid="c.177.37/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.37/2" qnum="HL7519">Whether they have responded to the National Audit Office report <I>Maintaining and improving Britain's railway stations</I>, which was published in July 2005.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.38" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100164" speakername="Lord Davies of Oldham" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000053">
	<p pid="c.177.38/1">Yes. Her Majesty's Government responded by Treasury minute on <phrase class="date" code="2006-04-26">26 April 2006</phrase>. Copies are available in the Library of the House (reference: Cm 6775).</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.39" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000054">
	Railways: West Midlands Franchise
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.40" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100068" speakername="Lord Bradshaw" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000054">
	<p pid="c.177.40/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.40/2" qnum="HL7520">Why the West Midlands Passenger Transport Authority will not be a co-signatory of the new West Midlands rail franchise.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.41" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100164" speakername="Lord Davies of Oldham" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000055">
	<p pid="c.177.41/1">As set out in both the Transport and Rail White Papers, the Government are keen to devolve greater decision making to local and regional bodies. Local decision making can be effective and efficient only where the body making the decision is exposed to the financial implications of that decision.</p>
	<p pid="c.177.41/2">The published Department for Transport (Dft) guidance note<I> The new system for the role of English Passenger Transport Executives (PTEs) in the rail franchising process</I> sets out how PTEs can procure changes to local rail services in their areas without being co-signatories to franchise agreements. Centro PTE is seeking to make an economic case for retaining co-signatory status in relation to the West Midlands franchise. In order to establish the costs of such status more clearly, a view will be sought on the cost implications from the successful bidder for the franchise prior to conclusion of the franchise agreement.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.42" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000057">
	Sudan: Darfur
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.43" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000057">
	<p pid="c.177.43/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.43/2" qnum="HL7580">What reports they have received about the recent heavy fighting in Darfur, involving the Sudanese army and the Janjaweed militia; and what information they have about the numbers of recent fatalities and casualties.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.44" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000058">
	<p pid="c.177.44/1">There are credible reports that in recent weeks Arab militia forces, the &quot;Janjaweed&quot;, have been acting in close co-operation with the Government of Sudan air force and armed forces in attacking non-signatory rebel groups in Darfur. We have consistently made clear to the Government of Sudan that they must stop the fighting and implement the peace agreement, including by disarming the Janjaweed. My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for International Development intends to raise this with the Government when he travels to Sudan later this month.</p>
	<p pid="c.177.44/2">No reliable figures exist for the numbers of conflict-related dead and injured. Exact figures are unlikely ever to be known. But every death, casualty or rape in Sudan is a tragedy. That is why we are pressing the Government of Sudan and the rebel groups to stop the fighting; to agree to the deployment of a UN force in Darfur; to co-operate in bolstering the African Union in the interim; to commit to and implement the Darfur peace agreement; and to ensure full humanitarian access for the UN and non-governmental organisations in Darfur.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.45" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000060">
	Sudan: Darfur
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.46" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000060">
	<p pid="c.177.46/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.46/2" qnum="HL7581">What role they are playing to ensure that an international peacekeeping presence in Darfur will be sustained; and whether they envisage a role for British and NATO troops in such a peacekeeping force.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.47" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000061">
	<p pid="c.177.47/1">The UK is continuing to support the African Union (AU) mission in Darfur (AMIS). We were its first donor and have to date provided &pound;52 million of assistance. This has been used for budgetary support, to purchase vehicles and other equipment, and to airlift troops to and from Darfur. The AU is now planning to increase the size of AMIS by two battalions (approximately 1,200 troops). We stand ready to assist it in this. Meanwhile, at our urging, the UN is helping to bolster AMIS prior to any transition to a UN force. We are considering contributing additional UK personnel as part of the UN assistance package to the AU, before a UN peacekeeping force deploys as mandated by UN Security Council Resolution 1706.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.48" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000062">
	Sudan: Darfur
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.49" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000062">
	<p pid="c.177.49/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.49/2" qnum="HL7584">What assessment they have made of the eye witness account of Paul Salopek in the report he was compiling for <I>National Geographic</I> magazine about the situation in Darfur, his subsequent arrest and imprisonment by the Sudanese authorities; and what representations they are making to the Government of Sudan about this matter.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.50" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0001.htm#06101756000063">
	<p pid="c.177.50/1">While reporting on the culture and history of the Sahel for <I>National Geographic</I> magazine, Paul Salopek, a freelance journalist, crossed the border from Chad into Sudan without a visa. He was arrested and imprisoned on <phrase class="date" code="2006-08-06">6 August</phrase> on charges of entering the country without a visa, passing information illegally and espionage.</p>
	<p pid="c.177.50/2">Following representations by the US Government to the Government of Sudan, Mr Salopek, a US National, was released on <phrase class="date" code="2006-09-09">9 September</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.51" nospeaker="true" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0002.htm#06101756000065">
	Traffic Management Act 2004
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.52" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100271" speakername="Lord Hanningfield" colon="" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0002.htm#06101756000065">
	<p pid="c.177.52/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="c.177.52/2" qnum="HL7533">How many consultations on the permits scheme contained within the Traffic Management Act 2004 have taken place; how many are still to take place; and what is the reason for any duplication that may have occurred during this process.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2006-10-17c.177.53" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100164" speakername="Lord Davies of Oldham" colon=":" colnum="177"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199697/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/61017w0002.htm#06101756000066">
	<p pid="c.177.53/1">A consultation entitled &quot;The Traffic Management Act 2004 secondary legislation on Notices, Directions and Restrictions Permit Schemes and Fixed Penalty Notices and Revision of Section 74 of the New Roads and Street Works Act 1991 (Charges for Unreasonably Prolonged Occupation of the Highway)&quot; was issued on <phrase class="date" code="2005-02-01">1 February 2005</phrase>. However, there were no draft regulations for permit schemes as part of this consultation.</p>
	<p pid="c.177.53/2">Responses to this consultation were received which included wide-ranging views on the concept of permit schemes. The Permits Working Group was reconvened to consider these responses and further consider proposals for the operation of permit schemes. The requirement to consult on draft regulations means that a further consultation, which is to commence shortly, will be necessary.</p>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

