<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">

<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >

<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >

<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY micro "&#181;" >

<!ENTITY euro "&#8364;" >
<!ENTITY sup2 "&#178;" >
]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="b" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.17.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_wqn0">
	Avian Flu
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.17.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100077" speakername="Lord Brightman" colon="" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_wqn0">
	<p pid="b.17.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.17.1/2" qnum="HL1786">Whether guidance from the Foreign and Commonwealth Office to the general traveller indicates that Laos is regarded as being clear of the risk of avian flu.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.17.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_spmin0">
	<p pid="b.17.2/1">The Foreign and Commonwealth Office (FCO) travel advice does not indicate that Laos is clear of avian flu. We cannot be sure there is no risk of avian flu in Laos. The current travel advice for Laos states:</p>
	<p pid="b.17.2/2">&quot;Since January 2004, there have been over 50 human deaths in Asia confirmed as resulting from bird flu (also known as avian flu and avian influenza). There have been no human deaths in Laos. The World Health Organisation (WHO) has reported on the possibility of a human flu pandemic following this outbreak&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.17.2/3">The current travel advice and avian influenza fact sheet are available on the FCO website at <a href="http://www.fco.gov.uk">www.fco.gov.uk</a>. The fact sheet makes clear that Laos is among a number of countries to have suffered an outbreak of avian flu in poultry and gives further advice to those travelling to these countries.</p>
	<p pid="b.17.2/4">Following the noble Lord's Question and to ensure that this information is given as clearly as possible, the travel advice for Laos was amended on <phrase class="date" code="">21 October</phrase> to include an explicit reference to the 2004 outbreak of avian flu in poultry in Laos.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.17.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_wqn1">
	Belfast Airports: Passenger Levies
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.17.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_wqn1">
	<p pid="b.17.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.17.4/2" qnum="HL1976">Whether they are paid any form of levy per passenger by either of the Belfast airports; if so, for what reason; how much; and for what purpose.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.17.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100802" speakername="Lord McKenzie of Luton" colon=":" colnum="17"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_spnew0">
	<p pid="b.17.5/1">There are no government levies, either per passenger or otherwise, on any airports in the UK. The only tax paid to the Government on flights is air passenger duty (APD). APD is payable by aircraft operators rather than airport operators for each passenger carried from a UK airport on chargeable aircraft. Rates of APD are as follows.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="b.17.5/4"> <td></td> <td>In the lowest<br/>    class of travel</td> <td>In other than the lowest class of travel</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.17.5/5"> <td>Passengers flying to destinations    within the European Economic    Area (1)</td> <td>&pound;5</td> <td>&pound;10</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.17.5/6"> <td>New EU Member States</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.17.5/7"> <td>Countries applying to join EU</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.17.5/8"> <td>Switzerland</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.17.5/9"> <td>Certain EU Member States'    dependent territories (2)</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.17.5/10"> <td>Other destinations</td> <td>&pound;20</td> <td>&pound;40</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="b.17.5/13">(1) Austria, Belgium, Denmark, Finland (including Aland Islands), France, Germany, Greece, Iceland, Ireland, Italy, Luxembourg, the Netherlands, Norway, Portugal, Spain, Sweden and the UK (including Isle of Man).</p>
	<p pid="b.17.5/14">(2) The Azores, the Balearic Islands, the Canary Islands, Corsica, the Faroe Islands, Madeira, Sardinia, Sicily, the Channel Islands and Gibraltar.</p>
	<p pid="b.17.5/15">Revenue figures for air passenger duty are collected for the UK as a whole and are not broken down by either airport or region. The Exchequer raised &pound;791 million from air passenger duty in 2003&ndash;04 for the UK as a whole. Historical air passenger revenue figures can be found in table 1.2D of financial statistics published by the Office for National Statistics.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.18.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_wqn2">
	Belfast Education and Library Board
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.18.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_wqn2">
	<p pid="b.18.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.18.1/2" qnum="HL1621">How the recently appointed members of the Belfast Education and Library Board were selected; by whom and after what process they were selected; and what is the perceived community background of each member.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.18.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="18"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_spmin1">
	<p pid="b.18.2/1">Appointments to the Belfast Education and Library Board are made by the Education Minister. The members appointed in July 2005 were selected in accordance with legislative requirements and the code of practice laid down by the Commissioner for Public Appointments.</p>
	<p pid="b.18.2/2">Fourteen members were nominated by the relevant local council, in this case Belfast City Council. Eight members were nominated by the transferors and trustees. The Minister approved those nominees for appointment.</p>
	<p pid="b.18.2/3">The remaining 13 members were appointed through a process that is regulated by the Commissioner for Public Appointments. On this occasion, six members met the criteria for reappointment. The remaining seven appointments were made by the Minister following a process that reflected the commissioner's requirements, particularly the need for public appointments to be made on merit.</p>
	<p pid="b.18.2/4">This process involved shortlisting and interviewing carried out by a panel that included an independent assessor nominated by the commissioner. The panel's recommendations were passed to the Minister for Education who made the final decision on appointments.</p>
	<p pid="b.18.2/5">The commissioner's independent assessor found the process used to have met the exacting standards set down by OCPA.</p>
	<p pid="b.18.2/6">The information available in respect of the community background of members on the Belfast Education and Library Board is detailed in the table below. To enable Ministers and departments to ensure that the pool of candidates from which appointments are made contains a fair and equitable representation of the Northern Ireland community, in accordance with OCPA guidelines, details of community background are sought from each candidate for monitoring purposes. This information is not made available to the shortlisting and interview panels or to the Minister when decisions on appointments are being made.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="b.18.2/9"> <td></td> <td>Protestant (percentage)</td> <td>Roman Catholic (percentage)</td> <td>Other (percentage)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.18.2/10"> <td><i>BELB</i></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.18.2/11"> <td>District Council Nominees</td> <td>46</td> <td>54</td> <td>-</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.18.2/12"> <td>Transferor/Trustee Reps</td> <td>50</td> <td>50</td> <td>-</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.18.2/13"> <td>General Interest Members</td> <td>31</td> <td>69</td> <td>-</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.18.2/14"> <td>Overall Balance    (percentage)</td> <td>40</td> <td>60</td> <td>-</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.19.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_wqn3">
	Civil Contingency Reaction Force
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.19.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100778" speakername="Lord Garden" colon="" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_wqn3">
	<p pid="b.19.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.19.1/2" qnum="HL1585">What proportion of the trained establishment of the Civil Contingency Reserve Force is available in each region of the United Kingdom.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.19.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_spmin2">
	<p pid="b.19.2/1">I am assuming that the noble Lord is referring to the Civil Contingency Reaction Force (CCRF). All CCRFs in the 14 day designated regions are fully manned to respond effectively to the demands made upon them. When CCRF members are mobilised for overseas commitments they are immediately replaced by other personnel.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.19.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_wqn4">
	Cultural Property Website
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.19.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100527" speakername="Lord Redesdale" colon="" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_wqn4">
	<p pid="b.19.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.19.4/2" qnum="HL1855">What progress they have made on developing a cultural property advice website.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.19.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100164" speakername="Lord Davies of Oldham" colon=":" colnum="19"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_spnew1">
	<p pid="b.19.5/1">The Museums, Libraries and Archives Council has contracted independent consultants to create the content for a website which will include a variety of information relating to cultural property. Running alongside that project, and funded by this department, is the setting up of a linked site which will offer advice to those to wishing purchase cultural property.</p>
	<p pid="b.19.5/2">It is intended that both interlinked sites will be launched in 2006.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.20.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_wqn5">
	Democratic Republic of Congo
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.20.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_wqn5">
	<p pid="b.20.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.20.1/2" qnum="HL1858">Whether they will take up the recommendations of the International Crisis Group in its report of 19 October, DRC: A Congo action plan, that the United Nations Organisation Mission in the Congo (MONUC) should take the lead in preparing for military action against the Forces D&eacute;mocratiques de Lib&eacute;ration du Rwanda, and that MONUC should be strengthened so that it can fulfil its mandate to protect civilians.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.20.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w01.htm#51102w01_spnew2">
	<p pid="b.20.2/1">The United Nations Organisation Mission in the Congo (MONUC) has begun exerting military pressure on the Forces Democratiques de Liberation du Rwanda (FDLR), to disrupt their operations in the Kivu provinces. We have encouraged MONUC to take a robust stance against the FDLR, including in support of Congolese army actions, but are clear that the solution to the problem requires other measures as well as military pressure.</p>
	<p pid="b.20.2/2">The international community has made clear in UN Security Council resolutions that civilian protection is an integral part of MONUC's Chapter VII mandate. We would consider strengthening MONUC based on a realistic concept of operations presented by the Department for Peacekeeping Operations to the Security Council.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.20.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn0">
	European Consumer Centre
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.20.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100804" speakername="Lord Dykes" colon="" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn0">
	<p pid="b.20.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.20.4/2" qnum="HL1909">What steps they are taking to ensure that United Kingdom consumers are aware of their rights in the single European market, in terms of purchase and credit contracts.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.20.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="20"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_spmin0">
	<p pid="b.20.5/1">The European Consumer Centre (ECC) provides advice and assistance to consumers with queries about goods and services purchased from a trader based in another member state, including those purchased by a credit card. The ECC also distributes information on national and European consumer legislation and how it can be used in the UK. In the UK the ECC function is delivered by Citizens Advice, funded by both the European Commission and the Department of Trade and Industry.</p>
	<p pid="b.20.5/2">The ECC can also direct unresolved cross-border consumer queries to alternative dispute resolution (ADR) schemes, such as ombudsmen and arbitration, in other member states through a network of national clearing houses.</p>
	<p pid="b.20.5/3">The euroconsumer website (<a href="http://www.euroconsumer.org.uk">www.euroconsumer. org.uk</a>), developed by the UK ECC and launched in June 2004 provides top tips on avoiding problems, fact sheets on specific issues, contact details of UK ADR bodies, and a page to log queries. The site contains information on the importance of contacting the trader initially and how to do this. It also contains addresses and links to network partners in other member states.</p>
	<p pid="b.20.5/4">The Department of Trade and Industry also fund Consumer Direct, a telephone and online consumer advice service. Consumer Direct signpost any individuals with queries regarding their consumer rights in the single European market, to the UK ECC.</p>
	<p pid="b.20.5/5">The Department of Trade and Industry website provides consumers with information on buying goods and services in other EU member states and details the effect of EU directives on subjects such as sale of goods, timeshare and distance and doorstep selling. It also provides links to consumer advice organisations such as the UK ECC and Consumer Direct.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.21.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn1">
	Gaza: Israeli Withdrawal
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.21.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100650" speakername="Lord Turnberg" colon="" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn1">
	<p pid="b.21.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.21.1/2" qnum="HL1831">What representations they have made to the Egyptian Government about the smuggling of arms into Gaza following Israel's withdrawal.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.21.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_spnew0">
	<p pid="b.21.2/1">We have had regular discussions with the Egyptians about the Israeli withdrawal from Gaza, including supporting Egyptian efforts to regularise the situation along the border. We have also urged the Egyptians to exercise controls to prevent the smuggling of goods, including weapons, into and out of Gaza.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.21.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn2">
	Gaza: Reconstruction
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.21.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100851" speakername="Baroness Tonge" colon="" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn2">
	<p pid="b.21.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.21.4/2" qnum="HL1793">What discussions they have had with international financial bodies concerning investment in and the re-construction of Gaza.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.21.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="21"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_spnew1">
	<p pid="b.21.5/1">We are working closely with quartet special envoy for disengagement, James Wolfensohn, and the World Bank in supporting the efforts of the Palestinian Authority to prepare a medium term development plan for presentation to donors. The Government will ensure that their future assistance is in line with the plan's priorities and time-scales.</p>
	<p pid="b.21.5/2">We supported the European Investment Bank's recent work with the European Commission on proposals for helping to stimulate the private sector in Gaza and the West Bank. At the informal Council of Economic and Finance Ministers of the European Union on <phrase class="date" code="">10 September</phrase>, EU Finance Ministers invited the European Investment Bank and the European Commission to take forward, consistent with Mr Wolfensohn's efforts, technical work on a package to help support infrastructure and private sector development in Gaza and the West Bank.</p>
	<p pid="b.21.5/3">On <phrase class="date" code="">21 September</phrase>, my right honourable friend the Chancellor of the Exchequer (Gordon Brown) announced that he had commissioned a report into the opportunities to support economic development to accompany and enhance the peace process. The preparation of this report will involve consultations with the representatives of the international financial bodies with programmes in Gaza and the West Bank.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.22.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn3">
	HM Treasury: Expenditure on Taxis
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.22.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100271" speakername="Lord Hanningfield" colon="" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn3">
	<p pid="b.22.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.22.1/2" qnum="HL1917">How much HM Treasury spent on taxis in each of the past eight years.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.22.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100802" speakername="Lord McKenzie of Luton" colon=":" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_spnew2">
	<p pid="b.22.2/1">The Treasury's estimated spending on taxis in the past eight years is as follows:</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="b.22.2/4"> <td></td> <td>&pound;,000</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.22.2/5"> <td>1997&ndash;98</td> <td>83</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.22.2/6"> <td>1998&ndash;99</td> <td>149</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.22.2/7"> <td>1999&ndash;2000</td> <td>123</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.22.2/8"> <td>2000&ndash;01</td> <td>143</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.22.2/9"> <td>2001&ndash;02</td> <td>120</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.22.2/10"> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>163</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.22.2/11"> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>151</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.22.2/12"> <td>2004&ndash;05</td> <td>149</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="b.22.2/15">The figures for 2002-03 onwards include courier costs, since the Treasury has a combined contract for courier and taxi services, and it is not feasible to disaggregate the courier element. The figure for 1997&ndash;98 is an estimate, made part way through 1997&ndash;98, of the full costs of taxis for that year, provided in response to a previous Parliamentary Question. An actual out-turn figure for 1997&ndash;98 could now be provided only at disproportionate cost.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.22.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn4">
	Iraq: Weapons Used Against British Forces
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.22.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100029" speakername="Lord Avebury" colon="" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn4">
	<p pid="b.22.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.22.4/2" qnum="HL1631">What evidence they have of the nature and origin of weapons used recently against British forces in Iraq; and whether they will place copies of any such evidence in the Library of the House; and</p>
	<p pid="b.22.4/3" qnum="HL1701">Whether they will publish the evidence on which the Prime Minister based his statement that information about explosive devices used against British troops in Iraq suggests the involvement of either Iranian elements or Hezbollah.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.22.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_spnew3">
	<p pid="b.22.5/1">As a matter of routine, we examine weapons used against British Forces with a view to determine their origins. We are withholding this information on the grounds that to release it would prejudice the capability, effectiveness, and security of the Armed Forces.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.22.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn5">
	Israel: Security Wall
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.22.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100851" speakername="Baroness Tonge" colon="" colnum="22"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn5">
	<p pid="b.22.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.22.7/2" qnum="HL1791">What discussions they have had with the United States administration concerning the route of Israel's security wall, outside the Green Line.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.23.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_spnew4">
	<p pid="b.23.0/1">We have regular discussions with the United States administration concerning the route of the barrier. Most recently my right honourable friend the Foreign Secretary discussed this with the US Secretary of State on <phrase class="date" code="">15 October</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="b.23.0/2">The quartet (US, UN, EU and Russia) also discussed this issue during its meeting on <phrase class="date" code="">20 September</phrase> in New York.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.23.1" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn6">
	Israel: Security Wall
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.23.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100851" speakername="Baroness Tonge" colon="" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn6">
	<p pid="b.23.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.23.2/2" qnum="HL1792">What discussions they have had with the member states of the European Union concerning the route of Israel's security wall, outside the Green Line.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.23.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_spnew5">
	<p pid="b.23.3/1">We have had regular discussions with European Union member states concerning the route of the barrier, both bilaterally and at the monthly EU Foreign Ministers meeting in Brussels.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.23.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn7">
	Israel: Targeted Killings
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.23.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100851" speakername="Baroness Tonge" colon="" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn7">
	<p pid="b.23.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.23.5/2" qnum="HL1790">What action they will take in appropriate international fora with regard to the Israeli policy of targeted assassinations in Palestine.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.23.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_spnew6">
	<p pid="b.23.6/1">Israel has the right to protect its citizens from terrorist attacks, which we condemn absolutely. However, it must act within international law. Targeted killings are contrary to international law. We have repeatedly made this clear to the Israeli Government. We will continue to discuss and take action on this issue in international fora as and when necessary.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.23.7" nospeaker="true" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn8">
	Lisbon Agenda
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.23.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100518" speakername="Lord Radice" colon="" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_wqn8">
	<p pid="b.23.8/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.23.8/2" qnum="HL1724">Whether they will give specific responsibility for the Lisbon Agenda to a Minister; and, if so, to which one.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.23.9" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w02.htm#51102w02_spmin1">
	<p pid="b.23.9/1">The Lisbon Agenda covers a wide range of government activity across the economic, social, and environmental policy fields. Cabinet oversight and the committee system ensure consistency across all departmental activities, and the UK's national Lisbon reform programme&mdash;published on <phrase class="date" code="">13 October</phrase>&mdash;demonstrates the range of mutually reinforcing actions the Government are taking to promote the Lisbon goals.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.23.10" nospeaker="true" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn0">
	National Firearms Licensing Management System
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.23.11" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100416" speakername="Lord Marlesford" colon="" colnum="23"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn0">
	<p pid="b.23.11/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.23.11/2" qnum="HL1714">On what date they intend to reschedule the live (Beta) pilot of the National Firearms Licensing Management System required under Section 39 of the Firearms (Amendment) (No. 2) Act 1997; and</p>
	<p pid="b.23.11/3" qnum="HL1715">Who is the supplier of the National Firearms Licensing Management System required under Section 39 of the Firearms (Amendment) (No. 2) Act 1997; and what is the total value of the contract to this supplier.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.24.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_spmin0">
	<p pid="b.24.0/1">The National Firearms Certificate Holders Register as required under Section 39 of the Firearms (Amendment) (No.2) Act 1997 has been supplied by PITO and resides on the Police National Computer (PNC). The means to populate this register is being handled by means of the National Firearms Licensing Management System. The contract to provide this system was awarded to Anite Public Sector. The total value of all work carried out to date including the cost of the contracted work amounts to &pound;5.6m. The live (Beta) pilot of the National Firearms Licensing Management System has now been rescheduled to commence on <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-14">Monday 14 November 2005</phrase> for the Metropolitan Police Service and on <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-21">Monday 21 November 2005</phrase> for the Lancashire Constabulary. The first of these pilots will be observed by Essex Police and the second by Greater Manchester Police.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.24.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn1">
	North/South Language Body
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.24.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn1">
	<p pid="b.24.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.24.2/2" qnum="HL1602">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Rooker on 10 October (<i>WA 56</i>) concerning Ulster-Scots culture, whether they are committed to affording equal respect and recognition to Ulster-Scots and the Irish language.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.24.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_spnew0">
	<p pid="b.24.3/1">Yes.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.24.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn2">
	Northern Ireland Assembly: Staff Annual Bonus
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.24.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn2">
	<p pid="b.24.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.24.5/2" qnum="HL1742">What is the amount of the annual bonus paid to Northern Ireland Assembly staff to reward their performance during the introduction of devolved government; whether it continues to be paid in the absence of sittings; whether the bonus is pensionable; and how many people are currently in receipt of the bonus.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.24.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_spnew1">
	<p pid="b.24.6/1">An Assembly premium of &pound;1,000 per annum was awarded to all Assembly Secretariat staff with effect from <phrase class="date" code="2000-05-30">30 May 2000</phrase>. This premium continues to be paid to 256 Secretariat staff and is pensionable.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.24.7" nospeaker="true" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn3">
	Northern Ireland Civil Service: Sick Leave
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.24.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn3">
	<p pid="b.24.8/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.24.8/2" qnum="HL1617">What measures have been successful in the campaign to reduce sick leave in the Northern Ireland Civil Service.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.25.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_spnew2">
	<p pid="b.25.0/1">Managing attendance is a key priority within Northern Ireland departments and there is a comprehensive range of policies and procedures in place, aimed at helping and supporting staff throughout their illness. These include access to professional help and support while absent from work, and assistance with rehabilitation and any reasonable adjustments to ease a return to work. Considerable importance is also placed on trying to prevent staff going off ill by offering a range of health promotion activities and advice, and encouraging a work life balance.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.25.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn4">
	Northern Ireland Commissioner for Children and Young People
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.25.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100410" speakername="Lord Maginnis of Drumglass" colon="" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn4">
	<p pid="b.25.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.25.2/2" qnum="HL1663">How many staff are employed, and at what grade, by the Northern Ireland Commission for Children and Young People; what is its projected annual budget between 2005 and 2008; and what is the religious and gender balance of staff at each grade.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.25.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="25"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_spnew3">
	<p pid="b.25.3/1">At present there are 19 permanent staff employed in the Office of the Commissioner for Children and Young People for Northern Ireland. Due to the relatively small number employed in the organisation, information on religion and gender has been grouped to protect the anonymity of individuals. The grades within the organisation are equivalent to Northern Ireland Civil Service grades.</p>
	<table>
		<caption>Group 1: One Grade 3, Grade 5, Grade 6 and two Grade 7s.</caption>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/5"> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/6"> <td>Total number of staff</td> <td>5</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/7"> <td><i>Religious affiliation</i></td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/8"> <td>Roman Catholic</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/9"> <td>Protestant</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/10"> <td>Neither</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/11"> <td><i>Gender</i></td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/12"> <td>Male</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/13"> <td>Female</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/14"> <td>Disability</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<table>
		<caption>Group 2: Three Deputy Principals, four Staff Officers, -- three EOIs, three EOIIs, four AOs and four AAs.</caption>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/20"> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/21"> <td>Total number of staff</td> <td>14</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/22"> <td><i>Religious affiliation</i></td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/23"> <td>Roman Catholic</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/24"> <td>Protestant</td> <td>10</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/25"> <td>Neither</td> <td>1</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/26"> <td><i>Gender</i></td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/27"> <td>Male</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/28"> <td>Female</td> <td>11</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.25.3/29"> <td>Disability</td> <td>2</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="b.25.3/32">At this stage, the commissioner's projected annual budget is &pound;1,897,000 for each of the following financial years &mdash;2005&ndash;06, 2006&ndash;07, 2007&ndash;08.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.26.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn5">
	Northern Ireland Department of Culture, Arts and Leisure: Funding of Festivals
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.26.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn5">
	<p pid="b.26.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.26.1/2" qnum="HL1620">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Bassam of Brighton on 10 October (<i>WA 61</i>) concerning the funding of festivals, who applied to the Northern Ireland Department of Culture, Arts and Leisure for funding of activities associated with the annual 12th July Celebrations; how much was requested; and for what and how the &pound;28,165 funding was allocated.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.26.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_spnew4">
	<p pid="b.26.2/1">Two applications for funding were received by the Department of Culture, Arts and Leisure for activities associated with the annual 12th July in 2005. In both cases, the amount of funding requested by the applicant was approved. Funding of &pound;22,650 was allocated to the Belfast County Grand Lodge to engage the services of a consultant to co-ordinate the Better Twelfth initiative, and a further &pound;5,515 was also allocated to the Belfast County Grand Lodge to co-ordinate a 12th July art competition for schools</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.26.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn6">
	Northern Ireland Department of Culture, Arts and Leisure: Funding of Festivals
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.26.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn6">
	<p pid="b.26.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.26.4/2" qnum="HL1725">When the Northern Ireland Department of Culture, Arts and Leisure received (a) applications; and (b) business cases for the funding of festivals in West Belfast, New Lodge and Ardoyne in 2005; when these applications were agreed and letters of offer sent; and whether they will place copies of these documents in the Library of the House.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.26.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_spnew5">
	<p pid="b.26.5/1">The information is as follows.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="b.26.5/4"> <td>Festival</td> <td>Application and Business Case received</td> <td>Letter of Offer Issued</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.26.5/5"> <td>West Belfast</td> <td>20 June 2005</td> <td>None to date</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.26.5/6"> <td>Gtr New Lodge</td> <td>29 June 2005</td> <td>26 July 2005</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.26.5/7"> <td>Ardoyne</td> <td>20 June 2005</td> <td>29 July 2005</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="b.26.5/10">Copies of these documents will be placed in the Library.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.26.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn7">
	Northern Ireland Department of Culture, Arts and Leisure: Organisation of Festivals
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.26.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn7">
	<p pid="b.26.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.26.7/2" qnum="HL1730">How much the Northern Ireland Department of Culture, Arts and Leisure has spent in each of the past five years on consultants and away days, in connection with the development of policy for the organisation of festivals.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.26.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="26"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_spnew6">
	<p pid="b.26.8/1">The information is as follows.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="b.26.8/4"> <td></td> <td>2001</td> <td>2002</td> <td>2003</td> <td>2004</td> <td>2005</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.26.8/5"> <td>Consultants</td> <td>NIL</td> <td>NIL</td> <td>&pound;51,780.53</td> <td>NIL</td> <td>NIL</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.26.8/6"> <td>One Day Consultations</td> <td>NIL</td> <td>NIL</td> <td>&pound;1,640</td> <td>NIL</td> <td>NIL</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.27.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="27"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn8">
	Northern Ireland Department of Culture, Arts and Leisure: West Belfast Festival
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.27.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="27"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn8">
	<p pid="b.27.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.27.1/2" qnum="HL1603">On what date the letter offering funding from the Northern Ireland Department of Culture, Arts and Leisure was issued to the West Belfast Festival this year; and how much funding it offered.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.27.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="27"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_spnew7">
	<p pid="b.27.2/1">No such letter has been issued.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.27.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="27"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn9">
	Northern Ireland Equality Commission
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.27.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100410" speakername="Lord Maginnis of Drumglass" colon="" colnum="27"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_wqn9">
	<p pid="b.27.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.27.4/2" qnum="HL1661">How many staff are employed, and at what grade, by the Northern Ireland Equality Commission; what was its annual budget between 1999 and 2005; and what is the religious and gender balance of staff at each grade.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.27.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="27"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w03.htm#51102w03_spnew8">
	<p pid="b.27.5/1">A total of 137 are employed by the Equality Commission for Northern Ireland. Thirty-two per cent of the staff are male and 68 per cent. female. The following table provides the gender breakdown in relation to each grade.</p>
	<table>
		<caption>Staffing numbers by grade as at 18 October 2005</caption>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/5"> <td></td> <td>Gender</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/6"> <td>Grade</td> <td>Male</td> <td>Female</td> <td>Total</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/7"> <td>Grade 5</td> <td>-</td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/8"> <td>Grade 6</td> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/9"> <td>Grade 7</td> <td>-</td> <td>3</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/10"> <td>Deputy Principal</td> <td>12</td> <td>9</td> <td>21</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/11"> <td>Staff Officer</td> <td>17</td> <td>37</td> <td>54</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/12"> <td>Executive Officer 1</td> <td>5</td> <td>11</td> <td>16</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/13"> <td>Executive Officer 2/PS</td> <td>0</td> <td>4</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/14"> <td>Administrative Officer</td> <td>4</td> <td>24</td> <td>28</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/15"> <td>Administrative Assistant</td> <td>5</td> <td>1</td> <td>6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/16"> <td>Industrial (Cleaner)</td> <td>-</td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/17"> <td>Total</td> <td>44</td> <td>93</td> <td>137</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="b.27.5/20">Regulation 16 of the Fair Employment (Monitoring) Regulations NI 1999 prevents disclosure of the religion of the commission's workforce to the level of detail requested by the noble Lord. The overall breakdown however is that 36 per cent. of the workforce are Protestant and 58 per cent. are Roman Catholic. Six per cent have been classified as &quot;non-determined&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.27.5/21">The commission's annual budget between 1999 and 2005 is as follows.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/24"> <td>Year</td> <td>Budget (&pound;s)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/25"> <td>1999&ndash;2000</td> <td>2,823,426</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/26"> <td>2000&ndash;01</td> <td>6,116,000</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/27"> <td>2001&ndash;02</td> <td>7,359,000</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/28"> <td>2002&ndash;03</td> <td>7,512,000</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/29"> <td>2003&ndash;04</td> <td>7,024,000</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/30"> <td>2004&ndash;05</td> <td>6,779,490</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.27.5/31"> <td>2005&ndash;06</td> <td>7,137,000</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.28.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="28"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_wqn0">
	Northern Ireland Schools: Surplus Places
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.28.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="28"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_wqn0">
	<p pid="b.28.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.28.1/2" qnum="HL1678">How many vacant places there are in schools in Northern Ireland; what is the cost of those places; what proportion of the education budget this represents; and what action they propose to take to address this issue.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.28.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="28"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_spnew0">
	<p pid="b.28.2/1">There were an estimated 47,300 surplus places in schools in Northern Ireland in 2004&ndash;05. Of these, 31,600 were in primary schools and 15,700 were in post primary schools.</p>
	<p pid="b.28.2/2">Funding is provided to schools from the education budget mainly on the basis of the numbers and characteristics of the pupils attending rather than on the capacity of the school. Estimates for the overall costs of surplus capacity in classrooms are not available.</p>
	<p pid="b.28.2/3">Surplus places are removed from the estate through closures and amalgamations, and through the capital programme when buildings are replaced. The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Northern Ireland with responsibility for education has highlighted to the Education and Library Boards and the Council for Catholic Maintained Schools the need to take action to tackle surplus places and offered financial support towards the costs of speeding up rationalisation proposals. Following a review of the procurement and delivery arrangements for the schools' estate earlier this year the department has also been examining how to improve the planning of school provision in future, including the need for rationalisation.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.28.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="28"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_wqn1">
	Northern Ireland: Multicultural Strategy
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.28.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100629" speakername="Lord Tebbit" colon="" colnum="28"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_wqn1">
	<p pid="b.28.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.28.4/2" qnum="HL1754">Further to the Written Statement &quot;Northern Ireland: Racial Equality Issue&quot; by the Lord Rooker on 19 July (<i>WS 87&ndash;88</i>), whether they intend to pursue a multicultural strategy in Northern Ireland; and, if so, what benefits they would expect from such a strategy.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.28.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="28"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_spnew1">
	<p pid="b.28.5/1">The Racial Equality Strategy for Northern Ireland, together with The Good Relations Policy and Strategic Framework, which was published on <phrase class="date" code="2005-03-21">21 March 2005</phrase>, provide solid foundations for a future shared between and within the communities of Northern Ireland&mdash;both old and new. Both documents are available in the Library.</p>
	<p pid="b.28.5/2">If a &quot;multicultural strategy&quot; means one which encourages cultural separatism, then clearly that is not the answer. Society and communities benefit from diverse culture within a framework of integration where different racial groups live together, not just side by side. However, Government do not think that successful integration has to mean assimilation.</p>
	<p pid="b.28.5/3">Her Majesty's Government are committed to building a cohesive society by creating a sense of belonging based on common opportunities and mutual expectations on all people within Northern Ireland to contribute to society and respect others. This approach does not just apply to minority communities. Without widespread social participation and valuing of all local cultures, those from majority communities can also feel excluded or left behind by social change.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.29.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_wqn2">
	Northern Ireland: Classroom Assistants
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.29.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_wqn2">
	<p pid="b.29.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.29.1/2" qnum="HL1740">Whether in Northern Ireland teaching assistants are covered by the teachers' exemption in the fair employment and treatment legislation; and whether their appointments are monitored by education authorities in relation to fair employment law.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.29.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_spnew2">
	<p pid="b.29.2/1">Classroom (teaching) assistants are not exempt from the provisions of the Fair Employment and Treatment (Northern Ireland) Order 1998. It is the responsibility of the employing authority to monitor in relation to fair employment law.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.29.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_wqn3">
	Northern Ireland: Education Policy
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.29.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_wqn3">
	<p pid="b.29.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.29.4/2" qnum="HL1850">In what way education policy concerning streaming is different in Northern Ireland from that currently practised in England.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.29.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_spnew3">
	<p pid="b.29.5/1">Government policy in Northern Ireland, as in England, is that it is a matter for individual schools to decide how to organise their classes to best meet their pupils' educational needs.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.29.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_wqn4">
	Northern Ireland: Festivals
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.29.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_wqn4">
	<p pid="b.29.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.29.7/2" qnum="HL1598">Whether they will bring forward proposals to alter the funding of cultural festivals in Northern Ireland; and, if so, when.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.29.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_spnew4">
	<p pid="b.29.8/1">Yes. DCAL will consult on these after the publication of the Draft Priorities and Budget 2005.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.29.9" nospeaker="true" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_wqn5">
	Northern Ireland: Maintenance of Watercourses
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.29.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="29"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_wqn5">
	<p pid="b.29.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.29.10/2" qnum="HL1741">Whether they believe that the present arrangements for littoral owners to clear river beds and banks is effective and adequate; and whether they will consider bringing forward legislation to give the appropriate Northern Ireland department the power to undertake this work.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.30.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_spnew5">
	<p pid="b.30.0/1">Riparian owners are responsible for the maintenance of watercourses which are not designated by the Drainage Council for Northern Ireland. Some 6,800 kilometres of watercourses in Northern Ireland are already designated and maintained by Rivers Agency as necessary to ensure free flow. These are essentially watercourses where maintenance is beyond the capability of riparian owners and where intervention by Rivers Agency provides value for money. In the case of the undesignated watercourses, the agency may require riparian owners to undertake maintenance, with the possibility of prosecution for non-compliance. I consider that these arrangements are adequate and have no plans to bring forward legislation to transfer responsibility for the maintenance of all watercourses to central government. To do so would divert resources from essential flood protection schemes to protect life and property.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.30.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_wqn6">
	Northern Ireland: Population Figures
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.30.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100410" speakername="Lord Maginnis of Drumglass" colon="" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_wqn6">
	<p pid="b.30.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.30.2/2" qnum="HL1867">What has been (a) the overall population; (b) the number of births; and (c) the birthrate, in Northern Ireland for the years 1971, 1981, 1991 and 2001; and what are the Northern Ireland Statistics and Research Agency's projected figures for 2011.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.30.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_spnew6">
	<p pid="b.30.3/1">The following table gives the official estimate of the size of the Northern Ireland population; the number of births registered; and the birth rate, in Northern Ireland for the years 1971, 1981, 1991 and 2001; and projected figures for 2011.</p>
	<table>
		<caption>Table: The overall population, number of births and the birth rate, in Northern Ireland for the years 1971, 1981, 1991, 2001 and 2011</caption>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="b.30.3/5"> <td>Year</td> <td>Population 1</td> <td>Number of Births Registered 2</td> <td>Birth Rate 3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.30.3/6"> <td><i>1971</i></td> <td><i>1,540,400</i></td> <td><i>31,765</i></td> <td><i>20.6</i></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.30.3/7"> <td><i>1981</i></td> <td><i>1,543,000</i></td> <td><i>27,166</i></td> <td><i>17.6</i></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.30.3/8"> <td><i>1991</i></td> <td><i>1,607,300</i></td> <td><i>26,028</i></td> <td><i>16.2</i></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.30.3/9"> <td><i>2001</i></td> <td><i>1,689,300</i></td> <td><i>21,962</i></td> <td><i>13.0</i></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.30.3/10"> <td><i>2011    (projected)</i></td> <td><i>1,767,500</i></td> <td><i>21,400</i></td> <td><i>12.1</i></td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="b.30.3/13">1 Mid-year population estimates for 1971&ndash;2001 and projections for 2011.</p>
	<p pid="b.30.3/14">2 Births for 1971 include a small number registered to mothers who live outside Northern Ireland. Births are projected from mid-year to mid-year, the projected birth figure projected for 2011 is the average of the 2010&ndash;11 and 2011&ndash;12 years.</p>
	<p pid="b.30.3/15">3 Rate per 1,000 population.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.30.4" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_wqn7">
	Northern Ireland: Population Figures
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.30.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100410" speakername="Lord Maginnis of Drumglass" colon="" colnum="30"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_wqn7">
	<p pid="b.30.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.30.5/2" qnum="HL1868">What are the Northern Ireland Statistics and Research Agency's population figures for 11 to 18 year-olds in the years 2000 to 2004; and what are the projections for 2005.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.31.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w04.htm#51102w04_spnew7">
	<p pid="b.31.0/1">The following table gives the estimated population of Northern Ireland for 11 to 18 year-olds at <phrase class="date" code="">30 June</phrase> in each year between 2000 and 2004. Also included is the projected population of 11 to 18 year-olds for the year 2005.</p>
	<p pid="b.31.0/2">Table: Northern Ireland population estimate for 11 to 18 year-olds at <phrase class="date" code="">30 June</phrase> in each year between 2000 to 2004. Projected population of 11 to 18 year- olds for the year 2005.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="b.31.0/5"> <td>Year</td> <td>Population aged 11&ndash;18 years 1</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.31.0/6"> <td>2000</td> <td>212,300</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.31.0/7"> <td>2001</td> <td>212,500</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.31.0/8"> <td>2002</td> <td>213,200</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.31.0/9"> <td>2003</td> <td>212, 600</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.31.0/10"> <td>2004</td> <td>210,900</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.31.0/11"> <td>2005 (projected)</td> <td>208,100</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="b.31.0/14">1 Mid-year population estimates for 2000&ndash;04 and 2005.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.31.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn0">
	Northern Ireland: Post-primary Education
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.31.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100410" speakername="Lord Maginnis of Drumglass" colon="" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn0">
	<p pid="b.31.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.31.2/2" qnum="HL1869">What was the projected population figure for 11 to 18 year olds in the year 2005 on which the Northern Ireland Post-primary Review Working Group based its conclusions.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.31.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_spnew0">
	<p pid="b.31.3/1">The Post-primary Review Working Group considered a range of statistical information when making its recommendations for new post-primary arrangements, including post-primary school population projections (to 2009&ndash;10) and population projections for the 11&ndash;18 age group (to 2040). The group was concerned with the medium (2010) and long-term (2040) changes in population from 2001. The projected population figure for 11&ndash;18 year-olds in the year 2005 as used by the Costello Working Group was 207,267. An incorrect figure of 199,052 appears in the published report.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.31.4" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn1">
	Northern Ireland: Post-primary Education
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.31.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn1">
	<p pid="b.31.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.31.5/2" qnum="HL1944">Whether they will implement policies on post-primary education in Northern Ireland in accordance with the views of the majority of those responding to the consultation process.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.31.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_spnew1">
	<p pid="b.31.6/1">The Post-primary Review Working Group was required, by its remit, to provide advice on new arrangements for post-primary education, taking account of the responses to the consultation on the Burns recommendations, including the diversity of views on academic selection. In January 2004, the Government accepted the recommendations of the Post-primary Review Working Group as a sound basis for new post-primary arrangements, and these recommendations are being implemented.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.31.7" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn2">
	Northern Ireland: Post-primary Education
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.31.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100410" speakername="Lord Maginnis of Drumglass" colon="" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn2">
	<p pid="b.31.8/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.31.8/2" qnum="HL1961">When a departmental decision to introduce new post-primary arrangements in Northern Ireland was made; and what is the proposed date of implementation.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.32.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_spnew2">
	<p pid="b.32.0/1">On <phrase class="date" code="2004-01-26">26 January 2004</phrase> the Government announced that they had accepted the recommendations of the Post-primary Review Working Group as a sound basis for new post-primary arrangements in Northern Ireland.</p>
	<p pid="b.32.0/2">These recommendations are being implemented to enable the last transfer test to be held in autumn 2008, and the first pupils to transfer to secondary education under the new arrangements in September 2010.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.32.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn3">
	Northern Ireland: Primary Education
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.32.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100410" speakername="Lord Maginnis of Drumglass" colon="" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn3">
	<p pid="b.32.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.32.2/2" qnum="HL1870">How much is spent per capita in Northern Ireland on primary school education in (a) the controlled; (b) the Catholic maintained; (c) the integrated; and (d) the Irish medium sectors.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.32.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_spnew3">
	<p pid="b.32.3/1">The figures below set out the net expenditure per primary pupil for 2003&ndash;04 and have been taken from the latest available out-turn statements published by the funding authorities.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="b.32.3/4"> <td>Sector</td> <td>Per Capita Expenditure</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.32.3/5"> <td>(a) Controlled</td> <td>&pound;2,694</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.32.3/6"> <td>(b) Roman Catholic Maintained</td> <td>&pound;2,617</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.32.3/7"> <td>(c) Integrated</td> <td>&pound;2,954</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.32.3/8"> <td>(d) Irish Medium</td> <td>&pound;2,719</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="b.32.3/11">Notes:</p>
	<p pid="b.32.3/12">1. The figures include funding made available to schools under local management of schools funding formulae arrangements and funding initially held centrally held by the funding authorities and distributed to schools in the course of the year (such as funding for long-term sickness absences and maternity leave).</p>
	<p pid="b.32.3/13">2. The figures exclude resources for certain services (such as home to school transport, curriculum advisory support services and, school meals) which are managed centrally by the education and library boards and not costed to individual schools.</p>
	<p pid="b.32.3/14">3. The figures for the integrated sector includes funding for both the controlled integrated and grant-maintained integrated sectors.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.32.4" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#wa_table_15">
	Northern Ireland: Primary Education
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.32.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100410" speakername="Lord Maginnis of Drumglass" colon="" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#wa_table_15">
	<p pid="b.32.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.32.5/2" qnum="HL1871">Which primary schools in Northern Ireland, working under the aegis of the Council for Catholic Maintained Schools, currently have 40 or fewer pupils enrolled.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.32.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="32"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#wa_table_15">
	<p pid="b.32.6/1">The requested information, in respect of 2004&ndash;05, is as follows:</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/2">All Saints, Banbridge</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/3">All Saints, Omagh</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/4">Altayeskey</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/5">Anamar</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/6">Braid</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/7">Clintyclay</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/8">Crievagh</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/9">Envagh</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/10">Gortnaghey</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/11">Guiness</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/12">Listress</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/13">Loughash</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/14">Lourdes</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/15">Magheralough</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/16">Magilligan</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/17">Roscavey</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/18">St Anne's, Donaghadee</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/19">St Brigid's, Augher</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/20">St Brigid's, Plumbridge</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/21">St Colman's, Moira</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/22">St Colmcille's, Armagh</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/23">St Colomba's, Dromore, Omagh</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/24">St Davog's Scraghey</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/25">St Francis', Castlewellan</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/26">St James', Markethill</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/27">James', Tandragee</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/28">St John's, Eglish</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/29">St Joseph's, Ahoghill</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/30">St Joseph's, Artigarvan</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/31">St Joseph's, Caledon</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/32">St Macartan's, Dromore, Omagh</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/33">St Malachy's, Moneymore</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/34">St Mary's (Laught)</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/35">St Mary's, Aghadowey</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/36">St Mary's, Ballygowan</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/37">St Mary's, Comber</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/38">St Mary's, Fivemiletown</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/39">St Mary's, Rathlin Island</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/40">St Matthew's, Newtownsaville</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/41">St Patrick's, Aughtercloney, Ahoghill</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/42">St Patrick's, Carrickmore</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/43">St Patrick's, Newtownsaville</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/44">Tir-na-nog</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/45">Note:</p>
	<p pid="b.32.6/46">1. Enrolments taken as all children attending a school, including those in nursery and reception classes as well as year one to year seven.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.33.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn4">
	Northern Ireland: Public Order
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.33.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn4">
	<p pid="b.33.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.33.1/2" qnum="HL1785">Whether they consider the remarks of Father Alex Reid on 13 October, in which he described the Protestant population of Northern Ireland as Nazis, to be in contravention of the Public Order (Northern Ireland) Order 1987.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.33.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="33"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_spnew4">
	<p pid="b.33.2/1">The chief constable has advised me that the matter is currently under investigation. It would therefore be inappropriate to comment until that investigation has been completed.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.34.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn5">
	Northern Ireland: Railways
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.34.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn5">
	<p pid="b.34.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.34.1/2" qnum="HL1748">What plans they have to extend the railway system in Northern Ireland to (a) Comber; (b) Armagh; and (c) Banbridge.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.34.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_spnew5">
	<p pid="b.34.2/1">None.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.34.3" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn6">
	Northern Ireland: Railways
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.34.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn6">
	<p pid="b.34.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.34.4/2" qnum="HL1749">Whether they will encourage Northern Ireland Railways to run direct Enterprise trains from Londonderry to Dublin daily.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.34.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_spnew6">
	<p pid="b.34.5/1">There are no plans at present to run direct Enterprise trains from Londonderry to Dublin.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.34.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn7">
	Northern Ireland: Smoking Controls
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.34.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100345" speakername="Lord Kilclooney" colon="" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn7">
	<p pid="b.34.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.34.7/2" qnum="HL1830">Further to the Written Statement by the Lord Rooker on 18 October (<i>WS 48</i>), how many Members of the legislative assembly from each of the political parties support the proposal for a complete ban on smoking in workplaces and in all enclosed public places in Northern Ireland.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.34.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_spnew7">
	<p pid="b.34.8/1">The five main political parties in Northern Ireland are on record, through their party websites, as supporting comprehensive controls on smoking in enclosed public places and workplaces. All have welcomed <phrase class="honfriend" id="unknown" name="None">the honourable Member for St Helen's (Shaun Woodward's)</phrase> announcement on <phrase class="date" code="">17 October</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="b.34.8/2">In addition, 27 MLAs formally registered their support for such controls with the Department of Health, Social Services and Public Safety. The breakdown was as follows.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="b.34.8/5"> <td></td> <td>Number</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.34.8/6"> <td>Alliance</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.34.8/7"> <td>DUP</td> <td>4</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.34.8/8"> <td>SDLP</td> <td>3</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.34.8/9"> <td>Sinn Fein</td> <td>12</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.34.8/10"> <td>UUP</td> <td>5</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="b.34.8/13">No MLA formally registered opposition to the introduction of comprehensive controls.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.34.9" nospeaker="true" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn8">
	Northern Ireland: Teachers
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.34.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn8">
	<p pid="b.34.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.34.10/2" qnum="HL1729">Whether any education boards in Northern Ireland ask the religion of candidates for teacher appointments; if so, why; under what provision; and what is the information used for.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.34.11" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="34"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_spnew8">
	<p pid="b.34.11/1">No.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.35.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn9">
	Northern Ireland: War Memorials
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.35.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_wqn9">
	<p pid="b.35.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.35.1/2" qnum="HL1946">What role local authorities in Northern Ireland have in the building and maintenance of war memorials; and how the memorials which are the responsibility of the local authorities are defined.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.35.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w05.htm#51102w05_spnew9">
	<p pid="b.35.2/1">The Local Government Act (Northern Ireland) 1923 (as amended) provides that, subject to the approval of the Department of the Environment, district councils in Northern Ireland may erect war memorials, either alone or jointly with another council or councils. The 1923 Act also enables district councils to maintain, repair, protect or light war memorials.</p>
	<p pid="b.35.2/2">The 1923 Act does not define war memorials which are the responsibility of district councils. However, the power enabling councils to maintain, repair, protect or light them applies whether or not the memorials are owned by the councils.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.35.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn0">
	Palestinian Authority
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.35.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100650" speakername="Lord Turnberg" colon="" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn0">
	<p pid="b.35.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.35.4/2" qnum="HL1832">What discussions they have had with the Palestinian Authority regarding the resurgence of attempted and actual terrorist attacks against Israel following their withdrawal from Gaza and four settlements in the West Bank.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.35.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_spnew0">
	<p pid="b.35.5/1">We have had regular discussions on this important issue with the Palestinian Authority leadership. My honourable friend the Minister of State for the Foreign and Commonwealth Office (Dr Kim Howells) raised with Palestinian Authority representatives the need for the Palestinian Authority to build on the opportunity offered by disengagement, to stop violence, and to show real progress on security reform, during his visit to the region on 27&ndash;<phrase class="date" code="">30 September</phrase>.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.35.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn1">
	Private Notice Questions
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.35.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100645" speakername="Lord Trefgarne" colon="" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn1">
	<p pid="b.35.7/1">asked the Leader of the House:</p>
	<p pid="b.35.7/2" qnum="HL1902">How many Private Notice Questions have been tabled in each of the Parliamentary Sessions since she was appointed Leader; and how many of these she has allowed.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.35.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_spnew1">
	<p pid="b.35.8/1">Since my appointment in 2003, four Private Notice Questions were submitted in 2002&ndash;03; one in 2003&ndash;04; three in 2004&ndash;05; and two in 2005&ndash;06. One was allowed in Session 2004&ndash;05.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.35.9" nospeaker="true" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn2">
	Railways: Great Western Franchise
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.35.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100271" speakername="Lord Hanningfield" colon="" colnum="35"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn2">
	<p pid="b.35.10/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.35.10/2" qnum="HL1877">What were the findings of the Strategic Rail Authority's consultation exercise into the new Great Western franchise, in particular the continued operation of a sleeper service as part of the franchise.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.36.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100164" speakername="Lord Davies of Oldham" colon=":" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_spnew2">
	<p pid="b.36.0/1">The stakeholder consultation on the new Greater Western franchise closed on <phrase class="date" code="2005-08-02">2 August 2005</phrase>. Two hundred and fifty-three responses were received. Sixty-three responses related to the sleeper service. Some said that if usage was low it was reasonable to question the continued operation of the service, but most opposed its withdrawal.</p>
	<p pid="b.36.0/2">No decision has yet been taken on the future of the sleeper service. Bids for the franchise are currently being evaluated, and it is expected that the award of the new franchise, together with a decision on the future of the sleeper service, will be announced by the end of this year.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.36.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn3">
	Sudan: Darfur
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.36.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100012" speakername="Lord Alton of Liverpool" colon="" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn3">
	<p pid="b.36.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.36.2/2" qnum="HL1719">Whether the government of Sudan are co-operating with the International Criminal Court in its investigation of the violence in Darfur.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.36.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100817" speakername="Lord Triesman" colon=":" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_spnew3">
	<p pid="b.36.3/1">United Nations Security Council Resolution (UNSCR) 1593 of <phrase class="date" code="2005-03-31">31 March 2005</phrase>, which referred the situation in Darfur to the International Criminal Court (ICC), urged all states and concerned regional and other international organisations to co-operate fully with the court. In particular, it called on the government of Sudan to cooperate fully with the court. While recognising that states not party to the Rome Statute have no obligation under the statute, the resolution was passed under Chapter VII of the UN Charter and is therefore binding on UN member states.</p>
	<p pid="b.36.3/2">The ICC Chief Prosecutor has not made any public statement on co-operation between the court and the government of Sudan. The Chief Prosecutor will make his second six-monthly report to the Security Council in December as required under the terms of UNSCR 1593. He can use that opportunity to report any concerns in relation to co-operation between the court and the government of Sudan and other involved states and organisations.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.36.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn4">
	Ulster-Scots Agency
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.36.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn4">
	<p pid="b.36.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.36.5/2" qnum="HL1781">Why the money used to provide transitional funding for cultural festivals was not used to cover the projected shortfall for the Ulster-Scots Agency in 2004.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.36.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="36"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_spnew4">
	<p pid="b.36.6/1">There was no shortfall in the Ulster-Scots Agency's budget in 2004.</p>
	<p pid="b.36.6/2">Funding for festivals is a separate issue.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.37.0" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn5">
	Ulster-Scots Agency
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.37.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn5">
	<p pid="b.37.1/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.37.1/2" qnum="HL1782">Whether they afford the same recognition to Ulster-Scots and Irish culture, language and identity as to Irish language; why the Ulster-Scots Agency receives less funding than the Irish Language Agency; and what steps they are taking to move to equal funding.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.37.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_spnew5">
	<p pid="b.37.2/1">Yes. Funding is based on the agreed corporate and business plans of the relevant organisation.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.37.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn6">
	Waterways Ireland
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.37.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn6">
	<p pid="b.37.4/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.37.4/2" qnum="HL1682">Whether courses on bullying and harassment have been held in Waterways Ireland since 4 April.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.37.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_spnew6">
	<p pid="b.37.5/1">Yes, on <phrase class="date" code="">19 April</phrase> and <phrase class="date" code="">20 April</phrase> this year.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.37.6" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn7">
	Waterways Ireland
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.37.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="37"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn7">
	<p pid="b.37.7/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.37.7/2" qnum="HL1728">Further to the Written Answer by the Baroness Farringdon of Ribbleton on 21 July (<i>WA 324</i>) concerning Waterways Ireland, why the post of director of marketing and communications did not require relevant academic qualifications and experience, when the director posts required proven expertise in specific disciplines, relevant academic qualifications and membership of professional bodies.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.38.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="38"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_spnew7">
	<p pid="b.38.0/1">The appointment of the director of marketing and communications met the relevant criteria for the post.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.38.1" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="38"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn8">
	Waterways Ireland
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.38.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="38"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn8">
	<p pid="b.38.2/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.38.2/2" qnum="HL1737">Further to the Written Answer by the Lord Rooker on 6 June (<i>WA 36</i>), what best public sector principles and practices will be included in Waterways Ireland's written policy on recruitment and promotions to apply to future appointments and promotions.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.38.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="38"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_spnew8">
	<p pid="b.38.3/1">Waterways Ireland is a cross-border body. The chief executive of Waterways Ireland will ensure that best public sector principles and practices which operate in both jurisdictions will apply to its written policy on recruitment and promotions.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.38.4" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="38"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn9">
	Waterways Ireland
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.38.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="38"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn9">
	<p pid="b.38.5/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.38.5/2" qnum="HL1780">What were the wages and salary costs of Waterways Ireland in 2004; and how much was paid to staff in Northern Ireland.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.38.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="38"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_spnew9">
	<p pid="b.38.6/1">The wages and salary costs of Waterways Ireland in 2004 were &euro;14,543,503. Of this, staff in Northern Ireland were paid &euro;3,147,497.</p>
</reply>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.38.7" nospeaker="true" inserted-heading="true" colnum="38"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn10">
	Waterways Ireland
</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.38.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100358" speakername="Lord Laird" colon="" colnum="38"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_wqn10">
	<p pid="b.38.8/1">asked Her Majesty's Government:</p>
	<p pid="b.38.8/2" qnum="HL1784">What steps they are taking to reduce the religious imbalance in employment in Waterways Ireland in Northern Ireland.</p>
</ques>

<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/wrans/2005-11-02b.38.9" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="38"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds05/text/51102w06.htm#51102w06_spnew10">
	<p pid="b.38.9/1">Waterways Ireland is an equal opportunities employer and its employment practices reflect that policy.</p>
</reply>
</publicwhip>

