<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<publicwhip>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2207" date="2004-12-24" filename="day-bb-04_bb-12-24f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-04/bb-12-24f.htm">
*S2M-2207# Des McNulty: Make Poverty History Campaign in 2005—That the Parliament welcomes the UK Government’s commitment to the millennium development goals; welcomes the First Minister’s recent statement that Scotland’s devolved government can contribute to international development; notes that the crucial G8 meeting will be held in Scotland in July 2005; notes with concern that the current debt crisis, trade injustice and shortcomings of aid further exacerbate poverty, inequality, the HIV/AIDS crisis and environmental degradation across the developing world; notes that, if the international community is to make poverty history, then there needs to be further co-ordinated political action by the world’s governments, including the United Kingdom, aimed at trade justice, dropping the debt and providing more and better aid, and considers that the UK Government should lead the way for change and use its influence when it holds the presidency of the G8 and chairs the EU to make poverty history in 2005. Supported by: Bill Butler*, Robert Brown*, Richard Lochhead*, Patrick Harvie*, Scott Barrie*, Mike Pringle*, Mrs Margaret Ewing*, Trish Godman*, Robin Harper*, Murray Tosh*, Christine May*, Marlyn Glen*, Mr Alasdair Morrison*, Maureen Macmillan*, Cathie Craigie*, Mr Kenneth Macintosh*, Susan Deacon* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2207" date="2005-01-10" filename="day-bb-05_bb-01-10f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-01-10f.htm">
 S2M-2207# Make Poverty History Campaign in 2005 (lodged on 23 December 2004) Jackie Baillie*, Mr Mark Ruskell* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2207" date="2005-01-11" filename="day-bb-05_bb-01-11f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-01-11f.htm">
 S2M-2207# Make Poverty History Campaign in 2005 (lodged on 23 December 2004) Dr Elaine Murray*, Mrs Mary Mulligan* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2207" date="2005-01-12" filename="day-bb-05_bb-01-12f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-01-12f.htm">
 S2M-2207 # Make Poverty History Campaign in 2005 (lodged on 23 December 2004) Mr John Swinney*, Margaret Smith*, Marilyn Livingstone*, Irene Oldfather*, Ms Wendy Alexander*, Brian Adam*, Karen Gillon* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2207" date="2005-01-13" filename="day-bb-05_bb-01-13f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-01-13f.htm">
 S2M-2207# Make Poverty History Campaign in 2005 (lodged on 23 December 2004) Donald Gorrie*, Linda Fabiani*, David Mundell*, Mike Watson*, Richard Baker*, Shiona Baird*, Chris Ballance*, Eleanor Scott*, Mark Ballard*, Rob Gibson* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2207" date="2005-01-14" filename="day-bb-05_bb-01-14f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-01-14f.htm">
 S2M-2207# Make Poverty History Campaign in 2005 (lodged on 23 December 2004) Karen Whitefield* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2207" date="2005-01-17" filename="day-bb-05_bb-01-17f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-01-17f.htm">
 S2M-2207# Make Poverty History Campaign in 2005 (lodged on 23 December 2004) Mr Frank McAveety*, Alex Neil* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2207" date="2005-01-19" filename="day-bb-05_bb-01-19f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-01-19f.htm">
 S2M-2207# Make Poverty History Campaign in 2005 (lodged on 23 December 2004) Sarah Boyack*, Dennis Canavan* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2207" date="2005-01-20" filename="day-bb-05_bb-01-20f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-01-20f.htm">
 S2M-2207# Make Poverty History Campaign in 2005 (lodged on 23 December 2004) Mr Duncan McNeil* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2207" date="2005-01-27" filename="day-bb-05_bb-01-27f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-01-27f.htm">
 S2M-2207 #Make Poverty History Campaign in 2005 (lodged on 23 December 2004) Elaine Smith* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2207" date="2005-02-04" filename="day-bb-05_bb-02-04f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-02-04f.htm">
 S2M-2207# Make Poverty History Campaign in 2005 (lodged on 23 December 2004) Mr John Home Robertson* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2207" date="2005-02-14" filename="day-bb-05_BB-02-14f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/BB-02-14f.htm">
 Business Bulletin No.27/2005: Monday 14 February 2005 Contents An A B C D E F G H I J Section F – Motions and Amendments Motions and amendments are normally only printed the day after the day on which they are lodged and then with the complete list of motions and amendments lodged the previous week which is published in this section of the Bulletin every Monday. That list also contains any motions lodged for debate in the forthcoming week. Where the text of a motion or amendment is altered, the motion or amendment is re-printed with the changes marked by asterisks in the text. Where a motion or amendment attracts additional support after it is first published, that additional support is shown separately at the end of this section. Motions which members wish to be considered for debate as members’ business in the Parliament are marked with a hash symbol (#). Motions in which a member has indicated a declarable interest are marked with an "R". An indication is also provided where motions and amendments have been withdrawn. A full list of current motions is available to view each Monday in paper copy at the Chamber Desk or alternatively on the Scottish Parliament web site at Current Motions (http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/motionsAndAmendments/motions.htm). A search facility is also available on the Scottish Parliament web site at: http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/motionsAndAmendments/index.htm New and altered motions and amendments * S2M-2428 Mrs Nanette Milne:Congratulations to Prince Charles and Camilla Parker Bowles—That the Parliament sends its congratulations to Prince Charles, Duke of Rothesay, and Camilla Parker Bowles on the news of their recent engagement; hopes that the couple will enjoy many years of happiness together; is delighted that the couple have chosen to honeymoon in the beautiful north east of Scotland, and believes that the vast majority of people in Scotland will wish them well in this important step forward. * S2M-2427 Mrs Mary Mulligan:Congratulations to Home Aid, Bathgate—That the Parliament congratulates Home Aid in Bathgate, West Lothian, on its contribution to furniture recycling; notes that redistribution of furniture helps both the environment and those who find it difficult to furnish their homes, and congratulates Home Aid on its innovative partnership with Oregon in the United States of America for recycling furniture beyond Scotland. * S2M-2426# Mr Brian Monteith:Resources to Police Boards—That the Parliament recognises the vital role that the police play within Scottish communities; believes that it is vital that Scotland’s police forces are adequately resourced to ensure maximum protection to the public; acknowledges that Scottish police boards have very little time to brief and consult constituent local authorities before finalising the budget for their police force area; agrees that it is vital that figures provided by the Scottish Executive with regard to local authority grants are as accurate as possible to aid this process; therefore notes with concern that there were errors in the detail of local authority funding announced by the Executive on 8 December 2004 which have resulted in uncertainty facing many police boards across Scotland with regard to grant support for police loan charges and common police services; is concerned that some local authorities have had to source additional funding, such as Scottish Borders which has had to find an additional £650,000 from its already-agreed budget allocations, and therefore considers that the Executive should engage urgently with our police boards to resolve any problems and to ensure that such mistakes are not repeated in the future. * S2M-2425# Pauline McNeill:Franz Ferdinand Rocks—That the Parliament congratulates Franz Ferdinand on winning the Best British Band and Best Rock Act awards at the 25th Brit Awards; welcomes the First Minister’s view that Scotland should be a future host to the Brit Awards; notes that Scotland has an abundance of talented musicians, demonstrated by the fact that 11 acts are to appear at the international music festival in Texas, South by Southwest; believes that Scotland has a strong contemporary music industry which makes a significant contribution to the Scottish economy, comprising of small, medium and large companies; supports the work of the Cross Party Group on the Scottish Contemporary Music Industry which brings together virtually all strands of the music industry; recognises the commitment of the Scottish Executive to the industry and the funding of research into the feasibility of creating a music industry forum; further recognises initiatives such as Music Works, funded by Scottish Enterprise, and the need for the enterprise agencies to promote a distinct music industry strategy so as to encourage further development of Scottish-based musicians and related business activity, and sends its good wishes to all bands who are participating in South by Southwest. Supported by: John Home Robertson*, Richard Baker*, Bristow Muldoon*, Patrick Harvie*, Mike Watson*, Mr Alasdair Morrison*, Sarah Boyack*, Christine May*, Alex Neil*, Trish Godman* * S2M-2424 Stewart Stevenson:The Fight Against Email Spam—That the Parliament welcomes the anti-spam alliance of 13 countries across the European Union and urges other countries to join them in the exchange of appropriate information as part of the fight to identify and close down sources of unsolicited marketing emails, many of which would, if seen by children, have the potential to corrupt and deprave. Supported by: Dr Jean Turner*, Helen Eadie*, John Scott*, Mr David Davidson*, Fergus Ewing*, Mr Kenny MacAskill*, Eleanor Scott*, Chris Ballance*, Richard Lochhead*, Mrs Nanette Milne*, Dr Elaine Murray*, Jim Mather*, Mike Pringle*, Ms Sandra White*, Brian Adam*, Ms Rosemary Byrne*, Alex Fergusson*, Bristow Muldoon*, Robin Harper* S2M-2423 # Tommy Sheridan:Commiserations to Camilla—That the Parliament notes the forthcoming marriage of Prince Charles and Camilla Parker Bowles; expresses its congratulations to the heir to the throne for finally making an honest man and woman of himself and his bidie-in, and expresses commiserations to the bride-to-be on marrying into a family which has been described as dysfunctional. Supported by: Ms Rosemary Byrne* S2M-2422 # Tommy Sheridan:Tax the Rich—That the Parliament notes the Prime Minister’s recent rejection of a higher top-rate income tax level; believes that such protection of the rich and super-rich amounts to a “protection racket” which ensures that the obscene income inequality gap in Scotland and across Britain continues to grow and shame our society, and further believes that higher tax rates linked to a living minimum wage and legal maximum wage would radically assault the twin scourges of low pay and inequality of income. Supported by: Ms Rosemary Byrne* S2M-2421 Cathy Jamieson:Fire ( Scotland) Bill—That the Parliament agrees that the Fire ( Scotland) Bill be passed. Supported by: Hugh Henry S2M-2420 Tommy Sheridan:Congratulations to Franz Ferdinand—That the Parliament congratulates the Glasgow-based band, Franz Ferdinand, for doing Scotland proud in winning the Best Group and Best Rock Act at the Brits Music Awards ceremony in London on 9 February 2005; believes that Scotland has an abundance of artistic and creative talent that should be nourished, cherished and promoted, and further believes that successful Scots performers, writers and artists should be more involved in developing an all-inclusive strategy to harness our talents across the whole of Scotland. Supported by: Dr Jean Turner*, Ms Rosemary Byrne*, Roseanna Cunningham*, Mr Bruce McFee*, Rosie Kane*, Ms Sandra White*, Tricia Marwick*, Chris Ballance*, Stewart Stevenson*, Eleanor Scott*, Colin Fox*, Mr Jamie Stone*, Pauline McNeill* S2M-2419 Margaret Jamieson:Responsible Development of Onshore Wind Farms—That the Parliament notes with concern the continued scaremongering on the subject of onshore wind farms; regrets the tactics being used by some members of the Scottish Parliament to promote the view that all wind farm proposals are in very remote areas; recognises the proposal to build Whitelee wind farm, which crosses the boundaries of East Ayrshire, East Renfrewshire and South Lanarkshire local authority areas and which, if approved, would be the largest onshore development in Europe, providing almost half of the Scottish renewable target, and would be immediately adjacent to a major centre of power demand; welcomes the potential 300 construction jobs over a phased 30-month construction period, the £250 million of contracts that could be tendered for by Scottish companies and the provision of an easily-accessible visitor centre, and calls on all interested bodies involved in this exciting project to work towards a successful outcome to coincide with the G8 summit’s focus on climate change when the eyes of the world will be on Scotland. S2M-2418 Iain Smith:Final Review of Oral Questions and Minor Rule-changes—That the Parliament (a) notes the Procedures Committee’s 2nd Report, 2005 (Session 2), Final Review of Oral Questions (SP Paper 287) and agrees that the changes to standing orders set out in Annexe A to the report be made with effect from Friday 18 March 2005, but that the current Rules 13.6 and 13.7 continue to have effect for the purposes of any Question Time in the week beginning Monday 21 March 2005; and (b) notes the Committee’s 1st Report, 2005 (Session 2), Minor Rule-changes (SP Paper 271) and agrees that the changes to standing orders set out in Annexe A to the report be made with effect from *18* March 2005. Supported by: Cathie Craigie S2M-2417 Brian Adam:Proposal for a Committee Bill—That the Parliament agrees to the proposal for a Committee Bill under Rule 9.15 contained in the 1 st Report 2005 (Session 2) of the Standards Committee, Replacing the Members’ Interests Order (SP Paper 266). S2M-2416 Irene Oldfather:British Heart Foundation - Real Valentine Appeal—That the Parliament recognises that heart disease is the UK’s biggest killer and that, every two minutes, someone in the United Kingdom has a heart attack; acknowledges that a healthy diet and regular exercise is the best way to avoid heart disease; agrees, however, that sufferers of heart disease should have access to the best levels of care possible; appreciates the work of the British Heart Foundation (BHF) for more than 40 years in leading the fight against heart disease by funding research, education and care; supports the charity’s Real Valentine Appeal which aims to raise £1 million to fund 30 new British Heart Foundation nurses who provide specialist care, reassurance and advice to patients, and encourages as many Scottish people as possible to get involved and post a Valentine note, either online on the BHF website or in a BHF shop window, to their loved one for a small donation to the campaign. S2M-2415 Ms Rosemary Byrne:Scottish Suffragette Women—That the Parliament pays tribute to the life of Flora Drummond; recognises her contribution to the suffragette movement; acknowledges the personal sacrifice she made while on hunger strike and in prison at nine different times; regrets that the role of Scottish suffragette women is not taught widely in Scottish education, and calls on the Scottish Executive to commemorate the role of Scottish suffragette women by pressurising Her Majesty’s Government for a posthumous pardon for all concerned. S2M-2414 Donald Gorrie:Review of SPCB Posts and Tasks—That the Parliament considers that, as part of its contribution to the Scottish Executive’s drive to make all government in Scotland as effective and economical as possible, the Scottish Parliamentary Corporate Body (SPCB) should appoint an outside consultant to examine and report on the numbers and remits of the staff employed at Grades 5 to 8 by the SPCB in order to ensure that they match as well as possible the tasks which need to be done. S2M-2413 Shiona Baird:Historic Scotland Ranger Service, Holyrood Park—That the Parliament commends the Historic Scotland Ranger Service for its dedicated work in preserving the unique heritage of Holyrood Park; congratulates it on organising walks for MSPs during the Parliament’s Environment Week to inform them of this heritage, and urges more MSPs to engage with the fascinating history and archaeology on their doorstep. Supported by: Chris Ballance, Rob Gibson, Mike Pringle, Eleanor Scott, Robin Harper, Mark Ballard, Roseanna Cunningham, Colin Fox, Murray Tosh, Dr Jean Turner*, Mr Kenny MacAskill*, Mr David Davidson*, Ms Sandra White*, Patrick Harvie*, Mr Mark Ruskell*, Mr Jamie Stone*, Ms Rosemary Byrne* S2M-2412 Bill Aitken on behalf of the Edinburgh Tram (Line Two) Bill Committee:Edinburgh Tram (Line Two) Bill - Preliminary Stage—That the Parliament agrees to the general principles of the Edinburgh Tram (Line Two) Bill and that the Bill should proceed as a Private Bill. Supported by: Jeremy Purvis S2M-2411 # Bill Butler:Co-operative Education—That the Parliament commends the work being undertaken by the Co-operative Group in Scotland to work in partnership with the Scottish Executive and local authorities to introduce knowledge and experience of co-operative principles into the mainstream curriculum of Scottish education; recognises that co-operatives offer a unique and valuable form of business structure from which Scotland can derive economic and social benefit and recognises the need to make more Scots aware of the value of co-operation; supports the establishment of the Co-operative Education Trust Scotland which will involve the wider co-operative movement in education, and believes that the Scottish Executive, Careers Scotland, Learning and Teaching Scotland and local authorities should continue to work with the co-operative movement to ensure the distribution of co-operative resource materials for use in schools, support for teacher placements in the co-operative business environment and support for the involvement of the young co-operatives in schools. Supported by: Eleanor Scott, Mr Kenneth Macintosh, Rosie Kane, Sarah Boyack, Mr Alasdair Morrison, Mr Jamie Stone, Mike Watson, Marlyn Glen, Ms Wendy Alexander, Christine May, Helen Eadie, Cathie Craigie, Bristow Muldoon, Linda Fabiani, Michael McMahon, Elaine Smith, Margaret Jamieson, Jackie Baillie, Mr Frank McAveety, Scott Barrie, Mrs Margaret Ewing, Marilyn Livingstone, Janis Hughes, Ms Sandra White*, Mr Mark Ruskell*, Maureen Macmillan* S2M-2409 Carolyn Leckie:Justice and Apology for the Conlon and Maguire Families—That the Parliament welcomes the visit to the House of Commons on 9 February 2005 by Gerry Conlon and other members of the Conlon and Maguire families, who were victims of one of Britain’s most appalling miscarriages of justice and were wrongfully imprisoned for terms of up to 15 years for crimes they had no part in; notes that Guiseppe Conlon, father of Gerry Conlon, died in prison while serving a sentence for a crime he did not commit; considers that the public apology hoped for by the families from the UK Government for this terrible injustice is long overdue; notes with grave concern that, despite the overturning of all the sentences on the Conlon and Maguire families in 1989 and 1991, no police officers or other officials involved in this injustice have ever been prosecuted for their part in it, nor has the UK Government officially recognised that they were all innocent, and believes that the UK Government should issue a full apology to all, that agreement should be reached with all the families on appropriate financial compensation and that justice should be seen to be done for the injustice they suffered. Supported by: Frances Curran, Rosie Kane, Chris Ballance, Ms Rosemary Byrne, Tommy Sheridan, Colin Fox S2M-2408 # Donald Gorrie:Suicides by Older People in Scotland—That the Parliament is concerned at the statistics about suicides by older people in Scotland, especially older men; believes that more attention needs to be given to treating depression in general and, especially, among older people, persuading older men suffering from depression to discuss their problems with their GP and improving the performance of the primary care system in recognising the symptoms of depression and treating it more rapidly, and considers that the relevant authorities should undertake more research into the causes of depression and suicide and should add older people as a priority group to the other seven priority groups focused on in Choose Life, the national strategy to prevent suicide. Supported by: Iain Smith, Mike Pringle, Robert Brown, John Farquhar Munro, Margaret Smith, Jeremy Purvis, George Lyon, Nora Radcliffe, Ms Sandra White* S2M-2407 Mark Ballard:Link Between Transport Choices and Income—That the Parliament notes the finding of the Scottish Household Survey that, in households with a net income of £5,000 to £10,000, only 20% of householders drive regularly while 55% use the bus regularly, whereas in households with an income of over £40,000, 74% drive regularly and only 29% regularly use the bus; further notes that the data ranges between these two extremes show that the wealthier the household, the more likely its members are to use a car and the less likely they are to use a bus; believes that this survey reflects the income distribution and transport choices of people who will be subject to Edinburgh’s congestion charge which will, therefore, be levied proportionately more on the rich and not the poor; commends the Yes to Edinburgh campaign and the Get Edinburgh Moving campaign for their brave work towards tackling gridlock in Edinburgh, and condemns the Scottish Socialist Party, the Scottish National Party, the Scottish Liberal Democrats and the Scottish Conservative and Unionist Party for campaigning against action to prevent congestion, respiratory disease and road death, all of which disproportionately affect low income Edinburgh households without cars. Supported by: Robin Harper S2M-2406 Alex Neil:Scottish Development International—That the Parliament conveys its congratulations to Scottish Development International for being declared the “world’s most consistently high performing agency” by GDP Global Development which reached this conclusion after conducting a survey of 178 investment agencies across the world as part of an annual performance benchmarking exercise. Supported by: Michael Matheson, Ms Sandra White*, Christine May* S2M-2405 Lewis Macdonald:The Draft Landfill Allowances Scheme ( Scotland) Regulations 2005—That the Environment and Rural Development Committee recommends that the draft Landfill Allowances Scheme ( Scotland) Regulations 2005 be approved. Supported by: Ross Finnie S2M-2404 Johann Lamont:The Draft Housing Support Grant ( Scotland) Order 2005—That the Communities Committee recommends that the draft Housing Support Grant ( Scotland) Order 2005 be approved. Supported by: Malcolm Chisholm S2M-2403 Allan Wilson:The Draft Renewables Obligation ( Scotland) Order 2005—That the Enterprise and Culture Committee recommends that the draft Renewables Obligation ( Scotland) Order 2005 be approved. Supported by: Mr Jim Wallace S2M-2398 Christine Grahame:Tory Comments—That the Parliament condemns the comments of Dominic Grieve, the Conservative Shadow Attorney General, who stated on “Good Morning Scotland” on Monday 7 February 2005 that “The problem in Scotland has absolutely nothing to do with immigration levels. I’m afraid it is to do with the fact that Scotland is not a very attractive place for people to come and settle”, comments which demonstrate an insulting and ignorant attitude to Scotland, and calls on him to apologise to the people of Scotland. Supported by: Mrs Margaret Ewing, Alex Neil, Fergus Ewing, Michael Matheson, Fiona Hyslop, Rob Gibson, Brian Adam, Jim Mather, Roseanna Cunningham S2M-2392 Rosie Kane:Excessive Profits on BP and Shell Oil Companies—That the Parliament notes that the BP and Shell oil companies have announced record annual profits of over £18 billion; further notes that Shell and BP intend to pay out over £15 billion in dividends in 2005 and concludes that neither therefore requires their excessive profits for investment purposes; believes that, if carbon emissions are to be reduced, it will require the delivery of a fully-integrated public transport system, and therefore urges the Chancellor of the Exchequer to introduce a windfall tax of 50% on oil companies’ pre-tax profits, the windfall to be used solely to improve public transport in Britain such as improving ferry services to Scotland’s islands, improving rural bus services and restoring the Borders rail link. Supported by: Frances Curran, Carolyn Leckie, Tommy Sheridan, Ms Rosemary Byrne, Colin Fox, Chris Ballance* S2M-2388 Ms Margaret Curran on behalf of the Parliamentary Bureau:Approval of SSI—That the Parliament agrees that the draft Remote Monitoring Requirements (Prescribed Courts) ( Scotland) Regulations 2005 be approved. Supported by: Tavish Scott S2M-2387 # Christine May:Fairtrade Fortnight—That the Parliament recognises that Fairtrade Fortnight will take place between 1 and 13 March 2005; supports this important series of events in raising awareness of the need to provide workers and producers in Third World countries with a better deal in return for their produce; congratulates the growing number of towns and organisations which have succeeded in achieving the Fairtrade mark; notes that more Fairtrade products are being bought by individuals and used within businesses, and encourages all MSPs and consumers to participate in these events which will help protect the livelihood of small farmers and producers who too often face exploitation. Supported by: Donald Gorrie, Mary Scanlon, Mr John Swinney, Nora Radcliffe, Mr Jamie Stone, Robin Harper, Dr Elaine Murray, Elaine Smith, Richard Baker, Mr Andrew Arbuckle, Robert Brown, Tricia Marwick, Eleanor Scott, Mike Pringle, Brian Adam, Mr Kenny MacAskill, Alex Neil, Ms Wendy Alexander, Chris Ballance, Margaret Jamieson, Bill Butler, Linda Fabiani, Des McNulty, Richard Lochhead, Karen Gillon, Sarah Boyack, Michael McMahon, Mr Frank McAveety, Christine Grahame, Mr Bruce McFee, Mrs Margaret Ewing, Bristow Muldoon, Trish Godman, Fiona Hyslop, Susan Deacon, Mr Kenneth Macintosh, Ms Rosemary Byrne, Marlyn Glen, Helen Eadie, Cathie Craigie, Mike Rumbles, Scott Barrie, Marilyn Livingstone, Patrick Harvie, Ms Sandra White*, Tommy Sheridan*, Maureen Macmillan* S2M-2386 John Farquhar Munro:Ellen MacArthur—That the Parliament congratulates yachtswoman Ellen MacArthur after sailing around the world in record time and completing her 27,000 mile voyage in 71 days, 14 hours, 18 minutes and 33 seconds, beating the previous record set by Francis Joyon. Supported by: Margaret Mitchell, Alex Johnstone, Linda Fabiani, Bruce Crawford, Phil Gallie, Lord James Douglas-Hamilton, Jackie Baillie, Fiona Hyslop, Tricia Marwick, Shiona Baird, Nicola Sturgeon, Christine Grahame, Margaret Smith, Mrs Margaret Ewing, Murdo Fraser, Colin Fox, Fergus Ewing, Alex Neil, Mr Kenneth Macintosh, Mr Jamie Stone, Alex Fergusson, Eleanor Scott, Rosie Kane, David Mundell, Elaine Smith, Murray Tosh, Mr Jamie McGrigor, Mr Frank McAveety, Cathie Craigie, Mr Andrew Arbuckle, Mary Scanlon, Margaret Jamieson, Mr John Swinney, Mr David Davidson, Donald Gorrie, Ms Wendy Alexander, Christine May, Dr Elaine Murray, Mr Brian Monteith, Mr Alasdair Morrison, Mike Pringle, Ms Rosemary Byrne, Robin Harper, Bill Aitken, Michael Matheson, George Lyon, Karen Gillon, Susan Deacon, Dr Jean Turner, Mrs Nanette Milne, Marilyn Livingstone, Roseanna Cunningham, Ms Sandra White*, Mr Mark Ruskell*, Chris Ballance*, Maureen Macmillan* S2M-2385 Brian Adam:Commonwealth Local Government Conference 2005, Aberdeen—That the Parliament congratulates the city of Aberdeen on its successful bid to host the Commonwealth Local Government Conference from 15 to 17 March 2005 and hopes that this prestigious gathering, which will attract a number of heads of state and world statesmen, will enhance Aberdeen and Scotland’s position on the world stage. Supported by: Michael Matheson, Donald Gorrie, Mike Pringle, Stewart Stevenson, Jim Mather, Robin Harper, Mr Jamie Stone, Robert Brown, Rob Gibson, Mr Adam Ingram, Fergus Ewing, Eleanor Scott, Mr David Davidson, Des McNulty, Karen Gillon, Richard Lochhead, Tricia Marwick, Ms Sandra White, Dr Jean Turner, Mrs Nanette Milne, Nora Radcliffe, Alex Johnstone, Mrs Margaret Ewing, Maureen Macmillan* S2M-2384 # Linda Fabiani:Scottish Civic Forum—That the Parliament notes the concerns raised about the financing of the Scottish Civic Forum; further notes that the forum was set up to help fulfil the founding principles of the Parliament and, in particular, the engagement of Scotland’s people in the new democracy; considers that all those who have an interest in the open democracy heralded in 1999 should act to ensure a continued and healthy future for the forum, and believes that the Scottish Parliamentary Corporate Body should investigate the possibility of funding the forum directly. Supported by: Rob Gibson, Mr Kenny MacAskill, Tricia Marwick, Mr Jamie Stone, Ms Rosemary Byrne R, Fiona Hyslop, Christine Grahame, Bruce Crawford, Patrick Harvie, Alex Neil, Jim Mather, Mr John Swinney, Michael Matheson, Mr Adam Ingram, Donald Gorrie, Mrs Margaret Ewing, Eleanor Scott, Dr Jean Turner*, Mr Mark Ruskell*, Chris Ballance*, Tommy Sheridan* S2M-2383 # Alex Fergusson:The Museum of Lead Mining at Wanlockhead—That the Parliament recognises the 30 th anniversary of the Museum of Lead Mining at Wanlockhead in Upper Nithsdale, Dumfriesshire, Scotland’s highest village; applauds the trustees in attracting over 40,000 visitors over that period and recognises the many awards which have been achieved, including the 1993 Gulbenkian Award for “Most Improved Rural Gallery”, the Small Museum of the Year Award 1993 and the Kintore Trust Award for Conservation 1996; further recognises its economic importance to Upper Nithsdale as a recognised four-star tourist attraction and as the employer of up to 20 people during the opening season and commends Dumfries and Galloway Council on its ongoing financial support; notes with concern that all these achievements, and others, have been won through local funding alone with no central recognition of this unique monument to Scottish lead mining, and believes that the Scottish Executive should recognise Wanlockhead as a museum of national importance by bringing it under the auspices of the National Museums of Scotland. Supported by: David Mundell, Bill Aitken, Colin Fox, Alasdair Morgan, Mark Ballard, Alex Neil, John Scott, Mary Scanlon, Mr Ted Brocklebank, Alex Johnstone, Murdo Fraser, Mr Adam Ingram, Roseanna Cunningham, Tricia Marwick, Dr Jean Turner, Mr John Swinney, Mr David Davidson, Murray Tosh, Mr Andrew Arbuckle, Bruce Crawford, Chris Ballance*, Mr Jamie McGrigor*, Mrs Nanette Milne*, Rob Gibson*, Christine Grahame*, Phil Gallie*, Mr Kenny MacAskill*, Ms Rosemary Byrne*, Lord James Douglas-Hamilton* S2M-2382 Margaret Jamieson:Carers’ Cottage, Kilmarnock—That the Parliament congratulates the Princess Royal Trust East Ayrshire Carers Centre on the opening of the Carers’ Cottage, Howard Park, Kilmarnock, and recognises the donations of time, money, goods and vision by many individuals, public and private organisations to make the facility a reality for adult and young carers in East Ayrshire. Supported by: Michael Matheson, Donald Gorrie, Dr Elaine Murray, Jackie Baillie, Mr Kenneth Macintosh, Helen Eadie, Mrs Mary Mulligan*, Christine May*, Karen Whitefield*, Sarah Boyack*, Bill Butler*, Maureen Macmillan*, Mr Jamie Stone* S2M-2381 Chris Ballance:Scottish Civic Forum—That the Parliament recognises that Scottish Civic Forum was established, in line with the Constitutional Steering Group’s recommendations, as a key element for encouraging and enabling civic engagement with the Parliament and that its role was reaffirmed by the Procedures Committee in 2003; notes that over 2,500 people have participated in forum events in 32 areas of Scotland over the last two and a half years and that the Forum publicises Scottish Parliament consultations, publications and issues independently and neutrally to over 5,000 contacts each month; further notes that the forum acts as an independent commentator on public participation and the Parliament and forms a conduit for civic society to articulate its own agenda to politicians, and therefore calls on the Scottish Executive to guarantee continued funding to Scottish Civic Forum and indeed consider increasing funding in order to enable the forum to establish participatory hubs across Scotland. Supported by: Shiona Baird, Patrick Harvie, Donald Gorrie, Murray Tosh, Eleanor Scott, Ms Rosemary Byrne, Robin Harper, Trish Godman, Dr Jean Turner*, Ms Sandra White* Motions and amendments which have attracted additional support S2M-2378 Solidarity with Glasgow Airport Firefighters (lodged on 4 February 2005) Ms Sandra White*, Bill Butler* S2M-2377 Reduce the Risk of Cancer (lodged on 4 February 2005) Sarah Boyack* S2M-2375 The Right to Protest (lodged on 4 February 2005) Mr Mark Ruskell* S2M-2374 A Tribute to Martyn Bennett (lodged on 4 February 2005) Sarah Boyack* S2M-2367 #Call for Action on the A90 (lodged on 3 February 2005) Dr Jean Turner* S2M-2364 #Civilian Peace Service (lodged on 2 February 2005) Dr Jean Turner*, Mr Mark Ruskell*, Chris Ballance*, Mr John Swinney*, Mike Pringle*, Mark Ballard*, Robert Brown*, Mr Kenny MacAskill*, Tricia Marwick*, Jim Mather*, Ms Sandra White*, Ms Rosemary Byrne*, Eleanor Scott*, Christine Grahame*, Alex Neil*, Robin Harper* S2M-2362 No Extradition of the NatWest Three (lodged on 1 February 2005) Christine May* S2M-2343 The Royal Incorporation of Architects in Scotland: Sustainable Design Accreditation (lodged on 31 January 2005) Sarah Boyack* S2M-2328 #Fife Constabulary - Use of Antisocial Behaviour Powers (lodged on 26 January 2005) Karen Whitefield*, Bill Butler*, Dr Elaine Murray*, Helen Eadie*, Bristow Muldoon* S2M-2326 #Use of Rubber Bullets (lodged on 26 January 2005) Mr Mark Ruskell* S2M-2207 #Make Poverty History Campaign in 2005 (lodged on 23 December 2004) Kate Maclean* Contents An A B C D E F G H I J 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2207" date="2005-02-21" filename="day-bb-05_bb-02-21f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-02-21f.htm">
 S2M-2207# Make Poverty History Campaign in 2005 (lodged on 23 December 2004) Cathy Peattie* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2207" date="2005-03-02" filename="day-bb-05_bb-03-02f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-03-02f.htm">
 S2M-2207# Make Poverty History Campaign in 2005 (lodged on 23 December 2004) Iain Smith* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2207" date="2005-04-25" filename="day-bb-05_bb-04-25f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-04-25f.htm">
S2M-2207# Des McNulty: Make Poverty History Campaign in 2005—That the Parliament welcomes the UK Government’s commitment to the millennium development goals; welcomes the First Minister’s recent statement that Scotland’s devolved government can contribute to international development; notes that the crucial G8 meeting will be held in Scotland in July 2005; notes with concern that the current debt crisis, trade injustice and shortcomings of aid further exacerbate poverty, inequality, the HIV/AIDS crisis and environmental degradation across the developing world; notes that, if the international community is to make poverty history, then there needs to be further co-ordinated political action by the world’s governments, including the United Kingdom, aimed at trade justice, dropping the debt and providing more and better aid, and considers that the UK Government should lead the way for change and use its influence when it holds the presidency of the G8 and chairs the EU to make poverty history in 2005. Supported by: Bill Butler, Robert Brown, Richard Lochhead, Patrick Harvie, Scott Barrie, Mike Pringle, Mrs Margaret Ewing, Trish Godman, Robin Harper, Murray Tosh, Christine May, Marlyn Glen, Mr Alasdair Morrison, Maureen Macmillan, Cathie Craigie, Mr Kenneth Macintosh, Susan Deacon, Jackie Baillie, Mr Mark Ruskell, Dr Elaine Murray, Mrs Mary Mulligan, Mr John Swinney, Margaret Smith, Marilyn Livingstone, Irene Oldfather, Ms Wendy Alexander, Brian Adam, Karen Gillon, Donald Gorrie, Linda Fabiani, David Mundell, Mike Watson, Richard Baker, Shiona Baird, Chris Ballance, Eleanor Scott, Mark Ballard, Rob Gibson, Karen Whitefield, Mr Frank McAveety, Alex Neil, Sarah Boyack, Dennis Canavan, Mr Duncan McNeil, Elaine Smith, Mr John Home Robertson, Kate Maclean, Cathy Peattie, Iain Smith Motions and amendments which have attracted additional support 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2207" date="2005-04-27" filename="day-bb-05_bb-04-27f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-04-27f.htm">
 S2M-2207# Make Poverty History Campaign in 2005 (lodged on 23 December 2004) Christine Grahame* Contents An A B C D E F G H I J 
</spmotion>

</publicwhip>
