<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<publicwhip>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2188" date="2004-12-21" filename="day-bb-04_bb-12-21f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-04/bb-12-21f.htm">
*S2M-2188 Shiona Baird: Are You Cold?—That the Parliament congratulates the West of Scotland Seniors Forum, Glasgow City Council and NHS Greater Glasgow for launching the "Are You Cold?" helpline in response to research by Energy Action Scotland and the University of Strathclyde which has shown poverty to be the main cause of premature death among Scotland’s elderly; notes that too many vulnerable elderly people are still unaware of the free central heating and free insulation programmes, heating allowances and advisory services which are available to them; commends the helpline initiative for its clarity and simplicity in informing vulnerable older people about their entitlements, and urges the Scottish Executive to encourage the roll-out of similar, easy-to-understand and easy-to-access helplines across Scotland. Supported by: Robert Brown*, Chris Ballance* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2188" date="2004-12-22" filename="day-bb-04_bb-12-22f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-04/bb-12-22f.htm">
 S2M-2188 Are You Cold? (lodged on 20 December 2004) John Swinburne*, Eleanor Scott*, Fergus Ewing*, Rob Gibson*, Patrick Harvie*, Robin Harper*, Mr Mark Ruskell*, Murray Tosh*, Christine Grahame*, Ms Sandra White*, Mrs Nanette Milne*, Tommy Sheridan* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2188" date="2004-12-23" filename="day-bb-04_bb-12-23f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-04/bb-12-23f.htm">
S2M-2188 Are You Cold? (lodged on 20 December 2004) Ms Rosemary Byrne*, Roseanna Cunningham*, Trish Godman*, Donald Gorrie*, Frances Curran* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2188" date="2004-12-24" filename="day-bb-04_bb-12-24f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-04/bb-12-24f.htm">
S2M-2188 Shiona Baird: Are You Cold?—That the Parliament congratulates the West of Scotland Seniors Forum, Glasgow City Council and NHS Greater Glasgow for launching the "Are You Cold?" helpline in response to research by Energy Action Scotland and the University of Strathclyde which has shown poverty to be the main cause of premature death among Scotland’s elderly; notes that too many vulnerable elderly people are still unaware of the free central heating and free insulation programmes, heating allowances and advisory services which are available to them; commends the helpline initiative for its clarity and simplicity in informing vulnerable older people about their entitlements, and urges the Scottish Executive to encourage the roll-out of similar, easy-to-understand and easy-to-access helplines across Scotland. Supported by: Robert Brown, Chris Ballance, John Swinburne, Eleanor Scott, Fergus Ewing, Rob Gibson, Patrick Harvie, Robin Harper, Mr Mark Ruskell, Murray Tosh, Christine Grahame, Ms Sandra White, Mrs Nanette Milne, Tommy Sheridan, Ms Rosemary Byrne, Roseanna Cunningham, Trish Godman, Donald Gorrie, Frances Curran, Mrs Margaret Ewing*, Mary Scanlon* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2188" date="2005-01-13" filename="day-bb-05_bb-01-13f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-01-13f.htm">
 S2M-2188 Are You Cold? (lodged on 20 December 2004) Linda Fabiani* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2188" date="2005-01-27" filename="day-bb-05_bb-01-27f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-01-27f.htm">
 S2M-2188 Are You Cold? (lodged on 20 December 2004) Elaine Smith* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2188" date="2005-02-04" filename="day-bb-05_bb-02-04f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-02-04f.htm">
 S2M-2188 Are You Cold? (lodged on 20 December 2004) Dr Jean Turner* 
</spmotion>

</publicwhip>
