<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<publicwhip>

<spmotion spid="S2M-5147" date="2006-11-15" filename="day-bb-06_bb-11-15f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-06/bb-11-15f.htm">
*S2M-5147&lt;&gt; Mr Andrew Arbuckle: Community Energy Initiatives—That the Parliament supports community energy initiatives such those on Gigha and at Cathkin Braes; believes that not only do these initiatives involve and enthuse local people but that they also provide a template for other communities throughout Scotland, and further believes that the example of many continental towns where community heating projects exist also provides a possible answer to rising fuel bills and that pilot projects involving communities in Scotland should be encouraged. Supported by: Margaret Smith*, Donald Gorrie* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-5147" date="2006-11-17" filename="day-bb-06_bb-11-17f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-06/bb-11-17f.htm">
 S2M-5147 Community Energy Initiatives (lodged on 14 November 2006) Roseanna Cunningham* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-5147" date="2006-11-20" filename="day-bb-06_bb-11-20f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-06/bb-11-20f.htm">
S2M-5147 Mr Andrew Arbuckle: Community Energy Initiatives—That the Parliament supports community energy initiatives such those on Gigha and at Cathkin Braes; believes that not only do these initiatives involve and enthuse local people but that they also provide a template for other communities throughout Scotland, and further believes that the example of many continental towns where community heating projects exist also provides a possible answer to rising fuel bills and that pilot projects involving communities in Scotland should be encouraged. Supported by: Margaret Smith, Donald Gorrie, Roseanna Cunningham 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-5147" date="2006-11-23" filename="day-bb-06_bb-11-23f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-06/bb-11-23f.htm">
 S2M-5147&lt;&gt; Community Energy Initiatives (lodged on 14 November 2006) Nora Radcliffe* 
</spmotion>

</publicwhip>
