<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<publicwhip>

<spmotion spid="S2M-5050" date="2006-11-01" filename="day-bb-06_bb-11-01f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-06/bb-11-01f.htm">
 *S2M-5050 John Swinburne: Right of Tenure—That the Parliament is concerned by the fact that, despite recent legislation on housing, there still remain a number of houses within the private-rented sector from which the tenants can be served, without warning, with an eviction notice by the owner despite the fact that, for example, they were born in the house 70 years ago and have stayed there all their lives under the assumption that, as long as they paid their rent, they would have the peace of mind and security of the right of tenure. 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-5050" date="2006-11-02" filename="day-bb-06_bb-11-02f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-06/bb-11-02f.htm">
 S2M-5050 Right of Tenure (lodged on 31 October 2006) Carolyn Leckie*, Tommy Sheridan*, Ms Rosemary Byrne*, Frances Curran*, Rosie Kane* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-5050" date="2006-11-06" filename="day-bb-06_bb-11-06f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-06/bb-11-06f.htm">
S2M-5050 John Swinburne: Right of Tenure—That the Parliament is concerned by the fact that, despite recent legislation on housing, there still remain a number of houses within the private-rented sector from which the tenants can be served, without warning, with an eviction notice by the owner despite the fact that, for example, they were born in the house 70 years ago and have stayed there all their lives under the assumption that, as long as they paid their rent, they would have the peace of mind and security of the right of tenure. Supported by: Carolyn Leckie, Tommy Sheridan, Ms Rosemary Byrne, Frances Curran, Rosie Kane 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-5050" date="2006-11-08" filename="day-bb-06_bb-11-08f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-06/bb-11-08f.htm">
 S2M-5050 Right of Tenure (lodged on 31 October 2006) Donald Gorrie* 
</spmotion>

</publicwhip>
