<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<publicwhip>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2422" date="2005-02-11" filename="day-bb-05_BB-02-11f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/BB-02-11f.htm">
 * S2M-2422# Tommy Sheridan:Tax the Rich—That the Parliament notes the Prime Minister’s recent rejection of a higher top-rate income tax level; believes that such protection of the rich and super-rich amounts to a “protection racket” which ensures that the obscene income inequality gap in Scotland and across Britain continues to grow and shame our society, and further believes that higher tax rates linked to a living minimum wage and legal maximum wage would radically assault the twin scourges of low pay and inequality of income. 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2422" date="2005-02-14" filename="day-bb-05_BB-02-14f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/BB-02-14f.htm">
 S2M-2422 # Tommy Sheridan:Tax the Rich—That the Parliament notes the Prime Minister’s recent rejection of a higher top-rate income tax level; believes that such protection of the rich and super-rich amounts to a “protection racket” which ensures that the obscene income inequality gap in Scotland and across Britain continues to grow and shame our society, and further believes that higher tax rates linked to a living minimum wage and legal maximum wage would radically assault the twin scourges of low pay and inequality of income. Supported by: Ms Rosemary Byrne* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2422" date="2005-02-21" filename="day-bb-05_bb-02-21f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-02-21f.htm">
 S2M-2422# Tax the Rich (lodged on 10 February 2005) Frances Curran* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2422" date="2005-03-07" filename="day-bb-05_bb-03-07f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-03-07f.htm">
 S2M-2422# Tax the Rich (lodged on 10 February 2005) John Swinburne* 
</spmotion>

</publicwhip>
