<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<publicwhip>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2550" date="2005-03-09" filename="day-bb-05_bb-03-09f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-03-09f.htm">
*S2M-2550 Mr Brian Monteith: Stirling Council’s Neglect of Stirling’s Roads—That the Parliament notes the recent Accounts Commission report, Stirling Council - The Audit of Best Value and Community Planning, which states: "The Council’s road network is in a serious state of disrepair following years of under-investment. Stirling is one of only four councils where more than 20% of the roads network has deteriorated to a point at which it needs resurfacing to prolong future life. The Council has chosen to spend less than half its GAE allocation on roads maintenance. This makes it one of only three councils spending such a small amount"; further notes that previous reports, Maintaining Scotland’s roads by Audit Scotland and the Scottish Road Maintenance Condition survey for 2003-04 carried out by consultant engineers for the Society of Chief Officers of Transport also found Stirling’s roads to be in an unacceptable state and that Stirling Council’s own residents’ survey in 2002 showed that 58% of those taking part were dissatisfied with the level of roads servicing; understands that Stirling Council has chosen to spend less than half its GAE allocation on roads maintenance and that, while the sum Stirling Council has allocated in 2004-05 for roads maintenance is £2.3 million, the council itself has estimated that returning Stirling’s roads network to an average condition would cost in excess of £13 million, and calls on the Scottish Executive to ensure that Stirling Council’s Labour administration addresses its neglect of Stirling’s roads as a matter of urgency. 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2550" date="2005-03-10" filename="day-bb-05_bb-03-10f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-03-10f.htm">
 S2M-2550 Stirling Council’s Neglect of Stirling’s Roads (lodged on 8 March 2005) Alex Johnstone*, Lord James Douglas-Hamilton*, Murdo Fraser* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2550" date="2005-03-11" filename="day-bb-05_bb-03-11f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-03-11f.htm">
 S2M-2550 Stirling Council’s Neglect of Stirling’s Roads (lodged on 8 March 2005) John Scott*, Mr Ted Brocklebank*, Dr Jean Turner*, Bill Aitken* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-2550" date="2005-03-14" filename="day-bb-05_bb-03-14f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-05/bb-03-14f.htm">
 S2M-2550 Mr Brian Monteith:Stirling Council’s Neglect of Stirling’s Roads—That the Parliament notes the recent Accounts Commission report, Stirling Council - The Audit of Best Value and Community Planning, which states: “The Council’s road network is in a serious state of disrepair following years of under-investment. Stirling is one of only four councils where more than 20% of the roads network has deteriorated to a point at which it needs resurfacing to prolong future life. The Council has chosen to spend less than half its GAE allocation on roads maintenance. This makes it one of only three councils spending such a small amount”; further notes that previous reports, Maintaining Scotland’s roads by Audit Scotland and the Scottish Road Maintenance Condition survey for 2003-04 carried out by consultant engineers for the Society of Chief Officers of Transport also found Stirling’s roads to be in an unacceptable state and that Stirling Council’s own residents’ survey in 2002 showed that 58% of those taking part were dissatisfied with the level of roads servicing; understands that Stirling Council has chosen to spend less than half its GAE allocation on roads maintenance and that, while the sum Stirling Council has allocated in 2004-05 for roads maintenance is £2.3 million, the council itself has estimated that returning Stirling’s roads network to an average condition would cost in excess of £13 million, and calls on the Scottish Executive to ensure that Stirling Council’s Labour administration addresses its neglect of Stirling’s roads as a matter of urgency. Supported by: Alex Johnstone, Lord James Douglas-Hamilton, Murdo Fraser, John Scott, Mr Ted Brocklebank, Dr Jean Turner, Bill Aitken, Mrs Nanette Milne* 
</spmotion>

</publicwhip>
