<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<publicwhip>

<spmotion spid="S2M-5107" date="2006-11-08" filename="day-bb-06_bb-11-08f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-06/bb-11-08f.htm">
*S2M-5107 Dr Elaine Murray: Fund for Farepak Victims—That the Parliament welcomes the setting up of a fund by the Department of Trade and Industry to recompense Farepak victims; notes that retailers are being asked to make contributions; notes also that MPs are being asked to contribute a day’s salary to the fund, and urges MSPs to do likewise. 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-5107" date="2006-11-09" filename="day-bb-06_bb-11-09f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-06/bb-11-09f.htm">
 S2M-5107 Fund for Farepak Victims (lodged on 7 November 2006) Mr Andrew Arbuckle*, Robin Harper*, Cathy Peattie*, Mrs Mary Mulligan*, Mr Adam Ingram*, Mr John Swinney*, Ms Wendy Alexander* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-5107" date="2006-11-10" filename="day-bb-06_bb-11-10f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-06/bb-11-10f.htm">
 S2M-5107 Fund for Farepak Victims (lodged on 7 November 2006) Mr Jamie Stone*, Ms Rosemary Byrne*, Margaret Jamieson*, Trish Godman*, Scott Barrie*, Murray Tosh* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-5107" date="2006-11-13" filename="day-bb-06_bb-11-13f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-06/bb-11-13f.htm">
S2M-5107 Dr Elaine Murray: Fund for Farepak Victims—That the Parliament welcomes the setting up of a fund by the Department of Trade and Industry to recompense Farepak victims; notes that retailers are being asked to make contributions; notes also that MPs are being asked to contribute a day’s salary to the fund, and urges MSPs to do likewise. Supported by: Mr Andrew Arbuckle, Robin Harper, Cathy Peattie, Mrs Mary Mulligan, Mr Adam Ingram, Mr John Swinney, Ms Wendy Alexander, Mr Jamie Stone, Ms Rosemary Byrne, Margaret Jamieson, Trish Godman, Scott Barrie, Murray Tosh, Cathie Craigie*, Marilyn Livingstone* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-5107" date="2006-11-14" filename="day-bb-06_bb-11-14f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-06/bb-11-14f.htm">
S2M-5107*#* Dr Elaine Murray: Fund for Farepak Victims—That the Parliament welcomes the setting up of a fund by the Department of Trade and Industry to recompense Farepak victims*, such as those in Dumfries*; notes that retailers are being asked to make contributions; notes also that MPs are being asked to contribute a day’s salary to the fund, and *considers that* MSPs *should* do likewise. Motions and amendments which have attracted additional support 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-5107" date="2006-11-15" filename="day-bb-06_bb-11-15f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-06/bb-11-15f.htm">
 S2M-5107# Fund for Farepak Victims (lodged on 7 November 2006) Donald Gorrie*, Alex Fergusson* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-5107" date="2006-11-16" filename="day-bb-06_bb-11-16f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-06/bb-11-16f.htm">
S2M-5107# Fund for Farepak Victims (lodged on 7 November 2006) Irene Oldfather* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-5107" date="2006-11-20" filename="day-bb-06_bb-11-20f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-06/bb-11-20f.htm">
S2M-5107# Dr Elaine Murray: Fund for Farepak Victims—That the Parliament welcomes the setting up of a fund by the Department of Trade and Industry to recompense Farepak victims, such as those in Dumfries; notes that retailers are being asked to make contributions; notes also that MPs are being asked to contribute a day’s salary to the fund, and considers that MSPs should do likewise. Supported by: Mr Andrew Arbuckle, Robin Harper, Cathy Peattie, Mrs Mary Mulligan, Mr Adam Ingram, Mr John Swinney, Ms Wendy Alexander, Mr Jamie Stone, Ms Rosemary Byrne, Margaret Jamieson, Trish Godman, Scott Barrie, Murray Tosh, Cathie Craigie, Marilyn Livingstone, Donald Gorrie, Alex Fergusson, Irene Oldfather, John Scott* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S2M-5107" date="2006-11-21" filename="day-bb-06_bb-11-21f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-06/bb-11-21f.htm">
 S2M-5107# Fund for Farepak Victims (lodged on 7 November 2006) Maureen Macmillan* 
</spmotion>

</publicwhip>
