<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<publicwhip>

<spmotion spid="S3M-3775" date="2009-03-25" filename="day-bb-09_bb-03-25f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-09/bb-03-25f.htm">
 *S3M-3775 Bill Aitken: Combating Graffiti—That the Parliament agrees that graffiti not only reduces the appearance of many communities in Scotland but also has a definite adverse effect on the morale of people seeing it in their areas and congratulates the work carried out by Glasgow Community and Safety Services to clear graffiti from walls and street furniture, greatly improving the quality of life for Glasgow citizens. Supported by: Nanette Milne*, Elaine Smith*, Jamie McGrigor*, John Lamont*, Charlie Gordon*, Robert Brown*, Jackson Carlaw*, Murdo Fraser*, Kenneth Gibson*, Alasdair Allan*, Sandra White*, Ian McKee*, Robin Harper*, Hugh Henry*, Bill Butler*, Bill Kidd*, Patricia Ferguson*, Trish Godman*, Stuart McMillan* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-3775" date="2009-03-26" filename="day-bb-09_bb-03-26f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-09/bb-03-26f.htm">
 S3M-3775 Combating Graffiti (lodged on 24 March 2009) Bob Doris*, Gavin Brown*, Gil Paterson*, Des McNulty*, Jamie Hepburn* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-3775" date="2009-03-30" filename="day-bb-09_bb-03-30f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-09/bb-03-30f.htm">
S3M-3775 Bill Aitken: Combating Graffiti—That the Parliament agrees that graffiti not only reduces the appearance of many communities in Scotland but also has a definite adverse effect on the morale of people seeing it in their areas and congratulates the work carried out by Glasgow Community and Safety Services to clear graffiti from walls and street furniture, greatly improving the quality of life for Glasgow citizens. Supported by: Nanette Milne, Elaine Smith, Jamie McGrigor, John Lamont, Charlie Gordon, Robert Brown, Jackson Carlaw, Murdo Fraser, Kenneth Gibson, Alasdair Allan, Sandra White, Ian McKee, Robin Harper, Hugh Henry, Bill Butler, Bill Kidd, Patricia Ferguson, Trish Godman, Stuart McMillan, Bob Doris, Gavin Brown, Gil Paterson, Des McNulty, Jamie Hepburn, Margaret Mitchell*, Jack McConnell* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-3775" date="2009-04-22" filename="day-bb-09_bb-04-22f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-09/bb-04-22f.htm">
 S3M-3775 Combating Graffiti (lodged on 24 March 2009) Karen Whitefield* 
</spmotion>

</publicwhip>
