<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<publicwhip>

<spmotion spid="S3M-1091" date="2008-01-07" filename="day-bb-08_bb-01-07f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-08/bb-01-07f.htm">
*S3M-1091 Kenneth Gibson: Small Babies, Short Changed?—That the Parliament notes that in Scotland the number of babies born prematurely, before 37 weeks gestation, has remained fairly constant at between 6,424 and 6,880 over the last seven years; is aware that roughly one in eight of all babies are born prematurely and admitted to specialised baby units each year; commends the superb work and high level of care undertaken by medical and auxiliary staff in neonatal units; is nevertheless concerned that neonatal units are increasingly working in excess of their recommended capacity and with far too few specialised nursing staff; recognises that this vital service requires additional resources to ensure that neonatal units are staffed to provide appropriate levels of expert care; urges the Scottish Government to ensure that NHS boards are able to meet the standards set by the British Association of Perinatal Medicine in 2001 and further reduce mortality levels among premature babies, particularly very premature babies born before 28 weeks gestation; believes that babies should have the same one-to-one staffing levels in intensive care that adults receive; agrees that the various disciplines connected to maternity care must forge closer relationships and more clearly identify mothers at risk of having premature babies in order to provide them with earlier and clearer information about neonatal care services available, and welcomes the recommendations of BLISS, the premature baby charity, on how to tackle the main challenges facing neonatal care. 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-1091" date="2008-01-09" filename="day-bb-08_bb-01-09f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-08/bb-01-09f.htm">
 S3M-1091 Small Babies, Short Changed? (lodged on 3 January 2008) Brian Adam*, Christine Grahame*, Alasdair Allan*, Mary Scanlon*, Hugh O’Donnell*, Bashir Ahmad*, Bill Kidd*, Elaine Smith*, Stuart McMillan* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-1091" date="2008-01-10" filename="day-bb-08_bb-01-10f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-08/bb-01-10f.htm">
 S3M-1091 Small Babies, Short Changed? (lodged on 3 January 2008) James Kelly*, Jamie Hepburn*, Michael Matheson*, John Scott* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-1091" date="2008-01-11" filename="day-bb-08_bb-01-11f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-08/bb-01-11f.htm">
 S3M-1091 Small Babies, Short Changed? (lodged on 3 January 2008) Alex Neil* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-1091" date="2008-01-17" filename="day-bb-08_bb-01-17f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-08/bb-01-17f.htm">
 S3M-1091 Small Babies, Short Changed? (lodged on 3 January 2008) Dave Thompson* 
</spmotion>

</publicwhip>
