<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<publicwhip>

<spmotion spid="S3M-4128" date="2009-05-13" filename="day-bb-09_bb-05-13f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-09/bb-05-13f.htm">
*S3M-4128 Linda Fabiani: Police Non-emergency Contact Number—That the Parliament reaffirms its support for the principles of motion S1M-999 – "That the Parliament urges all members of the public who believe themselves to be in danger to contact the relevant emergency service by dialling 999 without hesitation; expresses concern that the recent campaign to minimise use of the 999 emergency call system may deter members of the public from contacting the emergency services on legitimate grounds; expresses its support for a full examination of the implications for the emergency services of the continuing expansion in forms of communication such as mobile telephones, and urges the Scottish Executive to initiate discussions with all interested parties to identify a means of responding to this challenge, in particular the setting up of a central call system which could connect callers to the local police station." - lodged on 12 June 2000 and calls for renewed effort to establish a single national non-emergency contact number for all police services. 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-4128" date="2009-05-18" filename="day-bb-09_bb-05-18f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-09/bb-05-18f.htm">
S3M-4128 Linda Fabiani: Police Non-emergency Contact Number—That the Parliament reaffirms its support for the principles of motion S1M-999 – "That the Parliament urges all members of the public who believe themselves to be in danger to contact the relevant emergency service by dialling 999 without hesitation; expresses concern that the recent campaign to minimise use of the 999 emergency call system may deter members of the public from contacting the emergency services on legitimate grounds; expresses its support for a full examination of the implications for the emergency services of the continuing expansion in forms of communication such as mobile telephones, and urges the Scottish Executive to initiate discussions with all interested parties to identify a means of responding to this challenge, in particular the setting up of a central call system which could connect callers to the local police station." - lodged on 12 June 2000 and calls for renewed effort to establish a single national non-emergency contact number for all police services. 
</spmotion>

</publicwhip>
