<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<publicwhip>

<spmotion spid="S3M-2714" date="2008-10-20" filename="day-bb-08_bb-10-20f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-08/bb-10-20f.htm">
 *S3M-2714 Cathy Jamieson: Who Cares? Scotland—That the Parliament congratulates Who Cares? Scotland on its 30th anniversary; recognises the valuable role that it has played in improving policy, practice and legislation on residential, foster and throughcare, as well as giving a voice to young people with experience of being looked after; regrets that the planned gala dinner at Kelvingrove Art Gallery has had to be cancelled after the pulling out of RBS and other business and financial organisations feeling unable to support the event due to the impact of the credit crunch; notes that Who Cares? Scotland will now be unable to realise the £75,000 fundraising target it hoped to achieve from the gala dinner; further notes that the loss of this potential income will impact directly on the future service and support available to young people, and calls on the Scottish Government to ensure that Who Cares? Scotland has adequate core funding to cover all of its planned work in the coming year, including those elements that the proceeds from the Gala Dinner would have financed. 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-2714" date="2008-10-27" filename="day-bb-08_bb-10-27f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-08/bb-10-27f.htm">
 S3M-2714 Who Cares? Scotland (lodged on 14 October 2008) Cathy Peattie* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-2714" date="2008-10-29" filename="day-bb-08_bb-10-29f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-08/bb-10-29f.htm">
 S3M-2714 Who Cares? Scotland (lodged on 14 October 2008) Jack McConnell* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-2714" date="2008-10-30" filename="day-bb-08_bb-10-30f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-08/bb-10-30f.htm">
 S3M-2714 Who Cares? Scotland (lodged on 14 October 2008) Peter Peacock* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-2714" date="2008-10-31" filename="day-bb-08_bb-10-31f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-08/bb-10-31f.htm">
 S3M-2714 Who Cares? Scotland (lodged on 14 October 2008) David Stewart*, George Foulkes*, Rhoda Grant* 
</spmotion>

</publicwhip>
