<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<publicwhip>

<spmotion spid="S3M-6860" date="2010-08-30" filename="day-bb-10_bb-08-30f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-10/bb-08-30f.htm">
*S3M-6860 Sandra White: Glasgow’s First Poet Laureate and Scotland’s Own Makar—That the Parliament pays tribute to the life and works of Edwin Morgan, Glasgow’s first Poet Laureate and Scotland’s own Makar, who sadly passed away on 19 August 2010, aged 90, considers Morgan to have been one of Scotland’s great poets and an inspirational force to all those who knew the man and his work; supports efforts to commemorate and ensure a lasting legacy for one of Scotland’s greatest in Glasgow’s west end where Morgan studied and lectured for a large part of his life; remembers the hopes and aspirations expressed in Morgan’s poem for the opening of the Scottish Parliament and hopes that, as Scotland’s parliamentarians prepare to return to Holyrood, the following excerpt from his poem – "We give you this great building, don’t let your work and hope be other than great when you enter and begin. So now begin. Open the doors and begin." – will ring true. Supported by: Kenneth Gibson*, Hugh O’Donnell*, Joe FitzPatrick*, Bob Doris*, Bill Kidd*, Stuart McMillan*, Anne McLaughlin*, Christopher Harvie*, Rob Gibson*, Elaine Smith*, Dave Thompson*, Liam McArthur*, Christina McKelvie*, Pauline McNeill*, Aileen Campbell*, Ken Macintosh*, Angela Constance*, Robin Harper* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-6860" date="2010-09-06" filename="day-bb-10_bb-09-06f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-10/bb-09-06f.htm">
 S3M-6860 Glasgow’s First Poet Laureate and Scotland’s Own Makar (lodged on 23 August 2010) Christine Grahame*, Michael Matheson*, Jamie Hepburn*, Jack McConnell* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-6860" date="2010-09-10" filename="day-bb-10_bb-09-10f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-10/bb-09-10f.htm">
 S3M-6860 Glasgow’s First Poet Laureate and Scotland’s Own Makar (lodged on 23 August 2010) Shirley-Anne Somerville* 
</spmotion>

</publicwhip>
