<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<publicwhip>

<spmotion spid="S3M-1103" date="2008-01-09" filename="day-bb-08_bb-01-09f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-08/bb-01-09f.htm">
*S3M-1103 John Lamont: James Thomson Memorial—That the Parliament congratulates Ednam, Stichill &amp; Berrymoss Community Council on the award of lottery funding to improve access to the Thomson Monument in the Scottish Borders which celebrates the importance of James Thomson, author of the words to the song Rule Britannia; recognises the historic role played by Scots such as James Thomson within the Union, and agrees that more should be done to celebrate the importance of Scots within the Union. Supported by: Nanette Milne*, Elizabeth Smith*, Jamie McGrigor*, Karen Gillon*, Jackson Carlaw* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-1103" date="2008-01-10" filename="day-bb-08_bb-01-10f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-08/bb-01-10f.htm">
 S3M-1103 James Thomson Memorial (lodged on 8 January 2008) John Scott*, Margaret Mitchell*, Mary Scanlon* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-1103" date="2008-01-11" filename="day-bb-08_bb-01-11f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-08/bb-01-11f.htm">
 S3M-1103 James Thomson Memorial (lodged on 8 January 2008) Ted Brocklebank*, Bill Aitken* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-1103" date="2008-01-14" filename="day-bb-08_bb-01-14f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-08/bb-01-14f.htm">
 S3M-1103 John Lamont: James Thomson Memorial—That the Parliament congratulates Ednam, Stichill &amp; Berrymoss Community Council on the award of lottery funding to improve access to the Thomson Monument in the Scottish Borders which celebrates the importance of James Thomson, author of the words to the song Rule Britannia; recognises the historic role played by Scots such as James Thomson within the Union, and agrees that more should be done to celebrate the importance of Scots within the Union. Supported by: Nanette Milne, Elizabeth Smith, Jamie McGrigor, Karen Gillon, Jackson Carlaw, John Scott, Margaret Mitchell, Mary Scanlon, Ted Brocklebank, Bill Aitken 
</spmotion>

</publicwhip>
