<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="" latest="yes">

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2003-03-07.89WS.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="89WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030307/wmstext/30307m01.htm#30307m01.html_dpthd0">
	TRADE AND INDUSTRY
</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2003-03-07.89WS.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="89WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030307/wmstext/30307m01.htm#30307m01.html_sbhd0">
	British Energy
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2003-03-07.89WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/960" speakername="Patricia Hewitt" speakeroffice="The Secretary of State for Trade and Industry" colnum="89WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030307/wmstext/30307m01.htm#30307m01.html_spmin0">
	<p pid=".89WS.2/1">The current British Energy (&quot;BE&quot;) Credit Facility Agreement (CFA) came into effect in September 2002 and expires on <phrase class="date" code="2003-03-09">9 March 2003</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid=".89WS.2/2">In my statement to the House on <phrase class="date" code="2003-02-24">24 February</phrase>, I confirmed that the Government would be prepared to continue to fund BE's operations while its restructuring plan was agreed and implemented, and that I was willing to extend the credit facility at a reduced level for a period after <phrase class="date" code="2003-03-09">9 March</phrase>. In that statement, I also confirmed that I intended to apply for state aids approval from the European Commission for this continued financing as Restructuring Aid. This application is being sent to the Commission today.</p>
	<p pid=".89WS.2/3">Sufficient proceeds have been received from the sale of BE's stake in Bruce Power to enable BE to repay all outstanding amounts under the credit facility (amounting to about &pound;215 million including interest and commission) to my Department today. On a contingency basis, I have decided with BE's agreement, to continue the credit facility, with the maximum amount available being reduced from &pound;650 million to &pound;200 million.</p>
	<p pid=".89WS.2/4">The credit facility will be extended to the earlier of <phrase class="date" code="2004-09-30">30 September 2004</phrase> or the date on which the restructuring plan becomes effective. The controls governing any drawings proposed by BE will remain in place. The credit facility will become repayable if certain milestones in the restructuring process are not achieved. We shall therefore continue to be ready with contingency plans for the administration of BE to ensure safety and security of supply.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2003-03-07.89WS.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="89WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030307/wmstext/30307m01.htm#30307m01.html_sbhd1">
	Energy Advisory Panel
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2003-03-07.89WS.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1328" speakername="Brian Wilson" speakeroffice="The Minister for Energy and Construction" colnum="89WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030307/wmstext/30307m01.htm#30307m01.html_spmin1">
	<p pid=".89WS.4/1">As announced in the recently published Energy White Paper (Cm 5761) we propose to establish a Sustainable Energy Policy Advisory Board. Against this background we have reviewed the position of the Energy Advisory Panel.</p>
	<p pid=".89WS.4/2">The Panel has provided very valuable assistance in our analysis of energy policy issues since it was established in 1993. This assistance has included advising Ministers direct as well as Departments. I am particularly grateful for its recent expert help in advising us in relation to the analysis underlying the Energy White Paper.</p>
	<p pid=".89WS.4/3">The Sustainable Energy Policy Advisory Board will advise the new Ministerial Group which will oversee the delivery of the commitments in the White Paper. The Advisory Board will be made up of senior, independent experts. It will provide the Ministerial group with a source of well-informed, independent advice on the approach and work of the network of departmental policy units involved in delivering the white paper. We shall be appointing members to the Advisory Board in due course.</p>
	<p pid=".89WS.4/4">We therefore propose to wind up the existing Energy Advisory Panel and I am writing to the Panel members thanking them for their service.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2003-03-07.90WS.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="90WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030307/wmstext/30307m01.htm#30307m01.html_dpthd1">
	TREASURY
</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2003-03-07.90WS.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="90WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030307/wmstext/30307m01.htm#30307m01.html_sbhd2">
	Finance Bill
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2003-03-07.90WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1171" speakername="Dawn Primarolo" speakeroffice="The Paymaster General" colnum="90WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030307/wmstext/30307m01.htm#30307m01.html_spmin2">
	<p pid=".90WS.2/1">It is expected that the Finance Bill will be published on <phrase class="date" code="2003-04-16">Wednesday 16 April</phrase>. Explanatory notes on the Bill's clauses will be available in the Vote Office and the Libraries of both Houses on that day. Member of the public will be able to obtain copies of the Explanatory Notes from the Treasury; these will also be available on the Treasury's website <a href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk">www.hm-treasury.gov.uk</a></p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2003-03-07.90WS.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="90WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030307/wmstext/30307m01.htm#30307m01.html_dpthd2">
	HOME DEPARTMENT
</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2003-03-07.90WS.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="90WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030307/wmstext/30307m01.htm#30307m01.html_sbhd3">
	National Asylum Support Service
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2003-03-07.90WS.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/980" speakername="Beverley Hughes" speakeroffice="The Minister for Citizenship and Immigration" colnum="90WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030307/wmstext/30307m01.htm#30307m01.html_spmin3">
	<p pid=".90WS.5/1">I have previously announced an independent review of the operations of the National Asylum Support Service (NASS). The independent Review has now been established with the following terms of reference:</p>
	<p pid=".90WS.5/2" class="indent">To review the organisation, management and staffing and expertise within NASS to identify changes necessary in the short to medium term to enable it consistently to achieve the appropriate standards of operational and administrative performance. Consideration of the staffing arrangements should include the balance between permanent, consultant and agency staff and the match between the skills of the staff and the job to be done, including the handling of complex and publicly sensitive projects and business. Consideration of the organisational arrangements should extend to relations with the remainder of IND, including whether tasks such as procurement should be centralised within IND and the linkage necessary between procurement and project terms.</p>
	<p pid=".90WS.5/3" class="indent">To submit a report, with recommendations, to the Minister of State responsible for immigration matters through the Director General of IND by the end of May 2003.</p>
	<p pid=".90WS.5/4">The independent Review will be conducted by Gill Noble, CB, formerly Director, Law and Order, Health and Local Government, HM Treasury, Ernie Finch, formerly of Marks and Spencer plc and Alan Barnish, retiring Chief Executive of Cambridgeshire County Council.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

