<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="c" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.37WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.37WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.37WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.37WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.37WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.37WS.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.37WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1899" speakername="Angela Eagle" speakeroffice="The Minister for Pensions and the Ageing Society" colnum="37WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0001.htm#09071651001361">
	<p pid="c.37WS.2/1">My noble Friend, The Minister for Employment Relations and Postal Affairs, Lord Young of Norwood Green, at the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills has made the following statement.</p>
	<p pid="c.37WS.2/2">&quot;The informal meeting of Employment and Social Policy Ministers took place on 8 to <phrase class="date" code="2009-07-09">9 July 2009</phrase> in Jonkoping, Sweden. I represented the UK.</p>
	<p pid="c.37WS.2/3">The theme of this informal meeting was labour market inclusion looking ahead to post-2010. The informal looked at maintaining employment and promoting mobility, upgrading skills and matching with labour market needs and increasing access to employment. Working time was also discussed over a Ministers-only lunch which I attended.</p>
	<p pid="c.37WS.2/4">In the opening session, member states agreed on the importance of active social security and labour market policies. They stressed the importance of ensuring help for those moving between jobs and those already outside the labour market. While the crisis tested member states' resolve to conduct further reforms, now was the time to prepare Europe for the economy of the future.</p>
	<p pid="c.37WS.2/5">Following on from the opening session, the meeting was split into three workshops, each devoted to a specific challenge: Workshop 1&mdash;Managing the impact of the financial crisis by increasing access to employment, Workshop 2&mdash;Facilitating access to employment by efficient reforms in the labour market and Workshop 3&mdash;Increasing employment through an active social security policy. I participated in Workshop 3 to present the UK approach to the reform of incapacity benefit and said that reform was ongoing. Others member states warned against repeating the mistakes of the past that caused long-term structural damage to economies.</p>
	<p pid="c.37WS.2/6">The presidency concluded that it saw these discussions as feeding into its work on the post-2010 strategy. The commission concurred. While the current Lisbon strategy remained the right framework for action, its forthcoming revision would need to take better account of the social dimension. The commission would set out initial views in its forthcoming consultation document.</p>
	<p pid="c.37WS.2/7">The meeting concluded with a private Ministers-only lunch discussion on the working time directive. Following the failure of negotiations on the directive, some member states insisted that any new proposal would need to deal with the opt-out. The UK along with Germany, Poland and others disagreed. A few member states urged caution and saw no point in proceeding if failure was clear from the outset. The Commission underlined the need to respect European Union law. Preliminary discussions would be needed with the European Parliament before deciding how to proceed. The presidency concluded that the majority of member states use the opt-out but that a way forward would need to be found.&quot;</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.38WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.38WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.38WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.38WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.38WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.38WS.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.38WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1981" speakername="Alistair Darling" speakeroffice="The Chancellor of the Exchequer" colnum="38WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0001.htm#09071651001362">
	<p pid="c.38WS.2/1">The Economic and Financial Affairs Council was held in Brussels on <phrase class="date" code="2009-07-07">7 July 2009</phrase>. The following items were discussed:</p>
	<p pid="c.38WS.2/2" class="italic">Presentation of the presidency work programme</p>
	<p pid="c.38WS.2/3">The Council took note of the presentation by the Swedish presidency of the ECOFIN work programme for the second half of 2009.</p>
	<p pid="c.38WS.2/4" class="italic">Follow up to the 18-<phrase class="date" code="2009-06-19">19 June</phrase> European Council</p>
	<p pid="c.38WS.2/5" class="indent"><i>a) Financial supervisory framework</i><i>&mdash;</i>The Council took stock of the presidency's strategy for taking forward work on European financial supervision and regulation following the agreement reached at the June ECOFIN and European Council. The UK is supportive of the timetable presented, with legislative proposals expected on <phrase class="date" code="2009-09-23">23 September</phrase>, and will engage fully in the upcoming negotiations to ensure that the legislation is in line with the agreement reached by leaders at the European Council, and in particular that any new powers granted to existing or proposed bodies would not impinge in any way on member states' fiscal responsibilities.</p>
	<p pid="c.38WS.2/6" class="indent"><i>b) Climate change financing</i>&mdash;Ministers also took note of conclusions agreed by heads at the June European Council on the financing of climate change. The presidency expects an agreement to be reached on a negotiating mandate at a meeting of the European Council in October, when ECOFIN will also revisit this issue. The Government believe that work should continue to ensure the EU reaches agreement on the key issues in advance of the Copenhagen conference in December.</p>
	<p pid="c.38WS.2/7" class="italic">Preparation for the G20 meetings</p>
	<p pid="c.38WS.2/8">The UK updated the Council on the outcome of a G20 deputies meeting on 27 and <phrase class="date" code="2009-06-28">28 June</phrase>. The presidency informed Ministers of its intentions of the handling of the preparation for further G20 meetings in September, including London meetings of G20 deputies on 3-<phrase class="date" code="2009-09-04">4 September</phrase> and G20 Finance Ministers and central bank governors on 4-<phrase class="date" code="2009-09-05">5 September</phrase>. There will be a lunch of EU Finance Ministers to prepare for these on <phrase class="date" code="2009-09-02">2 September</phrase>. The Government will look forward to working closely with the presidency to ensure co-ordination of work taken forward at G20 and EU levels.</p>
	<p pid="c.38WS.2/9" class="italic">Pro-cyclicality</p>
	<p pid="c.38WS.2/10">Following a report by the Economic and Financial Committee, ECOFIN adopted Council conclusions on pro-cyclical effects on financial markets. The conclusions assess work underway to reduce possible pro-cyclical effects of financial regulation, including on the issue of impaired assets. The UK is content with the conclusions, which represent a positive step forward on this issue, and looks forward to further discussion of the issue in the autumn.</p>
	<p pid="c.38WS.2/11" class="italic">Implementation of the Stability and Growth Pact</p>
	<p pid="c.38WS.2/12" class="indent"><i>a) Adoption of legal acts in the excessive deficit procedure</i>&mdash;ECOFIN adopted Council decisions for Latvia, Lithuania, Malta, Poland and Romania, formally entering these countries into the excessive deficit procedure, and issued recommendations on corrective action to be taken. It also issued a revised recommendation to Hungary on measures to be taken in order to correct its excessive deficit.</p>
	<p pid="c.38WS.2/13" class="indent"><i>b) Adoption of Council opinions on updated stability and convergence programmes</i>&mdash;The Council adopted opinions on the updated stability and convergence programmes of Slovenia, Slovakia, Austria, Belgium and Romania.</p>
	<p pid="c.38WS.2/14" class="italic">Any Other Business</p>
	<p pid="c.38WS.2/15" class="italic">Medium-Term Budgetary Objectives (MTOs) and Implicit Liabilities</p>
	<p pid="c.38WS.2/16">The Council took note of issues raised by the Slovenian Minister regarding the methodology to be used by member states from this autumn when they set medium-term objectives for their national budgets.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.39WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.39WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.39WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.39WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.39WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.39WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.39WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.39WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.39WS.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.39WS.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.40WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.40WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.40WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.40WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.40WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.40WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.40WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.40WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.41WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.41WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.41WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.41WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.41WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.41WS.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.41WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1555" speakername="Tessa Jowell" speakeroffice="The Minister for the Cabinet Office and for the Olympics, and Paymaster General" colnum="41WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0001.htm#09071651001368">
	<p pid="c.41WS.2/1">Today, the Cabinet Office's &quot;Annual Report and Accounts 2008-09&quot; (HC 442) has been laid before Parliament</p>
	<p pid="c.41WS.2/2">The annual report and accounts reports a loss and a contingent asset following the termination of phase 2 of the SCOPE programme in July 2008.</p>
	<p pid="c.41WS.2/3">The SCOPE programme was an information technology programme working with 10 partners across Government. It aimed to extend the benefits of communication and collaborative working afforded by current information technology by improving the way sensitive information was shared between and used by the security and intelligence agencies and Government Departments.</p>
	<p pid="c.41WS.2/4">The first phase of the programme was delivered on time and within budget in 2007. It has delivered extremely valuable benefits to the intelligence community in Government and has ensured that all its constituent members are now connected electronically.</p>
	<p pid="c.41WS.2/5">Phase 2 was about providing additional functionality, for example, to allow for greater collaborative working between the security and intelligence agencies and Departments.</p>
	<p pid="c.41WS.2/6">Phase 2 of the programme was cancelled following the failure of the main commercial supplier to the programme to meet key contractual milestones. As a consequence of termination, it was necessary to write off and report as a loss in the annual report and accounts that part of the value of the asset under construction which had no prospect of becoming viable.</p>
	<p pid="c.41WS.2/7">The Treasury has approved a write-off of &pound;24.4 million which has been managed within the Department's net resource requirement and budget and constitutes a charge against non-cash programme expenditure in the resource departmental expenditure limit.</p>
	<p pid="c.41WS.2/8">My Department is now working with the contractor to resolve issues arising from the termination of the programme, including consideration of the legal avenues available. The aim of the work is to ensure that Her Majesty's Government and, ultimately, the taxpayer recover the appropriate value from the supplier which relates to those undelivered parts of the programme. This is noted as a contingent asset in the annual report and accounts. The details of the discussions with the supplier are commercially confidential and are likely to remain so.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.41WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.41WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.41WS.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.41WS.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.41WS.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.41WS.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.42WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.42WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.42WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.42WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.42WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.42WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.42WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.42WS.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.42WS.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1918" speakername="John Healey" speakeroffice="The Minister for Housing" colnum="42WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0002.htm#09071651001371">
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/1">Yesterday, the Government published their &quot;Low Carbon Transition Plan&quot;. To respond to the challenge of climate change, we need to become a low-carbon country, achieving an 80 per cent. reduction in greenhouse gas emissions by 2050.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/2">We must also meet the challenge to build more homes, so that everyone has a decent secure and affordable home.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/3">To deliver both we need to change the way that we plan, design and build homes for the future. More than a quarter of Britain's carbon emissions come from our homes. We will need to reduce emissions from existing homes. The Government announced important measures to do so yesterday and we will set out more later this year. But, one in three of Britain's homes in 2050 will be built between now and then. We need to make sure that our homes in future are cleaner, greener and cheaper to run from the out set.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/4">Today I am reconfirming the Government's policy that all new homes will be zero-carbon from 2016 and announcing further details on the definition and standards we will legislate for.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/5">New buildings are only part of the answer for a low carbon and sustainable future. A differently planned and more sustainable built environment can encourage more sustainable ways of living.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/6">Today I am publishing the &quot;Planning Policy Statement&quot; which sets out the highest ever standards for green living, announcing the first four pioneering locations for Eco-towns in England and offering Government support to work with a further six second wave areas.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/7">By radically rethinking how we design, plan and build we can create zero-carbon developments which combine affordable housing with green infrastructure, greater energy efficiency and a higher quality of life.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/8">To support the Low Carbon Transition Plan and its route map to carbon reduction, today I am also announcing that we will review and combine the Climate Change and Renewable Energy Policy Planning Statements (PPS) consulting in detail on proposals before the end of the year.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/9" class="italic">Zero Carbon Homes</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/10">In July 2007, we announced that all homes would be zero-carbon from 2016. In December 2008, we published a consultation on the definitions of zero-carbon. I am announcing today details of the definition that will apply.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/11">A zero-carbon home is one whose net carbon dioxide emissions, taking account of emissions associated with all energy use in the home, is equal to zero or negative across the year. Our definition of &quot;energy use&quot; will cover both energy uses currently regulated by the Building Regulations and other energy used in the home. Homes meeting the new requirements will be cheaper to run because of high energy efficiency requirements, and occupants will be less vulnerable to rising gas and electricity prices. These homes will have better controls, including smart meters, so that people can more easily manage and reduce energy use. Technology for people to generate their own low carbon heat and electricity, with payments for surpluses will be designed and built into new zero-carbon homes or developments as a matter of course.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/12">Zero carbon homes will be designed and built to be highly energy efficient. Our consultation quoted two standards to illustrate our ambitions in this area. Respondents welcomed the proposition that energy efficiency should be the first priority, although many argued that the standards quoted were not suitable as a minimum regulatory standard to apply to every new home in England and that we do not have an appropriate established energy efficiency standard for the purpose of zero-carbon homes. I accept this.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/13">I am therefore setting up a specialist task group, reporting to me in the autumn to examine the energy efficiency metrics and standards which will realise our ambition of the highest practical energy efficiency level realisable in all dwelling types. Following the task group's report, I intend to announce decisions on a clear new standard by the end of this year.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/14">The net emissions of the home, taking account of its energy efficiency and on site energy supply (including, where relevant, connections to heat networks) will meet a minimum &quot;carbon compliance&quot; standard&mdash;in effect a regulatory level of carbon reduction to be achieved on-site compared to today's regulations.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/15">I have decided to set that level to be as ambitious as possible for on-site carbon mitigation, while being technically achievable. This will therefore be 70 per cent. of regulated energy use, based on the assumptions laid out in our consultation document. We will consider updating this as necessary in the light of technical changes, such as developments to the standard assessment procedure energy assessment tool, to maintain this overall level of ambition and provide continued certainty to industry.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/16">I can also confirm that new support for small scale renewable heat and electricity generation through the Renewable Heat Incentive and Clean Energy Cash Back, will be available for on-site renewables in zero-carbon homes, making these homes more attractive to occupants and potentially reducing the net costs faced by developers.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/17">Any carbon not mitigated on site will be dealt with through a range of good quality &quot;allowable solutions&quot;. The allowable solutions will cover carbon emitted from the home for 30 years after build. Responses to the consultation took different views about some of the solutions suggested. I have decided to indicate now those approaches that commanded broad support. We will consider with stakeholders the practical arrangements that would be required to permit them to be put in place and to ensure that standards are achieved in practice. I will announce decisions by the end of this year. Those that received broad support are:</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/18" class="indent">Further carbon reductions on site beyond the regulatory standard;</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/19" class="indent">Energy efficient appliances meeting a high standard which are installed as fittings within the home;</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/20" class="indent">Advanced forms of building control system which reduce the level of energy use in the home;</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/21" class="indent">Exports of low carbon or renewable heat from the development to other developments;</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/22" class="indent">Investments in low and zero-carbon community heat infrastructure.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/23" class="indent">Other allowable solutions remain under consideration.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/24">The wider policies supporting distributed energy will continue to develop over the coming years. Our consultation suggested setting a guideline maximum price we expect industry to bear in implementing allowable solutions. In the light of responses, I intend to do so following further work on costs. For the purposes of the impact assessment published today, I have included costs of allowable solutions up to the central option in our consultation of &pound;100 per tonne of carbon dioxide, reflecting the cost of off-site renewable electricity.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/25">Government will support industry as it responds to this challenge. Budget 2009 announced that the Government will report at the 2009 pre-Budget report on progress and set out its strategy to support a timely and effective housing supply response through the recovery, in order to maximise delivery of high quality, energy efficient homes, supporting our long term housing supply and environmental objectives. As part of this, the Government will identify, working with industry and other partners, the best regulatory and policy framework to support the Government's long-term housing objectives. In making the announcement today, I am making clear the priority the Government attach to tackling climate change over other potential demands on land values. We will examine the cumulative impact and costs of our existing regulatory policies and proposals that potentially affect land value including current implementation plans in the round in the context of the PBR work, taking the zero-carbon policy into account.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/26">Industry will need to develop innovative design and building technologies and techniques, and to support these efforts Government will work closely with the industry:</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/27" class="indent">The Technology Strategy Board is working with partners to enable it to harness the market for environmentally sustainable buildings, since 2004 investing &pound;46 million in this area. Under its Low Impact Buildings Innovation Platform a further total of &pound;50 million is now earmarked for allocation to research relevant to new build by 2011. This includes over &pound;30 million of capability building work to be awarded over the next two years and up to &pound;8.5 million in new build demonstration programmes;</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/28" class="indent">The Homes and Communities Agency (HCA) has a carbon challenge programme which aims to accelerate the home building industry's response to climate change by building homes that reach level 6 of the code for sustainable homes. Four new communities are planned which will together provide around 1,700 zero-carbon, highly sustainable demonstration homes;</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/29" class="indent">I am today announcing with the HCA support for the first schemes under the &pound;21 million Low Carbon Community Heating Initiative fund, launched in Budget 2009. Schemes will be supported in Exeter, Nottingham, Milton Keynes, Southampton, Birmingham and Newcastle.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/30" class="italic">Eco-<i>t</i>owns</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/31">Eco-towns respond to the demand to build more homes and to live in a more sustainable way. By radically rethinking how we design, plan and build our homes, we can create zero-carbon developments which combine affordable housing, environmental sensitivity, and outstanding quality. Eco-towns will pioneer genuinely sustainable living setting standards that will need to be followed more widely to deal with the challenge of climate change.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/32">The new Eco-town Planning Policy Statement (PPS) that I am publishing today sets out the highest ever standards for green living, and linked to it I can announce the first four pioneer locations for England's Eco-towns. These are: Whitehill-Bordon, St. Austell (Clay Country), Rackheath (Norwich) and NW Bicester, all led or strongly supported by their local authorities who can see both the potential for their new eco town and the benefit for existing communities in regeneration, higher quality jobs and new green infrastructure. Each of these four locations has the capacity to link well into existing development&mdash;as well as the scale to function as a new settlement. None are self contained developments in the middle of the countryside.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/33">These locations will receive continuing Government support including a share of a special &pound;60 million growth fund to support local infrastructure.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/34">Alongside the new Eco-towns PPS I am publishing a series of documents which demonstrate the detailed work and assessment on which my decisions today are based. These are:</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/35" class="indent">an update of the Sustainability Appraisal;</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/36" class="indent">a Sustainability Statement;</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/37" class="indent">an Impact Assessment;</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/38" class="indent">Summary of responses to the consultation on the draft PPS;</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/39" class="indent">a Location Decision Statement.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/40">I am placing copies in the Library of the House.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/41">However the PPS is a statement about potential. The decision on whether or not the eco-town schemes go ahead is for the local planning authority. Schemes can be considered in local plans and will be the subject of individual planning applications, and local consultation, which will be decided on their merits by the local authority.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/42">In addition to the first four pioneering locations in the PPS we have said we want to see up to ten Eco-towns by 2020, so I am making the offer to work with and help fund a further six more local authorities in developing proposals through regional and local plans. We have offered additional support to two authorities where proposals were not sufficiently advanced to be included in the PPS&mdash;Uttlesford and Doncaster to enable them to take forward these locations through their local plans if this is the preferred option they choose to pursue. I have set aside &pound;5 million to support these and other areas to carry out further assessment and technical work including potential future locations to come through plans in other regions.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/43">The eco-towns concept&mdash;more sustainable living in new communities&mdash;has attracted real interest. When a whole community is planned at this scale (5,000 homes is broadly the size necessary to support a secondary school) there is an opportunity to completely rethink how transport, employment, retail and other services are provided as well as designing housing to exemplary standards. In practice this means features such as smart homes with remote control of heating and ventilation, real time information on available transport, state of the art provision for home-working, including high quality broadband.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/44">The PPS I am publishing today sets out for the highest standards for green living ever set. Eco-town developments must be able to demonstrate essential features to achieve the highest levels of sustainability. Examples of the PPS standards include ensuring:</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/45" class="indent">zero-carbon status across all the town's buildings, including commercial and public buildings as well as homes&mdash;a significantly tougher threshold than any existing or agreed targets;</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/46" class="indent">40 per cent. of the area within the town to be green space, at least half of which should be open to the public as parks or recreation areas;</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/47" class="indent">a minimum of one job per house can be reached by walking, cycling or public transport to reduce dependence on the car;</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/48" class="indent">all homes are located within ten minutes walk of frequent public transport and everyday neighbourhood services;</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/49" class="indent">smart, efficient, affordable homes taking their energy from the sun, wind and earth.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/50" class="indent">Eco-towns offer great potential to test a wide range of innovative and emerging technologies because of the scale of the projects. To ensure we make the most of these opportunities, and to support business innovation, the Technology Strategy Board will work with the selected eco-towns to capture this potential. The Technology Strategy Board will look to co-ordinate and align with the work on eco-towns a range of activities drawing on current investments worth over &pound;200m through Innovation Platforms in the areas of Low Impact Buildings, Intelligent Transport Systems and Services and Low Carbon Vehicles and its programmes in the area of Energy Generation and Supply and Advanced Materials.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/51">Eco-towns can play a leading role in the development of electric cars through building in infrastructure such as charging points as a standard provision in all major public and services buildings. We will work with all the eco-town locations to develop their potential for supporting this technology and in piloting the next generation of electric and hybrid cars.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/52">Eco-towns will be major building projects which could employ large numbers of local people, many new to the sector and who will require training in the industry. They offer an opportunity to ensure that existing skills are upgraded to deliver the low carbon built environment and equip the construction workers of the future with the skills in sustainable design and building. Where public funds are committed, public sector agencies will look to use clauses in delivery contracts to ensure a proportion of apprenticeships are offered and these are &quot;green skills&quot; apprenticeships.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/53">Eco-towns can pilot and test new ways of delivering public services, as well as making them more sustainable and responsive to climate change, such as new and innovative schools to meet the needs of new and existing residents. Department of Children, Schools and Families (DCSF) will support eco-towns to ensure the design of schools, including travel to them, and the delivery of play and youth services and facilities are both innovative and sustainable. We will work closely with the promoters of eco-towns and the relevant local authorities to look at how best to meet those needs with the aim of ensuring that each of the eco-towns has a zero-carbon school in place by 2013.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/54">We want schools to be sustainable socially as well as environmentally. By 2010 all schools should be providing access to extended services for children and families. Eco-towns in particular should explore opportunities for co-locating children's and other support services alongside schools for example through Sure Start Children's Centres which bring together childcare, early education, health and family support services.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/55">Eco-towns will be designed as healthy and sustainable environments encouraging healthy living for all through active design principles, community involvement and encouraging healthy behaviours. The Department of Health will work with other Government Departments and associated research bodies in seeking to achieve a zero-carbon standard for health and social care facilities in the eco towns.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/56">Eco-towns also need to be sustainable travel towns, demonstrating how using &quot;smarter choices&quot; can secure significant increases in cycling, walking and public transport. All the homes in the demonstration projects should have secure cycle storage designed in from the outset.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/57">Good transport links are essential to the success of any new community. Three of the four eco-town locations I am announcing today are well located for rail transport. For the fourth, Bordon, I am announcing funding support for the next stage of feasibility work, working with Hampshire county council, to establish if restoration of a rail link can be achieved sustainably and subject to a sound business case.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/58">We want nature to be at the very heart of eco-towns and the development process will be used to restore wildlife habitats and weave the living landscape back together. We expect the eco-towns to become working demonstrations of the ways that biodiversity can contribute to safe, healthy and prosperous communities. Biodiversity projects are being developed at all four locations, and include the potential to work with the Eden project team.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/59">Eco-towns are large developments which will require all parts of the public sector to work together, and close working relations between local and central Government. I therefore propose to invite each of the eco-town local authorities to look at how their LAA could provide a suitable framework for planning future service provision and delivery in and around the eco-town area, for example through a stronger focus on a lower tier local authority within the LAA arrangement or sub area locality agreement.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/60">I propose to establish a formal relationship between local and central Government, in an arrangement based on the model of multi-area agreements (MAA), to negotiate the freedoms and flexibilities eco-town areas will need to realise their aspirations. I wish also to offer certainty that central Government are willing to work closely with the local authority and local communities to make the most of their new eco town opportunities.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/61">In addition I am asking the Homes and Communities Agency to provide support, expertise and advice to local partners and I expect the HCA's first step to be inclusion of the four eco-town locations in the first wave of single conversations between the agency and local authorities, with the agency assessing the detailed proposals as they come forward from the promoters in each location, and advising each location on funding, including growth funding. Providing there are proposals which represent good quality and value for money and are deliverable within a mixed community context, provision of affordable housing support in these locations will be presented by HCA as a regional priority in the allocation of resources from the National Affordable Housing Programme.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/62">The eco-town locations I am announcing today all have existing communities close by or within the area and I want them to benefit from their new eco-towns. We will, therefore, be inviting existing communities in the first eco-town locations to participate in the &quot;Green villages, towns and cities&quot; challenge for communities announced in the DECC Low Carbon Transition Plan published yesterday. In total, 15 communities will be selected to participate as &quot;test-hubs&quot;, with local residents, businesses, and the public sector playing a leading role.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/63">The need to develop thriving and sustainable communities able to take a strong role in shaping their community is at the heart of the eco-town concept. To support community anchor organisations in taking a leading role in shaping the eco-town proposals, and subject to local proposals, Government will invite eco-town pilot projects to apply for support within the &pound;70 million community builders fund for community organisations, including for the purchase of community assets.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/64">We have been well served by the Eco-towns challenge panel of independent experts and we want to maintain the creative contribution that independent professionals can make through the CABE design review process, CABE design support at local level, and the continuation of an independent advisory panel as the eco-town schemes are developed.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/65">Despite the difficult current market conditions caused by the recession, I expect 10,000 homes built by 2016 of which 30 per cent. will be affordable. To start this process we will support early demonstrator buildings to test and develop from the new technologies needed, and so that local communities can help shape their further development. For the next two years I am providing &pound;60 million start up funding from the growth fund for this work for the four locations identified today. This is additional to mainstream funding for services. We expect that the bulk of investment in these schemes will be from the private sector, but eco-towns will also benefit from similar levels of public investment to any comparable large housing scheme and this will include continued growth funding over the period of major development.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/66" class="italic">Planning</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/67">With the new PPS, eco-towns set the gold standard in development planning, but low carbon living means planning for all new development to cut carbon emissions.</p>
	<p pid="c.42WS.3/68">Our climate change &quot;Planning Policy Statement&quot; (PPS) published in December 2007 has put climate change at the heart of what is expected from good planning and complemented our earlier PPS on renewable energy. Neither now fully reflects the scale of the challenge we face. But neither fully reflects the scale of the challenge we now face in supporting the UK's transition to a low carbon country. We will therefore review and combine them, consulting in detail on proposals later this year.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.49WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.49WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.49WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.49WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.49WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.49WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.50WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.50WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.50WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.50WS.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.50WS.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1556" speakername="Kevan Jones" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence" colnum="50WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0003.htm#09071651001373">
	<p pid="c.50WS.1/1">Today the Department has published the Defence Estate Development Plan (DEDP) 2009&mdash;the first annual update of this vital internal planning document. The updated plan is evolutionary in nature and reflects the Department's consistent estate priorities. DEDP 09 sets out the authoritative framework, looking forward to 2030, for the coherent development of the estate to meet the future needs of defence, and the priorities for investment and rationalisation arising from it. It also informs our programme of engagement with the regions, which underpins the successful delivery of many of our estate programmes.</p>
	<p pid="c.50WS.1/2">The key changes are evolutionary in nature and include, amongst others, cross-Government support to the armed forces as set out in &quot;The Nation's Commitment&quot;, and revised targets for improving living accommodation for our people. Other changes reflect specific investment and basing decisions that support the generation of sustainable military capability.</p>
	<p pid="c.50WS.1/3">I have placed a copy of the plan in the House of Commons Library. The document will also be widely circulated to external stakeholders and will be published on the internet.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.50WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.50WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.50WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.50WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.51WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.51WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.51WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.51WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.52WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.52WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.52WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.52WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.52WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.52WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.54WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.54WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.54WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.54WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.54WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.54WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.54WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.54WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.55WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.55WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.55WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.55WS.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.55WS.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1765" speakername="Jim Fitzpatrick" speakeroffice="The Minister of State, Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs" colnum="55WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0004.htm#09071651001379">
	<p pid="c.55WS.1/1">As required under the Animal Health Act 1981 (as amended by the Animal Health Act 2002) the Government will publish today a review of controls on the import of animal products for the financial year 2008-09. I welcome the opportunity to review and report on efforts during the past year to reduce the risk of disease entering the country via imports of animal products.</p>
	<p pid="c.55WS.1/2">The control of imports of animal products remains a major concern for the Government as we fully appreciate the devastating effect that disease outbreaks can have on our farming of livestock and crops and on the environment and, in trying to protect animal health, we know how important it is to take a variety of measures at the border and inland. It has once again been a challenging year in monitoring the constantly changing disease situation around the world and evaluating and responding to threats. We continue to ensure that veterinary checks are carried out on legally imported animal products from non-European Union (EU) countries and work closely with Her Majesty's Revenue and Customs (HMRC)/United Kingdom Border Agency (UKBA) and other relevant Government Departments to combat the risk of major diseases entering the country through illegal imports from outside the EU.</p>
	<p pid="c.55WS.1/3">UKBA continues to deliver an enforcement strategy that targets anti-smuggling activity on the highest risk traffic to combat illegal imports of animal products into Great Britain (GB) and to review deployment of resources and react flexibly in response to changes in the pattern of risk.</p>
	<p pid="c.55WS.1/4">There continues to be a joined-up approach across Government Departments on an overall communications strategy to raise awareness among international travellers of the personal import rules for food, with a great deal of publicity continuing to be undertaken inland within GB, at the border and also overseas.</p>
	<p pid="c.55WS.1/5">These are some of the highlights of our working during the year:</p>
	<p pid="c.55WS.1/6" class="indent">EU veterinary week in November highlighted the programme of already ongoing work in respect of our cross-Government personal imports campaign at border control points, including a stand at Heathrow airport, terminal 3 during the week which had over 5,000 visitors and was covered by BBC Breakfast news;</p>
	<p pid="c.55WS.1/7" class="indent">new TV filler &quot;Don't bring me back&quot;, produced to support our overall personal imports campaign, has achieved some excellent airtime across a variety of channels with most of the transmissions going out in peak evening viewing time. It has built in value to be one of the top ten fillers of 2008-09. It has also received out of home play in locations such as surgeries and gyms;</p>
	<p pid="c.55WS.1/8" class="indent">food and veterinary office (FVO) visit in November 2008&mdash;inspectors indicated that the UK has a functioning import control system and recognised further improvements made by the UK.</p>
	<p pid="c.55WS.1/9">We will continue to monitor and assess the changing threats from around the world, and work with HMRC/UKBA and other enforcement partners to make sure that our enforcement activity at UK borders is targeted at the current risks.</p>
	<p pid="c.55WS.1/10">Copies of the Review are available on the DEFRA 'personal food imports' website: <a href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/animalh/illeqali">www.defra.gov.uk/animalh/illeqali</a>, and will be sent to stakeholders for information seeking their feedback. Hard copies will also be available on request.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.56WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.56WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.56WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.56WS.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.56WS.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1669" speakername="Hilary Benn" speakeroffice="The Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs" colnum="56WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0004.htm#09071651001380">
	<p pid="c.56WS.1/1">As at <phrase class="date" code="2009-06-30">30 June</phrase>, the end of the regulatory payment window for the 2008 single payment scheme, a total of &pound;1.625 billion, representing some 99.69 per cent. of the estimated total fund had been paid in full payments to 104,199 claimants.</p>
	<p pid="c.56WS.1/2">These figures confirm that the agency has helped to ensure that the UK as a whole has met the EU requirement that 96.154 per cent. of 2008 scheme payments be made by <phrase class="date" code="2009-06-30">30 June</phrase>. This follows earlier confirmation that the agency had met its formal performance targets for this scheme year.</p>
	<p pid="c.56WS.1/3">Reaching these targets continues to demonstrate improvements in RPA's performance and levels of service to its customers and provide another important step forward for the agency.</p>
	<p pid="c.56WS.1/4">Of the outstanding 2008 claims on which processing is not complete, approximately 400 are expected to result in a payment in due course. Work continues to complete the necessary validation of those claims as soon as possible. Interest will be paid to claimants on sums paid after <phrase class="date" code="2009-06-30">30 June</phrase> on the same basis as for previous scheme years. The agency will continue to address any cases of individual hardship as sympathetically as possible.</p>
	<p pid="c.56WS.1/5">Alongside that work, RPA has already begun processing the 107,000 or so claims that have been submitted under the 2009 SPS. Formal payment targets will be announced separately, but I know the agency Chief Executive is expecting to at least match RPA performance under the 2008 scheme when nearly &pound;1 billion was paid out by the end of December.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.57WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.57WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.57WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.57WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.57WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.57WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.57WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.57WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.57WS.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.57WS.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.57WS.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1752" speakername="Phil Woolas" speakeroffice="The Minister for Borders and Immigration" colnum="57WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0004.htm#09071651001382">
	<p pid="c.57WS.4/1">The biggest shake-up to our border protection and immigration system for over 45 years is well underway. The Borders, Citizenship and Immigration Bill, which will fundamentally overhaul the laws regarding obtaining British citizenship is currently progressing through Parliament. We will also look to simplify our immigration laws further through legislation to be published later this year in Parliament.</p>
	<p pid="c.57WS.4/2">The UK Border Agency was established in April 2008 to create a strong new force at the border by bringing together immigration, customs and visa checks to strengthen the UK border. We want the UK to stay open and attractive for both business and visitors, but at the same time we are determined to deliver a system of border control which is among the strongest in the world.</p>
	<p pid="c.57WS.4/3">Inward investment and tourism benefit Britain greatly. The Government are committed to boosting Britain's economy by bringing the right skills from around the world and ensuring that it is easy to visit legally. We want to continue to welcome the holidaymakers, visitors, business people and genuine students who come here, recognising the valuable contribution they make to economic growth and the way they enrich our society through cultural exchange.</p>
	<p pid="c.57WS.4/4">For the immigration system to command public support, both among the British public and legitimate migrants, we need an immigration system that is fair and effective. The integrity of the immigration system depends on robust borders, with effective security overseas and in the UK ensuring and enforcing compliance with our immigration laws. To help achieve this, those who benefit directly from our immigration system (migrants, employers and educational institutions) should contribute to the costs of the system and enable us to meet our strategic objectives.</p>
	<p pid="c.57WS.4/5">Later this summer the Government will publish a consultation document on charging for certain services we provide. To maintain our world class immigration system currently costs over &pound;2.2 billion per annum. UK Border Agency currently recovers approximately 30 per cent. of this spend through fees for applications and services we offer. We believe it is right that users of that system make an appropriate contribution to meeting those costs, to help manage the burden on the UK taxpayer. The purpose of consulting is to ensure that we are getting that balance right in the broader interests of the UK.</p>
	<p pid="c.57WS.4/6">The consultation document will set out some options on how we can charge for our services. We want a genuine debate on the most appropriate way to charge. We will be engaging with stakeholders throughout the consultation period in order to get the views and ideas from as many people as possible. Copies of the consultation paper will be placed in the Libraries of both Houses and will be available for downloading from the UK Border Agency website:</p>
	<p pid="c.57WS.4/7"><a href="http://www.ukba.homeoffice.gov.uk/aboutus/consultations/current/">http://www.ukba.homeoffice.gov.uk/aboutus/consultations/current/</a></p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.58WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.58WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.58WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.58WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.58WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.58WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.58WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.58WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.59WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.59WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.59WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.59WS.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.59WS.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1648" speakername="Alan Johnson" speakeroffice="The Secretary of State for the Home Department" colnum="59WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0005.htm#09071651001385">
	<p pid="c.59WS.1/1">In her written ministerial statement to the House on <phrase class="date" code="2009-02-12">12 February</phrase>, <phrase class="offrep" id="wms/2009-02-12.87"><i>Official Report</i>, columns 87-88WS</phrase>, the then Home Secretary, Member for Redittch, the right hon. Jacqui Smith, provided a progress report on the work being undertaken following the publication of the Privy Council review of intercept as evidence in January 2008.</p>
	<p pid="c.59WS.1/2">I am pleased to be able to provide a further update, and to explain why I have concluded it is right to provide the House with a full report after the summer recess.</p>
	<p pid="c.59WS.1/3">Since February, detailed work has focused on testing the practical impact and effect of the model developed. This work has been undertaken in concert with experienced independent legal practitioners. The programme is now complete, and work is now in hand to draw the emerging conclusions and test their validity. The Advisory Group of Privy Counsellors, the right hon. Sir John Chilcot, my noble Friend the right hon. Lord Archer of Sandwell, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1404" name="Alan Beith">the right hon. Member for Berwick-upon-Tweed (Sir Alan Beith)</phrase> and <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1587" name="Michael Howard">the right hon. and learned Member for Folkestone and Hythe (Michael Howard)</phrase> is following this closely. Indeed they also see merit in seeking further advice on key points for, as they noted in their interim report in February, the issues are complex. I know they share my determination to get this right. I should like to thank them for their continuing commitment and invaluable contribution.</p>
	<p pid="c.59WS.1/4">I look forward to discussing with them the final conclusions of the programme. I shall then provide a formal report to Parliament on the full findings of the work programme, and the Government's decision in the light of them, soon after the return following the summer recess.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.59WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.59WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.59WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.59WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.60WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.60WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.60WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.60WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.60WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.60WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.60WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.60WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.60WS.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.60WS.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.60WS.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.60WS.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.61WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.61WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.61WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.61WS.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.61WS.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1682" speakername="Bridget Prentice" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Justice" colnum="61WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0005.htm#09071651001389">
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/1">The tribunals service was created in April 2006, bringing together the administrative support for over 23 tribunals from across government into a single organisation so that tribunals were visibly independent of original decision makers, and to bring improved quality and efficiency in the provision of administrative and management support.</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/2">The provisions of the Tribunals, Courts and Enforcement Act 2007&mdash;TCE Act&mdash; followed these administrative changes and created a new judicial and legal framework, bringing together a range of formerly separate tribunals into a new unified two-tier tribunal structure&mdash;the first-tier and upper tribunal&mdash;under a senior president, Lord Justice Carnwath. The first-tier and the upper tribunal were established under the TCE Act on <phrase class="date" code="2008-11-03">3 November 2008</phrase>, with the first-tier tribunal being the first-instance tribunal for most jurisdictions. The upper tribunal mainly, but not exclusively, reviews and decides appeals from the first-tier tribunal. It also has the power to deal with judicial review work delegated from the High Courts of England and Wales and Northern Ireland and from the Court of Session.</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/3">The TCE Act has provided a cohesive statutory framework for a unified tribunal system dealing with nearly 600,000 cases a year which is committed to improvement and innovation for the benefit of the public.</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/4">The TCE Act also contains provisions for the jurisdictions of most existing tribunals administered by the tribunals service to transfer into the new two-tier structure. The main exception to this is the system of employment tribunals, which will remain as a distinct pillar within the tribunals system. The structure is designed to be flexible so that, in the future, when Parliament decides to create a new appeal right or jurisdiction, it will not be necessary to create a new tribunal to administer it.</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/5">Both the first-tier and upper tribunal are divided into chambers that group together jurisdictions, and their judiciary, dealing with like subjects or where individual panels need the same types of members. The following chambers have been established in the first-tier tribunal:</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/6" class="indent">Social Entitlement (3 Nov 2008)</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/7" class="indent">War Pensions and Armed Forces Compensation (3 Nov 2008)</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/8" class="indent">Health, Education and Social Care (3 Nov 2008)</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/9" class="indent">Tax (<phrase class="date" code="2009-04-01">1 April 2009</phrase>)</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/10">In the upper tribunal the following chambers have been established:</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/11" class="indent">Administrative Appeals (<phrase class="date" code="2008-11-03">3 November 2008</phrase>)</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/12" class="indent">Tax and Finance (<phrase class="date" code="2009-04-01">1 April 2009</phrase>), and</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/13" class="indent">Lands (<phrase class="date" code="2009-06-01">1 June 2009</phrase>)</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/14">Further chambers dealing with general regulatory matters and immigration and asylum appeals are to be established in 2009 and early 2010.</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/15">Everyone who holds a judicial office within the tribunals service, including those who have or will be transferred into one of the new chambers, have been asked to take the oath of allegiance. So far 2,622 judges have taken the oath.</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/16">The new judicial structure allows for the flexible deployment of judges, known as &quot;cross ticketing&quot;, within and across the new chambers. This will mean that suitably qualified judiciary can hear cases in jurisdictions other than the one to which they were first appointed without the need for a further Judicial Appointments Commission competition. This will reduce the costs of training and support. It will also enable the flexible deployment of judiciary to meet fluctuations in workloads between jurisdictions; it will encourage greater consistency of standards and approach across previously disparate jurisdictions; it will assist where there are difficulties in finding judges for particular locations and where there are recruitment difficulties in smaller jurisdictions. Working with the judiciary, the tribunals service has identified &pound;6 million of efficiency savings relating to judicial activity in 2009-10 in areas such as reducing adjournments and more effective deployment of judges. A further &pound;10 million in 2010-11 is now being sought.</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/17">The judges within this new structure are currently subject to widely differing rates of remuneration inherited from the tribunals from which they have transferred or will transfer and which have or will be abolished. Under the existing arrangements, therefore, many office holders will find themselves doing effectively the same job as each other for what would be unequal pay. This would hamper effective operation of the system and the delivery of efficiencies as well as leave pay inequalities in place. To address these issues, in March 2007 the Government commissioned the Senior Salaries Review Body to propose a pay structure for the tribunals judiciary following implementation of the TCE Act. The SSRB delivered its report No.66, Review of Tribunals' Judiciary Remuneration, in November 2008. The report includes 18 recommendations and proposes a single salary structure for tribunals judiciary linked to that already in operation for the courts judiciary and some tribunal judges. The report and the Government's response to each of the 18 recommendations have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses, the Vote Office and the Printed Paper Office.</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/18">The Government broadly accept those SSRB recommendations in relation to legally-qualified salaried and fee-paid tribunals judiciary, as an important step in supporting the tribunals service and the new judicial structure. Addressing the issues identified by the SSRB enables the tribunals system to operate as effectively and efficiently as possible.</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/19">While the Government recognise and support the important role played by non-legally qualified members, it has decided not to implement those recommendations that apply to non-legal members. In taking this decision, account was taken of the level of increases being recommended by the SSRB and the lack of market-based justification in the current economic and public expenditure climate. The Government will be prepared to review any specific recruitment and retention issues, which might arise, with any targeted salary or fee supplements being paid at the discretion of the Lord Chancellor. The Government will keep under review the arguments for drawing a link between the pay of fee-paid and salaried judiciary and that of non-legal members in the light of recruitment and retention data and the overall economic climate.</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/20">The impact of this new pay structure will see no change for over 92 per cent. of the salaried judiciary and 37 per cent. of legally qualified fee-paid members. Non-legally qualified members pay will be unaffected by these changes. Pay costs are expected to be no more than &pound;160,000 in the current year and &pound;400,000 incrementally in the remaining four transitional years.</p>
	<p pid="c.61WS.1/21">The creation of the tribunals service and the implementation of the TCE Act have been major steps in delivering improved services to tribunal users and a more effective and efficient system. Rationalisation of the judicial structure and, as a consequence, judicial pay is a key part of that.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.63WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.63WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.63WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.63WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.64WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.64WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.64WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.64WS.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.64WS.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1423" speakername="Jack Straw" speakeroffice="The Secretary of State for Justice and Lord Chancellor" colnum="64WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0005.htm#09071651001391">
	<p pid="c.64WS.1/1">Revised operational guidance to police forces on the issue of penalty notices for disorder for retail theft and criminal damage has been published today. Copies will be placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
	<p pid="c.64WS.1/2">Under the PND scheme, established under the Criminal Justice and Police Act 2001 (sections 1-11), the police can issue fixed penalty notices of &pound;80 for minor retail theft, criminal damage and cannabis possession. Recipients have 21 days in which either to pay the penalty or elect to have their case heard in court. If no action is taken, a fine of one and a half times the penalty amount is registered against the offender by the magistrates court.</p>
	<p pid="c.64WS.1/3">Under section 6 of the Criminal Justice and Police Act 2001, the Secretary of State has the power to issue guidance to the police on the issuing of penalty notices. The latest version of the guidance was issued in March 2005. In view of concerns raised over the inappropriate use of PNDs, we have now issued strengthened revised guidance on retail theft. This restricts use of the disposal to first-time offenders who are not substance mis-users where the value of goods stolen is less than &pound;100 or where damage caused is less than &pound;300. The definition of retail theft has also been tightened to ensure that the disposal can be considered only for cases of shoplifting where normally the goods recovered are fit for re-sale.</p>
	<p pid="c.64WS.1/4">I am very grateful to those hon. Members who have made representations to me about this issue, especially <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1896" name="Anne McIntosh">the hon. Member for the Vale of York (Mrs. Anne McIntosh)</phrase>.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.64WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.64WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.64WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.64WS.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.64WS.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1865" speakername="Michael Wills" speakeroffice="The Minister of State, Ministry of Justice" colnum="64WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0006.htm#09071651001392">
	<p pid="c.64WS.3/1">I have today laid before each House a revised copy of the Lord Chancellor's Code of Practice on the management of records, issued under section 46 of the Freedom of Information Act 2000. I have also published a copy of the Government's response to the public consultation entitled &quot;The Freedom of Information Act 2000: The designation of additional public authorities&quot;. Copies of this document are available in the Libraries of both Houses and also in the Vote Office and the Printed Paper Office.</p>
	<p pid="c.64WS.3/2">These publications support the Government's plans to increase the accessibility of public information and promote the culture of openness and transparency in public life. On <phrase class="date" code="2009-06-10">10 June</phrase> the Prime Minister committed to a reduction of the 30-year rule to 20-years in response to the 30 year rule review. The Government are considering carefully the practical details of implementing a new rule and aim to publish their full response in late summer.</p>
	<p pid="c.64WS.3/3">Responses to the consultation entitled &quot;The Freedom of Information Act 2000: The designation of additional public authorities&quot; show considerable support for the principle of extending the coverage of the Act to additional organisations through a series of section 5 orders.</p>
	<p pid="c.64WS.3/4">The response proposes an initial, focused section 5 order to be accompanied by action outside the Act to promote proactive publication&mdash;by voluntary adoption of the ICO's model publication scheme&mdash;and openness&mdash;by reminding public authorities and contractors of the existing guidance on access to information, which should inform contracting practices and responses to requests for information. The current list of bodies proposed for inclusion in this first section 5 order are:</p>
	<p pid="c.64WS.3/5" class="indent">Academy schools</p>
	<p pid="c.64WS.3/6" class="indent">Association of Chief Police Officers (ACPO)</p>
	<p pid="c.64WS.3/7" class="indent">Financial Ombudsman Service</p>
	<p pid="c.64WS.3/8" class="indent">UCAS</p>
	<p pid="c.64WS.3/9">These bodies will be consulted directly, and the Government aim to bring forward a section 5 order early in the 2009-10 session. The response also makes clear the Government's intention to engage with Network Rail and utility companies to consider whether section 5 or primary legislation might be appropriate means of including those bodies within the FOIA regime too.</p>
	<p pid="c.64WS.3/10">FOI depends on good records and information management. This is recognised in the FOI Act by provision at section 46 for guidance to be issued in the form of a code of practice. The first code of practice was issued in November 2002, nearly seven years ago. Much has changed since then, not least the increased use of information technology to create, store, share and publish records and other information. These changes have made it necessary to update the guidance and today the Lord Chancellor is issuing a revised code of practice.</p>
	<p pid="c.64WS.3/11">As well as addressing some of the challenges of digital records management, the revised code takes account of new ways of collaborative working. It also emphasises the business benefits of good records and information management and its relevance to data protection and other information legislation, as well as to freedom of information.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.66WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.66WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.66WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.66WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.66WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.66WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.66WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.66WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.66WS.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.66WS.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.66WS.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.66WS.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.66WS.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.66WS.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.66WS.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.66WS.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.66WS.8" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.66WS.8" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.66WS.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1997" speakername="Gordon Brown" speakeroffice="The Prime Minister" colnum="66WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0006.htm#09071651001395">
	<p pid="c.66WS.8/1">I have today published a list of gifts received and given by Ministers valued at more than &pound;140 for the period <phrase class="date" code="2008-04-01">1 April 2008</phrase> to <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-31">31 March 2009</phrase>. Copies of the lists have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.66WS.9" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.66WS.9" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.66WS.10" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.66WS.10" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.66WS.10" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1997" speakername="Gordon Brown" speakeroffice="The Prime Minister" colnum="66WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0006.htm#09071651001396">
	<p pid="c.66WS.10/1">I have today published a list of all overseas visits undertaken by Ministers costing &pound;500 or more during the period <phrase class="date" code="2008-04-01">1 April 2008</phrase> to <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-31">31 March 2009</phrase>. The list provides details of the date, destination and purpose of all such visits and the cost of Ministers' travel and accommodation where appropriate. Total expenditure on Ministerial overseas visits for 2008-09 is &pound;9.4 million. Copies of the list have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.66WS.11" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.66WS.11" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.66WS.12" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.66WS.12" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.66WS.12" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1997" speakername="Gordon Brown" speakeroffice="The Prime Minister" colnum="66WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0006.htm#09071651001397">
	<p pid="c.66WS.12/1">I have today published a list of official and charity receptions held at 10 Downing Street for the financial year 2008-09.</p>
	<p pid="c.66WS.12/2">The total cost of official receptions held at 10 Downing Street and Chequers for the financial year 2008-09 was &pound;136,000. The costs of the charity receptions are funded by the charities involved.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/5"> <td><i>Date</i></td> <td><i>Event</i></td> <td><i>Numbers</i></td> <td><i>Host</i></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/6"> <td>18/03/2009</td> <td>Government - Real Help Now</td> <td>90</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/7"> <td>17/03/2009</td> <td>Charity - London Jewish Museum</td> <td>80</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/8"> <td>12/03/2009</td> <td>Government - Health Taskforce</td> <td>100</td> <td>Prime Minister and Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/9"> <td>10/03/2009</td> <td>Charity - Mentoring and Befriending Foundation</td> <td>120</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/10"> <td>10/03/2009</td> <td>Charity - RNIB Reception</td> <td>80</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/11"> <td>05/03/2009</td> <td>Government - LGBT History Month</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/12"> <td>03/03/2009</td> <td>Charity - McAslan Family Trust</td> <td>100</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/13"> <td>02/03/2009</td> <td>Charity - Tesco Mum of the Year</td> <td>45</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/14"> <td>26/02/2009</td> <td>Charity - Reading Heroes</td> <td>70</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/15"> <td>24/02/2009</td> <td>Charity &mdash; St. John Eye Hospital</td> <td>100</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/16"> <td>18/02/2009</td> <td>Government - Rugby, Injured Players Foundation</td> <td>100</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/17"> <td>10/02/2009</td> <td>Charity - Save the Children</td> <td>100</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/18"> <td>28/01/2009</td> <td>Government - Regional Editors</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/19"> <td>27/01/2009</td> <td>Charity - Centerpoint</td> <td>100</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/20"> <td>26/01/2009</td> <td>Government - Apprenticeship Ambassadors Network</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minster</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/21"> <td>21/01/2009</td> <td>Government - Lobby Journalists</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/22"> <td>20/01/2009</td> <td>Charity - Whizz Kids</td> <td>100</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/23"> <td>15/01/2009</td> <td>Government - Diana Awards</td> <td>50</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/24"> <td>12/01/2009</td> <td>Government - Religious Leaders</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/25"> <td>16/12/2008</td> <td>Charity - Oxford Philomusica</td> <td>100</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/26"> <td>16/12/2008</td> <td>Government - Sun Military Awards</td> <td>80</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/27"> <td>15/12/2008</td> <td>Government - Christmas Tea</td> <td>100</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/28"> <td>09/12/2008</td> <td>Charity - Dyslexia Action</td> <td>80</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/29"> <td>04/12/2008</td> <td>Government - Teach First</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/30"> <td>02/12/2008</td> <td>Charity - Women for Women</td> <td>80</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/31"> <td>02/12/2008</td> <td>Government - Eve of Session</td> <td>170</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/32"> <td>25/11/2008</td> <td>Charity - Caron Keating Foundation</td> <td>40</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/33"> <td>24/11/2008</td> <td>Charity - Leeds Pianoforte Competition</td> <td>100</td> <td>Prime Minister and Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/34"> <td>24/11/2008</td> <td>Daily Mail Children's Champions</td> <td>40</td> <td>Prime Minister &amp; Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/35"> <td>19/11/2008</td> <td>Government - Special Olympics (held at the British Museum)</td> <td>170</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/36"> <td>18/11/2008</td> <td>Charity - Sir John Soane Museum</td> <td>80</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/37"> <td>17/11/2008</td> <td>Government - Global Fellows</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/38"> <td>12/11/2008</td> <td>Government - Apprenticeship</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/39"> <td>11/11/2008</td> <td>Charity - London Jewish Museum</td> <td>80</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/40"> <td>11/11/2008</td> <td>Government - Armistice Anniversary</td> <td>100</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/41"> <td>27/10/2008</td> <td>Government - Black History Month</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/42"> <td>22/10/2008</td> <td>Government - Para;ympics 2008</td> <td>500</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/43"> <td>21/10/2008</td> <td>Charity - Fight for Sight</td> <td>80</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/44"> <td>20/10/2008</td> <td>Government - Peace Awards</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/45"> <td>14/10/2008</td> <td>Charity - Dress for Success</td> <td>80</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/46"> <td>13/10/2008</td> <td>Charity Dinner - Waterford School Trust</td> <td>40</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/47"> <td>08/10/2008</td> <td>Government - British Mountaineering Council</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/48"> <td>07/10/2008</td> <td>Charity - Lord Mayor's Appeal</td> <td>150</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/49"> <td>03/10/2008</td> <td>Government - Church Leaders</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/50"> <td>03/10/2008</td> <td>Government - Olympics Reception(held at Lancaster House)</td> <td>670</td> <td>Prime Minister and Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/51"> <td>02/10/2008</td> <td>Government &mdash; BSME - Reception</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/52"> <td>01/10/2008</td> <td>Government - Older Peoples Day</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/53"> <td>01/10/2008</td> <td>Government- Sally Keeble Alcohol Licensing campaign</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/54"> <td>01/10/2008</td> <td>Pride of Britain Award winners</td> <td>40</td> <td>Prime Minister &amp; Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/55"> <td>29/09/2008</td> <td>Government - National Council for Educational Excellence</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/56"> <td>15/09/2008</td> <td>Charity - London Fashion Week</td> <td>200</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/57"> <td>11/09/2008</td> <td>Charity - Michael Palin Centre</td> <td>80</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/58"> <td>10/09/2008</td> <td>Government - Fulbright Scholars</td> <td>180</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/59"> <td>09/09/2008</td> <td>Charity - Alan Senitt Memorial Trust</td> <td>130</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/60"> <td>09/09/2008</td> <td>Government - ATA Veterans Badge presentation</td> <td>180</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/61"> <td>03/09/2008</td> <td>Charity &mdash; Middlesbrough Institute for Modern Art</td> <td>80</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/62"> <td>18/08/2008</td> <td>Charity - Wellbeing of Women</td> <td>120</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/63"> <td>24/07/2008</td> <td>Government - Local Heroes/Voluntary Sector</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/64"> <td>23/07/2008</td> <td>Government - Women's Land Army</td> <td>120</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/65"> <td>22/07/2008</td> <td>Government - Press Lobby</td> <td>200</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/66"> <td>22/07/2008</td> <td>Charity - Sarah McKechnie Foundation</td> <td>120</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/67"> <td>16/07/2008</td> <td>Government &mdash; TA100 Anniversary</td> <td>80</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/68"> <td>15/07/2008</td> <td>Charity - DEERA International</td> <td>80</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/69"> <td>11/07/2008</td> <td>Charity &mdash; Transplant in Mind</td> <td>70</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/70"> <td>10/07/2008</td> <td>Government &mdash; Police Bravery</td> <td>160</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/71"> <td>07/07/2008</td> <td>Government &mdash; Business in the Community</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/72"> <td>02/07/2008</td> <td>Government &mdash; NHS 60th Anniversary</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/73"> <td>01/07/2008</td> <td>Government &mdash; Creative Economy Programme</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister and Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/74"> <td>27/06/2008</td> <td>Charity Maggies Centres</td> <td>60</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/75"> <td>26/06/2008</td> <td>Government - Veterans Day</td> <td>40</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/76"> <td>18/06/2008</td> <td>Government &mdash; Big Arts</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister and Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/77"> <td>17/06/2008</td> <td>Charity &mdash; Tom Rhys Pryce</td> <td>80</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/78"> <td>10/06/2008</td> <td>Government &mdash; Carers</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/79"> <td>10/06/2008</td> <td>Charity &mdash; PACT</td> <td>50</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/80"> <td>05/06/2008</td> <td>Government &mdash; Spitfire Tribute Foundation</td> <td>80</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/81"> <td>02/06/2008</td> <td>Government &mdash; Daycare Trust</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/82"> <td>22/05/2008</td> <td>Government &mdash; Excellence in Nursing</td> <td>35</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/83"> <td>13/05/2008</td> <td>Charity &mdash; Pilotlight</td> <td>80</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/84"> <td>12/05/2008</td> <td>Government &mdash; Show Racism the Red Card</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/85"> <td>07/05/2008</td> <td>Government &mdash; Global Day of Prayer</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/86"> <td>06/05/2008</td> <td>Charity &mdash; New Children's Hospital Appeal</td> <td>40</td> <td>Mrs Brown</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.66WS.12/87"> <td>28/04/2008</td> <td>Government &mdash; Basra Development</td> <td>150</td> <td>Prime Minister</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.70WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.70WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.70WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.70WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.73WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.73WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.73WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.73WS.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.73WS.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1997" speakername="Gordon Brown" speakeroffice="The Prime Minister" colnum="73WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0008.htm#09071651001399">
	<p pid="c.73WS.1/1">Listed below are the names of special advisers in post at <phrase class="date" code="2009-07-16">16 July 2009</phrase>, the special advisers' pay ranges for 2009-10, the number of special advisers in each pay band by Department and the total pay bill cost of special advisers for 2008-09.</p>
	<p pid="c.73WS.1/2">All special advisers are appointed under terms and conditions set out in the Model Contract and Code of Conduct for Special Advisers to provide assistance on the full range of their appointing Minister's departmental responsibilities.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/5"> <td><i>Appointing Minister</i></td> <td><i>Special Adviser in post</i></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/6"> <td>The Prime Minister</td> <td>Greg Beales  Theo Bertram  Nicola Burdett  Nick Butler  Konrad Caulkett (p-t)  Matt Cavanagh  Brendan Cox  Dan Corry  Colin Currie (p-t)  Patrick Diamond  Michael Dugher  Justin Forsyth  Stuart Hudson  Michael Jacobs  Gavin Kelly  Richard Lloyd  Kirsty McNeill  David Muir  Sue Nye (p-t)  Nick Pearce  Lisa Perrin  Wilf Stevenson  Anthony Vigor  Stewart Wood  John Woodcock</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/7"> <td>Minister for Cabinet Office and the Olympics and Paymaster General</td> <td>Robert Philpot</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/8"> <td>Chief Whip (Commons) and Parliamentary Secretary to the Treasury</td> <td>Gary Follis  Luke Sullivan</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/9"> <td>Chief Whip (Lords)</td> <td>Ben Coffman  Sue Jackson</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/10"> <td>First Secretary of State, Secretary of State for Business, Innovation and Skills and Lord President of the Council</td> <td>Geoffrey Norris  Patrick Loughran</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/11"> <td>Minister of State (Business)</td> <td>Matt Cooke</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/12"> <td>Secretary of State for Children, Schools and Families</td> <td>Francine Bates  Alex Belardinelli</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/13"> <td>Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government</td> <td>Ann Rossiter  Jake Sumner</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/14"> <td>Minister of State (Housing)</td> <td>Ian Parker</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/15"> <td>Secretary of State for Culture, Media and Sport</td> <td>Philip French  Lenny Shallcross</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/16"> <td>Secretary of State for Defence</td> <td>Alaina Macdonald  Andrew Bagnall</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/17"> <td>Secretary of State for Energy and Climate Change</td> <td>Polly Billington  Tom Restrick</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/18"> <td>Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs</td> <td>Wesley Ball  Beatrice Stern</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/19"> <td>Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs</td> <td>Madlin Sadler/Sarah Schaefer (job share)</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/20"> <td>Secretary of State for Health</td> <td>Katie Myler</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/21"> <td>Secretary of State for the Home Department</td> <td>Clare Montagu  Mario Dunn</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/22"> <td>Leader of the House of Commons, Lord Privy Seal and Minister for Women and Equality</td> <td>Ayesha Hazarika  Anna Healy</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/23"> <td>Leader of the House of Lords, and Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster</td> <td>Philip Bassett  Jonathan Pearse</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/24"> <td>Secretary of State for International Development</td> <td>Richard Darlington  Stephen Doughty</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/25"> <td>Lord Chancellor and Secretary of State for Justice</td> <td>Mark Davies  Declan McHugh</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/26"> <td>Secretary of State for Northern Ireland</td> <td>Oonagh Blackman</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/27"> <td>Secretary of State for Scotland</td> <td>John McTeman  Tom Greatrex</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/28"> <td>Secretary of State for Transport</td> <td>Claire MacAleese  David Learn</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/29"> <td>Chancellor of the Exchequer1</td> <td>Sam White  Catherine McCleod</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/30"> <td>Chief Secretary</td> <td>Tony Danker  David Mills  Graham Dale</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/31"> <td>Secretary of State for Wales</td> <td>Andrew Bold  Dan Lodge</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/32"> <td>Secretary of State for Work and Pensions</td> <td>Will McDonald  Eleanor Wilcox</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/33"> <td colspan="2"><sup>(1)</sup> In addition, the Chancellor of the Exchequer has appointed Torsten Henricson-Bell and Geoffrey Spence to the Council of Economic Advisers.</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="c.73WS.1/36" class="italic">Pay bands for 2009-10</p>
	<p pid="c.73WS.1/37">The pay bands and pay ranges for special advisers for 2009-10 are as follows:</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/40"> <td>Scheme Ceiling</td> <td>&pound;142,668</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/41"> <td>Pay Band 4</td> <td>&pound;88,966-&pound;106,864</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/42"> <td>Pay Band 3 and Premium</td> <td>&pound;66,512 -&pound;103,263</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/43"> <td>Pay Band 2</td> <td>&pound;52,215-&pound;69,266</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/44"> <td>Pay Band 1</td> <td>&pound;40,352-&pound;54,121</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="c.73WS.1/47" class="italic">Advisers by Pay Band</p>
	<p pid="c.73WS.1/48">At <phrase class="date" code="2009-07-16">16 July 2009</phrase>, there were 74 Special Advisers in post. The number of special advisers in each pay band by department is as follows:</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/51"> <td></td> <td colspan="4"><i>Pay band </i><sup>(<i>1</i>)</sup></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/52"> <td><i>Department</i></td> <td><i>1</i></td> <td><i>2</i></td> <td><i>3</i></td> <td><i>4</i></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/53"> <td>No. 10 <sup>(2)</sup></td> <td>4</td> <td>5</td> <td>14</td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/54"> <td>Cabinet Office</td> <td></td> <td>1</td> <td></td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/55"> <td>Chief Whips' Offices (Commons and Lords)</td> <td>2</td> <td></td> <td>2</td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/56"> <td>Business, Innovation and Skills</td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/57"> <td>Children, Schools and Families</td> <td></td> <td>2</td> <td></td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/58"> <td>Communities and Local Government</td> <td></td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/59"> <td>Culture, Media and Sport</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>1</td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/60"> <td>Defence</td> <td></td> <td>2</td> <td></td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/61"> <td>Energy and Climate Change</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>2</td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/62"> <td>Environment, Food and Rural Affairs</td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> <td></td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/63"> <td>Foreign and Commonwealth Office<sup>(3)</sup></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>1</td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/64"> <td>Health</td> <td></td> <td>1</td> <td></td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/65"> <td>Home Office</td> <td></td> <td>2</td> <td></td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/66"> <td>Leader of the House of Commons, Lord Privy Seal and Minister for Women and Equality</td> <td></td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/67"> <td>Leader of the House of Lords and Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster</td> <td>1</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td colspan="2">1</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/68"> <td>International Development</td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> <td></td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/69"> <td>Justice (Lord Chancellor)</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>1</td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/70"> <td>Northern Ireland Office</td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>1</td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/71"> <td>Scotland Office</td> <td></td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/72"> <td>Transport</td> <td></td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/73"> <td>HM Treasury<sup>(4)</sup></td> <td>1</td> <td>3</td> <td>3</td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/74"> <td>Wales Office</td> <td></td> <td>1</td> <td></td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/75"> <td>Work and Pensions</td> <td>1</td> <td>1</td> <td></td> <td colspan="2"></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.73WS.1/76"> <td>Total</td> <td>12</td> <td>26</td> <td>30</td> <td colspan="2">1</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="c.73WS.1/79" class="italic">Paybill costs</p>
	<p pid="c.73WS.1/80">The paybill for special advisers in 2008-2009 was &pound;5.9m<sup>(5)</sup>.</p>
	<p pid="c.73WS.1/81" class="indent"><sup>(1)</sup>Plus three special advisers whose pay bands have yet to be agreed.</p>
	<p pid="c.73WS.1/82" class="indent"><sup>(2)</sup>Plus two special advisers who are paid beyond Pay Band 4 but within the scheme ceiling.</p>
	<p pid="c.73WS.1/83" class="indent"><sup>(3)</sup>Job share</p>
	<p pid="c.73WS.1/84" class="indent"><sup>(4)</sup>Includes the two members of the Council of Economic Advisers who are employed on special adviser terms.</p>
	<p pid="c.73WS.1/85" class="indent"><sup>(5)</sup>This figure includes salary, severance pay and estimate of pension costs.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.75WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.75WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.75WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.75WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.77WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.77WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.77WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.77WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.77WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.77WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.77WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.77WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.78WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.78WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.78WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.78WS.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.78WS.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1997" speakername="Gordon Brown" speakeroffice="The Prime Minister" colnum="78WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0009.htm#09071651001403">
	<p pid="c.78WS.1/1">I am today laying before the House the Government's &quot;Road to 2010&quot; plan (Cm 7675). This is a strategy that will lead us into the 2010 Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (NPT) review conference and beyond. The &quot;Road to 2010&quot; covers every dimension of the nuclear issues that are facing us today and sets out how the UK will play a leading role in tackling them. Next year's conference provides an opportunity to renew and re-invigorate the bargain at the heart of the NPT which grants states access to civil nuclear power in return for a commitment not to proliferate nuclear weapons, and places a responsibility on nuclear weapons states to show leadership on the question of disarmament.</p>
	<p pid="c.78WS.1/2">The UK remains committed to the reduction and eventual elimination of nuclear weapons, and to ensuring that nations have access to nuclear technology for peaceful purposes. All states, including Iran and North Korea, have a right to such access&mdash;and we are ready to help, so long as these states reject the development of nuclear weapons. To promote the development of cost-effective civil nuclear technology which cannot be diverted for use in weapons programmes, we are launching a nuclear science centre of excellence. This centre will enhance collaborations between academia, industry and Government, both domestically and internationally, to focus on this important and difficult task. The Government are committing &pound;20 million over the first five years to this centre.</p>
	<p pid="c.78WS.1/3">All nuclear material must be held securely, to prevent it falling into the hands of terrorist groups or hostile states. The UK believes that nuclear security must become the fourth pillar of the global nuclear framework, alongside civil power, non-proliferation and disarmament. Momentum for greater nuclear security is growing, with President Obama announcing a nuclear security summit in the spring of next year, which the UK will take a full part in. In order to help reduce the risk that material will be lost or stolen, the UK is making an offer to assist any nation with security improvements should they request our help. This assistance could be in the form of using our expertise to strengthen security, for example through improving facilities or through training personnel. To improve our defensive measures, the Government are also providing an additional &pound;3 million to maintain our world-leading forensics and detection capability at the Atomic Weapons Establishment (AWE).</p>
	<p pid="c.78WS.1/4">The Government recognise that urgent action is required to address proliferation of nuclear weapons. The &quot;Road to 2010&quot; plan sets out a phased approach which will enable progress on non-proliferation and multilateral disarmament. In the first instance, steps must be taken to improve transparency of current weapons capabilities, as we seek greater control to prevent expansion of those capabilities. The second stage is verifiable multilateral reductions in arsenals. Finally, we must work globally both to establish the security conditions that will enable a world free from nuclear weapons and to overcome the technical and policy challenges associated with the complete abolition of nuclear weapons. For our part, as soon as it becomes useful for our arsenal to be included in a broader negotiation, Britain stands ready to participate and to act.</p>
	<p pid="c.78WS.1/5">There is growing momentum across the globe to tackle these strategic challenges. The UK has been a civil and military nuclear power for many decades and so we have a great deal of expertise to offer. As we head towards next year's NPT review conference, I am committed to making the UK a leading nation in the drive to develop credible answers to the nuclear questions that face us today. It is vital that we make progress&mdash;I believe this strategy sets out what the UK can do alone and in partnership with other countries in the period up to the conference and beyond to bring us the security and prosperity we seek in the decades to come.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.79WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.79WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.79WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.79WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.79WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.79WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.80WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.80WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.80WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.80WS.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.80WS.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1878" speakername="Sadiq Khan" speakeroffice="The Minister of State, Department for Transport" colnum="80WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0009.htm#09071651001405">
	<p pid="c.80WS.1/1">On <phrase class="date" code="2009-07-14">14 July</phrase> last year, my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1990" name="Tom Harris">the Member for Glasgow, South (Mr. Harris)</phrase>, made a statement offering assurance to Parliament that a statement will be published at least every 12 months until the completion of the construction of Crossrail, setting out information about the project's funding and finances. This assurance was placed on the Crossrail Register of Undertakings and Assurances.</p>
	<p pid="c.80WS.1/2">Government are committed to ensuring that there is a high level of transparency as to the progress and cost of the Crossrail project. Our intention in this area was set out in the Heads of Terms which were signed in November 2007. The Heads of Terms have now been superseded by the Crossrail Core Agreements, binding legal documents which set out the funding, governance and delivery arrangements for the Crossrail project. These were signed by the Secretary of State for Transport, Transport for London, and Cross London Rail Links Ltd on <phrase class="date" code="2009-12-03">3 December</phrase> last year, and were published in the House Library, with an accompanying statement to the House. Since the assurance was given, Cross London Rail Links Ltd has also changed its name to Crossrail Ltd.</p>
	<p pid="c.80WS.1/3">In line with my hon. Friend's assurance to the House I am therefore publishing this statement within 12 months of the Crossrail Act 2008 coming into force on <phrase class="date" code="2008-07-22">22 July 2008</phrase>, and set out below the information outlined in that assurance:</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="c.80WS.1/6"> <td>Total funding amounts provided to Crossrail Ltd by the Department for Transport and TfL in relation to the construction of Crossrail in the period 22 July 2008 to 30 May 2009.</td> <td>&pound;200.922 million</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.80WS.1/7"> <td>Expenditure incurred by Crossrail Ltd in relation to the construction of Crossrail in the period 22 July 2008 to 30 May 2009 (excluding recoverable VAT on land and property purchases).</td> <td>&pound;196.803 million</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.80WS.1/8"> <td>Total expenditure incurred by Crossrail Ltd in relation to the construction of Crossrail to the end of the period 22 July 2008 to 30 May 2009 (excluding recoverable VAT on land and property purchases).</td> <td>&pound;196.803 million</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="c.80WS.1/9"> <td>The amounts realised by the disposal of any land or property for the purposes of the construction of Crossrail by the Secretary of State, TfL or Crossrail Ltd in the period covered by the statement.</td> <td>Nil</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="c.80WS.1/12">The numbers above have been provided by Crossrail Ltd and are drawn from their accounts for the relevant periods.</p>
	<p pid="c.80WS.1/13">I can also confirm that the costs of the construction of Crossrail are likely to fall within the agreed budget, based on best current estimates of costs provided by Crossrail Ltd.</p>
	<p pid="c.80WS.1/14">The Government remain fully committed to Crossrail. This is a long-term major infrastructure project, helping, and responding to, London and the South-East's transport needs for the next half century and more.</p>
	<p pid="c.80WS.1/15">We remain confident that Crossrail will be delivered on time and on budget and that the project can be funded as planned.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.81WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.81WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.81WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.81WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.82WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.82WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.82WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.82WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.82WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.82WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.82WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.82WS.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.82WS.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1878" speakername="Sadiq Khan" speakeroffice="The Minister of State, Department for Transport" colnum="82WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0010.htm#09071651001408">
	<p pid="c.82WS.3/1">The Local Transport Act 2008 includes powers for the Secretary of State to confer additional functions on Passenger Focus (formally known as the Rail Passengers' Council&mdash;the statutory rail passenger watchdog) so it can represent bus, coach and tram passengers. The Act also enables secondary legislation to be made requiring certain persons to display certain information relating to public transport.</p>
	<p pid="c.82WS.3/2">The Department for Transport is today publishing a consultation on a draft order to extend Passenger Focus' remit and draft regulations requiring bus and coach operators to display information on their vehicles about who passengers should contact if they want to make a complaint. Copies of the consultation materials will be made available on the Department's website: <a href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations">www.dft.gov.uk/consultations</a>, and are being placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.82WS.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.82WS.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.82WS.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.82WS.5" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.82WS.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1878" speakername="Sadiq Khan" speakeroffice="The Minister of State, Department for Transport" colnum="82WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0010.htm#09071651001409">
	<p pid="c.82WS.5/1">Under section 19 of the Transport Act 1985, the Secretary of State has the power to designate bodies who may issue permits under that section to eligible community transport operators. These section 19 permits allow the holder to operate transport services for hire or reward, subject to certain conditions, without the need for a full public service vehicle operator's licence.</p>
	<p pid="c.82WS.5/2">While developing the policy proposals now contained in the Local Transport Act 2008, the Government signalled their intention to review the current list of designated bodies. The Department for Transport will shortly be publishing a consultation on how it intends to advance this review. Copies of the consultation materials will be made available on the Department's website&mdash;<a href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations-and">www.dft.gov.uk/consultations&mdash;and</a> will be placed in the Libraries of the House.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.82WS.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.82WS.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.82WS.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.82WS.7" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.82WS.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1594" speakername="Paul Clark" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport" colnum="82WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0010.htm#09071651001410">
	<p pid="c.82WS.7/1">The air travel organiser's licence (ATOL) system provides financial protection to those taking flight-inclusive package holidays overseas. It ensures that in the event of a tour operator becoming insolvent, consumers already abroad can complete their holidays and be returned to the UK and those who have paid for their holidays but have not yet departed will receive a full refund. It is operated by the Civil Aviation Authority (CAA).</p>
	<p pid="c.82WS.7/2">The failure of XL leisure group in September 2008 and the effects of the recession have caused serious financial difficulties for the air travel trust fund (ATTF), which meets the insolvency protection costs of the ATOL scheme. To help address this, between April and June this year, the CAA consulted on possible increases to the ATOL protection contribution (APC) paid by travel companies to the ATTF. The consultation looked at a range of possible increases to the current charge of &pound;1 per passenger to between &pound;2.50 and &pound;3.50 per passenger.</p>
	<p pid="c.82WS.7/3">Following the consultation, the CAA provided advice to the Secretary of State recommending the APC be increased from &pound;1 to &pound;2.50 per passenger with effect from 1st October 2009. After careful consideration, I have decided to approve the recommended increase. I am aware of the extra burden this will place on travel companies and consumers at difficult times, which is why I have agreed to an increase at the bottom of the range consulted on by the CAA. I believe this strikes the right balance between ensuring the future financial stability of the ATTF while keeping additional burdens on travel companies and consumers as low as practicable. I believe that &pound;2.50 for the protection that ATOL provides represents a good deal for consumers&mdash;it is cheaper than stand-alone airline failure insurance and represents less than 0.5 per cent. of the average ATOL holiday price. The CAA intends to review the rate of the APC before the ATTF moves into surplus, projected to be by the spring of 2012.</p>
	<p pid="c.82WS.7/4">The increased APC will allow the ATTF access to additional commercial credit facilities which will benefit from an increased and extended Government guarantee that the Government have agreed to in principle. The Government also intend to consult on reforms to the ATOL system in the autumn to make it fairer and more understandable for consumers. A copy of the CAA's advice to the Secretary of State and a summary of consultation responses will be placed in the House Library.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.83WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.83WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.83WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.83WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.83WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.83WS.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.83WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1421" speakername="Helen Goodman" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Work and Pensions" colnum="83WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090716/wmstext/90716m0010.htm#09071651001411">
	<p pid="c.83WS.2/1">I am pleased to announce publication of the annual report by the Secretary of State for Work and Pensions on the Social Fund 2008-09 and the Social Fund Commissioner's annual report 2008-09.</p>
	<p pid="c.83WS.2/2">The Secretary of State's Annual Report on the Social Fund for 2008-09 (Cm 7677) has been laid before Parliament and will be published later today. Copies are available in the Vote Office and the Printed Paper Office.</p>
	<p pid="c.83WS.2/3">The report records that total gross expenditure in 2008-09, excluding winter fuel payments, was over &pound;1.1 billion. This included over 252,000 non-repayable community care grants and over 3 million interest free loans together worth over &pound;761 million, funeral and cold weather payments totalling over &pound;258 million and almost 263,000 Sure Start maternity grants worth almost &pound;133 million. In addition an estimated 9 million households benefited from a winter fuel payment at an estimated cost of around &pound;2.7 billion.</p>
	<p pid="c.83WS.2/4">The Social Fund Commissioner's report will be published later today and copies have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.84WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.84WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.84WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.84WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.86WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.86WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16c.86WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-07-16d.86WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

