<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.13WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.13WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.13WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.13WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.13WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.13WS.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.13WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1882" speakername="David Lammy" speakeroffice="The Minister for Higher Education and Intellectual Property" colnum="13WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm091028/wmstext/91028m0001.htm#09102823000112">
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/1">My right hon. Friend the First Secretary of State, Lord Mandelson, has made the following statement:</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/2" class="indent">The Department for Business, Innovation and Skills, together with the Intellectual Property Office, is today &quot;&copy; The Way Ahead: A Strategy for Copyright in the Digital Age&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/3" class="indent">This report set out the policies which will drive the UK approach to copyright in the digital age, reflecting how the UK is working to deliver the right solutions at a domestic level and to help drive the agenda on copyright issues in Europe and internationally.</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/4" class="indent">The core objective of &quot;&copy; The Way Ahead: A Strategy for Copyright in the Digital Age&quot; is to ensure the copyright system supports creativity and promotes investment and jobs while also ensuring that consumers are able to act with certainty and clarity.</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/5" class="indent">Building on the framework for supporting the creative industries set out in the &quot;Digital Britain Report and Creative Britain&quot;, its ambition is to set out a copyright roadmap determining the lessons policy makers should take from the present to help decide where we should go in the future.</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/6" class="indent">This copyright strategy will support fair treatment for creators; secure a viable future for rights holders; allow consumers to benefit from the digital age; and create a simpler system for businesses to operate in.</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/7" class="indent">This copyright strategy highlights three principles that need to be kept in mind in order to create a positive environment for copyright owners, consumers and business.</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/8" class="indent">First, copyright is harmonised at a European level and any action pursued domestically needs to be understood within this context;</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/9" class="indent">secondly, a pragmatic recognition that intervention from Government will not be the most useful action in all areas requiring attention, with it being more beneficial for business and copyright owners to pursue many solutions; and</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/10" class="indent">finally, recognition that Government have a responsibility to serve the interests of all participants in the copyright framework.</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/11" class="indent">The strategy develops a number of policy announcements in the &quot;Digital Britain Report&quot;, as well as encouraging domestic and international actions, which satisfy these three principles. The strategy states that the UK will:</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/12" class="indent">Enable a system of copyright licensing on an opt-out rather than opt-in basis, as is successfully practised elsewhere in Europe.</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/13" class="indent">Take powers to allow &quot;orphan works&quot; that have no clear owner to be used without fear of criminal liability.</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/14" class="indent">Act to monitor the behaviour of collecting societies.</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/15" class="indent">Encourage creative industries to employ standard contract terms and licences that give creators more control over their work.</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/16" class="indent">Enable business to continue to develop new business models, products and services that better meet customer expectations on utility and price, including making it easier to license copyright works.</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/17" class="indent">Ensure consumers respect copyright by encouraging the development of attractive legitimate services and tackling illicit peer-to-peer file-sharing.</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/18" class="indent">Signal its readiness to consider sympathetically Europe-wide moves to let non-commercial users use copyright works without fear of legal complications.</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/19" class="indent">Inevitably there will be some questions about how this work links in with what we are going to do about tackling unlawful peer-to-peer file-sharing. On unlawful file-sharing I am intending to make clear our intention to go ahead with legislation in this area which will establish a proportionate, but effective, way of reducing significantly the level of online infringement which is causing such damage to our creative industries. The approach of requiring internet service providers to send notifications to subscribers identified by rights holders as unlawfully file-sharing, and collecting data on the number of notifications sent to each subscriber which the rights holder can obtain via a court order, has been debated for some time, as has the imposition of technical measures should that approach not produce the results anticipated.</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/20" class="indent">What I will also make clear, however, is that temporary account suspension could be included in the measures taken, something that we floated as part of a Government statement on <phrase class="date" code="2009-08-25">25 August 2009</phrase>. Additionally I will make it clear that we are not expecting the whole cost to fall on internet service providers, but on the basis of a flat fee approach costs will be shared so that both sides can plan and budget. The full details of what we are intending, and the official response to the consultation that closed on <phrase class="date" code="2009-09-29">29 September 2009</phrase> will be made clear when the legislation is published next month.</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/21" class="indent">The two policies are complementary. It is right for Government to intervene on unlawful file-sharing to help create the space in which innovative business offerings can emerge. But it is also right that this should be done against the background of a fair deal for all parties. Creators and those who invest in creativity must receive a fair reward&mdash;the creative industries are built on that precept&mdash;but we also need to move to reinstate the respect that copyright should command from reasonable law-abiding people. Without that respect we&mdash;and the creative industries&mdash;face a much harder struggle.</p>
	<p pid="a.13WS.2/22" class="indent">Copies of the &quot;Copyright Strategy&quot; will be placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.14WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.14WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.14WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.14WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.14WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.14WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.15WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.15WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.15WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.15WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.15WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.15WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.16WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.16WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.16WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.16WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.16WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.16WS.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.16WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1833" speakername="David Kidney" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Energy and Climate Change" colnum="16WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm091028/wmstext/91028m0001.htm#09102823000115">
	<p pid="a.16WS.2/1">Today my right hon. Friend the Minister of State for Energy and Climate Change, Lord Hunt, made the following ministerial statement:</p>
	<p pid="a.16WS.2/2" class="indent">I would like to inform the House that the Nuclear Decommissioning Authority (NDA) is close to concluding its sale process for the disposal of land adjacent to Sellafield in Cumbria.</p>
	<p pid="a.16WS.2/3" class="indent">I hope to be able to announce the successful bidder&mdash;who intends to develop the site for new nuclear power generation&mdash;shortly.</p>
	<p pid="a.16WS.2/4" class="indent">Proceeds from the sale of this site will be used by the NDA to offset the cost of decommissioning and to further its core mission. A successful outcome of the sale process will further demonstrate that major energy companies are gearing up for significant investment in low carbon energy in the UK.</p>
	<p pid="a.16WS.2/5" class="indent">I will place details of the outcome of this sale process, including the sum raised and the identity of the bidder in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
	<p pid="a.16WS.2/6" class="indent">Any new nuclear power station development will be subject to the regulatory and other consenting processes.</p>
	<p pid="a.16WS.2/7" class="indent">The land to be sold has been nominated into the Government's strategic siting assessment process which assesses sites for their suitability for new nuclear power stations. The Government will be consulting on their assessment of the sites that are potentially suitable for new nuclear power stations as part of their consultation on the draft &quot;National Policy Statement for Nuclear Power Generation&quot; which will be published this autumn.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.16WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.16WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.16WS.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.16WS.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.16WS.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.16WS.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.17WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.17WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.17WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.17WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.17WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.17WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.18WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.18WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.18WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.18WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.18WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.18WS.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.18WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1653" speakername="Chris Mole" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport" colnum="18WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm091028/wmstext/91028m0001.htm#09102823000118">
	<p pid="a.18WS.2/1">I regret to inform the House that some of the figures in the answer given to Parliamentary Question 276453 on <phrase class="date" code="2009-06-02">2 June</phrase>, <phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2009-06-02.298"><i>Official Report</i>, column 298W</phrase>, to <phrase class="honfriend" id="unknown" name="None">the hon. Member for Chipping Barnet (Mrs. T. Villiers)</phrase> about how much (a) the Department and (b) its agencies spent on car hire in each year since 2001 were incorrect.</p>
	<p pid="a.18WS.2/2">When preparing an answer to a current question it has come to light that there are some discrepancies with the data submitted for the previous answer given due to two errors in the transposition of data. The Government Car and Despatch Agency (GCDA) has also provided data for the last three financial years, whereas none was given by them for the previous question. They advise that figures are now available following improvements in record keeping and their undertaking of a contract to maintain vehicles on behalf of the Olympic development authority has resulted in an increase in car hire.</p>
	<p pid="a.18WS.2/3">The figures have been checked and the correct answer is below.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.18WS.2/6"> <td colspan="8"><i>&pound;</i></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.18WS.2/7"> <td></td> <td><i>2002-03</i></td> <td><i>2003-04</i></td> <td><i>2004-05</i></td> <td><i>2005-06</i></td> <td><i>2006-07</i></td> <td><i>2007-08</i></td> <td><i>2008-09</i></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.18WS.2/8"> <td>Department for  Transport  (Central)</td> <td>0</td> <td>156,918</td> <td>188,144</td> <td>208,126</td> <td>353,758</td> <td>220,352</td> <td>219,380</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.18WS.2/9"> <td>Executive Agencies</td> <td>1,045,417</td> <td>1,806,204</td> <td>2,002,484</td> <td>1,966,637</td> <td>2,385,202</td> <td>2,467,707</td> <td>2,756,202</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.18WS.2/12">It is not possible to provide costs for the Department for Transport or for the Driving Standards Agency in 2002-03 because the information is not available in a comparable format.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.18WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.18WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.18WS.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.18WS.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.19WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.19WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.19WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.19WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.20WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.20WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.20WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.20WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28a.20WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2009-10-28b.20WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

