<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;" >
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;" >
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;" >
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;" >
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;" >
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;" >
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;" >

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="b" latest="yes">

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.15WS.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="15WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#70510m0001.htm_dpthd0">
	Treasury
</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.15WS.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="15WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#07051082000010">
	Asset Freezing Regime
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.15WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1740" speakername="Edward Balls" speakeroffice="The Economic Secretary to the Treasury" colnum="15WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#07051082000145">
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/1">In my written ministerial statement of <phrase class="date" code="2006-10-10">10 October 2006</phrase>, I undertook to report to Parliament on a quarterly basis on the operation of the UK's asset freezing regime. This is the second of these reports and covers the period January-March 2007.<sup>(1)</sup></p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/2" class="italic">Asset-freezing framework</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/3">The Government launched their strategy to combat money laundering and terrorist finance on <phrase class="date" code="2007-02-28">28 February 2007</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/4">As my statement to Parliament of the same date explained, the strategy outlines the Government's key priorities for the future, along with measures to deliver these. New measures include further steps to promote the proactive use of asset-freezing powers; notably, the creation of a dedicated Treasury asset-freezing unit that will increase the expertise and operational focus brought to bear on asset freezing, in response to advice from law enforcement and security agencies.</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/5" class="italic">Asset-freezing designations</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/6">In the quarter January-March 2007, the Treasury made 19 domestic designations under the Terrorism (United Nations Measures) Order 2006 and the Al-Qaeda and Taliban (United Nations Measures) Order 2006.</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/7">Of these, 12 persons already designated under earlier Orders were re-designated under these Orders.</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/8">The Terrorism Order and the Al-Qaeda and Taliban Order provide, where appropriate, for designations to be made confidentially and with restricted circulation of notice. No persons were designated on this basis in this quarter.</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/9">Two persons were designated on the basis of closed source evidence provided by law enforcement and intelligence agencies.</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/10">There were no financial sanctions listings, in relation to terrorism or Al-Qaeda and the Taliban, of persons with links to the UK at the EU or the UN.</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/11">No designated persons have been delisted in this quarter.</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/12">A total of 223 separate accounts and approximately &pound;555,000<sup>(2)</sup> of suspected terrorist funds have been frozen in the UK since 2001.</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/13" class="italic">Litigation</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/14">There has been one case of domestic litigation regarding financial sanctions.</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/15" qnum="2006">EWCH 2328 (Admin), confirmed the High Court judgment of <phrase class="date" code="2006-09-22">22 September 2006</phrase> upholding the Treasury's actions regarding benefits payments to the households of listed individuals.</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/16" class="italic">Reviews</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/17">The Treasury keeps domestic asset-freezing cases under review. A number of formal reviews have been initiated in this quarter and the reviews of 12 cases have been completed. In all cases decisions were taken following the review to maintain the asset freeze.</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/18" class="italic">Licensing policy</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/19">In accordance with UN Security Council Resolution 1452 (2002), the Treasury operates a licensing system whereby designated persons and others are able to apply to make or receive payments under specific and, if necessary, monitored conditions. In this quarter, the following licences were issued:</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/20" class="indent">four listed persons were granted basic expenses licences;</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/21" class="indent">three of which were for benefits payments</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/22" class="indent">four listed persons were granted extraordinary expenses licences; and</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/23" class="indent">twenty-three listed persons were granted legal expenses licences.</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/24">In addition, the households of two listed persons were granted benefits licences in accordance with the policy I set out in my statement of <phrase class="date" code="2006-07-03">3 July 2006</phrase> to Parliament.</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/25" class="indent"><sup>(1)</sup> The detail that can be provided to the House on a quarterly basis is subject to the need to avoid the identification, directly or indirectly, of personal or operationally sensitive information.</p>
	<p pid="b.15WS.2/26" class="indent"><sup>(2 )</sup>This figure includes $58,000 of suspected terrorist funds frozen in the UK. This has been converted using current exchange rates. Future fluctuations in the exchange rate may impact on the contribution this sum makes to future totals of suspected terrorist funds frozen.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.16WS.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="16WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#07051082000011">
	Vulture Funds
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.16WS.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1997" speakername="Gordon Brown" speakeroffice="The Chancellor of the Exchequer" colnum="16WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#07051082000146">
	<p pid="b.16WS.1/1">I deplore the activities of so-called vulture funds that seek to profit from debts owed by the poorest countries in the world. I am determined to limit the damage done by such funds. The UK will therefore:</p>
	<p pid="b.16WS.1/2" class="indent">call on the World Bank to make the IDA Debt Reduction Facility available to HIPC countries before they reach decision point, in order to help countries to eliminate their commercial debts at the earliest possible opportunity and thereby reduce the likelihood of debts being sold on to aggressive creditors;</p>
	<p pid="b.16WS.1/3" class="indent">stand ready to scale up our contribution to the Debt Reduction Facility in support of this policy change;</p>
	<p pid="b.16WS.1/4" class="indent">take forward talks with leading commercial creditors on a voluntary code of conduct that will set out the actions that responsible creditors should take to help reduce the risk of litigation, including the requirement to participate in collective action to reduce unsustainable debts;</p>
	<p pid="b.16WS.1/5" class="indent">work with our G8 partners to develop a Charter on Responsible Lending that includes a commitment to protect developing countries from vulture fund activity;</p>
	<p pid="b.16WS.1/6" class="indent">work to ensure that HIPCs have access to the legal assistance they need to defend themselves against litigation, including by supporting proposals at the African Development Bank to develop a Legal Assistance Facility to help countries facing legal action gain access to technical and legal support;</p>
	<p pid="b.16WS.1/7" class="indent">continue to strengthen debt management capacity amongst HIPCs.</p>
	<p pid="b.16WS.1/8">I will also take forward discussions with my international partners on this issue, including at the G8 Finance Ministers' summit in Potsdam.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.17WS.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="17WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#70510m0001.htm_dpthd1">
	Communities and Local Government
</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.17WS.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="17WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#07051082000012">
	Thurrock Thames Gateway Development Corporation
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.17WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1762" speakername="Yvette Cooper" speakeroffice="The Minister for Housing and Planning" colnum="17WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#07051082000147">
	<p pid="b.17WS.2/1">The lifespan of the Thurrock Thames Gateway Development Corporation is to be extended by three years to 2014, following a public consultation.</p>
	<p pid="b.17WS.2/2">The Thurrock Thames Gateway Development Corporation was established to lead a step change in Thurrock, harnessing the opportunities presented by growth and regeneration to encourage new businesses and jobs, to develop new homes, schools and leisure activities, and to encourage good quality accessible services and a robust social infrastructure in support of a prosperous community. This lifespan extension will provide the Corporation with the necessary time to overcome barriers and challenges to the achievement of these aspirations, allowing them to build on their significant progress to date. Through continued joint working with Thurrock Council and other partner organisations, the TTGDC will be able to make the most of Thurrock for all members of the community.</p>
	<p pid="b.17WS.2/3">Thurrock is a key part of the Thames Gateway and the lifespan extension will help the Development Corporation to deliver effectively its proposed business plan and regeneration strategy and to promote key projects in the borough.</p>
	<p pid="b.17WS.2/4">To inform the decision, a public consultation was undertaken from <phrase class="date" code="">2 October</phrase> to the end of December 2006, seeking views from those consulted originally when the Thurrock Development Corporation was established. The vast majority of the responses were positive, recognising the challenges faced by the Development Corporation in Thurrock. A summary of responses to the consultation will be placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
	<p pid="b.17WS.2/5">The Thurrock Thames Gateway Development Corporation was established by Parliamentary Order in October 2003. The Order designating the urban development area and establishing the Thurrock Development Corporation (SI 2003 No. 2896) was laid before the House on <phrase class="date" code="2003-07-02">2 July 2003</phrase> and was debated on <phrase class="date" code="">15 October</phrase>, coming into force on <phrase class="date" code="2003-10-29">29 October 2003</phrase>. More information about the TTGDC is available at <a href="http://www.thurrocktgdc.org.uk">www.thurrocktgdc.org.uk</a>.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.17WS.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="17WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#70510m0001.htm_dpthd2">
	Defence
</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.17WS.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="17WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#07051082000013">
	Armed Forces Pay Review Body
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.17WS.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1996" speakername="Des Browne" speakeroffice="The Secretary of State for Defence" colnum="17WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#07051082000148">
	<p pid="b.17WS.5/1">The supplement to the 2007 report of the Armed Forces Pay Review Body (AFPRB) making recommendations on the pay of service medical and dental officers has been published today. Copies of the report are available in the Library of the House.</p>
	<p pid="b.17WS.5/2">The AFPRB has recommended an increase in basic military salary of 2 per cent. for all regular and reserve Defence Medical Services consultants, general medical practitioners and general dental practitioners. The review body also recommends a pay increase of 2 per cent. for junior doctors and cadets. In addition, the review body recommends that there should be an increase of 2 per cent. in the value of trainer pay, but no increase in the value of distinction and clinical excellence awards.</p>
	<p pid="b.17WS.5/3">The Government have agreed to accept the AFPRB's recommendations in full, with implementation effective from <phrase class="date" code="2007-04-01">1 April 2007</phrase>. The additional cost to the defence budget will be met within existing departmental expenditure limits.</p>
	<p pid="b.17WS.5/4">The Government have also accepted the AFPRB's recommendations to introduce a targeted financial retention incentive for emergency, intensive therapy and operation theatre nurses and an increase in the sum offered under the golden hello scheme for the same three nurse specialties.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.18WS.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="18WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#70510m0001.htm_dpthd3">
	Environment, Food and Rural Affairs
</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.18WS.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="18WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#07051082000014">
	Broiler Directive
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.18WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1580" speakername="Ben Bradshaw" speakeroffice="The Minister for Local Environment, Marine and Animal Welfare" colnum="18WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#07051082000149">
	<p pid="b.18WS.2/1">On <phrase class="date" code="">7 May</phrase> European Union (EU) Ministers agreed a Directive which for the first time establishes rules governing the conditions under which meat chickens are kept. The package of new measures includes detailed requirements for holdings where meat chickens are kept, the introduction of a maximum stocking density limit, data collection and scientific monitoring of impacts on chicken welfare, training for the industry and a possible new welfare labelling regime following a report from the European Commission. The Directive will come into force in 2010.</p>
	<p pid="b.18WS.2/2">The welfare of meat chickens is a major concern to people in the United Kingdom and throughout the EU. This is a major sector of livestock production with some 850 million meat chickens produced in the UK every year and 4 billion across the EU. It is therefore only right that we set harmonised welfare rules for these animals.</p>
	<p pid="b.18WS.2/3">It has taken nearly two years of negotiations to reach this point and Germany must be congratulated on concluding the Directive during their Presidency of the Council of Ministers. Some member states would have liked to further water down the proposals in respect of the maximum stocking density limit but the UK successfully fought off this challenge with support from other strongly minded welfare countries.</p>
	<p pid="b.18WS.2/4">The Directive provides a platform on which to build as well as sending a clear message to the rest of the world that the we and the EU care about animal welfare.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.18WS.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="18WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#70510m0001.htm_dpthd4">
	Health
</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.18WS.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="18WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#07051082000015">
	Mixed-sex Accommodation in Hospitals
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.18WS.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1676" speakername="Patricia Hewitt" speakeroffice="The Secretary of State for Health" colnum="18WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#07051082000150">
	<p pid="b.18WS.5/1">Today, the Department is publishing a report from the chief nursing officer on progress with mixed-sex accommodation in hospitals. This report highlights the actions the national health service should take to improve the provision of single-sex accommodation, and includes practical advice for trusts.</p>
	<p pid="b.18WS.5/2">The chief executive of the NHS, David Nicholson, has reiterated our commitment to single-sex accommodation by including it in the operating framework for the NHS for 2007-08. In addition, strategic health authorities (SHAs) have been asked to review performance in this area, and have been working with a number of trusts to agree plans for improvement. SHAs are also publishing statements today on the position in their region.</p>
	<p pid="b.18WS.5/3">Patients expect the NHS to deliver high standards of privacy and dignity that include, but are not restricted to, single-sex accommodation. Single-sex accommodation should be the norm in elective care, and remains the ideal for emergency treatment. However, we recognise that sometimes the need to treat and admit must take priority&mdash;the NHS will not turn a patient away just because a &quot;right-sex&quot; bed is not immediately available.</p>
	<p pid="b.18WS.5/4">Copies of the chief nursing officer's report have been placed in the Library.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.19WS.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="19WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#70510m0001.htm_dpthd5">
	Foreign and Commonwealth Office
</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.19WS.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="19WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#07051082000016">
	General Affairs and External Relations Council
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.19WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1378" speakername="Geoff Hoon" speakeroffice="The Minister for Europe" colnum="19WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0001.htm#07051082000151">
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/1">The General Affairs and External Relations Council (GAERC) will be held on 14 and <phrase class="date" code="">15 May</phrase> in Brussels. My right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs and I will represent the UK. The Minister of State with responsibility for defence equipment and support, Lord Drayson, will also attend the Defence Ministers' discussions on <phrase class="date" code="">14 May</phrase>, while Sir John Grant (UK permanent representative to the EU) will take the chair for the Development Ministers' discussions on <phrase class="date" code="">15 May</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/2">The agenda items are as follows:</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/3">Foreign Ministers</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/4" class="italic">General Affairs</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/5" class="italic">Preparation of the European Council on 21-<phrase class="date" code="">22 June</phrase></p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/6">The Council will discuss the presidency's draft annotated agenda for the 21-<phrase class="date" code="">22 June</phrase> European Council. The main topic for the European Council will be the constitutional treaty. But we expect it also to cover a number of justice and home affairs and economic and social issues, including strengthening police co-operation and climate change. There is also likely to be discussion of topical foreign policy issues.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/7">External Relations</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/8" class="italic">World Trade Organisation</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/9">The Commission is expected to update the Council on its latest contacts on the WTO/Doha round.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/10" class="italic">Sudan</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/11">The Council is expected to discuss recent developments in Sudan. Although the Government of Sudan have accepted the second phase of the UN support for the African Union peacekeeping force, they have yet to accept the third phase, a hybrid African Union/UN force. The conclusions of the April GAERC maintain EU pressure on Khartoum to accept the full African Union/UN peacekeeping force as well as the ceasefire and reinvigorated political process agreed in Addis Ababa last November.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/12">The Government are also urging EU and other international partners to address the gaps in funding for the African Union mission in Sudan.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/13" class="italic">Somalia</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/14">The Government welcome EU action in the region in support of the African Union mission to Somalia and the proposed Reconciliation Congress. The Council is expected to adopt conclusions stressing the importance of implementing UNSCR 1744 to address the political, security and humanitarian challenges in Somalia.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/15" class="italic">Preparation of the EU-Russia Summit</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/16">The Council is expected to discuss EU-Russia relations and preparations for the EU-Russia summit in Samara on 17 and <phrase class="date" code="">18 May</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/17" class="italic">Black Sea Region</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/18">Romania has asked to discuss the Black Sea region. The Government broadly support the Commission's Black Sea strategy, which gives an overview of the policy challenges in the region, the EU's approach to the region and proposes co-operation with regional organisations.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/19" class="italic">Iran</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/20">The High-Representative for the Common Foreign and Security Policy, Javier Solana is expected to brief the Council on his recent meeting with Ali Larijani, Secretary of Iran's Supreme National Security Council on <phrase class="date" code="">25 April</phrase>. The presidency is also expected to brief the Council on the E3+3 (Germany, France, UK, US, Russia and China) political directors meeting on <phrase class="date" code="">2 May</phrase>. This was the latest in a series of exchanges on Iran, and expressed strong agreement on the way ahead, reflecting shared concerns about Iran's non-compliance with International Atomic and Energy Agency Board and Security Council requirements.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/21" class="italic">Iraq</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/22">The presidency is expected to update the Council on the Iraq neighbours conference and the launch of the international compact in Sharm el-Sheikh on 3-<phrase class="date" code="">4 May</phrase>. The Government have urged EU support for Iraq's efforts to build constructive relationships with its neighbours.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/23" class="italic">Arab League Initiative</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/24">Malta has asked to discuss engagement with the Arab League on regional issues. The Government support the presidency's proposal to organise an EU troika meeting with representatives from the Arab League in Berlin in the coming months.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/25" class="italic">Middle East Peace Process</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/26">The Council is expected to discuss the Quartet's meeting with the Arab League on <phrase class="date" code="">4 May</phrase> and ways to build on increasing Arab involvement. The Council is also likely to discuss the political situation in Israel following the Winograd inquiry and ways to build the capacity of Palestinian institutions, including the re-engagement of the EUPOL COPPS (the EU's police mission in the Palestinian territories), which the Government support as a key to success in the wider political process.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/27" class="italic">Western Balkans</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/28">We expect the Council to discuss Kosovo and Serbia.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/29">The February Council conclusions set out the EU's support for former President Ahtisaari's proposals on Kosovo's status and make the restart of stabilisation and association agreement talks with Serbia conditional upon concrete action by a new Serb Government on co-operation with the International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia. The Government fully support this position.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/30">The Council is expected to adopt conclusions welcoming the establishment of the regional co-operation council. If a Government is formed in Belgrade, the Council may also adopt conclusions on Serbia.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/31" class="italic">International Moratorium on the Death Penalty</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/32">Italy has asked to discuss EU action to promote a global moratorium and eventual abolition of the death penalty. The Government fully support work towards this important EU objective.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/33">Joint Session of Foreign Ministers and Defence Ministers</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/34" class="italic">European Security and Defence Policy (ESDP) Mission in Kosovo</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/35">We expect the Council to discuss co-ordination arrangements between the head of the planned ESDP mission and the EU special representative in Kosovo as well as coordination between the EU and NATO. The Government will want to reiterate the importance of continued EU unity on the Kosovo final status process as expressed in the conclusions of the February GAERC.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/36" class="italic">European Security and Defence Policy Mission in Afghanistan</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/37">The Council is expected to discuss a civilian European Security and Defence Policy mission to Afghanistan in policing with links to the wider rule of law. This is likely to be launched in Kabul on <phrase class="date" code="">15 June</phrase>. The Government strongly support the mission as an important contribution to stability and development in Afghanistan.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/38" class="italic">Security Sector Reform in the Democratic Republic of Congo</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/39">The Council is expected to discuss progress on security sector reform in the Democratic Republic of Congo. Much of the Government's support in this sector is channelled through the EU security sector reform advisory mission (EUSEC Congo) and the EU police mission to Kinshasa (EUPOL Kinshasa). With the formation of a new Government, the EU is seeking to modify the mandates of the two missions to ensure that support is in line with the needs of the Congolese. The Government hope that in the future the two missions will combine to look at the security sector as a whole.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/40">Defence Ministers</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/41" class="italic">Operations</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/42" class="italic">Military aspects of EU/UN Co-operation</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/43">The presidency is expected to report on the outcome of a seminar on &quot;Military Aspects of EU/UN Co-operation in Crisis Management, in the Light of EUFOR RD Congo&quot; (the EU military mission which provided support to the UN during the 2006 election period in the Democratic Republic of Congo). The Council is expected to adopt conclusions expressing the EU's commitment to further strengthening co-operation with the UN. The Government support this commitment. Improving the EU's ability to cooperate with key international organisations, including the UN, is key to achieving the effective multilateral system, referred to in the European security strategy, for dealing with crises on a global basis.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/44" class="italic">Lessons Learned from EUFOR RD Congo</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/45">The Council is expected to discuss the lessons learned from EUFOR RD Congo. The Government support ongoing work to address the lessons learnt and believe this process will be a valuable contribution leading to improvements in future mission planning.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/46" class="italic">Western Balkans</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/47">High-Representative for the Common Foreign and Security Policy Javier Solana is expected to brief the Council on the ongoing reconfiguration of EUFOR ALTHEA, the EU military mission in Bosnia. The Government are pleased that the improved security situation has allowed the EU to reduce its level of forces, reflecting the considerable achievements of the international community in Bosnia.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/48" class="italic">AMIS (Sudan/Darfur)</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/49">The Council is expected to discuss the situation in Sudan/Darfur, and to adopt conclusions reaffirming support for the African Union mission in Sudan and underlining the urgency of transition to a full African Union/UN hybrid mission.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/50" class="italic">European Defence Agency</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/51">The head of the agency will present his report to the Council on the agency's activities in the previous and current year. The Council is expected to adopt conclusions noting the report and welcoming progress made. The Government support the work done by the agency over the reporting period.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/52" class="italic">Military Capabilities</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/53" class="italic">Rapid Response</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/54">The Council is expected to discuss ongoing work on a possible revision of the EU military rapid response concept, based on a tri-presidency (Germany, Portugal, Slovenia) &quot;Food for Thought&quot; paper. The Council is expected to adopt conclusions noting that the Battlegroups initiative has achieved full operational capability from <phrase class="date" code="2007-01-01">1 January 2007</phrase>. The Government support efforts to improve the EU's ability to react quickly to an emerging crisis, and are pleased with the progress of the Battlegroups initiative, championed during the UK presidency in 2005.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/55" class="italic">Headline Goal Process</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/56">The presidency is expected to update the Council on progress made on the headline goal process to strengthen European defence capabilities. The Government strongly support this work. Improving military capabilities of EU member states is a key objective of the European security and defence policy, and we welcome progress in the work conducted by the EU military staff and headline goal taskforce.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/57" class="italic">Capability Development Plan</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/58">The European Defence Agency will update the Council on progress on the capability development plan. The Government believe this is important work, which has the potential to provide the necessary link between the EU planning process and long-term capability work being conducted by the European Defence Agency.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/59" class="italic">Progress Report</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/60">The presidency will submit a report to the Council, setting out the progress made on military capability development over the last six months. The Council is expected to note this in the conclusions.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/61">Development Ministers</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/62" class="italic">Aid for Trade and Economic Partnership Agreements (EPAs)</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/63">The Council is expected to discuss a communication on a future Joint Commission/member states' strategy for delivering effective aid for trade commitments. The strategy will include a roadmap for the delivery of the Commission's and member states' commitments to each increase trade related assistance to &euro;1 billion by 2010 (&euro;2 billion in total). The Council will also be invited to discuss progress in negotiations on economic partnership agreements (EPAs). The Council is also expected to adopt conclusions. The Government will be urging donors to empower developing countries to demand increased aid for trade and will work to ensure that the EU market access offer is not diluted.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/64" class="italic">Complementarity and Division of Labour</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/65">The Council is expected to discuss aid effectiveness, and adopt conclusions on a voluntary code of conduct to promote complementarity and improved division of labour arrangements between member states and the Commission. The Government welcome the code of conduct but stress the need for arrangements to be flexible and practice-orientated.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/66" class="italic">Implementation of the Monterrey commitments</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/67">The Council is expected to review the implementation of commitments on financing for development (Monterrey), including monitoring the increase of both Community and member states' official development assistance (ODA). The Government are keen that the Council promotes the use of national timetables to achieve ODA targets.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/68" class="italic">Africa, Caribbean and Pacific (ACP) countries-EU Cooperation</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/69">The presidency is expected to brief the Council on progress on the EU-Africa strategy and adopt conclusions establishing a new EU-Africa energy partnership at the EU-Africa summit in December 2007. The Council is also expected to approve the agenda and Council positions for the EC-ACP Council of Ministers meeting on <phrase class="date" code="">25 May</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/70" class="italic">Madagascar Action Plan</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/71">The Government of Madagascar have recently completed a poverty-reduction strategy&mdash;the Madagascar action plan. There will be a discussion of lessons learned.</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/72" class="italic">Afghanistan</p>
	<p pid="b.19WS.2/73">The German Development Minister is expected to update the Council on her recent visit to Afghanistan. The UN special representative for Afghanistan and the Afghan Finance Minster are expected to be present for the discussion. The Government welcome the focus on development support for Afghanistan.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.24WS.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="24WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0002.htm#70510m0002.htm_dpthd0">
	Home Department
</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.24WS.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="24WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0002.htm#07051082000017">
	Identity Cards
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2007-05-10b.24WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1572" speakername="Joan Ryan" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for the Home Department" colnum="24WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070510/wmstext/70510m0002.htm#07051082000152">
	<p pid="b.24WS.2/1">The second ID cards scheme costs report is being laid before Parliament today. It sets out an estimate of the public expenditure likely to be incurred on the ID cards scheme over the next 10 years, in accordance with section 37 of the Identity Cards Act 2006. It reports on developments over the past six months, since the first costs report was published on <phrase class="date" code="2006-10-09">9 October 2006</phrase>.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

