<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">

<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >

<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >

<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >

<!ENTITY euro "&#8364;" >
]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13.113WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13a.113WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13.113WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13a.113WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13.113WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13a.113WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13.113WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13a.113WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13.113WS.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13a.113WS.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13.113WS.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13a.113WS.5" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13.113WS.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/741" speakername="Paul Boateng" speakeroffice="The Chief Secretary to the Treasury" colnum="113WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm041213/wmstext/41213m01.htm#41213m01.html_spmin1">
	<p>Legislation governing public service pensions requires public service pensions to be increased annually by the same percentage as additional pensions, state earnings-related pension and state second pension. My right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Work and Pensions announced on 6 December 2004, <phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2004-12-06.906"><i>Official Report</i> Column 906</phrase> that benefits such as additional pensions will be increased by 3.1 per cent., in line with the annual increase in the retail prices index up to September 2004. Public service pensions will therefore be increased by 3.1 per cent. from 11 April 2005, except those which have been in payment for less than a year, which will receive a pro-rata increase.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13.113WS.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13a.113WS.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13.113WS.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13a.113WS.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13.113WS.8" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13a.113WS.8" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13.113WS.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/748" speakername="Ben Bradshaw" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs" colnum="113WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm041213/wmstext/41213m01.htm#41213m01.html_spmin2">
	<p>I would like to set out the record of events surrounding the video taken on Burnside Farm in February 2001, following the point of order raised by the hon. Member for South-East Cambridgeshire (Mr. Paice), on 18 November 2004, <phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2004-11-18.1469"><i>Official Report</i> Column 1469</phrase>, about a video made at Burnside Farm.</p>
	<p>The video in question was recorded by Northumberland county council on 24 and 27 February 2001 following the discovery of foot and mouth on Burnside Farm. Defra (then MAFF) officials were aware of the video being made, as they were present on the farm on those two dates.</p>
	<p>The video was used in evidence by Northumberland county council against Robert Waugh, the occupier of the farm, at his trial in May 2002. Defra officials, who gave evidence at the trial, saw the video as part of the court proceedings. Northumberland county council say they did not release the video before the trial because of sub-judice rules.</p>
	<p>The video was made widely available to the media immediately after the trial and extracts from it were shown on the television news. Lord Whitty and Elliot Morley, both Ministers in Defra at the time, recall seeing extracts from the video on the news at that time.</p>
	<p>We have a record of a Defra official seeing the video again on 2 October 2002, at the offices of Northumberland county council, during preparations for the trial of Mr Scurr, the haulier, who had an association with Burnside Farm. The Defra official had already seen the video at Robert Waugh's trial and had requested a copy of it then.</p>
	<p>He made a further request after the October viewing and was sent a copy of the video on 18 February 2003.</p>
	<p>Officials at the Institute for Animal Health, Pirbright, who had been involved in the epidemiological investigation into the FMD outbreak, had obtained a copy of the video from Northumberland county council for training purposes after the Waugh trial. A Defra official saw the video at Pirbright in October 2002 and subsequently asked Northumberland county council for a copy. This was sent to him at the beginning of February 2003.</p>
	<p>As a result of correspondence received by Defra in September this year and the recent media and parliamentary interest in the video, Defra officials, who were unaware that copies had already been sent to two Defra officials separately in February 2003, asked Northumberland county council for copies of the video. These were received in Newcastle animal health divisional office on 1 October.</p>
	<p>This was the basis of my answer on 9 November 2004, <phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2004-11-09.576W"><i>Official Report</i> Column 576W</phrase>. The letter from Lord Whitty of 17 November to the Countess of Mar, referred to in the hon. Member for South-East Cambridgeshire's point of order, was based on the information that was discovered subsequently that two Defra officials had in fact received copies of the video in February 2003. As soon as this information was brought to my attention, my reply of 9 November was corrected in the pursuant answer tabled on 18 November 2004, <phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2004-11-18.2000W"><i>Official Report</i> Column 2000W</phrase>.</p>
	<p>So, the suggestion of a cover up of the video is not supported by the facts. The video was made by and was the property of Northumberland county council. The council made the video for use in evidence against the occupier of the farm, Mr Waugh, at his trial. The video was first put in the public domain by Northumberland county council in May 2002 and it was shown widely in the television news media at that time.</p>
	<p>The suggestion has been made that the video shows a dog pulling at a sheep carcase, which, it is claimed, casts doubt on the epidemiological evidence about the origin of the outbreak presented to the lessons to be learned inquiry, chaired by Dr Anderson. This is also not borne out by the facts. I am advised that it is not possible to identify with certainty the material in question. That is why the eye-witness evidence, collected meticulously by Defra, IAH and local authority officials who were actually present on the farm at the time should be considered paramount. This was the evidence presented to the Anderson inquiry, augmented by interviews conducted by Dr Anderson himself. It is worth recalling that Mr Waugh was prosecuted for leaving part of a dead pig lying on his premises. No sheep carcases were found anywhere on the farm. Furthermore, no clear evidence of infection has been found anywhere in the UK earlier than that at Burnside Farm.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13.115WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13a.115WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13.115WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13a.115WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13.115WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13a.115WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13.115WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13a.115WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13.115WS.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13a.115WS.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13.115WS.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-12-13a.115WS.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

