<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;" >
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.45WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.45WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.45WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.45WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.45WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.45WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.45WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.45WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.45WS.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.45WS.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.45WS.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.45WS.5" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.45WS.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1687" speakername="Maria Eagle" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Education and Skills" colnum="45WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm050608/wmstext/50608m01.htm#50608m01.html_spmin1">
	<p pid=".45WS.5/1">Following our receipt of the report of the Joint Committee on the draft Children (Contact) and Adoption Bill, I am pleased to say that the Government's response to that report is today being presented to Parliament.</p>
	<p pid=".45WS.5/2">The Bill, which we hope will be introduced in the current parliamentary session, would take forward the commitment we made in the Green Paper, &quot;Parental Separation: Children's Needs and Parents' Responsibilities&quot; to provide the courts with more flexible powers to facilitate contact and enforce contact orders.</p>
	<p pid=".45WS.5/3">At present, contact orders can be enforced only through contempt of court proceedings leading to fine or imprisonment. Courts have quite rightly been reluctant to use these measures because of the potential negative impact on the children involved. That is why they need additional, more flexible and realistic powers, of the sort that this Bill will provide. It will allow the courts to:</p>
	<p pid=".45WS.5/4" class="indent">(a) direct parties in a contact case to undertake a &quot;contact activity&quot; such as attending information sessions, meetings with a counsellor, parenting programmes/classes, or other activities designed to deal with contact disputes; and</p>
	<p pid=".45WS.5/5" class="indent">(b) attach conditions to contact orders which may require a party to undertake a contact activity.</p>
	<p pid=".45WS.5/6">Where a contact order has been breached, courts will be able to:</p>
	<p pid=".45WS.5/7" class="indent">(a) impose community-based &quot;enforcement orders&quot;; or</p>
	<p pid=".45WS.5/8" class="indent">(b) award financial compensation from one party to another (for example, where the cost of a holiday has been lost).</p>
	<p pid=".45WS.5/9">In addition, the Bill provides a statutory framework for the imposition of restrictions on inter-country adoptions from particular countries where there are concerns about adoption processes there.</p>
	<p pid=".45WS.5/10">We are very grateful to the Committee for the detailed consideration it gave to this Bill, and were pleased that much of the report has chimed so closely with our own thinking and approach in developing the Bill. It was particularly helpful that the Committee considered some issues where we though that greater examination would be important, and we were pleased that the Committee agreed with us that the use of electronic tagging would be disproportionate. We will therefore remove that provision, which appeared in square brackets in the draft Bill, from the Bill as introduced.</p>
	<p pid=".45WS.5/11">Most importantly, it is gratifying that the Committee has not recommended any change in the fundamentals of the Bill on either contact or inter-country adoption, and agrees with our firm belief that the welfare of children must remain the paramount consideration of the courts when determining any question in relation to their upbringing.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.46WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.46WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.46WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.46WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.46WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.46WS.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.46WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1533" speakername="Margaret Beckett" speakeroffice="The Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs" colnum="46WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm050608/wmstext/50608m01.htm#50608m01.html_spmin2">
	<p pid=".46WS.2/1">The Natural Environment and Rural Communities Bill before this House will establish a new non-departmental public body, Natural England, to conserve and enhance the resource of nature while realising the social and economic benefits for the people of England. The establishment of a single independent statutory organisation championing integrated resource management, nature conservation, biodiversity, landscape access and recreation will be a significant step forward building on the world class strengths and scientific and other expertise of the existing organisations. Establishment of Natural England will contribute at least &pound;6.5 million cumulative efficiencies by 2007&ndash;08, with further efficiencies in 2008&ndash;09 and 2009&ndash;10.</p>
	<p pid=".46WS.2/2">In order to establish, as early as possible, the benefits from creating this body&mdash;with a new and independent culture, delivering services in a more efficient, flexible and co-ordinated way&mdash;my Department proposes to undertake essential preparatory work relating to the appointment of the chair, chief executive officer and board members of Natural England. In accordance with the rules on Government accounting, the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs will seek parliamentary approval for additional resources of &pound;360,000 for this new service in a supplementary estimate following, or just before, Royal Assent. Pending that approval, urgent expenditure of &pound;360,000 will be met by a repayable cash advance from the Contingencies Fund.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.46WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.46WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.46WS.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.46WS.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.46WS.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="46WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm050608/wmstext/50608m01.htm#50608m01.html_sbhd3">
	Consular Feed Order 2005&ndash;06&ndash;08
</minor-heading>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.46WS.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.46WS.5" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.46WS.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2008" speakername="Douglas Alexander" speakeroffice="The Minister for Europe" colnum="46WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm050608/wmstext/50608m01.htm#50608m01.html_spmin3">
	<p pid=".46WS.5/1">The Foreign and Commonwealth Office has recently undertaken a review of the fees charged for visa and consular services overseas. On <phrase class="date" code="2005-06-07">7 June 2005</phrase> Her Majesty in Council approved the Consular Fees Order 2005. This revokes and replaces the Consular Fees Order (No 2) 1999. The Government are today announcing new fees to be charged under this Order with effect from <phrase class="date" code="2005-07-01">1 July 2005</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid=".46WS.5/2">The Order consolidates and re-categorises some of the fees that have previously been charged. It increases fees for notarial services, estate administration, attendances, matters undertaken relating to legal proceedings and repatriation and financial assistance. It raises fees for consular assistance in births, deaths, marriages and shipping, seamen and kindred matters. The Order also increases fees for certain passports and visas and for certain searches undertaken by consular officials.</p>
	<p pid=".46WS.5/3">Where consular fees have been raised then, in most cases, these fees have been increased by between 10 per cent. and 20 per cent. Overseas passport fees are raised from &pound;56.50 to &pound;69 (standard passport for those 16 years or over), from &pound;36.50 to &pound;45 (standard passports for those under 16) and from &pound;67.70 to &pound;82 (48 page passport). The fee for amending an existing passport abroad will be increased from &pound;46.90 to &pound;57. The Order also raises the fee for issuing emergency passports from &pound;35.50 to &pound;43.50 and temporary passport fees are increased from &pound;45.60 to &pound;55.</p>
	<p pid=".46WS.5/4">Fees for multiple entry visas valid for between one and 10 years that ranged from between &pound;60 and &pound;150 have been consolidated in the Order to one fee of &pound;85. The Order increases the fees for transit visas from &pound;27 to &pound;30 and for six-month multiple entry visas from &pound;36 to &pound;50. The Order also raises previously anomalous fees for returning residents, working holiday-makers, students, au pairs and those in employment or self-employed for under six months from &pound;36 to &pound;85. The fee for receiving an application for entry clearance (other than to the United Kingdom or the Crown Dependencies) is raised from &pound;22 to &pound;30.</p>
	<p pid=".46WS.5/5">The Order reduces the fees for a certificate of entitlement to right of abode from &pound;110 to &pound;85. Following the introduction of photo vignette visas the fee for a declaration of identity became obsolete and has been removed. This Order also deletes provision for gratis visas to be issued to citizens of the former Soviet Union following the abrogation of a bilateral agreement with former Soviet Union states.</p>
	<p pid=".46WS.5/6">In setting the new visa fees we have taken account of the views of those in the education sector, for whom the increase in the visa fee for students will be unwelcome. We recognise that international students bring significant economic and social benefits to the UK. UKvisas is committed to working closely with the education sector in the context of IND's new Joint Education Task Force to ensure that we have a genuine and informed dialogue with the education sector about immigration matters and develop better capacity to improve the evidence base on international students.</p>
	<p pid=".46WS.5/7">But it is right that those who benefit from consular and visa services should meet the cost of them, rather than the UK taxpayer. The new fees represent the full economic cost of what we do, and will ensure that British missions overseas continue to provide a high standard of service to visa and consular customers. They will also enable further investment in improvements to service delivery and the effectiveness of immigration control, as set out in the five-year strategy for immigration and asylum, and in consular services, as set out in the 2004 Consular Strategy.</p>
	<p pid=".46WS.5/8">The new fees are included in the attached table.</p>
	<table>
		<caption>Table of fees for Consular and Visa services</caption>
		<thead>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/12"> <th></th> <th>Fee (&pound;)</th> </tr>
		</thead>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/15"> <td>1. Preparing any certificate, declaration or document not otherwise provided for&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/16"> <td>(a) in standard form, per copy</td> <td>23.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/17"> <td>(b) not in standard form, per 100 words&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/18"> <td>(i) in English</td> <td>29.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/19"> <td>(ii) in any other language</td> <td>47.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/20"> <td>2. Preparing or signing, or both, a declaration of existence Except in connection with pay or pensions payable by a department of Her Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom or of any other Government within the Commonwealth.</td> <td>11.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/21"> <td>3.&mdash;2. Attesting or legalising a signature or seal except where&mdash;</td> <td>19.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/22"> <td>(a) the signature or seal is on a certificate or survey of foreign passenger ships running to or from the United Kingdom, or</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/23"> <td>(b) the signature or seal is on a document required for the deposit or withdrawal of money in or from any British Post Office or other Government Savings Bank, or</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/24"> <td>(c) the signature or seal is in connection with stocks or bonds on the registers of the Post Office, with Savings Bank annuities or with annuities granted direct by the National Debt Commissioners</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/25"> <td>(3) Administering an oath or receiving a declaration or affirmation except where&mdash;</td> <td>35.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/26"> <td>(a) the oath, declaration or affirmation is made under the Merchant Shipping Act 1995 or in connection with the loss of a passport, or</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/27"> <td>(b) fee 17, 22, 23, 25, 34 or 35 is to be taken</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/28"> <td>4. Supplying witnesses, for each witness</td> <td>14.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/29"> <td>5. Initialling alterations in any document not prepared by the consular officer or marking exhibits, for each initialling or marking</td> <td>7.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/30"> <td>6. Making or verifying (including certifying where necessary) a copy of a document&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/31"> <td>(a) in typescript or made by photographic process outside the consular premises, for each page</td> <td>23.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/32"> <td>(b) by photographic process, if the copy is made in the consular premises, for each page (with a minimum charge of &pound;17.50)</td> <td>3.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/33"> <td>7. Uniting documents and sealing the fastening (except where fee 35 is applicable), or affixing a photograph to a document not prepared by the consular officer and if necessary certifying it (except where fee 17 is applicable)</td> <td>14.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/34"> <td>8. Obtaining a legalisation or other certification from another authority upon any document in addition to costs, if any</td> <td>29.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/35"> <td>9. Supplying certified copies of documents forming part of the records of a court which is, or was formerly, established under the Foreign Jurisdiction Acts 1890 and 1913&mdash;for every page</td> <td>41.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/36"> <td>10. Making or verifying (including certifying where necessary) a translation in writing of a document or part of a document, for each 100 words or characters (or part thereof) in the foreign language&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/37"> <td>(a) from or into Amharic, Chinese, Japanese or Korean (three Japanese Kana being counted as one character when used independently)</td> <td>47.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/38"> <td>(b) from or into any other language except where fee 25 or 37 is to be taken</td> <td>29.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/39"> <td>11. Translating and interpreting viva voce (except where necessary for the performance of official duties)&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/40"> <td>for every 15 minutes</td> <td>21.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/41"> <td>12. Issuing a passport of not more than 32 pages which includes replacing an expired passport, issuing a new passport of full validity when an original passport of restricted validity is unavailable, and, for applications made in the United Kingdom only, issuing a new passport with amended personal details&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/42"> <td>(a) for applications made by post in the United Kingdom</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/43"> <td>(i) where the applicant is aged 16 years or over</td> <td>42.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/44"> <td>(ii) where the applicant is under 16 years old (for a passport valid for 5 years)</td> <td>25.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/45"> <td>(b) for applications made in person in the United Kingdom</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/46"> <td>(i) where the applicant is aged 16 years or over using the fast-track service</td> <td>70.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/47"> <td>(ii) where the applicant is under 16 years old (for a passport valid for 5 years) using the fast-track service</td> <td>60.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/48"> <td>(iii) where the applicant is aged 16 years or over using the fast-track collect service</td> <td>83.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/49"> <td>(iv) where the applicant is under 16 years old (for a passport valid for 5 years) using the fast-track collect service</td> <td>70.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/50"> <td>(v) where the applicant is aged 16 years or over using the premium service</td> <td>89.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/51"> <td>(vi) where the applicant is under 16 years old (for a passport valid for 5 years) using the premium service</td> <td>71.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/52"> <td>(c) for applications made abroad</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/53"> <td>(i) where the applicant is aged 16 years or over</td> <td>69.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/54"> <td>(ii) where the applicant is under 16 years old (for a passport valid for 5 years)</td> <td>45.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/55"> <td>13. Issuing a passport of 48 pages which includes replacing an expired passport, and issuing a new passport of full validity when an original passport of restricted validity is unavailable, and, for applications made in the United Kingdom only, issuing a new passport with amended personal details&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/56"> <td>(a) for applications made by post in the United Kingdom</td> <td>54.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/57"> <td>(b) for applications made in person in the United Kingdom</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/58"> <td>(i) using the fast-track service</td> <td>71.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/59"> <td>(ii) using the fast-track collect service</td> <td>84.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/60"> <td>(iii) using the premium service</td> <td>95.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/61"> <td>(c) for applications made abroad</td> <td>82.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/62"> <td>14. Issuing a collective passport&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/63"> <td>(a) for applications made by post in the United Kingdom</td> <td>39.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/64"> <td>(b) for applications made in person in the United Kingdom</td> <td>54.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/65"> <td>15. Amending or extending an existing passport where the application is made abroad</td> <td>57.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/66"> <td>16.&mdash;3. Receiving an application for entry clearance (other than for the United Kingdom or for the Crown Dependencies)</td> <td>30.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/67"> <td>(2) Preparing or forwarding, or both, any letter, certificate, declaration or other document which may be required by an authority in any country or territory in connection with an application for or the issue or renewal of an entry clearance (for a country or territory for which the consular officer does not himself have authority to issue entry clearance), a residence permit or identity card or forwarding any other certificate or document (except a Home Office travel document and applications for registration and naturalisation)</td> <td>41.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/68"> <td>(3) Preparing or forwarding, or both, an application for registration or naturalisation to the Home Office</td> <td>41.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/69"> <td>17.&mdash;4. Issuing and, where required, preparing an Emergency Passport or other document not otherwise provided for in lieu of a passport</td> <td>43.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/70"> <td>(2) Issuing a Temporary Passport valid for not more than one year</td> <td>55.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/71"> <td>18.&mdash;5. Receiving, outside the United Kingdom, an application for&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/72"> <td>(a) a visa for passing through the United Kingdom without entering it</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/73"> <td>(b) entry clearance for passing through the United Kingdom</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/74"> <td>(c) entry clearance</td> <td>30.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/75"> <td>(i) as a visitor, in each case for single, double and multiple entries valid for up to six months from the date of issue</td> <td>50.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/76"> <td>(ii) for settlement</td> <td>260.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/77"> <td>(iii) for marriage</td> <td>260.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/78"> <td>(iv) for any purpose other than those listed in paragraphs (a) and (b) and sub- paragraphs (i), (ii) and (iii) listed above</td> <td>85.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/79"> <td>(d) a certificate of entitlement to the right of abode</td> <td>85.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/80"> <td>(3) The fees prescribed in paragraph (1) apply in relation to entry clearance for the Crown Dependencies as they apply in relation to entry clearances for the United Kingdom.</td> <td>20.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/81"> <td>(4) Receiving in the United Kingdom an application made in the United Kingdom for a certificate of entitlement to the right of abode</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/82"> <td>19. Renewing a Travel Certificate, a certificate of identity or other travel document on behalf of a Commonwealth country or of a dependency of a Commonwealth country except where fee 21 is to be taken</td> <td>41.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/83"> <td>20. Renewing a Travel Certificate, a certificate of identity or other travel document on behalf of a dependency of the United Kingdom except where fee 21 is to be taken</td> <td>41.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/84"> <td>21. Revalidating or renewing a Seaman's Certificate of Nationality and Identity or a Seaman's Identity Book in addition to fee 16 where applicable</td> <td>41.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/85"> <td>22. Receiving notice of an intended marriage</td> <td>41.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/86"> <td>23. Solemnising or attending a marriage under the Foreign Marriage Acts 1892 and 1947, administering oaths to the parties and registering the marriage</td> <td>88.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/87"> <td>24. Issuing in English or in the local language a certificate that no impediment to an intended marriage has been shown to exist</td> <td>41.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/88"> <td>25. Transmitting a record of a marriage under the local law to the appropriate Registrar General in accordance with Article     7(1) of the Foreign Marriage Order 1970, including the provision of any necessary certification</td> <td>23.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/89"> <td>26. Issuing a &quot;certificate de coutume&quot; for an intended marriage in accordance with the local law</td> <td>41.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/90"> <td>27. Registering a birth or death in addition to fee 29 where applicable</td> <td>64.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/91"> <td>28. Making an addition to or correction in the consular register of births, deaths or marriages at the request of the parties concerned</td> <td>23.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/92"> <td>29. Furnishing a certified copy of an entry in the consular register of births, deaths or marriages in addition to fee 30 or fee 27 where applicable</td> <td>41.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/93"> <td>30. Making a search in&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/94"> <td>(a) the consular registers of births, deaths or marriages where the number or date of entry is not provided</td> <td>41.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/95"> <td>(b) the records of the United Kingdom Passport Agency where the request originates in the United Kingdom</td> <td>10.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/96"> <td>(c) any other records or archives of Her Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom in addition to fee 29 where applicable</td> <td>72.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/97"> <td>31. Having a search made for, or obtaining copies of, or both, entries in the local registers or records not kept by a consular officer&mdash;for an entry in a local register of births, deaths or marriages or for any other document in addition to costs exceeding &pound;5.00</td> <td>84.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/98"> <td>32. Administering in full or in part, safeguarding, or arranging the transmission of all or part of the personal effects and other estate of a deceased person or proceeds thereof, excepting the wages and personal effects of a seaman and except where the gross current market value is less than &pound;1,000, on the amount of the gross current market value</td> <td>2% roundedto the nearest&pound;10.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/99"> <td>but with a fee, where a local lawyer is employed and the matters or things to be done by the consular officer are nominal, of</td> <td>53.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/100"> <td>33. Attending (except in connection with commercial enquiries) for each hour or lesser period, including if appropriate the time taken in proceeding from a reasonable point of departure and in returning to a reasonable point&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/101"> <td>(a) at the consular premises or elsewhere during customary business hours except that where the attendance is for the purpose of supervising an examination and two or more persons are sitting examinations at the same time the fee may be apportioned between them</td> <td>84.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/102"> <td>(b) at the consular premises or elsewhere outside customary business hours</td> <td>84.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/103"> <td>with a maximum in any one period of 24 hours for each consular officer of</td> <td>610.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/104"> <td>34. Presiding at the taking of evidence under a commission or order from a Court, including any matter or thing done by the consular officer as examiner&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/105"> <td>(a) for the first two hours or less on the first day</td> <td>168.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/106"> <td>(b) for each additional hour or less</td> <td>84.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/107"> <td>35. Providing evidence of service or attempted service in addition to fee 33 or 36</td> <td>84.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/108"> <td>36. Providing the services of a consular officer or consular employee&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/109"> <td>(a) to assist the consular officer in the taking of evidence under a commission or order from a Court, for each such person&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/110"> <td>for each hour or less</td> <td>84.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/111"> <td>(b) to effect or endeavour to effect service of a document, for each hour or shorter period elsewhere than at the consular premises&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/112"> <td>during customary business hours</td> <td>84.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/113"> <td>outside customary business hours</td> <td>105.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/114"> <td>37. Forwarding a request to a local authority for the taking of evidence or the service of a document, where necessary, certifying the accuracy of a translation accompanying the document</td> <td>84.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/115"> <td>38. Arranging the repatriation of a person or a group of persons of the same family and travelling together</td> <td>84.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/116"> <td>39. Arranging for currency to be made available against the payment of a sterling cheque or against the deposit elsewhere of funds with or to the order of Her Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom in addition to fee 33 where applicable</td> <td>42.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/117"> <td>40. Granting or considering whether to grant a provisional certificate of registry, whether the owner is a private individual or body corporate</td> <td>246.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/118"> <td>41. Receiving a return of the birth or death of any person on board a ship and endorsing the agreement with the crew accordingly</td> <td>35.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/119"> <td>42. Examining or arranging for the examination of provisions or water, payable by the party who proves to be in default in addition to the cost, if any, of survey</td> <td>35.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/120"> <td>43. Noting a marine protest and furnishing one certified copy if required</td> <td>29.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/121"> <td>for every further copy</td> <td>29.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/122"> <td>44. Extending a marine protest, filing the original and furnishing one certified copy if required&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/123"> <td>(a) for any number of words up to 200, excluding the declaratory clause</td> <td>70.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/124"> <td>(b) for every subsequent 100 words or less</td> <td>29.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/125"> <td>in addition to fees 1 and 3 where applicable</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/126"> <td>45. Making a request, or issuing or arranging for the issue of a document, in connection with a survey of a ship&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/127"> <td>(a) for the purposes of the International Convention for the Safety of Life at Sea 1974 (SOLAS) or of the International Convention for the Prevention of Pollution from Ships 1973 as modified by its Protocol of 1978 (MARPOL)</td> <td>47.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/128"> <td>(b) for any other purpose</td> <td>84.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/129"> <td>in addition to fee 6 where applicable</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/130"> <td>46. Issuing a bill of health</td> <td>29.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/131"> <td>47. Preparing or signing, or both, any document, whether required by the Merchant Shipping Acts or by the local authorities, relating to the master or the members of the crew of a ship, to their numbers, names or other details, or to their engagement, discharge, desertion or death except where&mdash;</td> <td>47.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/132"> <td>(a) fee 41 is taken in addition to fee 33, or</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/133"> <td>(b) a death inquiry is held under section 271 of the Merchant Shipping Act 1995</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/134"> <td>48. Signing and, if required, sealing any documents at the request of the master of the ship except where&mdash;</td> <td>47.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/135"> <td>(a) this is required under the Merchant Shipping Act 1995, or</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/136"> <td>(b) fee 47 is taken</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/137"> <td>49. Inspecting&mdash;</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/138"> <td>(a) a ship's papers when required to enable a consular officer to do any matter or thing in respect of a ship</td> <td>35.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/139"> <td>except where fee 47 is taken in addition to fee 33</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/140"> <td>(b) the marking of a ship, irrespective of the number of visits</td> <td>35.00</td> </tr>
			<tr pid=".46WS.5/141"> <td>in addition to fee 33</td> <td></td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.53WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.53WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.53WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.53WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.53WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.53WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.54WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.54WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.54WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.54WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08.54WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-06-08a.54WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

