<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.5WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.5WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.5WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.5WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.5WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.5WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.5WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.5WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.5WS.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.5WS.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.5WS.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.5WS.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.6WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.6WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.6WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.6WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.7WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.7WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.7WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.7WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.7WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.7WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.7WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.7WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.7WS.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.7WS.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.7WS.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.7WS.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.7WS.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.7WS.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.7WS.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.7WS.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.7WS.8" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.7WS.8" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.8WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.8WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.8WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.8WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.8WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.8WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.9WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.9WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.9WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.9WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.9WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.9WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.10WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.10WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.10WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.10WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.10WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.10WS.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.10WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1806" speakername="Tony Blair" speakeroffice="The Prime Minister" colnum="10WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm051129/wmstext/51129m02.htm#51129m02.html_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.10WS.2/1">The biennial Commonwealth Heads of Government meeting (CHOGM) took place in Valletta, Malta from 25 to <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-27">27 November</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.10WS.2/2">Her Majesty The Queen attended the meeting in herrole as Head of the Commonwealth. She also paid a state visit to Malta where she was most warmly welcomed by the Maltese people. The outgoing Commonwealth Chairman-in-Office, President Obasanjo of Nigeria, paid tribute on behalf of all Commonwealth members to the Queen's commitment and dedication to the Commonwealth.</p>
	<p pid="a.10WS.2/3">This year, for the first time, Commonwealth Foreign Ministers met in advance of CHOGM to receive reports from Commonwealth bodies and to prepare the communiqu&eacute;. The UK was represented by my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for International Development and my noble Friend the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs.</p>
	<p pid="a.10WS.2/4">Commonwealth Heads of Government last met in Abuja, Nigeria in December 2003. At Valletta, Heads reviewed developments since then.</p>
	<p pid="a.10WS.2/5">As in 2003, Heads issued a separate statement on multilateral trade. This highlighted the contribution that international trade makes to global prosperity, poverty elimination and sustainable development. They reaffirmed their commitments to the objectives of the Doha development agenda of the World Trade Organisation and to its conclusion by the end of 2006. While they welcomed the progress achieved since 2003 they stressed their deep concern about the pace of negotiations. The Commonwealth pledged its global influence to correct this and Heads committed to inject urgency into their negotiators at the WTO, encouraging them to be flexible and place priority on a genuinely development-oriented outcome for the round.</p>
	<p pid="a.10WS.2/6">The importance of agriculture to developing economies was highlighted, with a call for the end of export subsidies by 2010 and time-bound commitments for substantial reductions in trade distorting domestic support and significant improvements in market access.</p>
	<p pid="a.10WS.2/7">The importance of differential treatment for developing countries was highlighted in this context. Heads of Government also called for phased adjustment and other transitional measures to help vulnerable states, including small states and those traditionally dependent on preferential market access arrangements, to meet the trade and development challenges facing them. This was noted with particular reference to the impact on some Commonwealth members as a result of the liberalisation of the EU sugar regime. The G8 initiative on &quot;Aid for Trade&quot; was applauded as a means for meaningful market access.</p>
	<p pid="a.10WS.2/8">Heads discussed other development issues, including the millennium Development Goals, where there is mixed progress in the Commonwealth. Heads welcomed the G8 proposals for debt cancellation and commitments by many developed countries to achieve the 0.7 per cent. target. Heads confirmed their commitment to root out corruption. There was particular concern for vulnerable small states, which need help to diversify their economies. Some small states have been very badly affected by natural disasters. Heads endorsed a proposal from Bangladesh for the Commonwealth to develop proposals to address how it can help with disaster risk-reduction and responses.</p>
	<p pid="a.10WS.2/9">Heads also discussed terrorism, incitement and tolerance and reaffirmed their condemnation of all acts of terrorism. They emphasised that targeting and deliberate killing of civilians through acts of terrorism cannot be justified or legitimised by any cause or grievance. They commended the various initiatives to promote dialogue, tolerance and understanding among civilisations.</p>
	<p pid="a.10WS.2/10">Heads discussed how to use information and communications technologies to support development, reduce poverty and contribute to the attainment of the millennium Development Goals.</p>
	<p pid="a.10WS.2/11">During the summit, I met with the leaders of sugar producing Caribbean states and a number of other leaders, including the Prime Ministers of Malta, Mauritius, Pakistan and Singapore.</p>
	<p pid="a.10WS.2/12">The Commonwealth expressed its concern about recent developments in Uganda, including the detention of Kizza Besigye. As Secretary General McKinnon said on <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-27">Sunday 27 November</phrase>, Uganda knows what must happen between now and 2007 when it expects to host the next CHOGM. I also raised our concerns directly with President Museveni.</p>
	<p pid="a.10WS.2/13">It was agreed that the United Kingdom should return to the Commonwealth Ministerial Action Group (CMAG), the body charged with monitoring Commonwealth nations' compliance with the Harare principles.</p>
	<p pid="a.10WS.2/14">I participated in the Commonwealth sports breakfast and thanked Commonwealth leaders for supporting London's Olympic bid. Heads of Government looked forward to the Melbourne Commonwealth games in 2006 and I presented Glasgow's interest in hosting the games in 2014.</p>
	<p pid="a.10WS.2/15">Copies of the concluding communiqu&eacute;, the separate statements on trade and small states and the declaration on networking for development have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.12WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.12WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.12WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.12WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.12WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.12WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.12WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.12WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.12WS.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.12WS.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.12WS.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1648" speakername="Alan Johnson" speakeroffice="The Secretary of State for Trade and Industry" colnum="12WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm051129/wmstext/51129m03.htm#51129m03.html_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.12WS.4/1">The Prime Minister and I are pleased to inform the House that we have asked the Energy Minister, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1523" name="Malcolm Wicks">the hon. Member for Croydon, North (Malcolm Wicks)</phrase> to lead a review of UK energy policy and to bring forward policy proposals next year.</p>
	<p pid="a.12WS.4/2">The review will assess progress against the four goals set by the 2003 energy White Paper:</p>
	<p pid="a.12WS.4/3" class="indent">to put ourselves on a path to cut the UK's carbon dioxide emissions&mdash;the main contributor to global warming&mdash;by some 60 per cent. by about 2050 with real progress by 2020;</p>
	<p pid="a.12WS.4/4" class="indent">to maintain the reliability of energy supplies;</p>
	<p pid="a.12WS.4/5" class="indent">to promote competitive markets in the UK and beyond, helping to raise the rate of sustainable economic growth and to improve our productivity; and</p>
	<p pid="a.12WS.4/6" class="indent">to ensure that every home is adequately and affordably heated.</p>
	<p pid="a.12WS.4/7">The review has a broad scope and will consider aspects of both energy supply and demand focusing on medium and long-term policy measures beyond 2010. The review will consider all options including the role of current generating technologies, such as renewables, coal, gas and nuclear power, and new and emerging technologies, for example carbon, capture and storage. The review will also consider transport and the role of energy efficiency. The terms of reference for the review are annexed to this written statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.12WS.4/8">The review will be taken forward by a cross-departmental team based in the DTI, with officials drawn from key relevant departments and the Prime Minister's strategy unit. The review team will develop energy policy proposals during 2006.</p>
	<p pid="a.12WS.4/9">This review is part of our ongoing commitment to reviewing progress against the goals and, if necessary, taking steps to ensure we stay on track. It will be taken forward in the context of the Government's commitment to sound public finances and will take account of all short-term, medium-term and long-term costs and liabilities both to the taxpayer and energy user. The review is taking place against a background of strengthening evidence on the nature and extent of climate change and increasing concerns about the future security of UK energy supplies.</p>
	<p pid="a.12WS.4/10">Given the substantial challenge posed by climate change, Sir Nicholas Stern has already been asked to produce a report to the Prime Minister and Chancellor by autumn 2006 on the economics of climate change. The work undertaken as part of the stern review will be closely co-ordinated with, and complementary to the energy review.</p>
	<p pid="a.12WS.4/11" class="italic">ANNEX&mdash;Energy Review Terms of Reference</p>
	<p pid="a.12WS.4/12">The Government will review the UK's progress against the medium and long-term Energy White Paper goals and the options for further steps to achieve them. The aim will be to bring forward proposals on energy policy next year.</p>
	<p pid="a.12WS.4/13">The review will be informed by analysis and options drawn up by a review team led by the Energy Minister. This will be a team of officials drawn from key relevant departments and the Prime Minister's Strategy Unit. In drawing up the analysis and options, the Energy Minister will undertake extensive public and stakeholder consultation. The review will be taken forward in the context of the Government's commitment to sound public finances and will take account of all short-term, medium-term and long-term costs and liabilities both to the taxpayer and energy user. The review team will report to the Prime Minister and the Secretary of State for Trade and Industry in early summer.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.13WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.13WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.13WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.13WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.14WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.14WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.14WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.14WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.15WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.15WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.15WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.15WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.15WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.15WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.16WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.16WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.16WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.16WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.16WS.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.16WS.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.16WS.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.16WS.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.17WS.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.17WS.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29a.17WS.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-11-29b.17WS.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

