<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="" latest="yes">

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-06-08.3WS.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="3WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo040608/wmstext/40608m01.htm#40608m01.html_dpthd0">
	NORTHERN IRELAND
</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-06-08.3WS.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="3WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo040608/wmstext/40608m01.htm#40608m01.html_sbhd0">
	Probation Board
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-06-08.3WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1131" speakername="Paul Murphy" speakeroffice="The Secretary of State for Northern Ireland" colnum="3WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo040608/wmstext/40608m01.htm#40608m01.html_spmin0">
	<p pid=".3WS.2/1">I have today published the Probation Board for Northern Ireland business plan for 2004&ndash;05. The plan sets out the board's key objectives and performance targets for the year. Copies of the plan have today been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-06-08.3WS.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="3WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo040608/wmstext/40608m01.htm#40608m01.html_sbhd1">
	Health and Social Services Estates Agency
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-06-08.3WS.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1231" speakername="Angela Smith" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Northern Ireland" colnum="3WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo040608/wmstext/40608m01.htm#40608m01.html_spmin1">
	<p pid=".3WS.4/1">Stage two of the quinquennial review of the Northern Ireland Health and Social Services Estates Agency has been completed. The report has been made available in the House of Commons, the House of Lords and the Northern Ireland Assembly's Libraries and on the Department of Health, Social Services and Public Safety's website.</p>
	<p pid=".3WS.4/2">The conclusion of the stage one report, published on <phrase class="date" code="2003-06-04">4 June 2003</phrase>, was that the Northern Ireland Health and Social Services Estates Agency should remain in being as an agency.</p>
	<p pid=".3WS.4/3">Stage two examined how the agency operated and looked at the potential for improving its future performance. The consultants invited views from a range of respondents, including Northern Ireland Public Service Alliance (NIPSA), HPSS boards trusts, and agencies and departmental staff. Their report makes recommendations to improve the agency's effectiveness and efficiency.</p>
	<p pid=".3WS.4/4">The report's overall conclusion is that much has already been done to address areas for improvement identified in the stage one report. The report recommends, however, more:</p>
	<p pid=".3WS.4/5" class="indent">monitoring of compliance with policy standards;</p>
	<p pid=".3WS.4/6" class="indent">consultation and engagement in formulating and monitoring standards;</p>
	<p pid=".3WS.4/7" class="indent">practically oriented advice to the Department which can influence capital plans;</p>
	<p pid=".3WS.4/8" class="indent">early engagement with the Department on estate-related policy issues with wider implications for capital planning;</p>
	<p pid=".3WS.4/9" class="indent">early involvement of the agency in the development and approval of capital plans and business cases;</p>
	<p pid=".3WS.4/10" class="indent">involvement in the development of policy which may have capital implications;</p>
	<p pid=".3WS.4/11" class="indent">communication and integration across all parts of the agency.</p>
	<p pid=".3WS.4/12">Implementation of the report's recommendations will improve the effectiveness of the agency and will enhance its ability to contribute to improvements in the quality of care to patients.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-06-08.4WS.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="4WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo040608/wmstext/40608m01.htm#40608m01.html_dpthd1">
	CONSTITUTIONAL AFFAIRS
</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-06-08.4WS.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="4WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo040608/wmstext/40608m01.htm#40608m01.html_sbhd2">
	Courts Agency
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-06-08.4WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1041" speakername="Christopher Leslie" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Constitutional Affairs" colnum="4WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo040608/wmstext/40608m01.htm#40608m01.html_spmin2">
	<p pid=".4WS.2/1">My noble Friend the Secretary of State, the Lord Falconer of Thoroton, has made the following written ministerial statement.</p>
	<p pid=".4WS.2/2" class="indent">&quot;The Queen has agreed that the new courts agency will be named Her Majesty's Courts Service when it is established in April 2005. The Courts Act 2003 allows the Lord Chancellor to create a new executive agency responsible for the administration of the magistrates' courts and the higher courts&quot;.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-06-08.4WS.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="4WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo040608/wmstext/40608m01.htm#40608m01.html_dpthd2">
	DEFENCE
</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-06-08.4WS.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="4WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo040608/wmstext/40608m01.htm#40608m01.html_sbhd3">
	Department of Defence Mental Health
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-06-08.4WS.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/784" speakername="Ivor Caplin" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence" colnum="4WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo040608/wmstext/40608m01.htm#40608m01.html_spmin3">
	<p pid=".4WS.5/1">As part of the Ministry of Defence strategy to modernise and improve defence mental health services, I can announce today that the Ministry of Defence has awarded a contract to King's College London, widely recognised as a leader in this field, to establish, in partnership with Defence Medical Services, a Department of Defence Mental Health.</p>
	<p pid=".4WS.5/2">This Department, which will come under the auspices of the Royal College of Defence Medicine, will be based in London as part of the King's College centre for military health research. It will have a small permanent staff, consisting of a senior lecturer in military health studies, who will be appointed by King's, and a clinical senior lecturer and nurse senior lecturer, who will be Defence Medical Services staff. Administrative support and accommodation will be provided by King's.</p>
	<p pid=".4WS.5/3">This department will become a centre of excellence for the study of service mental health conditions, enabling us to develop a better understanding of their causes, treatment and prevention. It will greatly enhance the level of training available to our mental health specialists, and provide invaluable support to our newly enhanced community-based teams of mental health specialists.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-06-08.4WS.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="4WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo040608/wmstext/40608m01.htm#40608m01.html_sbhd4">
	Iraq
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-06-08.4WS.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/990" speakername="Adam Ingram" speakeroffice="The Minister of State, Ministry of Defence" colnum="4WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo040608/wmstext/40608m01.htm#40608m01.html_spmin4">
	<p pid=".4WS.7/1">On <phrase class="date" code="2004-05-04">4 May</phrase>, I told the House that 33 cases of civilian deaths, injuries or alleged ill-treatment in Iraq have been investigated by Service Police. The Secretary of State repeated this figure in the House on <phrase class="date" code="2004-05-10">10 May</phrase>, as did the Prime Minister on <phrase class="date" code="2004-05-12">12 May</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid=".4WS.7/2">A detailed verification exercise was put in place to ensure that all cases were being properly investigated and centrally reported. As a result of this continuing exercise it has come to light that the figure given on <phrase class="date" code="2004-05-04">4 May</phrase> failed to incorporate details of investigations from all branches of the Service Police.</p>
	<p pid=".4WS.7/3">The correct number of investigations into civilian deaths, injuries or alleged ill-treatment undertaken at <phrase class="date" code="2004-05-04">4 May</phrase> was 61. Of these 23 were still in progress, 31 had concluded with no further action being taken and seven were pending a decision whether to prosecute. None of these additional 28 cases relates to detention facilities.</p>
	<p pid=".4WS.7/4">We have initiated a further 14 investigations since <phrase class="date" code="2004-05-04">4 May</phrase>. These new investigations can principally be attributed to the high operational tempo over the last month, and a small number of new allegations made by Iraqi civilians relating to earlier incidents.</p>
	<p pid=".4WS.7/5">Steps have been taken to ensure that information on all Service Police investigations into incidents in Iraq are now held centrally. I will continue to update the House on significant developments as appropriate.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-06-08.6WS.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="6WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo040608/wmstext/40608m01.htm#40608m01.html_dpthd3">
	WORK AND PENSIONS
</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-06-08.6WS.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="6WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo040608/wmstext/40608m01.htm#40608m01.html_sbhd5">
	Child Poverty
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2004-06-08.6WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1230" speakername="Andrew Smith" speakeroffice="The Secretary of State for Work and Pensions" colnum="6WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo040608/wmstext/40608m01.htm#40608m01.html_spmin5">
	<p pid=".6WS.2/1">Today I have published the Government response to the Work and Pensions Committee Second Report of Session 2003&ndash;04 [HC 85&ndash;1] &quot;Inquiry into Child Poverty in the UK&quot; (CM 6200). Copies have been placed in the Library and are available for the Vote Office.</p>
	<p pid=".6WS.2/2">I am grateful to the Select Committee for their report which is detailed, comprehensive and helpful.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

