<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">

<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >

<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >

<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >

<!ENTITY euro "&#8364;" >
]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="b" latest="yes">

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-14b.51.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="51"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050314/text/50314-53.htm#50314-53_head0">
	St Helena
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-14b.51.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="51"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050314/text/50314-53.htm#50314-53_spmin1">
	<p pid="b.51.1/1">My honourable friend the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for International Development (Mr Gareth Thomas) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="b.51.1/2">On <phrase class="date" code="2004-04-19">19 April 2004</phrase> (<i>Official Report</i>, Commons, col. <i>1WS</i>) I announced in a Written Statement that the Government would be undertaking feasibility and other investigatory work to determine how best to ensure access for St Helena when St Helena's passenger and supply ship, the RMS &quot;St Helena&quot;, is withdrawn from scheduled service in or around 2010.</p>
	<p pid="b.51.1/3">That work is now completed. We have looked not only at issues relating directly to access, but also at the potential of various access options to encourage the development of a vibrant island economy. This reflects our aim, shared with St Helena, to achieve economic growth for the island.</p>
	<p pid="b.51.1/4">We have decided that, subject to satisfactory contract bids and a rigorous environmental impact assessment, we will establish air access for St Helena. This will entail providing an airport, with a 2,250 metre runway, near the eastern coast at Prosperous Bay Plain. It will be capable of supporting the safe operation of long-haul jet aircraft, such as the Airbus A320 and Boeing 737&ndash;800. We will also provide advice to help establish regular air services; and we will support the St Helena Government in taking advantage of the economic benefits that the new investment should bring to the island. All private sector investment interest will be considered on an equal footing.</p>
	<p pid="b.51.1/5">For their part, among other supporting work, the St Helena Government will review local legislation on inward investment, immigration and taxation. Our shared aim with St Helena will be the creation of a policy environment, against a transformed background of good access, that will encourage sustainable economic development and progress for St Helena and its community.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-14b.51.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="51"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050314/text/50314-54.htm#50314-54_head0">
	Iraq: UK Service Personnel Prosecutions
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-14b.51.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100245" speakername="Lord Goldsmith" colon=":" colnum="51"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050314/text/50314-54.htm#50314-54_spmin0">
	<p pid="b.51.3/1">In June 2004 I advised of my superintendence over the Army Prosecuting Authority and undertook to inform the House of criminal proceedings against soldiers arising out of incidents in Iraq. I also superintend the RAF and Naval Prosecuting Authorities and am accountable to Parliament for any prosecutions decisions.</p>
	<p pid="b.51.3/2">It is therefore appropriate that I advise the House that senior aircraftman James Alexander Bowskill of 2 Squadron RAF Regiment, based at Royal Air Force Station Honington, has been charged with an offence contrary to Section 1 of the Road Traffic Act 1988.</p>
	<p pid="b.51.3/3">The charge reads that Bowskill drove a vehicle dangerously on a road, causing the deaths of five Iraqi civilians. The incident occurred in the vicinity of Basra, Iraq, on <phrase class="date" code="2004-02-03">3 February 2004</phrase>. The court martial will take place on <phrase class="date" code="2005-04-04">4 April 2005</phrase> at the Military Court Centre in Colchester.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-14b.52.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="52"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050314/text/50314-54.htm#50314-54_head1">
	Fundraising: Voluntary Sector Self-regulation
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-14b.52.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="52"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050314/text/50314-54.htm#50314-54_spmin1">
	<p pid="b.52.1/1">We are today publishing proposals for consultation on the principles on which the Government will base their assessment of the success of the self-regulation of voluntary sector fundraising.</p>
	<p pid="b.52.1/2">Self-regulation of fundraising was a recommendation of the Prime Minister's Strategy Unit review of the charitable and wider not-for-profit sector, <i>Private Action, Public Benefit</i>. The Government accepted the Strategy Unit's recommendation for self-regulation of fundraising, and have made provision in the Charities Bill for statutory regulation should self-regulation fail.</p>
	<p pid="b.52.1/3">The draft Charities Bill was subject to pre-legislative scrutiny by a Joint Committee of both Houses of Parliament. The report of the Joint Committee on the draft Charities Bill endorsed the self-regulation of fundraising initiative and recommended that the Government publish for consultation the criteria in accordance with which my right honourable friend the Home Secretary will judge whether self-regulation is working effectively.</p>
	<p pid="b.52.1/4">Proposals for a &quot;regulation of fundraising scheme&quot; have recently been published by the Institute of Fundraising. The main aim of the scheme is to maintain and build on the high levels of public trust and confidence in the voluntary sector's fundraising activities. The scheme will help the sector guard against future threats to the high levels of public confidence, and to provide the sector with a platform to defend itself against criticism.</p>
	<p pid="b.52.1/5">The principles in accordance with which the Government propose that the success of the &quot;regulation of fundraising scheme&quot; should be assessed include: measures of participation, comprising of the number of participating organisations, the proportion of fundraised income covered by scheme membership, and the range of organisations in the scheme's membership; and other measures such as the effectiveness of complaints handling, public awareness of the scheme, the promotion of best practice, the scheme's independence, effective sanctions for non-compliance, the impact of the scheme on non-members and effective liaison with other regulators.</p>
	<p pid="b.52.1/6">In the scheme's initial years the focus would be on measuring the take-up of the scheme within the sector as it develops its membership. It is envisaged that a formal assessment of the success of self-regulation would take place as part of the review of the impact of the Charities Bill which is due to take place within five years of enactment, and would report to Parliament.</p>
	<p pid="b.52.1/7">We are very grateful to all those who have contributed to the development of the proposals for the self-regulation of fundraising. I would particularly like to thank the Institute of Fundraising for taking the lead in developing the scheme, Rodney Buse for considering and consulting on an appropriate model for self-regulation to adopt, and the members of the steering committee for their work in taking the proposals forward.</p>
	<p pid="b.52.1/8">Copies of the consultation paper have been placed in the Library and will also be available on the Home Office website at <a href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/comrace/active/charitylaw/index.html">www.homeoffice.gov.uk/comrace/active/charitylaw/index.html</a>.</p>
	<p pid="b.52.1/9">Details of the proposed self-regulation scheme are available on the Institute of Fundraising website at <a href="http://www.institute-of-fundraising.org.uk">www.institute-of-fundraising.org.uk</a>.</p>
	<p pid="b.52.1/10">Comments are requested by <phrase class="date" code="2005-06-03">3 June 2005</phrase> and a further Statement will be made in due course.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-14b.53.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="53"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050314/text/50314-54.htm#50314-54_head2">
	Homelessness
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-14b.53.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100549" speakername="Lord Rooker" colon=":" colnum="53"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050314/text/50314-54.htm#50314-54_spmin2">
	<p pid="b.53.1/1">I am pleased to announce that the Government's new homelessness strategy <i>Sustainable Communities: Settled Homes; Changing Lives</i> has been launched.</p>
	<p pid="b.53.1/2"><i>Settled Homes; Changing Lives</i> follows on from our five-year plans, <i>Homes for All</i> and <i>People, Places and Prosperity</i>. It builds on our achievements to date in tackling the worst forms of homelessness. This has resulted in meeting challenging targets to significantly reduce rough sleeping since 1998 and put an end to the scandal of homeless families having to raise their children for long periods in cramped bed-and-breakfast hotels. It also sets out our plans for reducing homelessness further and halving the use of temporary accommodation by 2010.</p>
	<p pid="b.53.1/3">I have placed copies of our strategy for tackling homelessness in both House Libraries. The Government response to the ODPM Select Committee report on homelessness will be laid before Parliament today. Both documents are also available on the ODPM's website at <a href="http://www.odpm.gov.uk/stellent/groups/odpm-control/documents/contentservertemplate/odpm-index">www.odpm.gov.uk/stellent/groups/odpm&ndash;control/documents/contentservertemplate/odpm&ndash;index</a>.hcst?n=865&amp;1=2.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-14b.53.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="53"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050314/text/50314-54.htm#50314-54_head3">
	Asylum and Immigration: Statutory Instruments
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-14b.53.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100024" speakername="Baroness Ashton of Upholland" colon=":" colnum="53"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050314/text/50314-54.htm#50314-54_spmin3">
	<p pid="b.53.3/1">On <phrase class="date" code="2006-03-07">7 March</phrase> the Lord Chancellor made the following statutory instrument:</p>
	<p pid="b.53.3/2" class="indent">The Asylum and Immigration (Treatment of Claimants, etc.) Act 2004 (Commencement No. 5 and Transitional Provisions) Order.</p>
	<p pid="b.53.3/3">The order, is made in accordance with Section 48(3)(a), (4), (5) and (6) of the Asylum and Immigration (Treatment of Claimants, etc.) Act 2004, hereafter referred to as the 2004 Act. This order commences Section 26 (unification of appeal system) of, and Schedules 1 and 2 to the 2004 Act on <phrase class="date" code="2005-04-04">4 April 2005</phrase>. This order also contains transitional provisions in relation to pending appeals which were made to an adjudicator before <phrase class="date" code="2005-04-04">4 April 2005</phrase>, and in relation to further appeals and applications in such cases. Copies of the order have been made available to Members and Peers in the votes and printed pages office.</p>
	<p pid="b.53.3/4">On <phrase class="date" code="2006-03-10">10 March</phrase>, the Lord Chancellor also laid before Parliament the following statutory instruments.</p>
	<p pid="b.53.3/5">The Asylum and Immigration Tribunal (Fast Track Procedure) Rules 2005, and the Asylum and Immigration Tribunal (Fast Track Time Limits) Order 2005.</p>
	<p pid="b.53.3/6">The Asylum and Immigration Tribunal (Fast Track Procedure) Rules 2005 are made in accordance with Sections 106(1)&ndash;(3) and 112(3) of the Nationality, Immigration and Asylum Act 2002 and Section 40A(3) of the British Nationality Act 1981, after consulting with the Council on Tribunals in accordance with Section 8 of the Tribunals and Inquiries Act 1992. These rules prescribe a &quot;fast-track&quot; procedure for appeals and applications to the Asylum and Immigration Tribunal, where the appellant is in detention under the Immigration Acts at the locations listed in Schedule 2 to the rules. The rules come into force on <phrase class="date" code="2005-04-04">4 April 2005</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="b.53.3/7">The Asylum and Immigration Tribunal (Fast Track Time Limits) Order 2005 is made in accordance with Sections 26(8) and (9) of the 2004 Act, after consulting with the Lord Chief Justice in accordance with Section 26(10) of the 2004 Act. This order shortens the time limits for review applications made by parties to &quot;fast-track&quot; appeals to the Asylum and Immigration Tribunal. These are referred to as Section 103A applications.</p>
	<p pid="b.53.3/8">For a transitional period, Section 103A applications will initially be considered by a member of the Asylum and Immigration Tribunal. If the tribunal member does not make an order for reconsideration or grant permission for the application to be made out of time, the applicant may notify the appropriate court, under Paragraph 30(5)(a) of Schedule 2 to the 2004 Act, that he wishes the court to consider the application.</p>
	<p pid="b.53.3/9">This order reduces to two days the time limits for making the Section 103A application and for giving notice under Paragraph 30(5)(a), in cases where the fast-track procedure rules apply, so long as the appellant remains in detention when the application is made or notification is given. It comes into force on <phrase class="date" code="2005-04-04">4 April 2005</phrase>.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-14b.54.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="54"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050314/text/50314-55.htm#50314-55_head0">
	Genetics and Insurance
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-14b.54.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100670" speakername="Lord Warner" colon=":" colnum="54"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050314/text/50314-55.htm#50314-55_spmin0">
	<p pid="b.54.1/1">My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for Health has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="b.54.1/2">We are publishing today a new concordat and moratorium on genetics and insurance, which has been agreed between the Government and the Association of British Insurers (ABI). Copies have been placed in the Library. An electronic version has been placed on the Department of Health website at <a href="http://www.dh.gov.uk/publications">www.dh.gov.uk/publications</a>.</p>
	<p pid="b.54.1/3">The new framework, which comes into force today, provides that the use of genetic information by insurance companies will be transparent, fair, and subject to independent oversight. It will help to reassure patients who may be deterred from taking predictive genetic tests for fear of the insurance consequences, and is flexible enough to respond to fast-moving technological and clinical developments in genetic testing.</p>
	<p pid="b.54.1/4">The concordat balances the interest of patients and insurers. Those seeking insurance should not withhold information relevant to underwriting, and insurers should not treat people who have an adverse predictive genetic test result less favourably than others, except as provided for in the concordat.</p>
	<p pid="b.54.1/5">The moratorium on the use by insurers of predictive genetic test results is extended for an extra five years until <phrase class="date" code="">1 November 2011</phrase>. No one will be required to disclose the results of a predictive genetic test unless it has been approved by the Genetics and Insurance Committee (GAIC) and is for insurance of more than &pound;500,000 for life insurance or &pound;300,000 for other health insurance. This means that for the vast majority of insurance policies genetic tests results will not be used at all.</p>
	<p pid="b.54.1/6">The concordat clarifies the broad types of insurance for which predictive genetic test results may be relevant. They are life, critical illness, and income protection insurance policies. Insurers will not use the results from predictive genetic tests for travel insurance, private medical insurance, or any other one-off or annual policy, or for long-term-care insurance.</p>
	<p pid="b.54.1/7">The concordat also clarifies the circumstances when patients need not disclose genetic information, and how information will be handled by insurers. For example, genetic tests taken as part of a research study will not need to be disclosed to insurers. This is good news for United Kingdom clinical researchers, as it specifically rules out the use by insurers of the results of genetic tests taken during participation in clinical trials, removing a potential obstacle to patient recruitment in the development of diagnostic tests, treatments, and medicines.</p>
	<p pid="b.54.1/8">These commitments are backed up by independent oversight of the use of predictive genetic tests by GAIC together with the ABI's code of practice and an impartial complaint and arbitration process.</p>
	<p pid="b.54.1/9">The Government would like to thank the Human Genetics Commission, GAIC, patient groups including Breakthrough Breast Cancer, CancerBACUP and the Alzheimer's Society, and other research groups and individuals who have provided valuable contributions that have helped shape this new concordat and moratorium on genetics and insurance.</p>
	<p pid="b.54.1/10">The new framework means that insurance will continue to be available for people who take predictive genetic tests. They will need to disclose only the adverse results of predictive genetic tests for a limited range of unusually high-value insurance polices&mdash;and then only if the predictive genetic test has been approved by the GAIC. It is the Government's view that this approach is good news for individuals and insurance companies as it will ensure that the rights, safety and well-being of those taking predictive genetic tests are protected whilst also ensuring a viable and fair insurance market.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

