<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17a.21.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17b.21.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17a.21.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17b.21.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17a.21.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17b.21.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17a.21.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17b.21.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17a.22.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17b.22.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17a.22.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17b.22.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17a.24.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17b.24.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17a.24.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17b.24.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17a.24.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="24"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/60517-31.htm#60517-31_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.24.1/1">I am announcing today how the strategy which the Lord Chief Justice, the Chairman of the Judicial Appointments Commission and I have agreed to promote diversity within the judiciary is to be taken forward in the light of the implementation of the Constitutional Reform Act 2005. I am also announcing particular changes that will contribute to delivering my judicial diversity policy.</p>
	<p pid="a.24.1/2">Increasing the diversity of the judiciary, particularly the number of women and those from black and minority ethnic backgrounds, remains one of my key priorities. The launch of the Judicial Appointments Commission and the new responsibilities of the Lord Chief Justice provide an ideal opportunity to set in place a new strategy to build on the improvements made in recent years.</p>
	<p pid="a.24.1/3">The Lord Chief Justice, the Chairman of the Judicial Appointments Commission and I are committed to ensuring the continuation of a judiciary of the highest calibre, with candidates drawn from the widest possible range of available talent. We have agreed an integrated strategy by which we aim to bring about a more diverse judiciary with increased understanding of the communities it serves, to ensure a judiciary of the highest quality which contributes to increased public confidence in the justice system.</p>
	<p pid="a.24.1/4">The key planks of the strategy, which will require a co-ordinated approach by my department, the Judicial Appointments Commission and the judiciary, are:</p>
	<p pid="a.24.1/5" class="indent">to promote judicial service and widen the range of people eligible to apply for judicial office;</p>
	<p pid="a.24.1/6" class="indent">to encourage a wider range of applicants, so as to ensure the widest possible choice of candidates for selection;</p>
	<p pid="a.24.1/7" class="indent">to promote diversity through fair and open processes for selection to judicial office solely on merit; and,</p>
	<p pid="a.24.1/8" class="indent">to ensure that the culture and working environment for judicial office-holders encourages and supports a diverse judiciary and increases understanding of the communities served.</p>
	<p pid="a.24.1/9">Details of the division of responsibilities between my department, the Judicial Appointments Commission and the Directorate of Judicial Offices for England and Wales have today been published on the DCA website (<a href="http://www.dca.gov.uk">www.dca.gov.uk</a>). A comprehensive, co-ordinated and collaborative approach will be adopted by the three bodies to ensure that the diversity strategy is delivered effectively.</p>
	<p pid="a.24.1/10">This strategy is supported by research commissioned by my department to better understand the reasons for the under-representation of women and members of black and minority ethnic communities in the judiciary. The research, undertaken by Opinion Leader Research, has today been published on the DCA website (<a href="http://www.dca.gov.uk">www.dca.gov.uk</a>) and copies placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
	<p pid="a.24.1/11">I am also announcing today further measures to promote greater diversity in the judiciary:</p>
	<p pid="a.24.1/12" class="indent">the Judicial Work Shadowing Scheme is to be extended to cover tribunals, with 10 tribunals having signed up to participate in the scheme, so as to provide potential applicants with an enhanced understanding of judicial opportunities; and</p>
	<p pid="a.24.1/13" class="indent">a working group involving members of the judiciary and magistracy has reported on how experience as a magistrate can be counted in lieu of some sittings as a fee-paid judge, helping to encourage those from different backgrounds to consider a judicial career. The Judicial Appointments Commission will consider how best to take forward this work.</p>
	<p pid="a.24.1/14">The new strategy will ensure that my department, the Judicial Appointments Commission and the judiciary build on the success of recent years and continue to appoint judicial office-holders of the highest possible quality, in whom the public can have the utmost confidence.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17a.25.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17b.25.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17a.25.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-05-17b.25.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

