<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.87.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="87"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000721">
	ECOFIN
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.87.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/101012" speakername="Lord Sassoon" colon=":" colnum="87"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000003">
	<p pid="a.87.1/1">My right honourable friend the Chancellor of the Exchequer (George Osborne) has today made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/2">The Economic and Financial Affairs Council was held in Brussels on <phrase class="date" code="2011-02-15">15 February 2011</phrase>. The following items were discussed:</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/3"><I>Economic Governance</I></p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/4">The council held a first discussion on a package of legislative measures intended to strengthen economic governance in the EU, particularly in the euro area, in order to address the challenges posed by the sovereign debt crisis and prevent the emergence of similar problems in the future, while fully respecting the provisions in the UK's protocol to the treaty. In line with the deadlines set by the European Council, the presidency's intention is to reach agreement on a general approach on all six proposals at the <phrase class="date" code="2011-03-15">15 March</phrase> ECOFIN.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/5"><I>Savings Taxation Directive and Anti-fraud Agreements with Third Countries</I></p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/6">The council held an orientation debate on proposals to strengthen the provisions of the savings directive on the taxation of savings interest, and on antifraud and tax information exchange agreements with Andorra, Liechtenstein, Monaco, San Marino and Switzerland. The Government support the presidency's aim to maintain momentum on these proposals, to enable the council to make progress as soon as possible.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/7"><I>Preparation of the European Council (24</I><I> and </I><phrase class="date" code="2011-03-25">25 March 2011</phrase>)</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/8"><I>Macroeconomic and fiscal guidance</I></p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/9">The council adopted conclusions on macroeconomic and fiscal guidance for the EU, under the new European Semester. The Government believe that the reform priorities set out in the conclusions are important and necessary steps to help promote economic growth in the EU and its member states.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/10"><I>Appointment of an Executive Board Member of the European Central Bank</I></p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/11">Ministers adopted a recommendation on the nomination of Peter Praet (Belgium) as an executive board member of the European Central Bank to succeed Gertrude Tumpel-Gugerell, whose term of office expires on <phrase class="date" code="2011-05-31">31 May</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/12"><I>Implementation of the Stability and Growth Pact</I></p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/13">The council took note of a communication from the Commission assessing action taken by Bulgaria, Cyprus, Finland and Denmark in order to bring their government deficits below 3 per cent of GDP. It was agreed that these member states had taken effective action regarding their deficits, and that no further steps under the EU's excessive deficit procedure were required at present.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/14"><I>Preparation of the G20 Meeting of Finance Ministers and Governors (18</I><I> and </I><phrase class="date" code="2011-02-19">19 February</phrase>)</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/15">The council endorsed EU terms of reference in preparation for a meeting of G20 Finance Ministers and central bank governors to be held in Paris on 18 and <phrase class="date" code="2011-02-19">19 February</phrase>. Discussions are expected to focus on the global economy and the G20 framework for growth, the reform of the International Monetary System, commodities, financial regulation, and other issues such as development.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/16"><I>Discharge procedure in respect of the implementation of the 2009 EU </I><I>B</I><I>udget</I></p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/17">The council adopted a recommendation to the European Parliament on the discharge to be given to the Commission for implementation of the EU's general budget for 2009. The Dutch, Swedish and UK delegations withheld their consent on the discharge. This marks a step change in the UK Government's approach to financial management in the EU; the Government consider it unacceptable that the European Court of Auditors has not been able to grant a positive statement of assurance on the EU Budget as a whole for the 16th year in succession.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/18">Together with the Netherlands and Sweden, the Government also submitted a joint declaration, setting out concrete actions that would improve financial management (see attached).</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/19"><I>Budget guidelines for 2012</I></p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/20">The council adopted conclusions setting out its priorities for the EU's general budget for 2012, which will serve as the basis for negotiation with the European Parliament and the Commission later this year. The conclusions emphasise the need to take into account economic and budgetary constraints at the national level. The Government believe that the efforts made to curb the EU budget's growth in 2011 must be stepped up for the 2012 budget.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/21"><I>Joint declaration signed by the Netherlands, Sweden and the United Kingdom</I></p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/22">With reference to:</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/23">the European Court of Auditors' annual report on implementation of the 2009 EU Budget;</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/24">discharge to be given to the Commission in respect of the implementation of the budget for the financial year 2009;</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/25">draft council recommendation 5891/11 FIN 47 PE-L 14, + ADD 1, + ADD 2;</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/26">the Netherlands, Sweden and the United Kingdom are concerned that:</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/27">for the 16th year in succession, the European Court of Auditors has been unable to grant a positive unqualified statement of assurance on the EU Budget as a whole; andthe slow pace of reforms to the financial management of EU funds is detrimental to the credibility of the EU budget as a whole.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/28">the Netherlands, Sweden and United Kingdom highlight that independent EU-level audit is a crucial function and we therefore strongly support the work of the European Court of Auditors;</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/29">the Netherlands, Sweden and the United Kingdom agree with the European Court of Auditors that improving the quality of spending should be a high priority in order to attain significantly better results in the annual report on the 2010 budget;</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/30">the Netherlands, Sweden and the United Kingdom want to see concrete steps towards achieving the following specific objectives before the council debates discharge of the 2010 Budget:</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/31">member states are responsible for implementing the majority of funds from the EU Budget in co-operation with the Commission. Member states are responsible for conducting checks and for putting in place an effective and efficient control system. As part of a closer dialogue with member states, the Commission is invited to make proposals and to strengthen member state responsibility. Member states should account for the administration of EU funds at national level, including the proper functioning of internal control systems; for reasons of transparency and in order to incentivise sound financial management, member states' annual summaries should be made publicly available. At the same time, member states should be obliged to provide analysis of financial management data as an integral part of the annual summaries; andin support of a risk-based approach to auditing, a more structured dialogue between the Court of Auditors, the Commission and member states is necessary. The Commission should bring forward proposals to enable a stronger focus on the audit of larger projects and institutions which have a proven track record of risk.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.1/32">The forthcoming negotiations of the financial regulation provide an opportunity to take forward these proposals.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.89.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="89"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000722">
	Employment: Sickness Absence
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.89.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100992" speakername="Lord Freud" colon=":" colnum="89"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000033">
	<p pid="a.89.1/1">My right honourable friend the Minister for Employment (Chris Grayling) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.89.1/2">I wish to inform the House that today the Department for Work and Pensions, together with the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills, will be launching an independent review of sickness absence in Great Britain.</p>
	<p pid="a.89.1/3">It is estimated that around 300,000 people (approximately 1 per cent of the employed population) move on to sickness-related benefits (incapacity benefit or employment and support allowance) each year. These individuals make up a sizeable proportion of long-term sickness absences and around half of the total flow on to ESA every year. They constitute a significant cost to taxpayers, in addition to the costs incurred by employers covering absences, and the opportunity costs to the economy in missing out on the contribution of these individuals.</p>
	<p pid="a.89.1/4">In conjunction with the Minister for Employment Relations, Consumer and Postal Affairs, Ed Davey MP, I have invited Dame Carol Black, the National Director for Health and Work, and David Frost, current Director General of the British Chambers of Commerce, to co-chair an independent review of sickness absence to establish how we can mitigate the economic losses, as well providing effective support for those who would benefit from our help. The report will be jointly sponsored by the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills and the Department for Work and Pensions. The review will explore how the current system could be changed to help more people stay in work, thereby reducing costs. In addition, the review will examine whether the balance of these costs are appropriately shared and make recommendations for reform.</p>
	<p pid="a.89.1/5">The coalition Government are committed to reducing the burden of regulation of business in line with the objectives of the growth agenda. The sickness absence review will be conducted in this context, as well as informing the work of the existing employment law review. As such, the sickness absence review will complement the Government's ongoing welfare reform agenda.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.90.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="90"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000723">
	Finance: Regulation
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.90.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/101012" speakername="Lord Sassoon" colon=":" colnum="90"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000038">
	<p pid="a.90.1/1">The Government have today presented to Parliament a consultation document, <I>A New Approach </I><I>t</I><I>o Financial Regulation: Building </I><I>a</I><I> Stronger System</I> [Cm 8012], which provides further detail on the coalition Government's proposals to reform the framework of financial regulation in the UK following the complete failure of the tripartite system over many years to identify or tackle the build-up of risk in the financial system. That failure precipitated the biggest financial crisis for a generation, leading to a run on a major high-street bank and the part-nationalisation of two of the largest banks in the world. We need a wholly new approach. The reforms detailed today will address the fundamental weakness of the regulatory system created in 1997. This document is available on the Treasury website.</p>
	<p pid="a.90.1/2">This document expands and further consults on the Government's proposals, set out last year, to disband the Financial Services Authority and establish a new system of more specialised and focused financial services regulators. The Government's reforms focus on three key institutional changes: the creation of an independent Financial Policy Committee (FPC) in the Bank of England, the establishment of a new Prudential Regulation Authority (PRA) as a subsidiary of the Bank and the creation of an independent conduct-of-business regulator, the Financial Conduct Authority (FCA), which was formerly provisionally titled the &quot;consumer protection and markets authority&quot;. This corrects the failures of the past by creating regulators with clear objectives and the powers needed to deliver them.</p>
	<p pid="a.90.1/3"><I>A New Approach to Financial Regulation: Building a Stronger System</I> outlines the Government's thinking on a range of issues, including: the objectives of the new regulatory bodies and the factors that they must consider in fulfilling their objectives; the levers and likely tools that the FPC will have at its disposal to protect financial stability; the PRA's judgment-led approach in regulating firms; the FCA's more proactive and focused approach to regulating conduct in financial services and markets; accountability measures for the new regulatory bodies; and co-ordination mechanisms that will determine how the regulatory authorities will work together, and with regulated firms. Our reforms will create a stronger regulatory structure that reinforces stability in financial markets and helps to deliver better outcomes for consumers.</p>
	<p pid="a.90.1/4">Following the consultation, the Government will present a further White Paper, including a draft Bill for pre-legislative scrutiny, in the spring. The Government expect the new regulatory structure to be in place by the end of 2012.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.91.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="91"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000724">
	Fixed-Term Parliaments Bill [HL]
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.91.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100966" speakername="Lord Wallace of Tankerness" colon=":" colnum="91"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000042">
	<p pid="a.91.1/1">My honourable friend the Minister for Political and Constitutional Reform (Mark Harper) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.91.1/2">The Constitution Committee's eighth report summarised its inquiry into the Bill, and I am grateful to the committee for the careful scrutiny it has given the Bill. Today the Government have responded to the committee's report by means of a Command Paper that has been laid before both Houses of Parliament.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.91.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="91"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000725">
	Health: Personality Disorders
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.91.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100305" speakername="Earl Howe" colon=":" colnum="91"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000044">
	<p pid="a.91.3/1">My honourable friend the Minister of State, Department of Health (Paul Burstow) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.91.3/2">I am publishing today a joint Department of Health and Ministry of Justice consultation document on an offender personality disorder pathway implementation plan.</p>
	<p pid="a.91.3/3">This document sets out the Government's plans to reshape services, interventions and treatments for offenders with severe personality disorders. These plans would be implemented within the existing resources devoted to this area across the National Health Service and National Offender Management Service. The proposals take account of the learning from the dangerous and severe personality disorder programme, introduced by the previous Administration, and are aimed to improve identification and assessment, increase treatment capacity, provide additional psychological support in prisons and strengthen oversight for those released from custody.</p>
	<p pid="a.91.3/4">This consultation is an important opportunity for professional bodies, service providers in health and criminal justice, patients and the public to comment on how best to ensure continuity of care through the development of effective service pathways across custodial settings and in the community, to improve care, protect the public and make the best use possible of the available resources. The consultation sets out the Government's initial thoughts and invites views from interested persons or organisations.</p>
	<p pid="a.91.3/5">The consultation document has been placed in the Library. Copies are available to honourable Members from the Vote Office and to noble Lords from the Printed Paper Office.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.92.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="92"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000726">
	Housing: Social Housing
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.92.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100269" speakername="Baroness Hanham" colon=":" colnum="92"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000049">
	<p pid="a.92.1/1">My right honourable friend the Minister for Housing and Local Government (Grant Shapps) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.1/2">I am today publishing a paper which sets out the next steps in the Government's reform of the social housing system, in light of the responses we have received to our policy document, <I>Local Decisions</I><I>: </I><I>A Fairer Future For Social Housing</I>, published in November last year. The paper which I am publishing today also contains a summary of those responses and a copy has been placed in the Library of the House.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.1/3">The reforms to social housing which are being taken forward in the Localism Bill will give local authorities far greater freedom and flexibility in the types of tenancies they can grant to social housing tenants; in the way they allocate their social housing; and in how they discharge their main homelessness duty. The reforms will also significantly improve mobility for social tenants. The reforms to tenure will only affect new social tenancies. We will ensure that the security and rights of existing social tenants continue to be protected in law.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.1/4">I am publishing the response earlier than the usual three-month deadline from the end of consultation as I believe it will be useful to inform debate on the social housing provisions in the Bill.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.1/5">The response to the consultation was overwhelming. Nearly 700 responses were received from individuals and organisations. There was a very strong response from local authorities and other social landlords who, in the main, welcomed the new freedoms and flexibilities which the Government are giving them.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.1/6">The Localism Bill will give the Secretary of State the power to issue a direction to the Regulator of Social Housing on a tenancy standard and a direction on mobility. I am taking the opportunity presented through the paper that I am publishing today to set out the Government's thinking on what we believe should be contained in both of these directions. I intend to publish a full technical draft of the directions on tenure and mobility later this year, when they will be subject to a full consultation.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.92.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="92"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000727">
	Immigration
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.92.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100962" speakername="Baroness Neville-Jones" colon=":" colnum="92"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000055">
	<p pid="a.92.3/1">My honourable friend the Minister of State for Immigration (Damian Green) has today made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.3/2">I am announcing proposals to change the fees for immigration and nationality applications made to the UK Border Agency. The Government review these fees on a regular basis and makes appropriate changes as necessary. I will shortly lay regulations for fees that are set at levels above the normal administrative costs of the service. We have continued with our strategic approach to charging, setting certain fees above cost on the basis of the value of the service.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.3/3">These fees must be set out in regulations before both Houses of Parliament and are subject to the affirmative procedure. The fees allow us to generate revenue which is used to fund the UK immigration system and to set certain fees below cost recovery to support wider government objectives. The revenue generated will contribute towards securing our borders and controlling migration for the benefit of the UK. I will lay another set of regulations in Parliament for the fees for immigration and nationality services that are set at/below the cost of the service.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.3/4">A table with details of all the proposed increases is set out at Annex A. The table includes indicative unit costs for each application for FY 11/12. The unit cost is the estimated average cost to UK Border Agency of processing each application. Although our unit costs are not fixed over the course of the financial year, we publish unit costs so it is clear which fees we set over cost and by how much. Further details of all fees changes will be outlined in the Explanatory Memoranda accompanying both the regulations.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.3/5">Given the need to reduce public spending, we have had to carefully consider our fee levels to ensure that we can maintain good service levels to our customers and secure the border for the general public. In principle it is the right time to ask migrants to make a greater contribution to funding the UK Border Agency than was previously the case. Therefore we should continue to seek a shift in the funding provided by migrants to deliver the border and immigration system with a consequent reduction in the burden on UK taxpayers.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.3/6">In developing these proposals, we have sought to limit increases so as to avoid any broader economic impact (particularly on the most economically sensitive route of all, short-term visit visas).</p>
	<p pid="a.92.3/7">I believe these proposals continue to strike the right balance between maintaining secure and effective border controls, and ensuring that our fees structure does not inhibit the UK's ability to attract those migrants and visitors who make a valued contribution. It is right that those who benefit directly from the immigration system should pay to meet the costs of securing the UK's borders. This will help to support the immigration system, maintain public confidence, and ensure that migration is managed for the benefit of the UK.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.3/8">Full details on how to apply for all of these services will be provided on our website, <a href="http://www.ukba.homeoffice.gov.uk">www.ukba.homeoffice.gov.uk</a>.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/11"> <td></td> <td></td> <td></td> <td>Annex A</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/12"> <td colspan="4">Out of Country</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/13"> <td>Visas-non PBS (New products <sup>*</sup>)</td> <td>Unit Costs  April 2011</td> <td>Current Fees Oct/Nov 2010</td> <td>Proposed Fees April 2011</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/14"> <td>Visit visa - short</td> <td>&#163;140</td> <td>&#163;70</td> <td>&#163;76</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/15"> <td>Visit visa - long 2 year</td> <td>&#163;140</td> <td>&#163;245</td> <td>&#163;265</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/16"> <td>Visit visa - long 5 year</td> <td>&#163;140</td> <td>&#163;450</td> <td>&#163;486</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/17"> <td>Visit visa - long 10 year</td> <td>&#163;140</td> <td>&#163;650</td> <td>&#163;702</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/18"> <td>Short Term Student &lt;12 Months Visa</td> <td>&#163;140</td> <td>&#163;70</td> <td>&#163;140</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/19"> <td>Settlement</td> <td>&#163;391</td> <td>&#163;750</td> <td>&#163;810</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/20"> <td>Settlement - Dependant Relative</td> <td>&#163;458</td> <td>&#163;1,680</td> <td>&#163;1,814</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/21"> <td>Certificate of Entitlement</td> <td>&#163;355</td> <td>&#163;245</td> <td>&#163;265</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/22"> <td>Other Visa</td> <td>&#163;163</td> <td>&#163;245</td> <td>&#163;265</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/23"> <td>Transit Visa</td> <td>&#163;73</td> <td>&#163;47</td> <td>&#163;51</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/24"> <td>Vignette Transfer Fee</td> <td>&#163;163</td> <td>&#163;93</td> <td>&#163;100</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/25"> <td>Call Out/Out of Hours Fee</td> <td>&#163;134/hr</td> <td>130/hr max &#163;939/day</td> <td>&#163;130/hr</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/26"> <td>Forwarding documents to Commonwealth Countries/Overseas Territories (additional fee) <sup>*</sup></td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;65</td> <td>&#163;70</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/27"> <td>Handling applications on behalf of Commonwealth Countries/ Overseas Territories <sup>*</sup></td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;48</td> <td>&#163;50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/28"> <td>Single entry visa to Replace Biometric Residence Permit Overseas <sup>*</sup></td> <td>&#163;70</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;70</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/33"> <td>Visa - PBS (New products <sup>*</sup>)</td> <td>Unit Costs April 2011</td> <td>Current Fees Oct/Nov 2010</td> <td>Proposed Fees April 2011</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/34"> <td>Tier 1 (Entrepreneur, Investor, Exceptional Talent) - Main Apps</td> <td>&#163;432</td> <td>&#163;750</td> <td>&#163;800</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/35"> <td>Tier 1 (Entrepreneur, Investor, Exceptional Talent) - Dependants</td> <td>&#163;432</td> <td>&#163;750</td> <td>&#163;800</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/36"> <td>Tier 1 CESC - Main Apps</td> <td>&#163;432</td> <td>&#163;700</td> <td>&#163;720</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/37"> <td>Tier 1 CESC - Dependants</td> <td>&#163;432</td> <td>&#163;700</td> <td>&#163;800</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/38"> <td>Tier 1 (Transition)</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;332</td> <td>&#163;332</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/39"> <td>Tier 1 (Transition) CESC</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;300</td> <td>&#163;300</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/40"> <td>Tier 1 Post Study - Main</td> <td>&#163;459</td> <td>&#163;344</td> <td>&#163;474</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/41"> <td>Tier 1 Post Study - Dependants</td> <td>&#163;459</td> <td>&#163;344</td> <td>&#163;474</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/42"> <td>Tier 2 Gen, Sport &amp; MOR - Main Apps</td> <td>&#163;250</td> <td>&#163;350</td> <td>&#163;400</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/43"> <td>Tier 2 Gen, Sport &amp; MOR - Dependants</td> <td>&#163;250</td> <td>&#163;350</td> <td>&#163;400</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/44"> <td>Tier 2 ICT &lt;12Mths - Main Apps &amp; Dependants <sup>*</sup></td> <td>&#163;227</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;350</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/45"> <td>Tier 2 ICT &lt;12Mths - CESC Main Applicant <sup>*</sup></td> <td>&#163;227</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;315</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/46"> <td>Tier 2 CESC - Main Apps</td> <td>&#163;250</td> <td>&#163;300</td> <td>&#163;360</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/47"> <td>Tier 2 CESC - Dependants</td> <td>&#163;250</td> <td>&#163;300</td> <td>&#163;400</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/48"> <td>Tier 4 - Main Apps</td> <td>&#163;289</td> <td>&#163;220</td> <td>&#163;255</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/49"> <td>Tier 4 - Dependants</td> <td>&#163;289</td> <td>&#163;220</td> <td>&#163;255</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/50"> <td>Tier 5 Tem Work &amp; YM</td> <td>&#163;206</td> <td>&#163;130</td> <td>&#163;190</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/51"> <td>Tier 5 CESC</td> <td>&#163;206</td> <td>&#163;120</td> <td>&#163;171</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/52"> <td>Tier 5 CESC - Dependants</td> <td>&#163;206</td> <td>&#163;130</td> <td>&#163;190</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/53"> <td colspan="4">N.B. CESC = Council of Europe Social Charter reduction</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/54"> <td colspan="4">Applications to the Channel Islands under Employment and Study routes attract Tier 2 &amp; Tier 4 fees and costs respectively.</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/59"> <td colspan="4">In Country</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/60"> <td>Nationality (New products <sup>*</sup>)</td> <td>Unit Costs April 2011</td> <td>Current Fees Oct/Nov 2010</td> <td>Proposed Fees April 2011</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/61"> <td>Naturalisation (UK Citizenship) Single <sup>1</sup></td> <td>&#163;238</td> <td>&#163;780</td> <td>&#163;836</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/62"> <td>Naturalisation (UK Citizenship) Joint <sup>1</sup></td> <td>&#163;319</td> <td>&#163;1,010</td> <td>&#163;1,294</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/63"> <td>Naturalisation (UK Citizenship) Spouse <sup>1</sup></td> <td>&#163;238</td> <td>&#163;780</td> <td>&#163;836</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/64"> <td>Nationality Registration Adult <sup>1</sup></td> <td>&#163;238</td> <td>&#163;580</td> <td>&#163;620</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/65"> <td>Nationality Registration Minor <sup>2</sup></td> <td>&#163;238</td> <td>&#163;500</td> <td>&#163;540</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/66"> <td>Nationality Registration Multiple Minor Main <sup>2</sup></td> <td>&#163;319</td> <td>&#163;600</td> <td>&#163;810</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/67"> <td>Nationality Registration Multiple Minor Dependant <sup>2</sup></td> <td>&#163;238</td> <td>&#163;150</td> <td>&#163;270</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/68"> <td>Renunciation of Nationality</td> <td>&#163;238</td> <td>&#163;208</td> <td>&#163;225</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/69"> <td>Nationality Reissued Certificate</td> <td>&#163;88</td> <td>&#163;80</td> <td>&#163;86</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/70"> <td>Nationality Right of Abode</td> <td>&#163;162</td> <td>&#163;150</td> <td>&#163;162</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/71"> <td>Nationality Reconsiderations</td> <td>&#163;88</td> <td>&#163;100</td> <td>&#163;80</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/72"> <td>Status Letter (Nationality)</td> <td>&#163;88</td> <td>&#163;80</td> <td>&#163;86</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/73"> <td>Non-Acquisition Letter (Nationality)</td> <td>&#163;88</td> <td>&#163;80</td> <td>&#163;86</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/74"> <td>Nationality Correction to Certificate <sup>*</sup></td> <td>&#163;88</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;86</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/75"> <td colspan="4"><sup>1</sup> Additional &#163;80 per applicant is included to cover the ceremony fee.</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/76"> <td colspan="4"><sup>2</sup> Additional &#163;80 per applicant is required to cover the ceremony fee should the minor turn 18 during the application process. This will be requested at point of decision.</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/81"> <td>In UK - Non PBS (New products <sup>*</sup>)</td> <td>Unit Costs April 2011</td> <td>Current Fees Oct/Nov 2010</td> <td>Proposed Fees April 2011</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/82"> <td>ILR Postal Main</td> <td>&#163;243</td> <td>&#163;900</td> <td>&#163;972</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/83"> <td>ILR Postal Dependant</td> <td>&#163;243</td> <td>&#163;250</td> <td>&#163;486</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/84"> <td>ILR Postal CESC Main</td> <td>&#163;243</td> <td>&#163;850</td> <td>&#163;875</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/85"> <td>ILR Postal CESC Dependant</td> <td>&#163;243</td> <td>&#163;250</td> <td>&#163;486</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/86"> <td>ILR PEO Main</td> <td>&#163;243</td> <td>&#163;1,250</td> <td>&#163;1,350</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/87"> <td>ILR PEO Dependant</td> <td>&#163;243</td> <td>&#163;350</td> <td>&#163;675</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/88"> <td>ILR PEO CESC Main</td> <td>&#163;243</td> <td>&#163;1,100</td> <td>&#163;1,215</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/89"> <td>ILR PEO CESC Dependant</td> <td>&#163;243</td> <td>&#163;300</td> <td>&#163;675</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/90"> <td>ILR Dependant Relative Postal</td> <td>&#163;299</td> <td>&#163;1,680</td> <td>&#163;1,814</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/91"> <td>ILR Dependant Relative PEO</td> <td>&#163;299</td> <td>&#163;2,050</td> <td>&#163;2,214</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/92"> <td>LTR Non Student Postal Main</td> <td>&#163;418</td> <td>&#163;500</td> <td>&#163;550</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/93"> <td>LTR Non Student Postal Dependant</td> <td>&#163;418</td> <td>&#163;150</td> <td>&#163;275</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/94"> <td>LTR Non Student PEO Main</td> <td>&#163;419</td> <td>&#163;800</td> <td>&#163;850</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/95"> <td>LTR Non Student PEO Dependant</td> <td>&#163;419</td> <td>&#163;200</td> <td>&#163;425</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/96"> <td>Transfer of Conditions Postal Main</td> <td>&#163;219</td> <td>&#163;200</td> <td>&#163;216</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/97"> <td>Transfer of Conditions Postal Dependant</td> <td>&#163;219</td> <td>&#163;50</td> <td>&#163;108</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/98"> <td>Transfer of Conditions PEO Main</td> <td>&#163;219</td> <td>&#163;600</td> <td>&#163;648</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/99"> <td>Transfer of Conditions PEO Dependant</td> <td>&#163;219</td> <td>&#163;150</td> <td>&#163;324</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/100"> <td>Travel Documents Adult (CoT)</td> <td>&#163;241</td> <td>&#163;220</td> <td>&#163;238</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/101"> <td>Travel Documents Adult CTD</td> <td>&#163;241</td> <td>&#163;77.50</td> <td>&#163;77.50</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/102"> <td>Travel Documents Child (CoT)</td> <td>&#163;152</td> <td>&#163;138</td> <td>&#163;149</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/103"> <td>Travel Documents Child CTD</td> <td>&#163;152</td> <td>&#163;49</td> <td>&#163;49</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/104"> <td>Replacement Biometric Residence Permit</td> <td>&#163;37</td> <td>&#163;30</td> <td>&#163;37</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/105"> <td>Mobile Case working (Premium+)</td> <td>&#163;2,211</td> <td>&#163;15,000</td> <td>&#163;6,000 + PEO Fee</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/106"> <td>Call Out/Out of Hours Fee</td> <td>&#163;134/hr</td> <td>&#163;130/hr max &#163;939/day</td> <td>&#163;130/hr</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/107"> <td>Work Permit Technical Changes</td> <td>&#163;123</td> <td>&#163;20</td> <td>&#163;22</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/108"> <td>Residual FLR IED Postal - Main</td> <td>&#163;246</td> <td>&#163;500</td> <td>&#163;550</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/109"> <td>Residual FLR IED Postal - Dependants</td> <td>&#163;238</td> <td>&#163;150</td> <td>&#163;275</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/110"> <td>Residual FLR IED PEO - Main</td> <td>&#163;148</td> <td>&#163;800</td> <td>&#163;850</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/111"> <td>Residual FLR IED PEO - Dependants</td> <td>&#163;148</td> <td>&#163;200</td> <td>&#163;425</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/112"> <td>Residual FLR BUS Postal - Main</td> <td>&#163;148</td> <td>&#163;850</td> <td>&#163;1,000</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/113"> <td>Residual FLR BUS Postal - Dependants</td> <td>&#163;148</td> <td>&#163;250</td> <td>&#163;500</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/114"> <td>Employment LTR outside PBS Postal</td> <td>&#163;362</td> <td>&#163;500</td> <td>&#163;550</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/115"> <td>Employment LTR outside PBS Postal Dependant</td> <td>&#163;362</td> <td>&#163;150</td> <td>&#163;275</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/116"> <td>Employment LTR outside PBS PEO</td> <td>&#163;303</td> <td>&#163;800</td> <td>&#163;850</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/117"> <td>Employment LTR outside PBS PEO Dependant</td> <td>&#163;303</td> <td>&#163;200</td> <td>&#163;425</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/118"> <td>Additional Out of Hours Caseworking<sup>1</sup> - PEO Main <sup>*</sup></td> <td>n/a</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;300</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/119"> <td>Additional Out of Hours Caseworking<sup>1</sup> - PEO Dependant <sup>*</sup></td> <td>n/a</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;150</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/120"> <td>EEA Applications at PEO (per person) <sup>*</sup></td> <td>n/a</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;300</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/121"> <td colspan="4"><sup>1</sup> Out of hours caseworking fee payable on top of standard PEO fee</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/122"> <td colspan="4">CESC = Council of Europe Social Charter reduction</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/123"> <td colspan="4">LTR = Leave to Remain</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/124"> <td colspan="4">PEO = Public Enquiry Office</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/125"> <td colspan="4">ILR = Indefinite Leave to Remain</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/130"> <td>In UK - PBS New products <sup>*</sup>)</td> <td>Unit Costs April 2011</td> <td>Current Fees Oct/Nov 2010</td> <td>Proposed Fees April 2011</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/131"> <td>Tier 1 - Postal Main</td> <td>&#163;269</td> <td>&#163;850</td> <td>&#163;1,000</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/132"> <td>Tier 1 - Postal Dependant</td> <td>&#163;269</td> <td>&#163;250</td> <td>&#163;500</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/133"> <td>Tier 1 - Postal CESC Main</td> <td>&#163;269</td> <td>&#163;770</td> <td>&#163;900</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/134"> <td>Tier 1 - Postal CESC Dependant</td> <td>&#163;269</td> <td>&#163;250</td> <td>&#163;500</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/135"> <td>Tier 1 - PEO Main</td> <td>&#163;253</td> <td>&#163;1,150</td> <td>&#163;1,300</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/136"> <td>Tier 1 - PEO Dependant</td> <td>&#163;253</td> <td>&#163;300</td> <td>&#163;650</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/137"> <td>Tier 1 - PEO CESC Main</td> <td>&#163;253</td> <td>&#163;1,000</td> <td>&#163;1,170</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/138"> <td>Tier 1 - PEO CESC Dependant</td> <td>&#163;253</td> <td>&#163;300</td> <td>&#163;650</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/139"> <td>Tier 1</td> <td>(Post Study) - Postal Main</td> <td>&#163;337</td> <td>&#163;550</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/140"> <td>Tier 1 - (Post Study) - Postal Dependant</td> <td>&#163;337</td> <td>&#163;150</td> <td>&#163;297</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/141"> <td>Tier 1</td> <td>(Post Study) - PEO Main</td> <td>&#163;337</td> <td>&#163;850</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/142"> <td>Tier 1</td> <td>(Post Study) - PEO Dependant</td> <td>&#163;337</td> <td>&#163;250</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/143"> <td>Tier 1 - Transition Postal Main</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;500</td> <td>&#163;500</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/144"> <td>Tier 1 - Transition Postal Dependant</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;150</td> <td>&#163;250</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/145"> <td>Tier 1 - Transition PEO Main</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;700</td> <td>&#163;700</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/146"> <td>Tier 1 - Transition PEO Dependant</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;200</td> <td>&#163;350</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/147"> <td>Tier 2 - Postal Main</td> <td>&#163;169</td> <td>&#163;500</td> <td>&#163;550</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/148"> <td>Tier 2- Postal Dependant</td> <td>&#163;169</td> <td>&#163;150</td> <td>&#163;275</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/149"> <td>Tier 2 - Postal CESC Main</td> <td>&#163;155</td> <td>&#163;450</td> <td>&#163;495</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/150"> <td>Tier 2 - Postal CESC Dependant</td> <td>&#163;155</td> <td>&#163;150</td> <td>&#163;275</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/151"> <td>Tier 2 - PEO Main</td> <td>&#163;169</td> <td>&#163;800</td> <td>&#163;850</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/152"> <td>Tier 2 - PEO Dependant</td> <td>&#163;169</td> <td>&#163;200</td> <td>&#163;425</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/153"> <td>Tier 2 - PEO CESC Main</td> <td>&#163;169</td> <td>&#163;700</td> <td>&#163;765</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/154"> <td>Tier 2 - PEO CESC Dependant</td> <td>&#163;169</td> <td>&#163;200</td> <td>&#163;425</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/155"> <td>Tier 2 - Postal Main (ICT &lt;12 months) <sup>*</sup></td> <td>&#163;169</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;350</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/156"> <td>Tier 2 - Postal Dependants (ICT &lt;12 months) <sup>*</sup></td> <td>&#163;169</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;175</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/157"> <td>Tier 2 - PEO Main (ICT &lt;12 months) <sup>*</sup></td> <td>&#163;169</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;650</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/158"> <td>Tier 2 - PEO Dependants (ICT &lt;12 months) <sup>*</sup></td> <td>&#163;169</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;325</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/159"> <td>Tier 2 - Postal CESC Main (ICT &lt;12 months) <sup>*</sup></td> <td>&#163;155</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;315</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/160"> <td>Tier 2 - PEO CESC Main (ICT &lt;12 months) <sup>*</sup></td> <td>&#163;169</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;585</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/161"> <td>Tier 4 - Postal Main</td> <td>&#163;316</td> <td>&#163;357</td> <td>&#163;386</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/162"> <td>Tier 4 - Postal Dependant</td> <td>&#163;316</td> <td>&#163;100</td> <td>&#163;193</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/163"> <td>Tier 4- PEO Main</td> <td>&#163;316</td> <td>&#163;650</td> <td>&#163;702</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/164"> <td>Tier 4 - PEO Dependant</td> <td>&#163;316</td> <td>&#163;150</td> <td>&#163;351</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/165"> <td>Tier 5- Postal Main</td> <td>&#163;235</td> <td>&#163;130</td> <td>&#163;190</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/166"> <td>Tier 5 - Postal Dependant</td> <td>&#163;235</td> <td>&#163;30</td> <td>&#163;95</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/167"> <td>Tier 5- Postal CESC Main</td> <td>&#163;235</td> <td>&#163;120</td> <td>&#163;171</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/168"> <td>Tier 5 - Postal CESC Dependant</td> <td>&#163;235</td> <td>&#163;30</td> <td>&#163;95</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/169"> <td>Tier 5 - PEO Main</td> <td>&#163;240</td> <td>&#163;600</td> <td>&#163;648</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/170"> <td>Tier 5- PEO Dependant</td> <td>&#163;240</td> <td>&#163;150</td> <td>&#163;324</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/171"> <td>Tier 5 - PEO CESC Main</td> <td>&#163;240</td> <td>&#163;550</td> <td>&#163;583</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/172"> <td>Tier 5- PEO CESC Dependant</td> <td>&#163;240</td> <td>&#163;150</td> <td>&#163;324</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/173"> <td>PBS Dependants Applying Separately - Postal</td> <td>&#163;418</td> <td>&#163;500</td> <td>&#163;550</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/174"> <td>PBS Dependants Applying Separately - PEO</td> <td>&#163;419</td> <td>&#163;800</td> <td>&#163;850</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/175"> <td>Tier 4 - Permission to Change Course<sup>1*</sup></td> <td>&#163;160</td> <td>n/a</td> <td>&#163;160</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/176"> <td colspan="4">N.B. CESC = Council of Europe Social Charter reduction</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/177"> <td colspan="4"><sup>1</sup> Only for migrants that applied to UKBA for permission to study between  31 March and 4 October 2009</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/182"> <td>PBS Sponsorship</td> <td>Unit Costs April 2011</td> <td>Current Fees Nov 2010</td> <td>Proposed Fees April 2011</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/183"> <td>Tier 2 Large Sponsor Licence</td> <td>&#163;1,007</td> <td>&#163;1,000</td> <td>&#163;1,025</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/184"> <td>Tier 2 Small Sponsor Licence</td> <td>&#163;1,007</td> <td>&#163;300</td> <td>&#163;310</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/185"> <td>Tier 4 Sponsor Licence</td> <td>&#163;1,007</td> <td>&#163;400</td> <td>&#163;410</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/186"> <td>Tier 5 Sponsor Licence</td> <td>&#163;1,007</td> <td>&#163;400</td> <td>&#163;410</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/187"> <td>Tier 2, Tier 4 &amp;/or Tier 5 Licence (where sponsor currently holds T4 or T5 licence)</td> <td>&#163;1,007</td> <td>&#163;600</td> <td>&#163;615</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/188"> <td>Highly Trusted Sponsor Licence</td> <td>&#163;1,007</td> <td>&#163;400</td> <td>&#163;410</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/189"> <td>Sponsor Action Plan</td> <td>&#163;1,007</td> <td>&#163;1,000</td> <td>&#163;1,000</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/190"> <td>Tier 2 COS</td> <td>&#163;172</td> <td>&#163;170</td> <td>&#163;175</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/191"> <td>Tier 5 COS</td> <td>&#163;15</td> <td>&#163;10</td> <td>&#163;10</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.92.3/192"> <td>Tier 4 CAS</td> <td>&#163;15</td> <td>&#163;10</td> <td>&#163;10</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.98.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="98"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000728">
	Inland Waterways
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.98.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100286" speakername="Lord Henley" colon=":" colnum="98"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000631">
	<p pid="a.98.1/1">My honourable friend the Minister for Natural Environment and Fisheries (Richard Benyon) has today made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.98.1/2">On <phrase class="date" code="2010-06-21">21 June 2010</phrase>, I made a statement about inland waterways policy for England and Wales (Col. 4WS). I said that we were considering the appropriate civil society model for British Waterways, including the possible inclusion of the Environment Agency's navigations. On <phrase class="date" code="2011-10-14">14 October</phrase>, the Government subsequently announced our intention to move British Waterways in England and Wales from being a public corporation to a new waterways charity, subject to parliamentary approval.</p>
	<p pid="a.98.1/3">As a result of work undertaken by the Government, British Waterways and the Environment Agency over the past few months, I am convinced by the compelling vision of a national trust for the waterways that includes the British Waterways and Environment Agency navigations. However, I wish to take a phased approach to the delivery of this vision so that assets and liabilities can be transferred sustainably. In phase 1, the liabilities and assets of British Waterways in England and Wales will transfer into the new charity, alongside an &quot;endowment&quot; consisting of the property portfolio owned by British Waterways in England and Wales. In phase 2, the EA navigations would transfer to the new charity, if sufficient funding can be found in the next Spending Review to enable the charity to take on the liabilities associated with them, and subject to the agreement of the charity's trustees.</p>
	<p pid="a.98.1/4">The Government's proposed approach, which will be subject to public consultation as part of the forthcoming consultation on setting up the new charity, is that the EA navigations should transfer to the new charity in 2015-16 in the next Spending Review period, if it is affordable to do so. To maintain momentum, a review will be undertaken in 2014 to assess the progress and achievements of the new charity and to consider the options for the transfer of the EA navigations.</p>
	<p pid="a.98.1/5">The Government are absolutely committed to delivering our exciting vision for a national trust for the waterways over the coming years, and consider that over time the new waterways charity offers the most sustainable future for both the BW waterways and EA navigations.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.99.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="99"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000729">
	Ministry of Defence: Votes A Annual Estimates
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.99.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100026" speakername="Lord Astor of Hever" colon=":" colnum="99"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000636">
	<p pid="a.99.1/1">My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for Defence (Liam Fox) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.99.1/2">The Ministry of Defence Supplementary Votes A Estimate 2010-11 will be laid before the House on <phrase class="date" code="2011-02-17">17 February 2011</phrase> as HC 777. This outlines the maximum numbers of personnel to be maintained for each service in the Armed Forces during financial year 2010-11.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.99.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100026" speakername="Lord Astor of Hever" colon=":" colnum="99"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000638">
	<p pid="a.99.2/1">My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for Defence (Liam Fox) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.99.2/2">The Ministry of Defence Votes A Estimate 2011-12 will be laid before the House on <phrase class="date" code="2011-02-17">17 February 2011</phrase> as HC 769. This outlines the maximum numbers of personnel to be maintained for each service in the Armed Forces during financial year 2011-12.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.100.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="100"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000730">
	Northern Ireland: Robert Hamill Inquiry
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.100.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100592" speakername="Lord Shutt of Greetland" colon=":" colnum="100"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000640">
	<p pid="a.100.1/1">My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland (Owen Paterson) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.1/2">In my Written Statement of <phrase class="date" code="2011-01-31">31 January 2011</phrase>, I informed the House that, following an announcement by the Public Prosecution Service for Northern Ireland that it planned to prosecute three individuals in connection with the death of Robert Hamill, I would not publish the report of the Robert Hamill inquiry until these legal proceedings had concluded. Publishing the report while proceedings are ongoing would jeopardise the individuals' right to a fair trial.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.1/3">I also set out the checking process which is required to meet the obligations on me in relation to Article 2 of the European Convention on Human Rights and in relation to national security. I can confirm that this checking process has now been completed and I have received advice from the checking team which confirms that there is nothing in the report which, if published, could breach Article 2 of the European Convention on Human Rights by putting the lives or safety of individuals at risk, or put national security at risk. I am therefore satisfied that once legal proceedings have concluded, the report can be published in full. I have advised Sir Edwin Jowitt, the chairman of the inquiry, of this.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.1/4">I have also asked Sir Edwin to retain formal custody of the report in a secure location until the legal proceedings have concluded and it can be submitted to me and be published. The report has not been shown to me or to any other member of the Government, or to any officials except the two members of the team which carried out the checking process. I have not been briefed on the contents of the report, nor have any officials other than those in the checking team.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.1/5">Again, I reassure the House that once the legal proceedings have concluded, I intend to publish the report in full and as soon as practicable. Once a timetable for publication becomes clear, I will update the House accordingly.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.100.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="100"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000731">
	Railways: High Speed Rail
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.100.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100028" speakername="Earl Attlee" colon=":" colnum="100"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000645">
	<p pid="a.100.3/1">My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for Transport (Philip Hammond) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.3/2">Today, I am launching the consultation on the Government's proposals for a national high speed rail network. <I>High Speed Rail: Investing in Britain</I><I>'</I><I>s Future</I> sets out the Government's case for this network, the details of the Government's strategy and the proposed route for an initial phase from London to the West Midlands. It will be one of the most extensive national consultations ever undertaken.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.3/3">I believe that a national high speed rail network from London to Birmingham, with onward legs to Leeds and Manchester, could transform Britain's competitiveness as profoundly as the coming of the railways in the 19th century. It would reshape Britain's economic geography, helping to bridge the north-south divide though massive improvements in journey times and better connections between cities-slashing almost an hour off the trip from London to Manchester.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.3/4">But the proposed High Speed Rail network would do more; it would address Britain's future transport capacity challenge, providing a huge uplift in long distance capacity and relieving pressure on overstretched conventional lines. It would bring around &#163;44 billion of net monetised benefits and support the creation of thousands of new jobs, as well as delivering unquantifiable strategic benefits. And it would help us to build a sustainable economy, by encouraging millions of people out of cars and off planes on to trains. Our competitors already recognise the huge benefits of high speed rail and are pressing ahead with ambitious plans. Britain cannot afford to be left behind.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.3/5">The Government's support for high speed rail was set out clearly in our programme for government, published in May last year. Since then, we have built upon the work already done by HS2 Ltd to consider the case for high speed rail in the UK. Last October's spending review settlement reaffirmed our support and provided over &#163;750 million to fund the development of our national network proposals over the next four years.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.3/6">Since then, the Government have received additional advice from HS2 Ltd on options for a national high speed rail network and on direct links to Heathrow and the High Speed 1 (HS1) line to the Channel Tunnel.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.3/7">The Government understand the concerns of those living near the proposed route. Following a series of visits that I made along the proposed London-West Midlands line, we have altered around half the original route, significantly reducing the potential local environmental impacts.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.3/8">In the Chilterns area of outstanding natural beauty, all but 1.2 miles would be in tunnel, cutting, or close to the A413 road corridor. Since HS2 Ltd's original report to Government was published in March 2010, the number of properties where high noise levels would be expected to be experienced has fallen from 350 to around 10.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.3/9">In December 2010, I set out our proposed high speed rail strategy, our preferred route and our approach to delivering a wider high speed network. However, we recognise that decisions should not be taken on a major infrastructure project of this scale until all those with an interest have had their say. So this consultation, which will run until <phrase class="date" code="2011-07-29">29 July</phrase>, seeks views on: the case for high speed rail; our strategy for a national high speed network; the proposed route for an initial line from London to the West Midlands; and our options for providing assistance to those who are detrimentally affected by any new line. Responses can be submitted through the HS2 Consultation website, or sent to a freepost address.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.3/10">Copies of the consultation document have been placed in the Library of the House and are available on the DfT website. I am also publishing a number of more detailed supporting documents, including a detailed economic case, a full appraisal of sustainability and a route engineering report.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.3/11">My department will be conducting a series of regional seminars to inform the strategic debate, together with a series of roadshows along the line of the proposed London-West Midlands route. These will give people the chance to discuss our plans and the specific local impacts and mitigation proposals with the engineers and other specialists working on the project.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.3/12">This is a once-in-a-generation infrastructure investment that would have a transformational effect on Britain's economy. Civic leaders of all political persuasions and business leaders from all parts of the United Kingdom support it. I urge all honourable Members with an interest to encourage their constituents to participate in the consultation. I will announce the outcome of this consultation process and the Government's decisions on our strategy for high speed rail before the end of 2011.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.102.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="102"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000732">
	Railways: Local and Regional Services
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.102.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100028" speakername="Earl Attlee" colon=":" colnum="102"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000657">
	<p pid="a.102.1/1">My right honourable friend the Minister of State for Transport (Theresa Villiers) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.102.1/2">Local authorities and integrated transport authorities from time to time wish to develop proposals for new or enhanced rail services where, in their view, they offer the best way of meeting the transport needs of their area. They have the necessary powers to secure the provision of such services but they are sometimes inhibited by the risk that significant revenue funding may need to be committed over the long term. I am keen to encourage local bodies to identify the best solutions for identified local needs and therefore wish to ensure that they are not deterred from considering an improved rail service where it clearly offers value for money.</p>
	<p pid="a.102.1/3">The Government's priority remains one of reducing the budget deficit, and therefore careful consideration has to be given to any proposal which might increase the cost of the railway, in either the short or long term. However, we recognise the arguments put forward by promoters that regional and local rail services need to adapt to population, housing and economic growth in localities. Therefore, it is only right that, once they have demonstrated value for money after a trial period, new or improved services promoted by local authorities are treated in a similar way to the more established services which are currently funded as part of the national network.</p>
	<p pid="a.102.1/4">I would therefore like to announce to the House that the Government still intend to fund the provision of new or enhanced services promoted by authorities which have rail industry support but, in view of the tough financial decisions made as part of the spending review, no such funding will be provided prior to April 2015 (the start of the next spending review period).</p>
	<p pid="a.102.1/5">It is important that the promoter demonstrates that a rail scheme is the best way to address regional and local transport issues; hence promoters would still be expected to fund a new or enhanced service for the first three years to demonstrate their commitment to the service and show that it delivers value for money in the light of actual experience.</p>
	<p pid="a.102.1/6">Schemes which the department would consider funding in this way would be subject to a number of conditions, details of which have been deposited in the Library of the House and will be made available on the Department for Transport's web site.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.103.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="103"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000733">
	Rural Development
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.103.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100286" speakername="Lord Henley" colon=":" colnum="103"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000663">
	<p pid="a.103.1/1">My right honourable friend the Minister for Agriculture and Food (James Paice) has today made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.103.1/2">I am today announcing a series of changes that I will be making to the operation and delivery of the socioeconomic elements of the Rural Development Programme for England 2007-13 (RDPE), which are currently delivered by the Regional Development Agencies.</p>
	<p pid="a.103.1/3">Future responsibility for delivery of support for farming and forestry competitiveness, diversification of the rural economy and rural quality of life under Axis 1 and 3 of the RDPE, and for management of the community-led Leader approach, will transfer from the eight existing RDAs to Defra. This will ensure continuity and consistency of delivery for customers, and compliance with the relevant European regulations.</p>
	<p pid="a.103.1/4">As responsibility transfers to Defra, I shall be looking to move as quickly as possible towards a more consistent national approach to delivery of the programme, with a clear focus on the Government's priorities for farming and forestry competitiveness and the needs of rural areas, managed nationally and delivered in a way which provides locally accessible support. So I have decided that we should aim to locate the RDPE teams in their existing towns or cities initially where that is cost-effective. In order to ensure as smooth a transition as possible, I will be introducing changes to the administration of the programme on a staggered basis from <phrase class="date" code="2011-07-01">1 July</phrase>. These will deliver a more consistent national approach and efficiency savings for the taxpayer, including moving away from existing regions as the key governance tier.</p>
	<p pid="a.103.1/5">We will engage further with stakeholders and customers about changes to the programme, building on the existing programme governance at the regional and national levels.</p>
	<p pid="a.103.1/6">I have now informed RDAs of their indicative budget allocations for 2011-12. I am pleased that, following the Spending Review, we are able to continue to deliver funding under Axis 1 and 3 and Leader over the remainder of the programme period. But budgets are constrained and I have asked RDAs to ensure that the funding available is focused on delivering against our key priorities for competitiveness and rural areas, whilst also beginning the process of putting in place the new nationally consistent approach to delivery in 2011-12. RDAs will inform applicants and local action groups of the position within their region. Customers should continue to remain in touch with their existing contacts within the RDAs for further information about the position on individual projects or applications.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.104.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="104"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000734">
	Terrorism: Finance
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.104.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/101012" speakername="Lord Sassoon" colon=":" colnum="104"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000669">
	<p pid="a.104.1/1">My honourable friend the Financial Secretary to the Treasury (Mark Hoban) has today made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/2">The Government are committed to reporting quarterly on the operation of the UK's terrorist asset-freezing regime. We believe this is essential to ensure transparency and accountability of the regime. The Terrorist Asset-Freezing etc. Act 2010 has enshrined in law the commitment to report quarterly to Parliament on the operation of the regime mandated by UN Security Council Resolution 1373.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/3">This report covers the period October to December 2010<sup>1</sup>. It is the last to cover the operation of the regime under the Terrorism (United Nations Measures) Order 2009, which was repealed on <phrase class="date" code="2011-12-17">17 December</phrase> when the Terrorist Asset-Freezing etc. Act came into force, and it also covers the first two weeks of the operation of the new Act.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/4">The new Act strengthens civil liberties safeguards and makes the new regime fairer, more proportionate and more transparent. A copy of the Act can be found on the HM Treasury's website: <a href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/fin_sanctions_terrorist.htm">www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/fin_sanctions_terrorist.htm</a></p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/5">The report also covers the operation of the UN al-Qaeda and Taliban asset-freezing regime.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/6">As of <phrase class="date" code="2010-12-31">31 December 2010</phrase>, a total of just under &#163;280,000<sup>2</sup> of funds relating to terrorism were frozen in the UK. This covers funds frozen under the UK's domestic terrorist asset-freezing regime, mandated by UN Security Council Resolution 1373, and also funds frozen under the UN al-Qaeda and Taliban asset freezing regime, mandated by UN Security Council Resolution 1267.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/7">(1) UK's domestic terrorist asset-freezing regime</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/8">As of <phrase class="date" code="2010-12-31">31 December 2010</phrase>, a total of 91 accounts containing just under &#163;140,000 were frozen in the UK under the domestic terrorist asset freezing regime mandated by UNSCR 1373.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/9">Operation of the Terrorism (United Nations Measures) Order 2009 (prior to <phrase class="date" code="2010-12-17">17 December 2010</phrase>)</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/10"><I>Asset-freezing designations</I></p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/11">In the quarter October to December 2010, the Treasury gave no new directions under the 2009 order.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/12"><I>Reviews under the 2009 Order</I></p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/13">The Treasury keeps domestic asset-freezing cases under review and completed 38 reviews in this quarter. As a result of these 38 reviews, six persons had their designations revoked.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/14"><I>Licensing</I></p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/15">Maintaining an effective licensing system is important to ensure the overall proportionality and fairness of the asset-freezing regime, whether the individuals concerned are subject to an asset freeze in accordance with a UN or EU listing, or domestic terrorism legislation. A licensing framework is put in place for each person on a case-by-case basis. The key objective of the licensing system is to strike an appropriate balance between minimising the risk of diversion of funds to terrorism and meeting the human rights of affected persons and their families. Licences contain appropriate controls to protect against the risk of the diversion of funds for terrorist finance.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/16">Four licences were issued this quarter in relation to four persons subject to an asset freeze under the 2009 order.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/17">In addition to issuing licences relating to a specific person, the Treasury may also issue general licences, which apply to all persons designated under a particular regime or regimes. Licences are granted where there is a legitimate need for such transactions to proceed and where they can proceed without giving rise to any risk of terrorist finance.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/18">One general licence was issued this quarter to allow third parties to pay a designated person's legal expenses under both the Act and the al-Qaeda and Taliban asset-freezing regime.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/19">No licences were varied or revoked this quarter.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/20"><I>Legal Challenges</I></p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/21">Two legal challenges against designations made under the 2009 Order were ongoing in the last quarter.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/22">Operation of the Terrorist Asset Freezing etc Act 2010 (after <phrase class="date" code="2010-12-17">17 December 2010</phrase>)</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/23">The Act contains a transitional provision that ensures that all designations and licences made under the 2009 order remain valid as final designations under the Act until <phrase class="date" code="2011-03-17">17 March 2011</phrase>. All UK asset freezes are therefore currently under review to consider whether they should be renewed under the new Act. The review process will be completed by <phrase class="date" code="2011-03-17">17 March 2011</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/24">No new designations or licences were made under the powers of the Act between <phrase class="date" code="2011-12-17">17 December</phrase> and the end of the quarter.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/25"><I>The Independent Reviewer</I></p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/26">Under the Act the Treasury is required to appoint an independent reviewer to review the operation of the domestic terrorist asset-freezing regime. The independent reviewer will report on the first nine months of the regime and every 12 months thereafter.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/27">The Treasury has decided to appoint David Anderson QC to the role of Independent Reviewer. He has recently been appointed by the Home Office as the independent reviewer of counter-terrorism legislation.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/28">(2) UN al-Qaeda and Taliban Asset Freezing Regime</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/29">The UN al-Qaeda and Taliban asset-freezing regime is implemented in the UK through EC Regulation 881/2002. Enforcement measures are provided for in the UK's Al-Qaeda and Taliban (Asset-Freezing) Regulations 2010.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/30">As of <phrase class="date" code="2010-12-31">31 December 2010</phrase>, a total of 112 accounts containing just under &#163;140,000<sup>3</sup> were frozen in the UK under the al-Qaeda and Taliban asset-freezing regime.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/31" class="indent"><sup>1</sup> The detail that can be provided to the House on a quarterly basis is subject to the need to avoid the identification, directly or indirectly, of personal or operationally sensitive information.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/32" class="indent"><sup>2</sup> This figure reflects the most updated account balances available and includes approximately $64,000 of suspected terrorist funds frozen in the UK. This has been converted using exchange rates as of <phrase class="date" code="2011-01-12">12 January 2011</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.1/33" class="indent"><sup>3</sup> Includes approximately $64,000 of suspected terrorist funds in the UK.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.106.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="106"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000735">
	Turks and Caicos Islands
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2011-02-28a.106.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100917" speakername="Baroness Verma" colon=":" colnum="106"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/110228-wms0001.htm#11022821000699">
	<p pid="a.106.1/1">My right honourable friend the Minister of State for International Development (Mr Alan Duncan) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.106.1/2">Further to the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs' (Henry Bellingham MP) Written Statement of <phrase class="date" code="2011-12-09">9 December</phrase> and the Department for International Development's Minute of <phrase class="date" code="2011-02-03">3 February</phrase> notifying Parliament that the Secretary of State for International Development had approved in principle a loan guarantee to the Turks and Caicos Islands Government (TCIG), I would like to update the House.</p>
	<p pid="a.106.1/3">The Department for International Development (DFID) has now finalised a guarantee in favour of Scotiabank (Turks and Caicos) Ltd to provide TCIG with access to a maximum capital amount of US$260 million over the next five years. I confirm that TCIG will immediately repay DfID its loan of &#163;29.9 million plus interest.</p>
	<p pid="a.106.1/4">This level of commercial borrowing is vital if TCIG is to turn around its dire financial situation. It will provide the time TCIG needs to implement budget measures which will lead to achieving a fiscal surplus in the financial year ending March 2013. As PUSS Bellingham and I reported to Parliament on <phrase class="date" code="2010-12-09">9 December 2010</phrase>, this is one of a number of key milestones to be reached before a date for elections can be set. Once the territory is in fiscal surplus it will be able to start to pay off its debt and should, after the five year period is over, if not before, be able to secure new and reduced bank lending without the need for a UK Government guarantee.</p>
	<p pid="a.106.1/5">The guarantee is intended to cost the UK taxpayer nothing. It will ensure that TCI does not fall victim to financial ruin and it is in line with DfID's responsibility to underpin the reasonable needs of all British Overseas Territories.</p>
	<p pid="a.106.1/6">The current Chief Financial Officer has done an excellent job in getting a grip on TCIG's public finances. To ensure that the financial plan stays on track to achieve a fiscal surplus, DfID reserves the right to require TCIG to retain the position of Chief Financial Officer for as long as the guarantee is in force and to nominate the holder of this post who shall then be appointed by the Governor.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

