<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">

<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >

<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >

<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >

<!ENTITY euro "&#8364;" >
]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="b" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-21b.1.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="1"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050321/text/50321-45.htm#50321-45_spnew4">
	Legal Services Reform
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-21b.1.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100203" speakername="Lord Falconer of Thoroton" colon=":" colnum="1"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050321/text/50321-45.htm#50321-46_spmin0">
	<p pid="b.1.1/1">On <phrase class="date" code="2004-12-15">15 December 2004</phrase>, I informed the House that I had warmly welcomed Sir David Clementi's report on the regulation of legal services in England and Wales and broadly accepted his main recommendations. Since publication of the report, I have met key stakeholders, including consumer groups, a number of times. In the course of these meetings we have built a strong consensus in support of consumer-focused reform of legal services.</p>
	<p pid="b.1.1/2">I will publish a White Paper later this year. I will set out detailed proposals for a legal services board. Regulatory powers will be vested in the board, and delegated by it to the professional bodies, as long as they meet the standards the board sets. The professional bodies will be required to separate their regulatory and representative functions.</p>
	<p pid="b.1.1/3">The White Paper will set out the arrangements for appointing members to the legal services board, and will propose a lay chair and a lay majority with appointments being made on merit, by the Secretary of State for Constitutional Affairs. The board will have a range of sanctions available. The White Paper will set these out, but I expect them to include setting targets, imposing fines, issuing guidance, directing a professional body and removing one or more regulatory powers, with the board ultimately having the power to remove regulatory powers from any professional body which has failed. Taken together, these arrangements provide a robust framework that will promote consumer interests.</p>
	<p pid="b.1.1/4">I accept Sir David's recommendation for an office for legal complaints. This will be simpler for consumers to use and understand and will provide consistent, fair and professional handling of cases for all complainants. As with the legal services board, the White Paper will set out the detailed arrangements, but I expect the office will also be led by a board with a lay chair and a lay majority.</p>
	<p pid="b.1.1/5">I warmly welcome Sir David's proposals to facilitate the creation of new business structures. Non-lawyers will be able for the first time to become managers, owners or investors in legal practices. This will create an opportunity to bring in new capital and develop new ways of working that should benefit consumers. Robust safeguards will be established to protect the consumer and the profession's reputation.</p>
	<p pid="b.1.1/6">Many of the changes that will be outlined in the White Paper will require legislation and I intend to bring forward that legislation when parliamentary time allows. I am committed to legislating to bring the regulatory framework I have described into full effect.</p>
	<p pid="b.1.1/7">I can announce today that I have set up a consumer panel to advise the Government as we take forward reforms. The panel will comprise representatives from Citizens Advice, the Federation of Small Businesses, the National Consumer Council, the Welsh Consumer Council and <i>Which?</i>.</p>
	<p pid="b.1.1/8">Going forward, I will continue to work closely with all interested parties to ensure that we establish a new framework for the regulation of legal services that protects and promotes the needs of consumers and allows the legal profession to flourish and retain its reputation as the best in the world.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-21b.4.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="4"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050321/text/50321-45.htm#50321-46_spmin2">
	Horseracing: Funding
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-21b.4.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100399" speakername="Lord McIntosh of Haringey" colon=":" colnum="4"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050321/text/50321-45.htm#50321-46_spnew0">
	<p pid="b.4.1/1">My right honourable friend the Minister of State for Sport and Tourism (Mr. Richard Caborn) made the following Written Ministerial Statement on <phrase class="date" code="2006-03-18">18 March</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="b.4.1/2">It remains the Government's view that commercial agreements between the relevant parties provide the appropriate long-term basis for the funding of racing. However, in the light of a judgment by the European Court of Justice last September it has become clear that the British Horseracing Board is not in a position to proceed immediately with its plans to fund racing by the sale of database rights in place of the current statutory levy. Following consultations with the Horserace Betting Levy Board, the British Horseracing Board and the Association of British Bookmakers, I have therefore accepted the interim recommendations made by the independent review group, chaired by Lord Donoughue, that more time is needed to develop the commercial options and that it is in the public interest in the well-being of the sport that the levy arrangements should therefore remain in place for a further limited period. We will accordingly be making an order under Part 2 of the Horserace Betting and Olympic Lottery Act 2004 to end the levy on <phrase class="date" code="">31 March 2009</phrase>, and to close the levy board six months later.</p>
	<p pid="b.4.1/3">I welcome the agreement of the parties that Lord Donoughue's group should continue to explore the commercial options, considering all areas relating to the funding of racing which it believes are relevant to establishing appropriate post-levy arrangements, with a view to preparing a final report this autumn. It will then be for the British Horseracing Board and the other parties to work towards putting agreed arrangements in place to meet the above timescale.</p>
	<p pid="b.4.1/4">In the mean time it is important that racing continues to take forward the modernisation of its structures, with priority being given to the establishment of an independent regulatory authority.</p>
	<p pid="b.4.1/5">It is also important that, both now and after the ending of the levy arrangements, there continues to be proper financial support for the advancement of veterinary science and education and for the improvement of breeds of horses, which are the levy board's other statutory purposes. I have therefore made clear the Government's wish to see the board, while it continues in being, take over the funding commitments previously given by the British Horseracing Board in respect of the Equine Fertility Unit and the equine genome project; to maintain support for veterinary science and education at 2.5 per cent of levy income and for breed societies at no less than current levels; to take forward consideration of the establishment of a university chair in the field of equine veterinary science; and to complete the grant to the national stud, for which budget provision was previously made, on the stud's proposed re-establishment as an independent charitable trust.</p>
	<p pid="b.4.1/6">I wish to place on record my appreciation of the work of the members and staff of the levy board, who have been contending with an extended period of uncertainty, and of their commitment to running the levy arrangements effectively for longer than had previously been expected.</p>
	<p pid="b.4.1/7">I am aware that other sports, particularly football, have also been affected by the ECJ judgment. I have met with representatives from the football industry and I look forward to working with them, as I have done with racing, as they develop their own solutions to the funding difficulties arising from this ruling.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-21b.7.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="7"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050321/text/50321-47.htm#50321-47_spmin0">
	Department of Health: Arm's Length Bodies
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2005-03-21b.7.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100670" speakername="Lord Warner" colon=":" colnum="7"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo050321/text/50321-47.htm#50321-47_spmin1">
	<p pid="b.7.1/1">My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for Health made the following Written Ministerial Statement on <phrase class="date" code="2006-03-18">18 March</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/2">On <phrase class="date" code="2004-11-30">30 November 2004</phrase> (<i>Official Report</i>, cols. <i>24&ndash;27 WS</i>) I announced the publication of an Implementation Framework for Reconfiguring the Department of Health's Arm's Length Bodies (ALBs) and achieving its three overarching objectives:</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/3" class="indent">a 50 per cent reduction in the number of ALBs;</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/4" class="indent">a saving in expenditure by ALBs of &pound;0.5 billion by 2007&ndash;08; and</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/5" class="indent">a reduction in posts of 25 per cent in the same period.</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/6">The ALB change programme is part of a wider programme to improve efficiency and cut bureaucracy in the management of the National Health Service. The aim of these activities is to reduce the burden on the front line and free up more resources for the delivery of front line services to patients and users. This wider programme is to ensure that the increased investment in the NHS&mdash;42 per cent in real terms from 2003&ndash;04 to 2007&ndash;08&mdash;is accompanied by modernisation that cuts out waste.</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/7">Today I am announcing the achievement of a further milestone towards the ALB change programme's key objectives. In November 2004 we made the following commitment as a first step towards our savings target on ALB expenditure:</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/8" class="indent">&quot;Even with these new functions, which bring new costs, we will be setting the 2005&ndash;06 budget for the ALB sector so that it will cost about &pound;100 million a year less to run than in 2003-04.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/9">I am pleased to report that I am today setting budgets for the operating costs of ALBs for 2005&ndash;06 which will reduce Department of Health funding by in excess of &pound;150 million compared with 2003&ndash;04. This is despite the fact that in 2004&ndash;05 the ALB sector assumed new functions agreed by Parliament that increased the sector's costs substantially. A significant proportion of the savings generated in Department of Health funding will be redeployed for investment in front line healthcare. We have additionally provided some &pound;50 million to fund one-off identified costs in ALBs. This includes initiatives which will deliver savings in future years and enable us to continue the downward trend in operating costs for the ALB sector when we set budgets for 2006&ndash;07 and 2007&ndash;08.</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/10">In setting the 2005&ndash;06 budgets, we have:</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/11" class="indent">invested in ALBs which deliver front line healthcare, like the National Blood Authority (an increase in Department of Health funding of more than &pound;38 million over 2003&ndash;04), or carry out crucial work to protect public health, like the Health Protection Agency (an increase in Department of Health funding of more than &pound;36 million over 2003&ndash;04);</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/12" class="indent">achieved the greatest savings in ALBs which provide central services to front line NHS organisations. The reduction in Department of Health funding for this group of ALBs comes to more than &pound;220 million compared to 2003-04 and provides a lower cost-base for overheads in future years; and</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/13" class="indent">met our commitment that spending on ALBs undertaking inspection and regulation will not exceed 0.4 per cent of the national spend on the NHS and social care and made progress on our policy of full cost-recovery for work relating to the independent health and social care sector.</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/14">Alongside these savings, we are also on course for ALBs to generate very substantial savings for the NHS front line by improving the efficiency of the services they provide centrally on behalf of the NHS.</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/15">We expect to generate further savings of over &pound;100 million in 2005&ndash;06 from new national framework agreements let by the NHS Purchasing and Supply Agency (PASA) alone. This follows savings of over &pound;25 million in 2004&ndash;05. PASA is on target to achieve savings of &pound;240 million per annum by 2007&ndash;08 for the NHS. Work is also under way to deliver efficiencies in the services offered by other ALBS. Taken together, this puts us well on course to meet or exceed our commitment to deliver &pound;250 million to the front line by the end of 2007&ndash;08 through efficiencies generated by ALBs, as promised in the <phrase class="date" code="2004-11-30">30 November 2004</phrase> implementation framework.</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/16">The major reconfiguration of individual ALBs is also on course. The total number of ALBs will have reduced from 38 in 2003&ndash;04 to 34 on <phrase class="date" code="">1 April</phrase> and is on course to reduce further to 31 by <phrase class="date" code="">1 October</phrase> this year. The changes are:</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/17" class="indent">the Family Health Services Appeal Authority (SHA) (FHSAA SHA) will be dissolved on <phrase class="date" code="">1 April</phrase> and its functions absorbed by the NHS Litigation Authority (NHSLA);</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/18" class="indent">the Health Development Agency (HDA) will be dissolved on <phrase class="date" code="">1 April</phrase> and its functions absorbed by the National Institute for Clinical Excellence (NICE);</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/19" class="indent">the National Clinical Assessment Authority (NCAA) will be dissolved on <phrase class="date" code="">1 April</phrase> and its functions transferred to the National Patient Safety Agency (NPSA);</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/20" class="indent">the NHS Information Authority (NHSIA) will be dissolved on <phrase class="date" code="">1 April</phrase> and certain functions transferred to the Health and Social Care Information Centre (HSCIC) and to the National Programme for IT (NPfIT);</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/21" class="indent">the National Radiological Protection Board (NRPB) will be dissolved on <phrase class="date" code="">1 April</phrase> and its functions transferred to the Health Protection Agency (HPA);</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/22" class="indent">The Public Health Laboratory Service (PHLS) will be dissolved on <phrase class="date" code="">1 April</phrase> and its functions transferred to the Health Protection Agency (HPA);</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/23" class="indent">the Human Tissue Authority (HTA) will be created on <phrase class="date" code="">1 April</phrase> and work closely with the Human Fertilisation and Embryology Authority (HFEA) ahead of the merger of the two bodies to form the Regulatory Authority for Tissue and Embryos (RATE) which requires new legislation;</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/24" class="indent">the Health and Social Care Information Centre (HSCIC) will come into being on <phrase class="date" code="">1 April</phrase> to co-ordinate information requirements across health and social care more efficiently;</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/25" class="indent">the National Programme for IT (NPfIT) will become an agency on <phrase class="date" code="">1 April</phrase>;</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/26" class="indent">the NHS Modernisation Agency and NHSU are due to be dissolved by <phrase class="date" code="2005-07-31">31 July 2005</phrase> and some of their functions taken on by the new NHS Institute for Learning, Skills and Innovation which is due to be set up by the same date;</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/27" class="indent">the National Blood Authority and UK Transplant will be merged and become NHS Blood and Transplant by <phrase class="date" code="2005-10-01">1 October 2005</phrase>; and</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/28" class="indent">NHS Estates is being wound down and will be dissolved no later than <phrase class="date" code="">1 October</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/29">Following is a table showing the 2005&ndash;06 recurrent operating costs budgets for 33 of the ALBs which will exist on <phrase class="date" code="">1 April</phrase> this year. The total of those budgets includes &pound;1,107 million grant in aid from the Department of Health, as well as income from other sources, such as fees charged to industry. The total grant in aid provided by the department in 2003&ndash;04 was &pound;1,265 million. Therefore the 2005&ndash;06 grant in aid is over &pound;150 million less than that included in 2003&ndash;04 operating costs. We have additionally funded &pound;50 million one-off costs in order to enable further recurrent savings in later years.</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/30">These changes are only the first part of our plan for reconfiguring the ALB sector. Over the coming year we will:</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/31" class="indent">drive forward further major reconfigurations of ALBs so that total numbers in the sector are reduced to 24 by April 2006;</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/32" class="indent">maintain momentum towards releasing at least &pound;0.5 billion for the front line by the end of 2007-08 through further reductions in overall;</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/33" class="indent">ALB budgets in 2006-07 and continued savings in the central services which ALBs provide on behalf of the NHS;</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/34" class="indent">as part of this, put in place firm plans for delivering further savings of &pound;35-40 million a year by 2007-08 through efficiencies in ALB overheads (for example back office services and accommodation), in line with the expectations set out in the Gershon review;</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/35" class="indent">make further reductions in the proportion of national spend on the NHS and social care which goes on inspection and regulation and make further progress on full cost recovery; and</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/36" class="indent">take forward the commitment in Wednesday's Budget announcement to bring together the Healthcare Commission and the Commission for Social Care Inspection by 2008.</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/37">The ALB budgets we are setting for 2005-06 will reduce Department of Health funding by more than &pound;150 million compared with 2003-04. The resulting savings will contribute to our overall investment in NHS front line healthcare. Taken together with growing efficiencies in services provided by ALBs to the wider NHS they place the sector on a firm footing to achieve the target of &pound;500 million savings by the end of 2007&ndash;08.</p>
	<table>
		<caption>ALB Recurrent Operating Costs 2005&ndash;06 -- 17 March 2005</caption>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/41"> <td></td> <td>Operating Costs 2005-06 excluding non-recurrent elements</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/42"> <td>ALB name</td> <td>&pound;000</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/43"> <td>Regulators</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/44"> <td>HC1</td> <td>78,732</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/45"> <td>MHAC</td> <td>5,218</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/46"> <td>Monitor</td> <td>12,000</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/47"> <td>CSCI1</td> <td>144,260</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/48"> <td>HFEA</td> <td>8,421</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/49"> <td>HTA</td> <td>1,000</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/50"> <td>CRHE</td> <td>1,950</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/51"> <td>GSCC</td> <td>14,310</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/52"> <td>PMETB</td> <td>6,742</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/53"> <td>DVTA</td> <td>281</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/54"> <td>MHRA</td> <td>62,970</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/55"> <td>Standards</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/56"> <td>NICE</td> <td>29,894</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/57"> <td>HdA</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/58"> <td>Public Welfare</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/59"> <td>NPSA</td> <td>28,618</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/60"> <td>NCAA</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/61"> <td>HPA</td> <td>228,600</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/62"> <td>NRPB</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/63"> <td>PHLS</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/64"> <td>NBSB</td> <td>19,739</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/65"> <td>NTA</td> <td>11,510</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/66"> <td>CPPIH</td> <td>29,930</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/67"> <td>Central Services</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/68"> <td>NBA (inc. BPL)</td> <td>401,700</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/69"> <td>UKT</td> <td>13,572</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/70"> <td>NHS LA</td> <td>14,095</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/71"> <td>FHSAA</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/72"> <td>NHS AC</td> <td>5,981</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/73"> <td>NILSI</td> <td>80,000</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/74"> <td>NHSU</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/75"> <td>NHS MOD</td> <td>0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/76"> <td>NHS IA/HSCIC</td> <td>42,900</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/77"> <td>DPB</td> <td>23,062</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/78"> <td>PPA</td> <td>75,606</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/79"> <td>NHS CFSMS</td> <td>14,897</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/80"> <td>NHS PA</td> <td>22,066</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/81"> <td>NHS PASA</td> <td>22,081</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/82"> <td>NHS LOGS</td> <td>70,658</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/83"> <td>NHS DIRECT</td> <td>161,900</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/84"> <td>NHS PROF</td> <td>31,000</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/85"> <td>NHS EST</td> <td>1,000</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/86"> <td>NPFIT</td> <td>115,230</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.7.1/87"> <td>Total</td> <td>1,779,923</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="b.7.1/90">Notes:</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/91">1 Operating costs exclude capital charges but include income from other sources, such as fee income, as well as DH funding.</p>
	<p pid="b.7.1/92">2 NHS Estates to be dissolved by <phrase class="date" code="2005-10-01">1 October 2005</phrase>&mdash;one off DH funding of &pound;17.9 million. Operating costs are transfers to other ALBs.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

