<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">

<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >

<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >

<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >

<!ENTITY euro "&#8364;" >
]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.121.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="121"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-63.htm#40916-63_head0">
	Incident in Commons Chamber
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.121.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="121"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-63.htm#40916-63_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.121.1/1">The House will wish to know that, after consultation through the usual channels, I have today sent the following letter to the Speaker of the House of Commons:</p>
	<p pid="a.121.1/2">&quot;On behalf of the whole House of Lords, I write to let you know that we utterly condemn the invasion yesterday of the Chamber of the House of Commons.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.1/3">Please be assured of this House's full co-operation in considering the implications of this incident for the security of Parliament. I look forward to continuing to work with you and others on this.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.1/4">The House of Lords is fully committed, with you and the House of Commons, to maintaining the parliamentary process in the face of disorder and disruption&quot;.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.121.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="121"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-63.htm#40916-63_spnew8">
	Iraq: Reconstruction
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.121.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="121"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-63.htm#40916-64_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.121.3/1">My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for International Development has made the following Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.3/2">I visited Baghdad and Basra from <phrase class="date" code="">31 August</phrase> to <phrase class="date" code="">1 September</phrase> to learn for myself about progress with reconstruction on the ground. I met Prime Minister Allawi, development Ministers, representatives from the United Nations, civil society and the Independent Electoral Commission of Iraq, and representatives from local government.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.3/3">The interim Iraqi Government are now clearly in charge, although recent events in Najaf have dominated their first months in power. The difficult security situation has inevitably slowed down the reconstruction effort of not just the UK, but also other donors and the multilateral agencies. However, it was clear that progress is still being made. 45 kilometres of water pipes have been laid in Basra since my last visit in February and electricity distribution is now more equitable across the national grid. Partially due to these efforts, the riots that happened in Basra last summer because of the lack of basic services have not reoccurred this year.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.3/4">While in Iraq I announced a number of new UK bilateral projects, focusing on building the capacity of the Iraqi administration, and promoting employment creation, in southern Iraq. These projects mark an important step forward in our reconstruction efforts in southern Iraq as we move from meeting short-term humanitarian and immediate infrastructure rehabilitation needs towards addressing longer-term development challenges. Southern Iraq should receive massive reconstruction funds over next two to three years from a range of sources, including the USA, Japan and the World Bank and UN trust funds. One of DFID's aims is to help the Iraqi administration to ensure that this money is spent quickly and well, and that the benefits of reconstruction are widely shared across the population. We are investing &pound;20.5 million in strengthening local management, planning and financial capacity in the four southern governorates of Basra, Muthanna, Dhi Qar and Maysan, including &pound;15 million for projects developed by the governorates. We have also started a new &pound;16.5 million programme to finance employment programmes and further emergency infrastructure repairs.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.3/5">DfID has committed &pound;331 million to humanitarian and reconstruction assistance in Iraq since March 2003. Of this total &pound;78 million has been allocated to bilateral reconstruction projects in southern Iraq; &pound;19 million to support for the new interim Iraqi Government, the justice sector, independent media, civil society and political participation; and &pound;28 million for consultants and secondments to the Coalition Provisional Authority while it was in office up to <phrase class="date" code="">28 June</phrase>. &pound;70 million has been paid into the trust funds managed by the United Nations and the World Bank, to be spent primarily on health, education, water and sanitation projects, assistance for refugees and strengthening governance; and nearly &pound;12 million has been committed to IMF and International Finance Corporation programmes for economic governance support and small business development. Updates on DfID's programmes can be found on the Internet at <a href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk">www.dfid.gov.uk</a>, as well as in the House Library.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.3/6">As on my previous two visits to Iraq, I was impressed by the extraordinary courage and commitment of all the people, both international and Iraqi, who are working to help the new Iraqi Government and the people of Iraq to build the better future that they deserve.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.125.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="125"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-63.htm#40916-64_head1">
	Post-Conflict Reconstruction Unit
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.125.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="125"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-63.htm#40916-64_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.125.1/1">My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for International Development has made the following Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.125.1/2">Together with the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the Secretary of State for Defence, I wish to inform Parliament of the Government's intention to improve the United Kingdom's capacity to deal with immediate post-conflict stabilisation, including by integrating civilian and military policy, planning and operations. In recent years, the United Kingdom, with the international community, has been increasingly involved in helping countries to stabilise after conflict. We need to deal better with conflict and instability, learn lessons and improve our capability to respond. Within this broader context, there is particular scope to improve the way in which we deal with immediate post-conflict situations, especially those which include military and civilian components. The Foreign and Commonwealth Office, Ministry of Defence and Department for International Development are working closely to develop the capabilities that are needed. The Foreign Secretary will chair a new Cabinet Sub-Committee on Post-Conflict Reconstruction. My right honourable friends and I expect to be in a position formally to establish an inter-departmental Post-Conflict Reconstruction Unit later this year to lead this work. It will have a policy and operational role. In spring 2005 we anticipate being able to inform Parliament about its initial capabilities. Meanwhile, my right honourable friends and I have placed a note in the House of Commons Library which provides more detail about the Government's aims and plans.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.126.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="126"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-63.htm#40916-64_head2">
	Pakistan: Cancellation of Ex-CDC Debt
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.126.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="126"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-63.htm#40916-64_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.126.1/1">My honourable friend the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for International Development (Mr Gareth Thomas) has made the following Statement:</p>
	<p pid="a.126.1/2">On <phrase class="date" code="2004-09-15">15 September 2004</phrase>, The Secretary of State for International Development wrote to Shaukat Aziz, Pakistan Prime Minister and Minister of Finance, to notify him that DfID has now cancelled Pakistan's ex-CDC debt amounting to &pound;19 million.</p>
	<p pid="a.126.1/3">The outstanding loans made by the former Commonwealth Development Corporation to public sector bodies in developing countries were removed from the newly formed CDC Capital Partners balance sheet on <phrase class="date" code="2000-08-31">31 August 2000</phrase> and transferred to DfID. In the case of Pakistan, the loan concerned was to the Karachi Water and Sewerage Board.</p>
	<p pid="a.126.1/4">The only other inter-governmental debt between the UK and Pakistan relates to export credit guarantees. Following the Paris Club agreement, this debt was rescheduled and is now valued at only &pound;9 million.</p>
	<p pid="a.126.1/5">In 2001 DfID agreed to cancel the ex-CDC debt, subject to Pakistan completing the second review of the poverty reduction growth facility (PRGF) with the International Monetary Fund. In the interim, the debt was suspended with no interest payments required from Pakistan to DfID. On <phrase class="date" code="2004-06-23">23 June 2004</phrase> the IMF executive board successfully completed the second annual review of Pakistan's PRGF, implying the ex-CDC debt can now be cancelled.</p>
	<p pid="a.126.1/6">The Pakistan programme continues to be a high priority for DfID. As announced to the House in March 2003, during 2003 DfID provided Pakistan with &pound;55 million to cancel debt held with the Asian Development Bank, World Bank and International Monetary Fund. Over the next two years (2004&ndash;05 and 2005&ndash;06), DfID's assistance to Pakistan will be &pound;70 million and &pound;74 million respectively. This will support the Government of Pakistan in achieving the millennium development goals through the implementation of their poverty reduction strategy (published in December 2003). Priorities for DfID are increasing the incomes of poor people, improving service delivery to poor people and increasing accountability of the state to poor people.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.127.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-63.htm#40916-64_spnew3">
	Compensation Agency: Corporate Plan for 2004&ndash;07 and Business Plan for 2004&ndash;05
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.127.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100013" speakername="Baroness Amos" colon=":" colnum="127"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-63.htm#40916-64_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.127.1/1">My right honourable friend the Minister of State for the Northern Ireland Office has made the following Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/2">The Compensation Agency will publish today its corporate plan for 2004&ndash;07 and business plan for 2004&ndash;05. I have set the agency the following key performance targets for 2004 to 2005:</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/3" class="italic">Claims under the Criminal Damage (Compensation) (Northern Ireland) Order 1977</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/4">1. Maintain average time taken to reach decisions at 18 weeks for claims received from <phrase class="date" code="2004-04-01">1 April 2004</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/5">2. Reduce by 85 per cent the number of claims in hand at <phrase class="date" code="2004-03-31">31 March 2004</phrase> on which no decision has been reached; and</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/6">3.* Process claims under the Criminal Damage and Terrorism Act schemes at a combined average unit cost of &pound;310.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/7" class="italic">Claims under the Terrorism Act 2000</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/8">4. Reach decisions on claims in 70 days for claims received from <phrase class="date" code="2004-04-01">1 April 2004</phrase>;</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/9">5. Reduce by 90 per cent the number of claims in hand at <phrase class="date" code="2004-03-31">31 March 2004</phrase> on which no decision has been reached; and</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/10">3.* Process claims under the Criminal Damage and Terrorism Act schemes at the combined average unit cost of &pound;310.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/11">* This unit cost target relates to claims under the Criminal Damage and Terrorism Act schemes. The work involved in processing these claims is carried out in a single organisational unit within the agency so the efficiency of this element of the agency's operations is measured by reference to a combined unit cost target.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/12" class="italic">Claims under Criminal Injuries (Compensation) (Northern Ireland) Order 1988</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/13">6. Reduce by 45 per cent the number of claims in hand at <phrase class="date" code="2004-03-31">31 March 2004</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/14" class="italic">Claims under the Criminal Injuries Compensation (Northern Ireland) Order 2002 (Tariff)</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/15">7. Decide 50 per cent of all applications within 12 months of receiving the application.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/16">8. Reach decisions on applications at an average unit cost of &pound;280.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/17" class="italic">Compliance with Legislation/Standards of Adjudication&mdash;All Schemes</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/18">9. The agency's standards of adjudication are appropriate; which will be confirmed by the department's Internal Audit Branch through random sampling of claims.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/19" class="italic">Value for Money&mdash;All Schemes </p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/20">10. Manage the workload in 2004&ndash;05 within a running costs budget (to cover salaries and administrative expenditure) to financial limits agreed with the Department (including in-year adjustments).</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.128.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="128"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-65.htm#40916-65_head0">
	Treasury Solicitor: Annual Report and Accounts 2003&ndash;04
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.128.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100245" speakername="Lord Goldsmith" colon=":" colnum="128"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-65.htm#40916-65_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.128.1/1">The Treasury Solicitor's annual report and accounts 2003&ndash;04 have today been published and laid before Parliament. Copies have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.128.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="128"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-65.htm#40916-65_head1">
	North Korea
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.128.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="128"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-65.htm#40916-65_spmin1">
	<p pid="a.128.3/1">My honourable friend, the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Mr Bill Rammell) visited the Democratic People's Republic of Korea (DPRK or North Korea) from 11 to <phrase class="date" code="">14 September</phrase>. It was the first ever visit by a British Minister. He undertook the trip because the North Koreans had agreed, for the first time, to substantive discussions on the nuclear issue and human rights. He met Foreign Minister Paek Nam Sun, Chairman of the Supreme People's Assembly Chae Thae Bok, Human Rights Minister Choe Su Hon and Kim Gye Gwan, head of the DPRK's delegation to the six-party talks on dismantling North Korea's nuclear programme.</p>
	<p pid="a.128.3/2">Mr Rammell stressed to Foreign Minister Paek and chief negotiator Kim Gye Gwan the importance which the UK and the international community attach to the continuation of the six-party talks. For some time, it has been clear that the North Koreans might not proceed with the scheduled fourth round of talks by the end of September. The Foreign Minister restated the DPRK's commitment to the talks process, but admitted the DPRK's reluctance to meet again in September. Mr Rammell also impressed the need for the DPRK to admit its uranium enrichment programme, and encouraged the regime to look to the example of Libya.</p>
	<p pid="a.128.3/3">Before the visit, the FCO delegation consulted on the human rights situation with three leading NGOs&mdash;Amnesty International, Human Rights Watch and Christian Solidarity World-wide. Armed with detailed information on individual cases, Mr Rammell was able to hand to Human Rights Minister Choe Su Hon a list of 18 named individuals, and asked for a full written response. In particular, he raised the cases of two South Korean pastors reportedly abducted to the DPRK from China whose details we learnt about from Christian Solidarity World-wide. He handed over satellite photographs of what appear to be a number of large prison camps in the DPRK and asked for both an explanation and access to them by diplomats resident in Pyongyang. He also pressed for the North Koreans to allow visits, so far barred, by the recently appointed UN special rapporteur for human rights in the DPRK and by other thematic UN human rights special rapporteurs; and further visits by Foreign Office human rights experts. Mr Rammell hopes to hear more about this at the UN General Assembly next week when he will meet Choe Su Hon again to continue discussions. He repeatedly made the points that blanket denials by the North Koreans of alleged human rights violations were simply not credible.</p>
	<p pid="a.128.3/4">Mr Rammell's visit coincided with reports of a large explosion in the north of the country. Having asked for an explanation, Foreign Minister Peak said it was a planned explosion of a mountain for the construction of a hydro-electric power plant. He agreed to the request that diplomats might visit to see for themselves. The arrangements are now in hand. The British Ambassador visited the blast site today, we have asked for an urgent report on the visit.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.129.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="129"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-65.htm#40916-65_head2">
	Asylum Claimants and Detention Policy
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.129.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100574" speakername="Baroness Scotland of Asthal" colon=":" colnum="129"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-65.htm#40916-65_spmin2">
	<p pid="a.129.1/1">A key element in the Government's strategy to speed up the processing of asylum claims has been the introduction of the fast-track asylum processes operated initially at the Oakington Reception Centre and now also at Harmondsworth Removal Centre and other locations. The use of detention to fast-track suitable claims under these processes is necessary to achieve the objective of delivering decisions quickly. This ensures, among other things, that those whose claims can be quickly decided can be removed as quickly as possible in the event that the claim is unsuccessful.</p>
	<p pid="a.129.1/2">The lawfulness of detaining asylum claimants for the sole purpose of deciding their claims quickly was upheld by the Court of Appeal and by the House of Lords in the case of Saadi.</p>
	<p pid="a.129.1/3">When we began the fast-track process we said that it was our intention to detain asylum claimants suitable for a quick decision for a period of about seven to 10 days. If we could not decide the claim within that timescale, the claimant would be released or moved to another place of detention with the facilities to support people detained for longer periods. In the vast majority of cases, we have been able to do exactly that. However, the need to ensure a really sharp focus on quality decision making, including for example in non-suspensive appeal (NSA) cases the need for a second pair of eyes, means we cannot always make decisions and serve them on claimants within the original seven to 10 day target timescale. While we are able to do this in over 95 per cent of non-NSA Oakington claims, our experience has shown us that NSA claims take slightly longer, with the majority of decisions being made and served within 14 days. The purpose of this announcement is to set out our revised fast-track process detention policy.</p>
	<p pid="a.129.1/4">The fast-track process has scheduled days set aside for specific activities (interviewing, serving the decision etc) but we intend this to be a guide to how the process will generally operate. There will always be occasions when for operational or other reasons it is not possible to undertake certain activities. This may be because the claimant is temporarily unwell, there is an interpreter problem, the claimant requires longer to obtain further evidence or wishes to submit late representations for example. The process must be flexible enough to accommodate such circumstances. We would not necessarily release people from detention or from the process or move them to another place of detention simply because the timetable cannot be adhered to, if the indications are that we can make and serve a decision within a reasonable timescale. However, the period of detention for making a quick decision will not be allowed to continue for longer than is reasonable in all the circumstances. We will aim to make decisions within 10 to 14 days, but there will be occasions where it is quicker, for example at Harmondsworth or a non-NSA decision at Oakington. However, we will continue to detain for the purpose of deciding the claim quickly, even beyond the 10 to 14-day timescale, unless the length of time before a decision can be made looks as if it will be longer than is reasonable in all the circumstances. Continued detention may also be merited in some cases irrespective of decision timescale, where our general detention criteria apply. We may also detain claimants after we have made and served a decision in accordance with our general detention criteria.</p>
	<p pid="a.129.1/5">Applicants with dependants may be detained for the purposes of making a quick decision on their claim, but there may be operational constraints on who can be detained from time to time. For example, the acceptance of families or pregnant females into Oakington may be halted temporarily if there is an illness circulating which might be harmful to them&mdash;chicken pox for example. The criteria for acceptance are applied equally to those entering the Oakington and Harmondsworth processes. The principal difference is that at Oakington, individuals with dependants on their asylum claims can be detained at the centre and at Harmondsworth they cannot. Separating dependants on a claim from the claimant can present operational difficulties and for that reason and the fact that it has no female or family accommodation, Harmondsworth will, in general, only accept male claimants who have no dependants on their claims. That is not to say that, at Oakington or Harmondsworth or any other location where fast-tracking is carried out, we will never detain a claimant who has dependants on their claim, even where it is not possible to detain the dependants with the claimant. There may be occasions when we believe it is necessary and right so to do.</p>
	<p pid="a.129.1/6">When deciding who to accept into fast-track processes, account is taken of any particular individual circumstances known to us which might make the claim particularly complex or unlikely to be resolved in the timescales, however flexibly applied. The existence of UK-based family ties (such as a spouse, partner or child) would not automatically exclude a claimant from the process as some issues, such as Article 8 family life ones, can be relatively easy to decide quickly given the case law and the individual's actual circumstances.</p>
	<p pid="a.129.1/7">We will continually review how our fast-track processes are operating, the criteria for acceptance into them and the indicative process timescales we aim for. This will apply equally to those we are presently operating and to any we may seek to introduce as part of our overall strategy of speeding up the asylum process and making it more effective.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.131.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="131"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-65.htm#40916-66_spnew0">
	Coal Investment Aid
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.131.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="131"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-65.htm#40916-66_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.131.1/1"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1138" name="Mike O'Brien">My honourable friend the Minister for Energy and E-commerce (Mike O'Brien)</phrase> has made the following Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.131.1/2">Following the acceptance of awards worth &pound;41 million in the first of three planned CIA application periods, up to &pound;19 million was available when bids in the second application period were invited in April 2004.</p>
	<p pid="a.131.1/3">When the deadline for applications passed on <phrase class="date" code="">1 June</phrase>, 12 applications had been received for a total of &pound;94.6 million. All but one were for projects at mines which are already eligible for support following awards in period 1.</p>
	<p pid="a.131.1/4">On review, the one new application was found to be incomplete. The applicant was given an opportunity to submit additional information but was unable to do so. This application therefore could not be considered for an award.</p>
	<p pid="a.131.1/5">Two further applications were for further support for projects which had already received substantial awards in period 1 and for which further awards could not be justified on value for money grounds.</p>
	<p pid="a.131.1/6">The nine remaining applications have been assessed and awarded further support worth a total of &pound;16.42 million. Most of this is expected to be drawn down by <phrase class="date" code="">31 March 2006</phrase>. These offers leave a balance of around &pound;2.5 million for further awards and to meet CIA administration costs.</p>
	<p pid="a.131.1/7">A summary of the period 2 awards is given below. More details will be published shortly on the DTI energy group website.</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/10"> <td>Applicant/Production Unit</td> <td>Project Description</td> <td>Period 1Award</td> <td>Period 2CIA Sought</td> <td>Period 2Award</td> <td>TonnesSecured Mt</td> <td>JobsSecured/Created</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/11"> <td>Eckington Colliery Partnerships, S Yorks</td> <td>Extension of main drift to access two new areas of reserves; acquisition of coal handling and other equipment</td> <td>&pound;0.063m</td> <td>&pound;0.014m</td> <td>&pound;0.014m</td> <td>0.3</td> <td>25/6</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/12"> <td>Energybuild, Aberpergwm,</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/13"> <td>S Glamorgan</td> <td>Recovery of cross-measure drifts to access reserves through fault; upgrade of coal preparation plant &amp; surface/admin facilities. Purchase of rail head.</td> <td>&pound;1.1m</td> <td>&pound;2.76m</td> <td>&pound;2.42m</td> <td>20.0</td> <td>78/100</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/14"> <td>Hatfield Colliery S Yorks</td> <td>Develop access to Barnsley Main seam</td> <td>&pound;15.0m1</td> <td>&pound;33.28m</td> <td>&pound;0.0m</td> <td>100</td> <td></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/15"> <td>Tower Colliery, Mid Glamorgan</td> <td>Development of replacement panels</td> <td>&pound;2.2m</td> <td>&pound;3.5m</td> <td>&pound;0.0m</td> <td>3.5</td> <td>420/0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/16"> <td>UK Coal plc, Ellington, Northumberland</td> <td>Development of replacement panels, purchase of new face equipment</td> <td>&pound;2.1m</td> <td>&pound;2.9m</td> <td>&pound;0.0m</td> <td>2.1</td> <td>360/0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/17"> <td>UK Coal plc, Daw Mill,</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/18"> <td>W Midlands</td> <td>Strategic development to access reserves in Warwickshire Thick seam; coal face mechanisation programme including purchase of set of powered roof supports; 3D surface seismic survey &amp; surface boreholes</td> <td>&pound;9.6m</td> <td>&pound;2.72m</td> <td>&pound;1.26m</td> <td>32.8</td> <td>543/0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/19"> <td>UK Coal plc, Harworth,</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/20"> <td>S Yorks</td> <td>Development driveage to access 2 areas of Deep Soft reserves; purchase of new face equipment</td> <td>&pound;4.6m</td> <td>&pound;4.8m</td> <td>&pound;1.72m</td> <td>10.4</td> <td>511/0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/21"> <td>UK Coal plc, Kellingley,</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/22"> <td>N Yorks</td> <td>Strategic driveage to access the Silkstone seam to the south of current workings and Beeston seam to the east; purchase of new face equipment; upgrade of No. 2 winders</td> <td>&pound;7.2m</td> <td>&pound;8.0m</td> <td>&pound;2.27m</td> <td>19.15</td> <td>630/0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/23"> <td>UK Coal plc, Maltby, S Yorks</td> <td>Strategic driveage to access reserves in Parkgate seam; provision of development &amp; face machinery</td> <td>&pound;2.4m</td> <td>&pound;7.53m</td> <td>&pound;2.71m</td> <td>9.03</td> <td>528/0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/24"> <td>UK Coal plc, Rossington,</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/25"> <td>S Yorks</td> <td>Strategic driveage to access reserves in Barnsley/Dunsil seam to the east of current workings; infrastructure improvements; 3D surface seismic survey</td> <td>&pound;3.2m</td> <td>&pound;3.54m</td> <td>&pound;1.39m</td> <td>15.6</td> <td>386/0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/26"> <td>UK Coal plc, Thoresby, Notts</td> <td>Development driveage to access reserves in Parkgate seam; purchase of new face and heading machinery and conveyor system.</td> <td>&pound;2.9m</td> <td>&pound;15.0m2</td> <td>&pound;2.09m</td> <td>16.5</td> <td>509/0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/27"> <td>UK Coal plc, Welbeck, Notts</td> <td>Development driveage to access reserves in Deep Soft seam; infrastructure improvements; upgrade of ROM handling plant</td> <td>&pound;5.2m</td> <td>&pound;10.66</td> <td>&pound;2.54m</td> <td>8.0</td> <td>528/0</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="a.131.1/28"> <td></td> <td>Total</td> <td>&pound;40.7m</td> <td>&pound;94.6m</td> <td>&pound;16.42m</td> <td>131.8</td> <td>3738/106</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="a.131.1/31" class="indent">1 Award was not taken up.</p>
	<p pid="a.131.1/32" class="indent">2 Included revision of project covered by period 1 award.</p>
	<p pid="a.131.1/33" class="indent">NB: No period 2 application was received from J Flack &amp; Sons Ltd for Hay Royds Colliery, W Yorks, which received an award of &pound;140,000 in period 1.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.135.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="135"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-65.htm#40916-66_head2">
	Rural Post Offices
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-09-16a.135.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="135"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200304/ldhansrd/vo040916/text/40916-65.htm#40916-66_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.135.1/1">My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for Trade and Industry (Ms Hewitt) has made the following Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.1/2">The Performance and Innovation Unit report on modernising the post office network, published in June 2000, recommended that the Government should support the rural network in the first instance to 2006. It also recommended that the Postal Services Commission, Postcomm, should advise the Government on options for the rural network after 2006. I have received that advice and have considered it very carefully.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.1/3">The Government are fully committed to supporting the Post Office's strategy for creating a viable and vibrant post office network that meets changing customer needs, providing reasonable access to services in rural communities.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.1/4">My honourable friend the then Minister of State for Energy, E-Commerce and Postal Services announced in the House on <phrase class="date" code="2002-12-02">2 December 2002</phrase> the Government's decision to make &pound;450 million available to support the rural post office network through from 2003 to 2006. That three-year package was intended as a transitional measure, designed to help rural post offices through the changes in the network's business between 2003 and 2006.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.1/5">At this point in the transition rural post offices continue to face real challenges and a large part of the rural network continues to be unsustainable commercially. For many post offices the number of customers they serve is simply too small to make the business attractive or sustainable. With the prospect of customer numbers continuing to fall as people access services in different ways it is clear that there are challenges ahead and that new ways to deliver services more efficiently and effectively are needed.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.1/6">How and where people access services is changing. It is not clear that the present network best meets those changing needs, or whether because of that the current shape and scale of the rural network is a viable long-term prospect. A solution for the longer-term will need to take these changes fully into account.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.1/7">Against this background Postcomm has advised the Government to review the reasons for and nature of our support of the rural network in the longer term. They advise that the nature of that support may need to change substantially.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.1/8">Postcomm's advice recognises that such changes must be well informed and that further work will be necessary. Pilot activity by the Post Office, funded by the Government, to test new ways of ensuring access to post office services in rural areas is under way. The lessons that will emerge from these trials over the next 12 to 18 months will be crucial in informing longer-term decisions about the future shape of the rural post office network. At this stage it is simply too early to draw conclusions. The Government have therefore concluded that now is not the right time to take decisions about the long-term future of the rural network.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.1/9">It is, however, vital that we continue to support the network through this continuing difficult period. The Government are committed to ensuring reasonable access for rural communities to postal and other services. It is also clear from Postcomm's advice to us that without government funding much of the current rural network would face closure.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.1/10">I am therefore pleased to announce that the Government have decided, subject to securing any further necessary state aid clearance from the European Commission, to extend the transitional financial facility for rural post offices for two further years from 2006 until 2008.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.1/11">The Government will make available up to a maximum of &pound;150 million a year until 2008 to enable Post Office Ltd to continue to meet the cost of maintaining the non-commercial part of the rural post office network and to pilot new ways of delivering services. Pilot activity is a key element of the current funding package&mdash;we have already allocated &pound;25 million to fund pilots. Our intention is that this will continue to be a key element of the package going forward.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.1/12">The funding will ensure that Post Office Ltd will have money to test new ways of delivering services and will not be forced to close unprofitable rural post offices because of a lack of funding.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.1/13">Current funding is from the gilts (government money previously received as &quot;dividends&quot; from the company and made available back to the company for certain specific uses) and it is our intention that the further funding to April 2008 will also come from these gilts. The detailed mechanism, sums of money and timing of payments will be subject to further detailed discussion with the company, as well as being subject to state aid clearance.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.1/14">The PIU report recommended that the Post Office should be required to prevent avoidable closures of rural post offices, in the first instance to 2006. Postcomm has advised us that it is concerned that this policy can lead to post offices being saved or reopened where it is clear that customer numbers have dwindled to levels far below what is sustainable. Furthermore it has recommended that this policy should not be extended beyond April 2006.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.1/15">The Government's direction to Post Office Limited to maintain the network and do all it can to prevent avoidable closures remains in place. There is no question of it being able to initiate the closure of offices. However, in response to Postcomm's immediate concern I propose to amend the definition of what is unavoidable so that when Post Office Ltd is responding to a closure (for example when a sub-postmaster decides to retire) it takes into account circumstances where there is no prospect of a viable future for a post office because of a collapse in demand for services in a particular location. The intention will be to ensure that Post Office Ltd is focused on maintaining access to services in rural areas fully taking into account local circumstances. These changes, yet to be worked up in detail, will be published.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.1/16">I believe that we will be better placed to take a decision on the longer-term future of the rural network, including whether the current policy on avoidable closures should continue beyond April 2006, when we have feedback from the pilot activity now being undertaken by the Post Office.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.1/17">I propose therefore to ask Post Office Ltd for a full report on pilot activity and its implications for future access to post office services by the end of 2005. I will then review the policy on avoidable closures beyond April 2006 at that point.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

