<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">

<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >

<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >

<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >

<!ENTITY euro "&#8364;" >
]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-12-02a.31.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo041202/text/41202-28.htm#41202-28_head0">
	Equatorial Guinea
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/lordswms/2004-12-02a.31.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100624" speakername="Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean" colon=":" colnum="31"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200405/ldhansrd/vo041202/text/41202-28.htm#41202-28_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.31.1/1">In his Written Answer to the Question from <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/697" name="Michael Ancram">the right honourable Member for Devizes (Mr Michael Ancram)</phrase> of <phrase class="date" code="">17 November</phrase> (<i>Official Report,</i> Commons, col. 1548W), my right honourable friend the Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Mr Jack Straw) set out what Her Majesty's Government knew of reports of a planned coup in Equatorial Guinea earlier this year. This Statement informs the House more widely of the position. At all times we acted properly, promptly, and entirely in accordance with international law.</p>
	<p pid="a.31.1/2">The United Kingdom has normal diplomatic relations with the Government of Equatorial Guinea, which is a former Spanish colony. We have no embassy in the country. Our High Commissioner in neighbouring Cameroon is accredited as Ambassador to Equatorial Guinea and has responsibility for relations with Equatorial Guinea. There is a British community of some hundreds, many involved in the energy sector. We have an honorary consul and a commercial attach&eacute; in the capital, Malabo.</p>
	<p pid="a.31.1/3">The country has in the past suffered political instability. Rumours of upheaval and further instability are common. For example, there were reports picked up by BBC Monitoring in October 2003 of an imminent planned coup. These appeared not to be accurate; certainly, there was no coup.</p>
	<p pid="a.31.1/4">On <phrase class="date" code="2006-01-29">29 January</phrase> this year, the Foreign Office received an intelligence report of preparations for a possible coup in Equatorial Guinea. The report was the first intelligence we had received. It was not definitive enough for us to conclude that a coup was likely or inevitable. It was passed by another government to us on the normal condition that it not be passed on. There were, coincidentally, reports on Spanish radio, and in both <i>El Pais</i> and <i>El Mundo</i> on <phrase class="date" code="2006-01-30">30 January</phrase>, making similar suggestions that a coup was being planned in Equatorial Guinea, and reporting that Spanish naval vessels were sailing towards the country.</p>
	<p pid="a.31.1/5">British newspapers have this week reported that a South African national, Johann Smith, is claiming to have passed to contacts in British intelligence in December 2003 and in January 2004 a note setting out in detail plans for a coup. We have no record of this information being passed to British officials at any time before May 2004.</p>
	<p pid="a.31.1/6">The Foreign Secretary received a submission (dated <phrase class="date" code="2006-01-30">30 January</phrase>) from FCO officials on the weekend of <phrase class="date" code="2006-01-30">30 January</phrase>/<phrase class="date" code="2006-02-01">1 February</phrase> which summarised both the media and intelligence reports and made recommendations to me. He considered the case and agreed that the FCO should approach an individual formerly connected with a British private military company (mentioned in the report of <phrase class="date" code="2006-01-29">29 January</phrase>), both to attempt to test the veracity of the report and to make it clear that the FCO was firmly opposed to any unconstitutional action such as <i>coups d'&eacute;tat. </i>A senior Foreign Office official did so within days. The individual concerned claimed no knowledge of the plans.</p>
	<p pid="a.31.1/7">On <phrase class="date" code="2006-02-03">3 February</phrase> we changed our travel advice to reflect our latest assessment. This read &quot;visitors should expect . . . isolated incidents of political unrest&quot; in Equatorial Guinea, particularly as &quot;legislative elections are scheduled for the first quarter of 2004&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.31.1/8">In anticipation of these elections our ambassador in Yaound&eacute; was due to visit Malabo in early February. We instructed him to continue with his planned visit. He found the situation calm. But, as a precaution, our consular crisis plan for Equatorial Guinea was reviewed. Given our limited British representation, it had not been recently updated.</p>
	<p pid="a.31.1/9">We did not pass the report of <phrase class="date" code="2006-01-29">29 January</phrase> to the Equatorial Guinea Government. It had been passed to us on the condition that it not be passed on to any third party. But there were two considerations of substance which led us to this judgment in any event: first, because there had been media reports about preparations for a possible coup which the Equatorial Guinea government would already have seen; and, secondly, because it was not definitive enough for us to conclude that a coup was likely or inevitable. Indeed, we went back to the originating government and to another government who had also received the report to check their belief in the veracity of the report. Their responses gave no certainty. The fact that the rumours were in the public domain suggested in any event that a successful coup was growing less likely.</p>
	<p pid="a.31.1/10">There have been some suggestions in the press that the British Government were under a legal obligation to act differently. We do not condone or support unconstitutional action including a <i>coup d'&eacute;tat </i>of any kind in other countries. But my understanding is that governments are under no legal obligation to pass on information which they may receive about such possible action.</p>
	<p pid="a.31.1/11">On <phrase class="date" code="2006-03-09">9 March</phrase> we learned that the Zimbabwean authorities had arrested a number of individuals in Harare, alleged to be on their way to effect a coup in Equatorial Guinea. A number of individuals were also arrested in Malabo in connection with the alleged coup plot. Over the following months, the names of a number of others allegedly involved appeared in the media.</p>
	<p pid="a.31.1/12">On <phrase class="date" code="">28 August</phrase> the Foreign Office press office was asked by the <i>Observer</i> if the Government knew before March that a coup was going to happen. It replied, correctly, that the FCO did not. As the Foreign Secretary told the right honourable Member for Devizes on <phrase class="date" code="">9 November</phrase> he had first heard reports of possible coup planning in late January this year. And this he followed up with a fuller account for the House in his answer to the right honourable Member's question on <phrase class="date" code="">17 November</phrase>.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

