<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">

<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >

<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >

<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY micro "&#181;" >

<!ENTITY euro "&#8364;" >
<!ENTITY sup2 "&#178;" >
]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="b" latest="yes">

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-07-04b.13.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="13"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo050704/text/50704-49.htm#50704-49_head0">
	Cleaner Fossil Fuel Technologies
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-07-04b.13.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100559" speakername="Lord Sainsbury of Turville" colon=":" colnum="13"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo050704/text/50704-49.htm#50704-49_spmin0">
	<p pid="b.13.1/1">My right honourable friend the Minister of State for Energy (Malcolm Wicks) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="b.13.1/2">The cleaner use of fossil fuels, including CO2 capture and storage and hydrogen, offer important options for the future UK and international sustainable energy mix. The project, announced by BP and its partners on <phrase class="date" code="">30 June</phrase>, is one of a number of potential innovative project opportunities that offer the prospect of demonstrating cleaner fossil fuel technologies, driving forward the next generation of plant.</p>
	<p pid="b.13.1/3">The Government recognise the importance of incentives in encouraging the development of cleaner fossil fuel energy technologies. In this regard, the Government recently published their carbon abatement technologies strategy and their response to the UK hydrogen strategic framework, which involves a combined package of &pound;40 million for funding demonstrations of emerging low-carbon technologies including carbon abatement technologies and hydrogen and fuel cells. Further, the Government are also examining how they might support the development of carbon capture and storage in the climate change programme review, including the potential for new economic incentives. The Government will, in parallel, continue work to resolve the regulatory and legal issues related to CO2 capture and storage.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-07-04b.14.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo050704/text/50704-49.htm#50704-49_head1">
	Public Expenditure Provisional Outturn White Paper 2004&ndash;05
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2005-07-04b.14.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100802" speakername="Lord McKenzie of Luton" colon=":" colnum="14"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200506/ldhansrd/vo050704/text/50704-49.htm#50704-49_spnew4">
	<p pid="b.14.1/1">My right honourable friend the Chief Secretary to the Treasury (Des Browne) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="b.14.1/2">The Treasury will publish the 2004&ndash;05 Public Expenditure Provisional Outturn White Paper on <phrase class="date" code="">Wednesday 20 July</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="b.14.1/3">The White Paper is an annual report to Parliament on the provisional outturn for public expenditure. It focuses on spending within departmental expenditure limits (DEL) and annually managed expenditure (AME), including information on individual supply estimates and administration costs limits.</p>
	<p pid="b.14.1/4">The outturn figures are described as provisional because they may be revised when departments' final accounts are published.</p>
	<p pid="b.14.1/5">A copy of the White Paper will be available in the Libraries of the House and will be accessible on the Treasury website.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

