<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;" >
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;" >
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;" >
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;" >
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;" >

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="b" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.3.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10c.3.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.3.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10c.3.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.4.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10c.4.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.4.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10c.4.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.5.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10c.5.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.5.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10c.5.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.6.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10c.6.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.6.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10c.6.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.7.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10c.7.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.7.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10c.7.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.7.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10c.7.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.7.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10c.7.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.7.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100779" speakername="Lord Drayson" colon=":" colnum="7"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/60110-32.htm#60110-32_spmin2">
	<p pid="b.7.3/1">My right honourable friend the Minister of State for the Armed Forces (Adam Ingram) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="b.7.3/2">I am announcing today that a new order has been made under Section 54 of the Reserve Forces Act 1996 so that reservists may continue to be called out into service to support operations in Iraq. The new order is effective until <phrase class="date" code="">3 January 2007</phrase> and replaces the previous order that expired earlier this month.</p>
	<p pid="b.7.3/3">During the course of the past year, some 2,000 reservists were called out and accepted into service to support operations in Iraq. Details of the next tranche of reservists to be called out were announced to the House on <phrase class="date" code="2005-12-06">6 December 2005</phrase> (<i>Official Report</i>, col. <i>WS 64</i>). Some 700 reservists are involved and they will be deployed to theatre from May, where the majority will complete six month tours. We remain very appreciative of the continuing support and commitment shown by reservists, their employers and their families.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.7.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10c.7.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.7.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10c.7.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.8.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10c.8.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.8.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10c.8.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2006-01-10b.8.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100164" speakername="Lord Davies of Oldham" colon=":" colnum="8"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld199900/ldhansrd/pdvn/lds06/text/60110-32.htm#60110-32_spnew0">
	<p pid="b.8.1/1">My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for Transport (Alistair Darling) made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="b.8.1/2">Ports in the United Kingdom play a vital role in supporting the national economy and contributing to sustainable development. The Government are committed to maintaining and enhancing that role through its broad approach to ports policy and through the decisions it takes on individual ports applications. We aim to exercise our responsibility in respect of applications as promptly as possible, consistent with the need to consider all relevant factors and allow all interested parties sufficient opportunity to comment.</p>
	<p pid="b.8.1/3">I can now report to the House that, as part of that process, my honourable friend the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State (Derek Twigg) announced on <phrase class="date" code="">21 December</phrase> that he was minded to approve the proposal from Hutchison Ports UK for a container port at Bathside Bay at Harwich, Essex. He noted, however, that there are some matters which require further clarification, including making sure that the right conditions are imposed on the development to secure the necessary highways improvements in good time to provide congestion relief. A similar letter, covering planning and listed building appeals related to the development, was issued by my right honourable friend the Deputy Prime Minister. The Government believe that this expansion in deep-sea container port capacity is justified by the economic benefits it will bring regionally and nationally. But they understand that there should be controls imposed on the development, to provide new road and rail infrastructure so that congestion does not increase, to provide compensatory habitats for wildlife displaced by the scheme, and to reduce other environmental impacts such as noise, pollution and the visual impact.</p>
	<p pid="b.8.1/4">My honourable friend had already announced in July last year that he was minded to approve the proposal from P&amp;O Ports for a new container port at London Gateway, near Thurrock in Essex. Working in conjunction with my right honourable friend the Deputy Prime Minister, who had announced in parallel that he was minded to approve the proposed adjoining logistics centre at London Gateway, we have invited representations regarding road access and other matters both on that proposal and now on Bathside Bay. We will consider any representations carefully before moving to final decisions.</p>
	<p pid="b.8.1/5">My honourable friend is also considering a separate proposal from Hutchison for providing further deep-sea container port capacity through the reconfiguration of the Felixstowe South site in Suffolk. He, together with my right honourable friend the Deputy Prime Minister, expects to make announcements on that shortly.</p>
	<p pid="b.8.1/6">The ports industry is responding to demand for capacity in other traffic sectors as well. On <phrase class="date" code="">21 December</phrase>, my honourable friend also made a final decision approving the application from Associated British Ports plc to construct a short-sea container terminal at Quay 2005 in Hull. After carefully considering the likely impacts on local residents, and balancing them against the wider economic benefits, the Government are satisfied that this project will overall bring significant benefits to the city of Hull and the region as a whole. The Government are also satisfied that the project's likely impacts on nature conservation sites will be adequately compensated for by the creation of replacement habitat in the Humber estuary.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

