<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-06-30a.135.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="135"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100630-wms0001.htm#10063033000043">
	Debt Management Office
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-06-30a.135.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/101012" speakername="Lord Sassoon" colon=":" colnum="135"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100630-wms0001.htm#10063033000003">
	<p pid="a.135.1/1">My honourable friend the Economic Secretary to the Treasury (Justine Greening) has today made the following Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.1/2">The United Kingdom Debt Management Office (DMO) has today published its business plan for the year 2010-11. Copies have been deposited in the Libraries of both Houses and are available on the DMO's website at <a href="http://www.dmo.gov.uk">www.dmo.gov.uk</a>.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-06-30a.135.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="135"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100630-wms0001.htm#10063033000044">
	Defence Support Group and Met Office: Key Targets
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-06-30a.135.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100026" speakername="Lord Astor of Hever" colon=":" colnum="135"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100630-wms0001.htm#10063033000005">
	<p pid="a.135.3/1">My honourable friend the Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology (Peter Luff) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.3/2">The following key targets have been agreed with the chief executives of the Defence Support Group (DSG) for the FY2010-11. They are designed to drive continued improvements in the agency's performance and are as follows:</p>
	<p pid="a.135.3/3"><I>Defence Support Group (DSG)</I></p>
	<p pid="a.135.3/4"><I>KT1: Quality</I></p>
	<p pid="a.135.3/5">Deliver an improved quality performance by achieving fewer than three attributable major customer concerns within DSG's air business and implementing a new system to record major customer concerns for the land business and set a baseline against which future years' targets can be set.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.3/6"><I>KT2: Financial Performance</I></p>
	<p pid="a.135.3/7">To achieve at least a 3.5 per cent return on capital employed.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.3/8"><I>KT3: Efficiency</I></p>
	<p pid="a.135.3/9">To develop a phased DSG capacity and capability optimisation plan.</p>
	<p pid="a.135.3/10"><I>KT4: Delivery</I></p>
	<p pid="a.135.3/11">To meet delivery targets as agreed with the customer:</p>
	<p pid="a.135.3/12">air business-to achieve 95 per cent of customer programmes; andland business-to meet customer agreed targets for delivery schedules on critical programme lines (94 per cent September 10, 94 per cent December 10 and 97 per cent March 11) and land load tasks (92 per cent of urgent specified tasks, 85 per cent of routine tasks).</p>
	<p pid="a.135.3/13"><I>Met Office</I></p>
	<p pid="a.135.3/14">The Ministry of Defence plans shortly to release information on Met Office FY2010-11.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-06-30a.136.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="136"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100630-wms0001.htm#10063033000045">
	Fishing: Trawlerman Scheme
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-06-30a.136.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100684" speakername="Baroness Wilcox" colon=":" colnum="136"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100630-wms0001.htm#10063033000018">
	<p pid="a.136.1/1">The Government have today published a Statement on the operation of the former Icelandic water trawlermen compensation scheme. Copies have been placed in both Libraries of the House and on the Department for Business' website at <a href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/employment-matters/strategies/trawlermen">http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/employment-matters/strategies/trawlermen</a>.</p>
	<p pid="a.136.1/2">The Government received around 3,400 applications under the new scheme. To date around &#163;3.7 million has been paid or is being paid, to just over 600 successful claimants. We are currently considering how best to take forward around 100 cases where claimants have been unable to provide copies of their fishing records. Around 400 appeals have been received to date, of which around 200 have been processed.</p>
	<p pid="a.136.1/3">We believe that the new scheme delivers the Government's objective of compensating former trawlermen for the loss of their livelihoods following the cod war treaties of the 1970s, and that we have met in full the recommendations made by the Parliamentary Ombudsman in her 2007 report. Total payments of around &#163;60 million have now been made to trawlermen under this and the two previous compensation schemes, and we believe this issue has now been brought to a successful close.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-06-30a.136.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="136"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100630-wms0001.htm#10063033000046">
	Justice: Family Courts
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-06-30a.136.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100408" speakername="Lord McNally" colon=":" colnum="136"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100630-wms0001.htm#10063033000021">
	<p pid="a.136.3/1">My honourable friend the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Ministry of Justice (Jonathan Djanogly) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.136.3/2">My honourable friend the Parliamentary Under-Secretary for State for Children and Families (Tim Loughton) and I wish to make the following Statement to the House about our plans for a comprehensive review of the family justice system.</p>
	<p pid="a.136.3/3">My honourable friend and I have asked David Norgrove to build on his preliminary work in this area to undertake a comprehensive review of the family justice system. This review will examine both public and private law cases. In public law this means looking at how the courts, with other agencies, manage cases involving children and the public care system. In private law this means looking at contact and residence disputes between family members and will include considering how to increase the use of mediation when couples break up, and how best to provide greater access rights to non-resident parents and grandparents.</p>
	<p pid="a.136.3/4">The review will also examine the processes involved in granting divorces and awarding ancillary relief, but will not extend to the law as it relates to the grounds for divorce or the amounts of ancillary relief that should be awarded.</p>
	<p pid="a.136.3/5">The terms of reference have set this out in more detail and a copy has been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
	<p pid="a.136.3/6">The panel is today launching its call for evidence. The panel wishes to hear from children, families, professionals and representative groups involved in the family justice system. A series of questions has been posed to frame responses; a copy of these questions has been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-06-30a.137.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="137"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100630-wms0001.htm#10063033000047">
	Local Government: Doncaster
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-06-30a.137.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/lord/100269" speakername="Baroness Hanham" colon=":" colnum="137"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201011/ldhansrd/text/100630-wms0001.htm#10063033000027">
	<p pid="a.137.1/1">My honourable friend the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State (Bob Neill) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.1/2">On <phrase class="date" code="2010-06-02">2 June</phrase> my right honourable friend the Secretary of State, announced to the House a package of intensive measures which he was proposing to turn around the governance of Doncaster Metropolitan Borough Council after 15 years of poor governance and dysfunctional politics. He gave the authority until <phrase class="date" code="2010-06-23">23 June</phrase> to make any representations on the draft direction he was proposing.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.1/3">Having now given careful consideration to the representations received, we note that the authority accepts intervention is appropriate, and we recognise the commitment shown from the mayor, members and officers which has begun to address some of the outstanding issues.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.1/4">I confirm we remain satisfied that there is a strong case for intervention at Doncaster Metropolitan Borough Council, and accordingly, I have issued a direction under Section 15 of the Local Government Act 1999 specifying the form of intervention, together with an Explanatory Memorandum.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.1/5">The direction requires the authority to take specific actions, specify certain functions will be exercised by the Secretary of State and specify that certain other functions will be exercised by commissioners appointed by the Secretary of State.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.1/6">As empowered by the direction we have from <phrase class="date" code="2010-07-01">1 July 2010</phrase> appointed Rob Vincent to be the chief executive at Doncaster Metropolitan Borough Council. He is an experienced and well respected chief executive, currently at Kirklees Council, who will be at Doncaster for a period of 18 months. He will also make recommendations to me by <phrase class="date" code="2010-10-31">31 October 2010</phrase> as to the appointment of a monitoring officer and chief finance officer, which the direction empowers us to make.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.1/7">We have also as specified in the direction appointed three commissioners-Sir John Harman, Jessica Crowe, and Julie Kenny. They will be responsible for any matter referred to them by statutory officers due to concerns about the authority's approach. They will also be responsible for senior officer appointments, discipline and dismissal. I am delighted that each has agreed to make their expertise available to the authority to draw on and assist it in its recovery.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.1/8">The direction also requires the authority to co-operate with a recovery board comprising the commissioners, chief executive, children's board chair and five other experts who we will be appointing to provide external support and challenge to the authority and monitor and report on the progress of recovery.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.1/9">I believe the intervention package we have now put in place will secure the progress that Doncaster has already begun to make, and enable necessary further significant improvements to be made. We are very grateful to the Local Government Association and others within the local government sector who have helped in the development of this intervention package, and to Jo Miller, deputy chief executive at the Local Government Association, who stepped in and provided stability as the acting chief executive at the authority during transition.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.1/10">The mayor, members and officers at Doncaster, with the support this intervention package gives, now have the opportunity to address, and once and for all resolve, the long-standing problems at that council so that it can provide the services and local leadership the people of Doncaster have the right to expect.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.1/11">Copies of the direction and Explanatory Memorandum have been placed in the Library of the House.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

