<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="b" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.63.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="63"  time="unknown" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000007">
	[Mr. Mike Hancock in the Chair]
	 &mdash; 
	School Sixth Forms
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.63.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="63"  time="unknown" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000001">
	<p pid="b.63.1/1" class="italic">Motion made, and Question proposed, That the sitting be now adjourned<i>.&mdash;(</i><i>Mark</i>. Tami.)</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.63.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1767" speakername="Mike Hancock" colnum="63"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000431">
	<p pid="b.63.2/1"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1626" name="Michael Penning">The hon. Member for Hemel Hempstead (Mike Penning)</phrase> has told the Chair that he is not willing to take interventions because he will make a very brief speech.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.63.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1381" speakername="David Lidington" colnum="63"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000432">
	<p pid="b.63.3/1">On a point of order, Mr. Hancock. Can you give us guidance on how we are supposed to conduct the debate when, as far as I can see, no Minister from the relevant Department is present to respond to my hon. Friend?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.63.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1945" speakername="Peter Bottomley" colnum="63"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000433">
	<p pid="b.63.4/1">Further to that point of order, Mr. Hancock, I am not sure that there is even an official present who might be able to tell the Minister what to say, or even what we have said.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.63.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1767" speakername="Mike Hancock" colnum="63"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000434">
	<p pid="b.63.5/1">I do not quite understand that latter point, but I am sure that the Minister's hon. Friend, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1372" name="Mark Tami">the hon. Member for Alyn and Deeside (Mark Tami)</phrase>, will sit here in eager anticipation of his arrival.</p>
	<p pid="b.63.5/2">I deplore the fact that the Minister is not present, which is a discourtesy to the House and the Chamber. I hope that the usual channels will report that back. I have sought advice from the Clerk and the debate may proceed. I am sure that the hon. Member for Alyn and Deeside will do his best to take copious notes of what is said. I do not want to delay proceedings any longer because so many hon. Members want to make a point. I hope that the Minister will have a very good excuse when he arrives. He owes an apology to every hon. Member who has taken the time and trouble to turn up. It is the first time in nearly 10 years that I have chaired proceedings and the Minister has not been present. It is a craven insult to the House.</p>
	<p pid="b.63.5/3">As I said, the hon. Member for Hemel Hempstead does not want to take interventions, so that as many hon. Members as possible can comment, and I shall do my best to help to achieve that.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.63.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1626" speakername="Michael Penning" colnum="63"  time="009:32:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000435">
	<p pid="b.63.6/1">I reiterate your comments, Mr. Hancock, about the insult to the House and those hon. Members who have turned up for this important debate. It is also an insult to my constituents and the children of this country, who have been so badly affected by the funding fiasco. It is a shame that the Minister was not here earlier to hear your comments.</p>
	<p pid="b.63.6/2">The funding of sixth forms and further education colleges is very important for my constituents, as it is for people throughout the country. The fiasco of the past two and a half months&mdash;at least&mdash;has caused great anxiety in colleges, and among headmasters, pupils and parents. It has been described by headmasters as &quot;incompetent and dishonest&quot; and I am desperately concerned about the fact that, with the Learning and Skills Council in its dying throes, its chief executive still does not seem to understand the seriousness of the situation. The chief executive said in a recent interview for <i>The Daily Telegraph</i> that the Learning and Skills Council is a fascinating place to work. It may be interesting, but I wish, for the sake of the pupils, parents and headmasters in my constituency, that he was doing a bit more work, so that the current situation had not occurred. Frankly, he should be a little more contrite about how what has happened has affected pupils.</p>
	<p pid="b.63.6/3">I want to give a brief resum&eacute; of what has happened in Hertfordshire. On <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-02">2 March</phrase> schools in my constituency were told their final allocation of funding for 2009-10. That was the funding that they were to set their budgets by for the end of March, which they could take up to ensure that they had suitable building work done, suitable facilities, and suitable staff in employment, and so that they knew exactly where they were. I have seen the letters that went out from the LSC about that funding. By the last week in March there was a clear indication of a problem throughout the country, and particularly in Hertfordshire. By <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-27">27 March</phrase> schools in Hertfordshire had their funding slashed. Thirteen schools had had their funding cut by up to &pound;25,000; 33 schools had it cut by between &pound;25,000 and &pound;50,000; 24 schools had it cut by between &pound;50,000 and &pound;100,000; and five schools had it cut by more than &pound;100,000. Those are huge figures, whether they are &pound;25,000 or &pound;100,000, when someone is trying to set funding for the following year, and achieve a legal budget&mdash;one that is not in deficit, because it is illegal for the governors of schools to set a deficit budget.</p>
	<p pid="b.63.6/4">Many schools in my constituency, in good faith, gave instructions for building works. The refurbishment of a small classroom was one instance. One school took on two members of staff. The news was therefore something of a shock. We then saw the plethora of articles around the country claiming that everything would be okay, and telling us &quot;We will try to sort this out.&quot; Interestingly, different messages were coming from the LSC, which said it just did not have the funding. The Government eventually announced that they would fill the budget hole&mdash;the cut affecting 16 to 18-year-olds throughout the country, although I am making particular reference to the constituency of Hemel Hempstead. They said they would bring forward a further allocation of funds&mdash;some &pound;210 million.</p>
	<p pid="b.63.6/5">My question to the Minister is about the description of that as additional funding. Where did the funding from <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-02">2 March</phrase> go? It was clearly there. If the LSC issued letters announcing that that was the funding for the year, how could the Government later say that it was additional and was filling a hole that was already there? Not one head teacher in my constituency has said that any money was made available additional to what they were promised on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-02">2 March</phrase>. The Government's description of it as additional funding is disingenuous, suggesting that it is extra money, when it is not. It goes only part way towards the cut in sixth-form funding that had already been made. Interestingly enough, the shortfall is partly caused, it would seem, by the &pound;65 million that was taken out of the further education budget and sent to the university student grant scheme. That might partly explain where some of the money comes from, but what has gone on has involved sheer incompetence.</p>
	<p pid="b.63.6/6">We have heard in the past couple of days&mdash;I have raised the matter on the Floor of the House&mdash;that the money will be sorted out and will be coming. We are a month into this year's budget. It is illegal not to have set the budget by <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-30">30 March</phrase>. It is a legal requirement for the LSC that the funding should have been addressed by the end of March. Naturally enough, I phoned the schools in my constituency yesterday, knowing that the debate was to take place, and realising that it had been on the Order Paper for some days, to find out whether they had had the promise of the funding that they required. They were all promised that by the end of April&mdash;admittedly a month late&mdash;they would have their funding. To be fair, some of them have been given it, although it is not, I stress, extra funding. One has received the &pound;25,000 that had been removed from its allocation, and another has been promised that it will have the money, although there is nothing in writing. Another school is concerned about funding of up to &pound;90,000 and is still formally without any contact from the LSC or the Government about where the funding will come from. The headmaster yesterday said to me, &quot;What am I going to do? It is not legal for me to be operating in this framework. I have a legal responsibility to my children, but I also have a legal responsibility under the Act, to make sure that I have the funds available for the pupils in my school.&quot; Another headmaster said to me, &quot;I will stop a capital project in another part of the school to fund this part of my school, because I will not allow a deficit budget. It would look terrible for my school.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.63.6/7">Through no fault of their own, wonderful schools in my constituency, which are doing excellent work for their pupils and the community, many of which have expanded and done well, with dramatically improving results, received letters saying formally that they contained the final allocation. What other word can one use for &quot;final&quot;, other than perhaps &quot;terminal&quot;, which might apply to the LSC and the Government?</p>
	<p pid="b.63.6/8">I am serious about this: the schools have had the letters and they have moved forward. They set their budgets in good faith only to be told three weeks later that there had been a mistake, a miscalculation. Frankly, the Learning and Skills Council and the Government cannot seem to get the funding ready in time for 2009-10. Telling schools three weeks before the cut-off time how much they were getting and then, two days before legally required, informing them that the funding had been cut, shows a degree of incompetence that borders on the insane.</p>
	<p pid="b.63.6/9">People want some destiny for their children. They want to know what is going on. They want to be able to pick the right school. For example, my daughter is doing the second year of her A-levels. She needed to know that she would have the facilities that were promised, that the school had set the curriculum and that the teachers would be available. We hear promise after promise from the Government&mdash;jam tomorrow&mdash;but the money is coming later. The schools still do not have a promise in writing that they will receive the funding that they deserve, and it is now a month after the legal requirement for the funding has passed.</p>
	<p pid="b.63.6/10">I ask the Minister not to stand up like the Secretary of State did in the main Chamber and say, &quot;You should have listened to the Budget.&quot; I ask him please to listen to the heads and governors. [Hon. Members: &quot;Hear, hear!&quot;] Please listen to what is going on in the country. It is shameful that the Minister was not here to listen to the start of the debate. It is an indication to parents and headmasters of how the Government are likely to treat them in future. What guarantee is there that that will not happen next year or the year after? If things do not change, parents have the right to ask, &quot;Are the Government fit for purpose? Are they capable of producing the education that children need and desire?&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.63.6/11">It is an indication of how much the question matters for the whole country&mdash;certainly those who care&mdash;that so many of my colleagues are sitting next to me and behind me. I did not lobby anyone to attend this debate. I simply asked Mr. Speaker, after he made his comments in the Chamber, whether he would be minded to grant an Adjournment debate. I thought long and hard as to whether it should be a half-hour debate. I now believe that an hour and a half is too short. The Minister should allow a debate in Government time on the fiasco of funding further education.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.66.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1767" speakername="Mike Hancock" colnum="66"  time="009:32:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000436">
	<p pid="b.66.0/1">Thank you, Mr. Penning, for keeping to your word and being brief. I shall try to ensure that everyone who wishes to speak can do so.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.66.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1798" speakername="Anne Main" colnum="66"  time="009:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000437">
	<p pid="b.66.1/1">I shall be brief, because so many of my colleagues wish to speak. As a fellow Hertfordshire MP, I echo everything said by my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1626" name="Michael Penning">the Member for Hemel Hempstead (Mike Penning)</phrase>, whom I congratulate on securing this debate. I am deeply disappointed that we have not had a statement on the subject.</p>
	<p pid="b.66.1/2">I shall touch on three things to do with the Learning and Skills Council and what has been described as a funding fiasco&mdash;and accurately so. The first is post-16 funding. The schools in my area have been adversely affected, as badly as every other school in Hertfordshire. At one point, anguished teachers from a top-ranking school in St. Albans wrote to me, saying that the head and the entire senior staff would resign over the matter because they could not make a budget or balance the school's books. As my hon. Friend suggested, they could be in a perilous position. They are angry. They are voters, as are the parents, and they will remember the Government's treatment of them.</p>
	<p pid="b.66.1/3">To say that the Government have no role in this is totally wrong. The Minister may remember his response to my inquiry as to why on earth we were in this state. His answer was that the shortfall was caused by more people taking up the post-16 education than had been budgeted for. When was that budget deficit recognised? The budget was set on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-02">2 March</phrase>; why did no one notice then that there were far more pupils than funding had been provided for? Has the Minister done anything to investigate why we are in this position? He recognises one of the reasons behind it.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.66.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" speakername="David Gauke" colnum="66"  time="009:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000438">
	<p pid="b.66.2/1">I am another fellow Hertfordshire MP, and my constituency has had the same experience. One school in my area, St. Clement Danes, has suffered a reduction in the forecast of the number of pupils from more than 280 to 273, yet the school always has more than 280 sixth-formers. It does not wash to explain the sudden shortfall as an increase in the number of pupils, because the school is full, as always; there is no change in the number of sixth-formers.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.67.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1798" speakername="Anne Main" colnum="67"  time="009:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000439">
	<p pid="b.67.0/1">My hon. Friend makes a valuable point. Indeed, it increases the merit of the argument for wanting a full-scale debate. There are so many imponderables to which we have no answer that the Minister owes the entire country the justice of coming to the House and explaining why that is so.</p>
	<p pid="b.67.0/2">I shall deal with two other matters, as so many of my hon. Friends wish to raise their own concerns. Oaklands is a further education college in my constituency. Hertfordshire has a policy of dealing in-house with special educational needs, and Oaklands is the only FE college that can offer extra education for such pupils who are severely disabled. In recognition of that, it decided on a massive expansion programme.</p>
	<p pid="b.67.0/3">The project budget was &pound;120 million. The school received help from St. Albans district council planning department, and it put together a comprehensive package. It did deals with developers to sell off part of its land in order to meet some of the costs, but a huge and vital part of the funding was the &pound;40 million that was to be provided by the Learning and Skills Council. It seems that that is likely not to be received. What on earth is supposed to happen to those severely disabled pupils, and every other pupil that takes advantage of the excellence of Oaklands college, if the project does not go ahead? The college has been hung out to dry by the Government, who seem not to be interested in what the LSC is doing.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.67.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" speakername="David Taylor" colnum="67"  time="009:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000440">
	<p pid="b.67.1/1">On a point of order, Mr. Hancock. Is it not the case that the debate should be confined to Learning and Skills Council funding for sixth forms? We seem to be wandering into the capital funding of further education, which is not the thrust of the debate. We are seeing a great deal of theatrical overstatement and bogus outrage.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.67.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1767" speakername="Mike Hancock" colnum="67"  time="009:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000441">
	<p pid="b.67.2/1">I am grateful, as always, for the advice of another Chairman on such matters, but on this occasion there is no point of order. The debate is about the funding of sixth-form colleges. As yet, I have not heard too much variance from the title given in the Order Paper.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.67.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1798" speakername="Anne Main" colnum="67"  time="009:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000442">
	<p pid="b.67.3/1">It is not theatrical overstatement; perhaps <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" name="David Taylor">the hon. Member for North-West Leicestershire (David Taylor)</phrase> should visit my constituency. Many of the youngsters wanting further education there look to Oaklands college. It is not inappropriate to speak of the college, as is handles 16-plus education.</p>
	<p pid="b.67.3/2">The final matter that I wish to raise today is that the LSC, finding itself in this difficulty, this funding fiasco, has wasted &pound;12.5 million on a lease in St. Albans that it can no longer afford. I rest my case. I ask the Minister to give us a statement, and a debate on the matter. My sixth-formers do not know whether their courses will be running in September. That is a disgrace.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.68.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1767" speakername="Mike Hancock" colnum="68"  time="009:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000443">
	<p pid="b.68.0/1">In order to help hon. Members, I intend to call first those who gave notice to Mr. Speaker of their wish to speak. I shall then call the others.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.68.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1381" speakername="David Lidington" colnum="68"  time="009:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000444">
	<p pid="b.68.1/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1626" name="Michael Penning">the Member for Hemel Hempstead (Mike Penning)</phrase> on securing this important debate.</p>
	<p pid="b.68.1/2">The first question that head teachers in my part of Buckinghamshire are asking is: how on earth have we got into this appalling and shocking mess? Was nobody at the Learning and Skills Council telling the Department what was going on? Was no one at the Department listening? Did nobody at the Department or the LSC bother to tell Ministers about the impending disaster? Perhaps Ministers were too busy worrying about other priorities and the Secretary of State's future ambitions in order to take note of what was about to happen.</p>
	<p pid="b.68.1/3">Frankly, it is appalling that the decay in the Government has reached such an extent that the prospects of a generation of rising sixth-formers, and the power of school governors and heads to set the budgets on which they and their pupils and staff can rely, are held as being of so little account by those who are supposed to be in charge of the national purse strings.</p>
	<p pid="b.68.1/4">School governors and heads are also asking what the budget statement meant. Like those in the constituency of my hon. Friend, heads in my schools have heard the generalised statement but have seen no detail. They have had nothing in writing to indicate that the money that they were told on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-30">30 March</phrase> would be cut is to be restored to their school budgets. As my hon. Friend said, the e-mails from the LSC reached schools on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-30">30 March</phrase>, 28 days after they received what the LSC had described as the final funding allocation for each school. They arrived not just at the last minute before the turn of the financial year, but just prior to a major school holiday and after schools had submitted budgets to their governing bodies for approval. The proposed reduction in funding was timed to coincide with the mid-point of the 2009-10 academic year and the introduction of new A-levels and other new post-16 courses.</p>
	<p pid="b.68.1/5">Offers of positions to staff and of places to students for September 2009 or earlier are legally binding, and whatever was in the e-mails on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-30">30 March</phrase> cannot override those legal obligations. A head teacher of one school in Aylesbury told me by letter that finding the &pound;60,000 reduction that he was told to identify could be done only by reducing staffing. He continued:</p>
	<p pid="b.68.1/6" class="indent">&quot;No changes in staffing can be made until September. To save &pound;60,000 in half a year means that we have to lose enough staff to save well over &pound;100,000 in a full year.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.68.1/7">That is the measure of the gravity of the crisis facing head teachers in every part of the country.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.68.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" speakername="David Taylor" colnum="68"  time="009:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000445">
	<p pid="b.68.2/1">I chaired the governing body at Ashby school&mdash;an excellent sixth form&mdash;and remain a member. Would the hon. Gentleman acknowledge that the key factor underpinning the LSC's undoubtedly lamentable lapses is that the budget amendments relate to the seven months from <phrase class="date" code="2009-09-01">1 September</phrase>, because of how the academic years lap around the budgetary years, and that in essence the budget from <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-01">1 April</phrase> to <phrase class="date" code="2009-08-31">31 August</phrase> is left in place untouched?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.69.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1381" speakername="David Lidington" colnum="69"  time="009:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0001.htm#09050659000446">
	<p pid="b.69.0/1">The hon. Gentleman is making a valiant fist at an indefensible case. However, he ignores the reality that if a school takes on a member of staff and has promised a place now from September next year, it must pay for it then. It cannot start to make budget adjustments from the beginning of the 2009-10 financial year to take account of the last-minute change announced by the LSC on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-30">30 March</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/2">This is happening at a time when the Government are urging schools and colleges not to cut, but to increase provision for a greater number of post-16 students and when the recession has reduced severely the opportunities for young people to go, at the age of 16, directly from school into employment. I do not think that the argument will wash that there was an unexpected surge in the number of people seeking sixth-form places. My schools are telling me that the LSC has always funded them on the basis of the number of sixth-formers in the previous September and that the cut is being imposed on the basis of that formula, not on account of some new upsurge identified only during the course of March this year.</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/3">I cannot exaggerate the sense of anger among head teachers in my schools. I do not know the politics of these men and women. The head of Aylesbury grammar school said:</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/4" class="indent">&quot;We are losing the equivalent of three members of staff, or our entire maintenance budget, for all departments across the school&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/5">The head of Misbourne upper school said:</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/6" class="indent">&quot;The reversal of funding levels has now destroyed coherent planning&quot;,</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/7">which</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/8" class="indent">&quot;makes providing a stable and productive learning community almost impossible&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/9">The head of Sir Henry Floyd grammar school said:</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/10" class="indent">&quot;We will have to cut 11 A-level teaching groups...and reduce the number of teaching groups in the most popular subjects&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/11">The head of Aylesbury high school said:</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/12" class="indent">&quot;We are working on rumours at the moment as to whether or not we will receive the original sum that we were allocated&mdash;it is in no one's interest to work in this way...The problem seems to be at the core of the LSC&mdash;the regional office does not know what is going on&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/13">The head of Princes Risborough upper school described the episode as a &quot;complete farce&quot;. He continued:</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/14" class="indent">&quot;To be given an interim budget with a reasonable assurance that the figures were robust and then to be told at the end of March just as we have to submit our new budgets that the amount will be cut drastically is ludicrous&mdash;how could any institution have a financially prudent plan?&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/15">The head of Mandeville upper school, which is pushing hard for the take-up of BTECs and other non-A-level qualifications, said:</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/16" class="indent">&quot;The reduction in funding could mean a lost opportunity for those students who excel at BTEC qualifications rather than traditional A-levels&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/17">Finally, the head of John Colet school said that</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/18" class="indent">&quot;to reduce our salaries budget further, we are going to have some staff teaching outside their specialism&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/19">That is bad enough in a secondary school, but for it possibly to affect a sixth form is intolerable.</p>
	<p pid="b.69.0/20">I hope that the Minister will pledge not just to ensure that the money will be made good, but that the schools will be told quickly and in detail how their individual budgets will be restored to the status quo ante. I also hope to hear him pledge that the Department will learn the lessons and that this sort of catastrophic failure of good administration and planning will never happen again. A strong case could be made for the Public Accounts Committee to investigate this business, because the Department has let down our schools very badly, whose interests it is supposed to defend.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.70.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1437" speakername="Tobias Ellwood" colnum="70"  time="009:56:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0002.htm#09050659000447">
	<p pid="b.70.0/1">It is a pleasure to participate in this important debate. I am grateful that the Minister is in his place. I understand that he might have missed the school bus this morning and perhaps even skipped registration, but let us hope that he has done his homework and that he can avoid detention by answering some of the questions put to him on this crucial issue.</p>
	<p pid="b.70.0/2">I congratulate my hon. Friend&mdash;and good friend&mdash;<phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1626" name="Michael Penning">the Member for Hemel Hempstead (Mike Penning)</phrase> on securing the debate. I underline his question: why was the subject not chosen for this week's topical debate, instead of the Opposition being left to secure this debate? For the benefit of <i>Hansard </i>readers, I would like to note how many Labour Members are filling the vast Benches opposite. I count the Minister himself and one other: <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" name="David Taylor">the hon. Member for North-West Leicestershire (David Taylor)</phrase>, who has not yet indicated that he wants to participate in the debate, although he did come out with a bizarre point of order that was wisely ruled out of order by you, Mr. Hancock.</p>
	<p pid="b.70.0/3">Today's debate is all about a funding gap in the money promised to schools by this Government via the LSC. They are now left with a shortfall of just less than &pound;2.7 billion, which is the clear fault of the LSC. A succession of gaffes has finally led to the resignation of its chief executive. Those of us who participated in yesterday's Report stage of the Apprenticeships, Skills, Children and Learning Bill will be fully aware that although the LSC is to be abolished, it will be replaced by not one but three other quangos, and the very characters now working for the LSC will be transferred to these new quangos. I envisage little improvement to the system responsible for so many problems. First came the fiasco over the college building programme. That was followed by the flagship Train to Gain programme, which is also in trouble, and then by the education maintenance allowances, which also went pear-shaped. However, what really takes the biscuit is the subject of today's debate: the underestimation of the demand for sixth-form places.</p>
	<p pid="b.70.0/4">Did the Government not anticipate the rise in places? First, there was the obligation for students to remain in education until the age of 18, although the Minister might say, &quot;Actually, it is not just education; it is other things as well.&quot; If he is honest, however, he will accept that level 3 apprenticeships are on the decline. Germany, France and other countries do not even have levels 1 and 2, because that is called normal education. Real apprenticeships kick in at level 3, but we do not have enough people going through them. It is no surprise, given the recession, that students are choosing to remain in the safety net of the educational environment, rather than wandering out into the unknown wilderness of the business world. The Government should have anticipated the increase in numbers, but they did not, which has led to today's fiasco. What were the LSC's tactics to deal with this crisis? It simply sent out letters, not to apologise, but to alter the values of funding to be given to schools&mdash;to the tune of about &pound;200,000 per school.</p>
	<p pid="b.70.0/5">My hon. Friends have cited schools in their areas and I shall do the same. The Minister will be familiar with some of the names because he is a fellow MP for the Dorset area. I refer to St. Peter's school, the boys' school and the grammar school, which he has visited. Those schools were told that they could offer places to students. St. Peter's, for example, was told that it could offer places to 430 students in September. The boys' school expects 350 students in September and the girls' school 369. However, they do not have anywhere near enough money to cover the cost of those places. When I spoke to all the head teachers this morning, they said that their funding would not cover those numbers. They say that it will cover considerably fewer students, with the number matching the 2007-08 figure. It is a scandal that the Government have not recognised the increase and assisted pupils who have followed their advice and stayed in education until they are 18. St. Peter's has a shortfall of &pound;90,000, the boys' school &pound;52,000 and the girls' school &pound;79,000. Moreover, there is a shortfall in funded places of between 50 and 100.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.71.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1944" speakername="Tim Loughton" colnum="71"  time="009:56:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0002.htm#09050659000448">
	<p pid="b.71.0/1">Does my hon. Friend not agree that there is a double whammy here? Worthing college and Northbrook college in my constituency face a &pound;1.5 million shortfall in the money that they were promised to cover the expansion of their college buildings, and they will not get that money for the foreseeable future. They are having to borrow the money, which is putting their finances in jeopardy. They are now faced with the additional shortfall in funding for the students to whom they have offered places. Therefore, this is not just a single problem, but a double whammy affecting the survival of many colleges.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.71.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1437" speakername="Tobias Ellwood" colnum="71"  time="009:56:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0002.htm#09050659000449">
	<p pid="b.71.1/1">My hon. Friend makes a very astute point. That is exactly the problem with the Government's whole education strategy.</p>
	<p pid="b.71.1/2">The problem with the funding is that it is retrospective. We look back at last year's figures and say, &quot;Okay, that's how many student they have; we will offer a set amount.&quot; However, the figures are based not on the number of pupils, but on a bid. Today, head teachers have to write a business plan to meet the numbers for next year. St. Peter's, for example, has money for 350 students, but it has 430. There is a lag of a year until it can pay for the 80 or so additional students going through its doors.</p>
	<p pid="b.71.1/3">The Government have taken a while to act. We have not heard a statement or any real comment; there have been hints and innuendo, and indications that the money might come through. In the Budget, &pound;250 million was earmarked right now, with another &pound;404 million promised for next year and another &pound;1.2 billion supposedly for the next five years. None the less, those are only indications because nothing has been confirmed. Perhaps we will hear something today. Let us not forget that we were also promised a loan guarantee system to help small and medium-sized businesses, but that has not come through. We were even promised aircraft carriers, but they have not turned up either. Schools will not hold their breath for the funding&mdash;they will not do anything until they get the cheque through the post.</p>
	<p pid="b.71.1/4">The sad thing is that the Government identified the shortfall more than five months ago. They recognised that the money would not be there for 5,000 students. It was the threat of legal action that made them realise that they had to address the problem. The Learning and Skills Council must be killed off and replaced with something more appropriate that recognises the importance of education.</p>
	<p pid="b.71.1/5">We have had a decade of Labour promising, &quot;Education, education, education&quot;, but what has happened instead? It is true that the budget has been doubled, but has that been reflected in a twofold improvement in education? I do not think so. One in four primary school children fail to meet basic standards. As I mentioned earlier, level 3 apprenticeships are on the decline. Grade inflation came up in yesterday's debate&mdash;that made the Minister rise to his feet. We have had the introduction of A* grades, employers refusing to recognise the worthiness of A-levels and GCSEs and setting their own exams&mdash;that is happening in universities as well&mdash;and now we have the fiasco of the LSC. I plead with the Minister for clarity, honesty and leadership to help us through the crisis. I ask for that not only for our benefit but for the benefit of our students.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.72.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1759" speakername="Stewart Jackson" colnum="72"  time="010:04:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0002.htm#09050659000450">
	<p pid="b.72.0/1">It is a pleasure to serve under your benign chairmanship, Mr. Hancock. I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1626" name="Michael Penning">the Member for Hemel Hempstead (Mike Penning)</phrase> on raising this important issue.</p>
	<p pid="b.72.0/2">Let us talk about what this debate is not about. It is not about my hon. Friends asking for more money, or asking for more money in order to cut budgets elsewhere&mdash;the rather puerile student union dividing-line approach taken by the Secretary of State for Children, Schools and Families last week, which was rather demeaning and symptomatic of the Government's decline, as we watch them crumble in front of our eyes. If that were happening to a budgie, we would take it to a vet and have it put down.</p>
	<p pid="b.72.0/3">The issue is about basic honesty, communication, administrative competence and transparency. Hon. Members rightly want to know why there was such a disconnect between what the LSC and the Department knew in January&mdash;if not before&mdash;and the schools' expectations, and why there was such a time lag in getting the right information to schools. Moreover, they want to know why there was no honesty when the difference first came to light. Why was it necessary to include the figures in a footnote on page 13 of the Learning and Skills Council's funding letter that arrived on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-02">2 March 2009</phrase>? It was almost as if those figures were hidden away in the hope that schools would not notice that they were several thousand pounds short in their budget for sixth-form education. Perhaps the Minister will consider that.</p>
	<p pid="b.72.0/4">Last autumn, the Government told us that they were uniquely placed, well equipped and fully prepared to deal with the economic recession. Why then was there no robust, predictive model to ascertain the likely and accurate take-up of school sixth-form places? If it was the case, as Mr. Geoff Russell told <i>The Guardian </i>recently, that it was impossible to predict student numbers accurately, why was there not better communication and liaison between the Department, the LSC and individual schools?</p>
	<p pid="b.72.0/5">As my hon. Friend rightly said, the situation has caused significant distress, unhappiness and worry for head teachers, senior staff, governors, pupils and parents. In my local education authority, 10 secondary schools have been affected, suffering a loss on paper of &pound;397,000. We are already underperforming in terms of the skills agenda, particularly with respect to NVQ level 3, compared with other education authorities in the east of England and elsewhere. Moreover, jobs in our area have been significantly hit by the economic recession. We cannot afford to lose sixth-form places for young people. We have lost funding for 70 learners in 2009-10. That does not sound much, but we are a relatively small unitary authority. Such a loss will have an impact on participation rates and on the delivery of the September guarantee. Inevitably, it will lead to larger class sizes, and there will be less flexibility to offer more specialist provision for some of our sixth-form learners, which will lead to an increase in the number of young people not in education, employment or training. Such a problem is already a significant issue in Peterborough.</p>
	<p pid="b.72.0/6">The Voyager school in Walton will lose &pound;71,000&mdash;the equivalent of two full-time teaching posts&mdash;the King's school in Peterborough will lose &pound;66,000, the Jack Hunt school, a specialist language college, &pound;52,000 and Ken Stimpson community school &pound;36,900. Two of those schools already have problems with respect to school improvements, and losing staff and being unable to fund and plan properly will mean that the school establishment only adds to its difficulties. Indeed, it will have an impact on staff morale, which will feed through to results. There will also be an impact on Peterborough regional college, which has similar problems. Don Lawson, the principal, to whom I spoke three weeks ago, told me that the college has been impacted severely by the further education capital programme debacle, which has not been fully resolved to the college's satisfaction. Frankly, that will jeopardise the very ambitious city regeneration plans for a university centre to complement the extra FE provision.</p>
	<p pid="b.72.0/7">Finally, as John Richards, the director of children's services in Peterborough, has said, schools do not operate their post-16 funding discretely from their statutory provision, which could have significant implications for their ability to deliver better outcomes overall.</p>
	<p pid="b.72.0/8">The Minister has some pertinent questions to answer. How did we get into this mess, who was responsible, who will be accountable for it and, more importantly, how can we have equitable funding for our schools? We do not want promises or extra money, but cash, so that young people in Peterborough and throughout the country can achieve their ambitions.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.73.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1945" speakername="Peter Bottomley" colnum="73"  time="010:11:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0002.htm#09050659000451">
	<p pid="b.73.0/1">I am grateful to my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1626" name="Michael Penning">the Member for Hemel Hempstead (Mike Penning)</phrase> for introducing this debate and I echo his thanks to Mr. Speaker for making it possible. Clearly, this subject should have been debated for a full day on the Floor of the House, with a Minister saying at the beginning, presuming he had arrived, what is happening and what is going to happen, followed by proper winding-up speeches.</p>
	<p pid="b.73.0/2">The catastrophe of schools and colleges that provide post-16 education having to cut staff must have been known about by Ministers and their advisers well in advance of the institutions and Parliament being notified. It comes on top of the current problems associated with the Government's supervision of the LSC and the capital funding for colleges. In Worthing, as my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1944" name="Tim Loughton">the Member for East Worthing and Shoreham (Tim Loughton)</phrase> has already pointed out, virtually every young person goes to Worthing and/or Northbrook college at age 16. One of the colleges uses huts that were rescued from Southampton docks at the end of the great war from 1918 to 1920, which should have been retired; the other was built for 600 pupils but now has more than 1,500, half of whose lessons take place in huts.</p>
	<p pid="b.73.0/3">We can leave aside capital spending, which is not the main theme of the debate. The colleges are being squeezed for &pound;1.5 million cash. The Government require the LSC to pay the money as a legal commitment, but it has not been received, and the LSCs had to go to the banks for money. The unpaid governors of colleges have major legal responsibilities, but they also have to deal with the question of how many staff they may have for post-16s. Will the Minister make it plain that the LSC has paid or will pay within days the money for those fees and ensure that the other costs on the capital schemes are capitalised so that they are not pushed into deficit? Capital sums can come in a week or so. I hope the Minister answers those two precise questions today.</p>
	<p pid="b.73.0/4">Will the Minister ask his advisers to send to each hon. Member present and all hon. Members for affected parts of the United Kingdom a copy of the document, marking the footnote on page 13, which is the relevant piece of information? Is the information in the footnote the least important piece of information&mdash;perhaps it is simply a detail&mdash;or was someone, in a clever-clever way, trying to keep the catastrophe away from publicity?</p>
	<p pid="b.73.0/5">Let us ask questions in terms not of &quot;education, education, education&quot;, but of &quot;statistics, statistics, statistics.&quot; I will even answer some of them for the Minister. How long has he and the DCSF known how many 16-year-olds there would be in September? The answer is 16 years&mdash;births are registered, so the number of 16-year-olds cannot be a big surprise. Did he or his predecessors, and will his successors, know participation trends? Yes, they did and they will. Do they watch the cash? No. Who is going to lose? Late applicants will lose&mdash;the people who thought they were going into work or who thought they were not going to be in employment, education or training, who decided that they wanted to apply for a post-16 course. Who will the colleges and schools turn down? They will reject those who apply late, so the person who needs the place most is the most likely to be turned away.</p>
	<p pid="b.73.0/6">I do not want to repeat what my hon. Friends have said&mdash;the Minister will be able to read a report of what was said in the first two minutes of the debate in the <i>Official Report</i>, and his Parliamentary Private Secretary, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1576" name="Liz Blackman">the hon. Member for Erewash (Liz Blackman)</phrase>, will be able to read a report of what was said in the first 20 minutes of the debate&mdash;but there is not a single Labour Back Bencher in the Chamber, yet half the colleges affected have Labour Members of Parliament. Either there has been a Whip's operation, or Labour Members&mdash;I am not saying that they do not care&mdash;do not dare speak up. Perhaps the Whips had a meeting and told them, &quot;This is what you ought to say if you go to the debate.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.73.0/7">When the Minister speaks, I hope he focuses on answering these questions: where is the cash and who will be excluded? I hope that he understands that our colleges are finding that they have to have eight fewer members of staff and perhaps to double-up, and that he explains the situation and does not pass the responsibility on to somebody else.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.75.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1395" speakername="Jacqui Lait" colnum="75"  time="010:17:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0003.htm#09050659000452">
	<p pid="b.75.0/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1626" name="Michael Penning">the Member for Hemel Hempstead (Mike Penning)</phrase> on securing this important debate, some six weeks after it first became obvious that the funding promised to our sixth forms in our schools was to be severely cut. I should like briefly to point out, if I may, that it is something of a disgrace that those six weeks passed without the Government volunteering any statement whatever, even if there have been answers to parliamentary questions and an apologetic passage in the Budget saying that they are trying to remedy a situation that should never have arisen in the first place.</p>
	<p pid="b.75.0/2">I was first alerted to the situation when I received a copy of a letter that was sent to the Minister by Langley Park school for boys, which is in my constituency. The school is expecting a huge increase in the size of its sixth form&mdash;Bromley schools offer a very good education, so it was no surprise to any of them that their sixth forms should increase when children are faced with a lack of opportunity that has largely been brought about by the Government's economic incompetence.</p>
	<p pid="b.75.0/3">The schools are facing 7 per cent. cuts in their budgets and they are having to say to children who need sixth-form education, &quot;You are not welcome.&quot; My LEA has worked well and has been prepared to dig deep into its reserves even if it should not have had to do so. It told me that it was going to try to accommodate the children, and that was followed by the Budget, which sounded as though the &pound;650 million was extra, new money, rather than money that was being cut. We saw through that fairly quickly.</p>
	<p pid="b.75.0/4">Although my head of education is somewhat reassured that the money will be available for the first year, so we will be able to educate our children up to the level that they want, need and deserve, there are serious concerns about education the year after. The biggest outrage of the lot, as many of my colleagues have mentioned, is that although the Labour party's mantra is &quot;education, education, education&quot;, no Labour Members are interested enough in education to be here.</p>
	<p pid="b.75.0/5">My local schools are determined to educate the children of Bromley and get them into university, but the 7 per cent. overall cut is extremely hard for them to deal with in what is a tight economic settlement anyway. Langley Park school for boys, the school that wrote to the Minister and first alerted me to the situation, pointed out that it had expected to be able to provide education for every person who applied.</p>
	<p pid="b.75.0/6">In one sense, I rejoice in the fact that the Learning and Skills Council is disappearing; on the other hand, I am heavy-hearted that it is being replaced by yet more bureaucracy rather than a return to the status quo ante, which was that the Department took responsibility for sixth-form funding. That was one of the biggest mistakes that this Government have made, but as usual, they wish to deny responsibility for their decisions, pass it on to quangos and hold their hands up.</p>
	<p pid="b.75.0/7">Schools cannot impress on the LSC the need for the money. The departing LSC members are probably suffering from something that we all suffer from: end-of-termitis. They know that they are going and they have no responsibility, so they do not care. This Government have set up a system that has let down children of all abilities, in order to keep theoretically within a budget that is clearly so expandable that within days during the Budget proceedings, they found the &pound;650 million that would have been cut from senior school funding. It is yet another example of how the Government are falling apart as we watch. Every single person in this country is affected by sheer incompetence right across Government and the loss of the will to govern. We as a society will have to deal with the consequences of the incompetence emerging daily not just from the Department but from the whole of Government.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.76.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1767" speakername="Mike Hancock" colnum="76"  time="010:17:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0003.htm#09050659000453">
	<p pid="b.76.0/1">Before I call the next speaker, we have about eight minutes and only two speakers left. I hope that they will recognise the importance of giving the Minister sufficient time to answer the many points made, as I am sure he is eager to do. We should make sure that he gets enough time.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.76.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1944" speakername="Tim Loughton" colnum="76"  time="010:22:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0003.htm#09050659000454">
	<p pid="b.76.1/1">I had not intended to speak in this debate, but I am so incensed by the complacency and indifference shown by the Government that I have been moved to speak. It is extraordinary. I have never been in a Westminster Hall debate where the Minister has arrived five minutes late, the officials 10 minutes late and the Parliamentary Private Secretary 21 minutes late. It shows complete and utter contempt for a subject that is important to Members of all parties, and no Government Member has bothered to turn out.</p>
	<p pid="b.76.1/2">I echo the comments of my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1945" name="Peter Bottomley">the Member for Worthing, West (Peter Bottomley)</phrase>. We share the serious problems faced by Worthing and Northbrook colleges, our two major colleges with a sixth form. It is a double whammy. About a month ago, we took a delegation from those two colleges to see the Minister with responsibility for further education, the Under-Secretary of State for Innovation, Universities and Skills, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1412" name="Sin Simon">the hon. Member for Birmingham, Erdington (Mr. Simon)</phrase>. The situation that they are facing is desperate. They put up &pound;1.5 million that they can ill afford, and that money has now been put in limbo, as has the future of their necessary rebuilding programme, for the reasons that my hon. Friend mentioned.</p>
	<p pid="b.76.1/3">The colleges do not just want to upgrade for the sake of upgrading. We are trying to deliver education for students in the 21st century in huts, in an area of high need. The colleges have tried to do everything that the Government have asked of them to improve the training and skills of the local work force, and they have been kicked in the guts by the way in which the Government have handled the situation. The finances of those colleges are already stretched because the Government, through the incompetence of the Learning and Skills Council, have reneged on the capital spend anticipated by the colleges.</p>
	<p pid="b.76.1/4">I have a letter from the head of the Coastal West Sussex partnership that says:</p>
	<p pid="b.76.1/5" class="indent">&quot;Investment in skills is a key plank of economic policy in our region, and supported through the South East Plan, by SEEDA through its education-led regeneration policies, and by all the local authorities along the coastal strip. There is a strong consensus that investment in skills is a critical action for addressing the economic issues of the coast&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.76.1/6">It is important in our part of the world. It is not an affluent area. We have had serious unemployment problems recently due to job cuts by big employers. Norwich Union announced the loss of more than 600 jobs, and GlaxoSmithKline and BOC Edwards have also announced job losses. One serious problem that local employers face is an insufficiency of local skills. If they can take on more skilled people, they can take on less skilled people on the back of that.</p>
	<p pid="b.76.1/7">Peter Corrigan, the principal of Worthing college, e-mailed my hon. Friend and me. In the wake of all the problems with capital funding shortfalls, he said:</p>
	<p pid="b.76.1/8" class="indent">&quot;At Worthing College our allocation should have been based on 1,451 full-time 16-18 year olds as a minimum. The allocation is 1,425, giving us a &pound;130,000 funding reduction on our baseline income. However, because we have successfully retained more students this year and applications are running at record levels, our most conservative estimate of numbers suggests we will recruit 1,500 16-18 year olds. This would mean educating 75 students without funding. The funding for 75 students is in the order of &pound;340,000.</p>
	<p pid="b.76.1/9" class="indent">The implications of this are that Colleges may turn away students and not be able to offer places to later applicants, who are often more needy and vulnerable. The recession means there are more young people looking to stay in education without the requisite funding for them. This would be a real negative for Worthing and Adur, increasing the number of young people who are NEET and not gaining qualifications and increasing their life chances.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.76.1/10">That is crucial. It is a double whammy that should not have happened at all. It has been compounded by the Government's incompetence and now by their indifference, and they have the brass neck to challenge the Opposition to match their funding commitment. That commitment was given late in the day, and we still lack the details, which are sorely needed at the sharp end by schools and colleges.</p>
	<p pid="b.76.1/11">This debate is timely. It should have been a topical debate in Government time. There is little more topical at the moment, or of interest to so many Members. I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1626" name="Michael Penning">the Member for Hemel Hempstead (Mike Penning)</phrase> on bringing it to the attention of a lacklustre Government Front Bench.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.77.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2038" speakername="Bob Spink" colnum="77"  time="010:27:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0003.htm#09050659000455">
	<p pid="b.77.0/1">We have before us one of the most caring and assiduous Ministers in the Government. He is an excellent chap and a superb Minister, but I do not envy him his position today. He has a difficult wicket on which to play. The King John school in my constituency was one of the first sixth-form colleges in the country&mdash;perhaps the first&mdash;and it certainly remains one of the best. However, like others, particularly SEEVIC college, it has suffered cuts in its capital funding. Such colleges trusted the Learning and Skills Council, and they now feel betrayed. However, we have been over all that, so I will not trawl through it again.</p>
	<p pid="b.77.0/2">The cuts have come at a time when we should be expanding the provision of further education and sixth-form opportunities for youngsters who will need them, particularly in my constituency, where traditional opportunities and outlets for them in the City of London have dried up somewhat, as we all know. I put it to the Minister, though, that creating yet more quangos is not the way to solve the problem.</p>
	<p pid="b.77.0/3">We should not be churlish, of course; we must be fair-minded. We should welcome the extra money that the Government have put into education. Over the past decade, they have done extremely well, but this problem is serious. I am sure that the Minister will do all that he can to address it. I look forward to hearing what he has to say. I want him to tell my sixth-form colleges how they can continue to provide a superb service for local people in my constituency.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.78.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1458" speakername="Stephen Williams" colnum="78"  time="010:29:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0003.htm#09050659000456">
	<p pid="b.78.0/1">It is a pleasure to serve under your chairmanship, Mr. Hancock. I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1626" name="Michael Penning">the hon. Member for Hemel Hempstead (Mike Penning)</phrase> on securing the debate and drawing such a crowd from his own party. I am pleased that the Minister turned up eventually. As those of us who have just completed consideration of the Apprenticeships, Skills, Children and Learning Bill will know, including <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1825" name="John Hayes">the hon. Member for South Holland and The Deepings (Mr. Hayes)</phrase>, a habit is developing of Ministers not turning up on time for proceedings. However, I will follow your exhortations to other hon. Members, Mr. Hancock, and try to keep my remarks brief so that the Minister has plenty of time to answer questions.</p>
	<p pid="b.78.0/2">This debate is on the latest in a litany of failures in the two new education Departments. Last year, they failed to send out confirmations of education maintenance allowances for young people. Moving to the next age group up, that was followed by a complete miscalculation of the number of people who would qualify for student grants. That led to the budget for higher education places being trimmed, which will cause a crisis this summer. On the Learning and Skills Council, we have had several debates in Westminster Hall and in the main Chamber on capital expenditure for further education colleges. There has been a long-term gap between the funding received by colleges and schools for 16 to 19-year-olds.</p>
	<p pid="b.78.0/3">This year, there is a real cash shortage in the provision that schools and colleges are receiving from the Government. That has led to yet another emergency announcement and emergency measure. Why has that taken place? As <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1945" name="Peter Bottomley">the hon. Member for Worthing, West (Peter Bottomley)</phrase> said in his powerful speech, it appears that it is partly because the Government were taken completely by surprise by the over-subscription caused by students deciding, rightly, to stay in education beyond the age of 16. That is amazing because, as he rightly said, the number of people in that cohort was known with considerable certainty before that time. We know from previous recessions that more 16 and 18-year-olds decide to stay in education and training at such times.</p>
	<p pid="b.78.0/4">With last year's student grants fiasco and the upcoming crisis in university places this summer, the two education Departments are building a record of being caught out and surprised by what goes on in the real world. Whichever party is in government in two years' time, I hope that the Departments will not be caught out again because we will have more people staying on at school sixth forms and going to further education colleges post-16. I hope they will ensure that there are enough places for 18-year-olds to continue in training or education, whether through adult apprenticeships or higher education.</p>
	<p pid="b.78.0/5">The Chancellor announced more emergency funding for this sector in the Budget, just as he had to do for the college capital expenditure programme. This year there will be an additional &pound;250 million and next year an additional &pound;400 million. That is not recession-related funding. It is not a bail-out for the banks or a loan for car companies; it is a bail-out for another Department that is guilty of mismanaging its budget. It is ridiculous that one reason why the Government were forced into the bail-out was the spectre of being sued by schools and colleges. That remains to be seen.</p>
	<p pid="b.78.0/6">A squeeze on future education budgets was also announced in the Budget. There will be a renewed efficiency drive in the sector with hundreds of millions of pounds having to be saved. Extra money was announced on the one hand, and on the other the sector was told that it will have to make significant savings. That could take us back to square one. What a way to treat a sector that is central in delivering the objective of the Government and other parties to have skilled people who can weather the recession and enter the workplace. This sector is crucial in delivering the diplomas for 14 to 19-year olds that are being rolled out across the country. It will also be crucial if the participation age is raised to 17 and then 18 over the next few years.</p>
	<p pid="b.78.0/7">After the fiasco in college capital expenditure, the Government were obliged to set up an inquiry into their own mismanagement or into that of an agency under their control. With this fiasco, I hope that the Minister will not announce an inquiry, nor hide behind officials at the Learning and Skills Council, but will take some responsibility for the two education Departments and answer the pertinent questions that have been put to him by hon. Members.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.79.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1825" speakername="John Hayes" colnum="79"  time="010:34:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0003.htm#09050659000457">
	<p pid="b.79.0/1">The subject of this debate characterises the fallacy, falsehood and failure that lie at the heart of the Government. Falsehood follows fallacy, and failure follows both. The most eloquent expression of those failures is in the field of education, in which the Government go from one farce or crisis to another. As my hon. Friends the Members for East Worthing and Shoreham (Tim Loughton) and for Aylesbury (Mr. Lidington) and <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1458" name="Stephen Williams">the hon. Member for Bristol, West (Stephen Williams)</phrase> said, Ministers refuse to come to the House to explain serious matters that have damning consequences for schools, colleges and universities, and therefore for learners and potential learners up and down the country.</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/2">This debate on sixth-form funding is yet another expression of the tortuous calamity that characterises the Learning and Skills Council and its relationship with the Department. There is blather and there are blunders: blather when promises are made and blunders when those promises are broken. The blunders illustrate institutionalised maladministration. We can examine this issue because my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1626" name="Michael Penning">the Member for Hemel Hempstead (Mike Penning)</phrase> has brought it to our attention, on which I congratulate him. As has been said, this debate would not have happened had it been left to Ministers. As my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1395" name="Jacqui Lait">the Member for Beckenham (Mrs. Lait)</phrase> said, we have known about this matter for six weeks, yet there has been no statement and no debate in Government time.</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/3">If I sound cross, it is not for myself or for the Opposition. I am cross for the learners, teachers, managers and governors in the schools and colleges that are so seriously affected by this incompetence. There will be a shortfall in funding for the next academic year brought about by what my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1858" name="Michael Gove">the Member for Surrey Heath (Michael Gove)</phrase> has described as a catastrophic miscalculation of the number of students staying in education. He said:</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/4" class="indent">&quot;Many schools planned their courses on the reasonable assumption that they would not be penalised for increasing participation post-16.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/5">Indeed, that course of action was positively encouraged by the Department.</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/6">Although I acknowledge that &pound;250 million was found hastily to cover the shortfall, this debate is vital. We must know why this happened and we must be assured that it will not happen again. Fallacy, failure and falsehood are symptomatic of a Government in their death throes. Edmund Burke wrote:</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/7" class="indent">&quot;Nothing turns out to be so oppressive and unjust as a feeble government&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/8">this Government are certainly feeble.</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/9">The LSC wrote several times to schools and sixth-form colleges about provisional funding allocations for 2009-10. It seems certain that it knew that those provisional calculations were wrong. We want to hear whether Ministers knew that too, and if not why not. On <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-02">2 March</phrase>, the LSC wrote again to confirm the funding and indicated that the number of learners was</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/10" class="indent">&quot;in excess of the anticipated number&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/11">and that it was seeking permission to fund the learners in full. Finally, on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-30">30 March</phrase>, the LSC wrote a third time with reduced allocations for school and sixth-form funding. Did realisation dawn on Ministers in the space of just one month? Surely that suggests falsehood&mdash;it is certainly indicative of failure. In respect of fallacy, what about the Prime Minister's claim that Labour has &quot;transformed&quot; education?</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/12">The Association of School and College Leaders said that a sixth form of 250 pupils would be &pound;50,000 to &pound;55,000 worse off than expected under the new arrangements. As my hon. Friend the Member for Hemel Hempstead said, many schools are worse off than that. A sixth-form college of 3,000 students stands to lose more than &pound;300,000. The minimum funding guarantee of an annual increase of at least 2.1 per cent. per learner for school sixth forms that have a funding rate per &quot;standard learner number&quot; of less than &pound;3,200 has been scrapped. It is therefore unsurprising that Dr. John Dunford, the general secretary of the ASCL, wrote to the Chancellor telling him that there was</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/13" class="indent">&quot;widespread disappointment and considerable anger&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/14">among schools that will suffer from the shortfalls.</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/15">There seems to be an emerging pattern in which quangos and Ministers do not speak. Rather like estranged partners in a marriage, they seems to have no communication, even though they are living cheek by jowl. It is extraordinary that the lines of accountability have been broken&mdash;or perhaps Ministers knew and did not say. I cannot believe that of this Minister or any others, but if that is not the case, there are fundamental problems with how the Government communicate with some of their key quangos and the way in which they act upon information from those quangos. As we have heard, however, they are about to set up several new quangos, which is likely to lead to further problems, as my hon. Friends have indicated.</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/16">The tendency that I have described is perhaps most damningly seen in the administrative upheaval surrounding the Building Colleges for the Future programme, which has been mentioned. Those who have argued that their sixth forms are having difficulties could equally have said the same of colleges in their locality. I know, for example, that Peterborough Regional college is struggling, and that colleges across the country are suffering a similar fate, because we heard that in yesterday's debate. This is the second time that I have spoken on this issue in just a few hours, so I am certainly earning my crust. I guess, in that regard, that the Minister is too.</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/17">The colleges programme was mismanaged by the very same officials in the LSC who are responsible for the problems that we are debating today. There seems to be endemic failure: information about capital projects has been mishandled, mismanaged and miscommunicated to Ministers. How could that possibly have happened? Perhaps we do know because, in that case, the Government commissioned a report from Sir Andrew Foster, who concluded that there was</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/18" class="indent">&quot;insufficient clarity and understanding around the relationship between the LSC and&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/19">the Department. The price for that insufficient clarity and understanding is being paid by learners and teachers across the country. That is why the outrage that we have heard this morning has found form in this debate and why this matter deserves to be debated on the Floor of the House. I hope that the Government will take the opportunity, as a result of this debate, to do just that.</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/20">Colleges and schools have progressed to an advanced stage of planning only to have their plans halted and their hopes shattered. Some 144 colleges have had their budgets frozen. Both situations are tied together by the inefficiency and sluggishness of the response&mdash;limousined Ministers arrive late and react slowly. When both crises broke, an explanation from the LSC was notably absent, and the ministerial response was little better, consisting of reactive statements and soundbites that went little way towards allaying the legitimate concerns of the sector.</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/21">Some &pound;250 million has been committed to sixth forms and &pound;300 million has been committed to colleges, but those pledges have been accompanied by a vast, confusing silence. No one seems to know where the money is going to or whom it will benefit. The &pound;300 million for the Building Colleges for the Future programme is little more than a drop in the water. Colleges and schools are still confused and uneasy about the direction in which their institutions are heading, and, as the weeks pass, key decisions cannot be made. The severity of the situation seems to grow daily, but there is now an opportunity to remedy that. As the LSC has not managed to explain to schools how it plans to compensate for the mistake, perhaps the Minister will take this opportunity to guarantee that all schools and colleges will receive full funding allocations. I have asked one of his colleagues to confirm that all schools and colleges will be fully funded, regardless of which stage in the process they are at. Will the Minister give that guarantee today, which was suggested in the letter of <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-02">2 March</phrase>? Will he also comment, in those terms, on exactly how that money will be allocated and on what basis it will be delivered to schools and colleges?</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/22">Will the Minister show that he understands the gravity of the situation and the outrage that people feel? To be helpful, I shall pose a number of questions that might assist him to give the assurances sought by the House and those affected. First, will he comment on the strategy that he intends to put in place to make such failures impossible in the future, in the way that my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1798" name="Anne Main">the Member for St. Albans (Anne Main)</phrase> demanded? Secondly, will he explain the structures and mechanisms that will make that possible, as my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1437" name="Tobias Ellwood">the Member for Bournemouth, East (Mr. Ellwood)</phrase> suggested? Will he outline when he first knew of the crisis, and how and when he made that information available to the House? Will he say what lines of communication broke down between the LSC and the Department? We know that the Department's officials attend key LSC meetings, so it is inconceivable that there was not a channel of communication. How, then, was that channel broken?</p>
	<p pid="b.79.0/23">Will the Minister comment on the possibility of carrying out an independent analysis of this matter, as my hon. Friend the Member for Aylesbury suggested? Perhaps that should be done by the Public Accounts Committee, or maybe Sir Andrew Foster should be revived to say a further word on this subject, as he has already reported on the debacle in colleges. Finally, will the Minister apologise unreservedly, up front and without passing the buck to officials? Will he say that Ministers owe the House and those who have participated in this debate&mdash;and, much more significantly, teachers and head teachers, governors and parents, and, most of all, students&mdash;an absolute apology, along with an assurance that this will never happen again?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.82.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1437" speakername="Tobias Ellwood" colnum="82"  time="010:34:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000458">
	<p pid="b.82.0/1">On a point of order, Mr. Hancock. I seek your guidance. Would it be in order for the Palace of Westminster, which put such an effort into setting out the chairs for Labour Members&mdash;all 30 of them&mdash;to get a rebate considering that only two of them have been used in the debate?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.82.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1767" speakername="Mike Hancock" colnum="82"  time="010:34:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000459">
	<p pid="b.82.1/1">That was a good try, Mr. Ellwood, but even your enterprise does not give me the right to say that is a legitimate point of order&mdash;it should be ignored by all.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.82.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1548" speakername="Jim Knight" speakeroffice="The Minister for Schools and Learners"  colnum="82"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000460">
	<p pid="b.82.2/1">Let me start by giving you, Mr. Hancock, as I have in writing, and the House, an apology for being two minutes late. I should have either walked or allowed more than seven minutes to get here from the Department, but I am seeing the Mayor of London today, on the anniversary of his election, and I will pass on my comments about the traffic situation around Westminster.</p>
	<p pid="b.82.2/2">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1626" name="Michael Penning">the hon. Member for Hemel Hempstead (Mike Penning)</phrase> on securing the debate, which has given an important opportunity for the Members present to express their concerns and anger, which we have heard this morning, and for me to explain what has happened in respect of the problems with post-16 funding, particularly for sixth forms.</p>
	<p pid="b.82.2/3">Obviously, the background to this issue is the importance of post-16 education. That is why the Government have raised the participation age and have introduced the September guarantee, which I shall talk more about later. As hon. Members have commented, the Learning and Skills Council has apologised, on <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-03">3 April</phrase>, for the problems. I should like to say, at the outset, that I am very sorry for the disruption that has been caused to school and college leaders over the conflicting content of the letters that they received in March. Thanks to the Chancellor's Budget statement, we can now confirm that there will be expanded funding&mdash;not just up to the levels that were promised, without the funding to back them, on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-02">2 March</phrase>, in the LSC letter, but beyond those levels&mdash;for post-16 education from September, when the money will be received by colleges.</p>
	<p pid="b.82.2/4">Let me work through the sequence of events&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.83.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1825" speakername="John Hayes" colnum="83"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000461">
	<p pid="b.83.0/1">Will the Minister give way?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.83.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1548" speakername="Jim Knight" colnum="83"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000462">
	<p pid="b.83.1/1">I want to work through the sequence of events before I give way to interventions, so that I manage to explain properly what went on.</p>
	<p pid="b.83.1/2">As Members who follow these things will be aware, the funding process starts in November every year, as it did last year, with the annual statement of priorities. The funding agreement between the Government and the LSC sets out the allocation of funding for post-16 learning. During the December to January period, that is then followed by a dialogue between schools, colleges and the LSC over what capacity they have in the system to deliver post-16 learning. In January, as the problems in the economy caused by the global banking crisis became clear, we agreed with the Treasury that there should be an additional 17,000 apprenticeship places to cope with some of the increase in demand that was starting to emerge. That figure not only took account of the data on previous years' out-turns, which is a normal part of the process, but looked at some of the projections of increased learner numbers for September.</p>
	<p pid="b.83.1/3">The moderation of bids then proceeds during February and the notification is usually sent to schools and colleges in March. This year, that happened with the letter of <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-02">2 March</phrase>, which was sent to school sixth forms. Unfortunately, that letter was not seen by Ministers and it did not have clearance. In the first paragraph, the letter included the phrase that it</p>
	<p pid="b.83.1/4" class="indent">&quot;establishes your final allocation for 2009/10&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.83.1/5">As I have said, the money was not there and it had not been agreed to make final allocations on that basis. The letter went on to state</p>
	<p pid="b.83.1/6" class="indent">&quot;We are awaiting the Secretary of State's approval for this increase&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.83.1/7">However, the apology that the LSC published on <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-03">3 April</phrase> states:</p>
	<p pid="b.83.1/8" class="indent">&quot;it is clear that our letter of <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-02">2 March</phrase> to schools has caused them confusion and concern for which we apologise. The letter set out that there were ongoing discussions with the Department and that further checks needed to be done; however, it was misleading to say that these were final rather than provisional allocations.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.83.1/9">I first saw the letter of <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-02">2 March</phrase> on the same day that that apology was issued&mdash;on <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-03">3 April</phrase>. That was the first time any Ministers saw that letter.</p>
	<p pid="b.83.1/10">The LSC wrote again to school sixth forms in a letter that I had approved to say, among other things&mdash;<i>[</i><i>Interruption.</i><i>]</i></p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.84.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1626" speakername="Michael Penning" colnum="84"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000463">
	<p pid="b.84.0/1">Will the Minister give way?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.84.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1767" speakername="Mike Hancock" colnum="84"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000464">
	<p pid="b.84.1/1">Order. I am trying to give the Minister the opportunity to be heard by everyone, not just those who want to harangue him.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.84.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1548" speakername="Jim Knight" colnum="84"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000465">
	<p pid="b.84.2/1">Thank you, Mr. Hancock. I know that the hon. Member for Hemel Hempstead wants to intervene. As I said to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1825" name="John Hayes">the hon. Member for South Holland and The Deepings (Mr. Hayes)</phrase>, I would like to conclude outlining the sequence of events so that they are clear and on the record.</p>
	<p pid="b.84.2/2">The letter of <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-27">27 March</phrase> that was sent to schools gave them their allocations. It has since caused anger and concern among leaders, which has been reflected by their representatives in the House. There are statutory reasons why a letter had to be sent out then: it was so that schools and colleges could rightly set their budgets. That letter said</p>
	<p pid="b.84.2/3" class="indent">&quot;We continue to consider options for further funding, including meeting emerging pressures from the impact of the recession and further recruitment during the year, especially to deliver the September Guarantee and tackle the needs of those not in education, employment or training. We continue to work with DCSF on the funding pressure and best estimates of demand.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.84.2/4">That letter was signalling that, beyond the estimates of learner demand that were emerging during February and March, recessionary impacts meant that demand was continuing to emerge&mdash;particularly because of the numbers of people aged 16 to 19, who were in employment but not training, losing their jobs. Such people wanted to come into learning in college and we needed to respond to that. The matter was the subject of discussions across Government, which concluded in the announcement made in the Budget. I was able to negotiate an additional &pound;655 million from the Treasury to fund post-16 learning over two years&mdash;&pound;251 million for this financial year and &pound;404 million for the following financial year. That will allow us to deliver our September guarantee and not only to fund the allocations that were made wrongly on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-02">2 March</phrase>, but to go beyond those allocations.</p>
	<p pid="b.84.2/5">A letter was then sent to schools and colleges by the LSC on <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-27">27 April</phrase> informing them about the news in the Budget and saying among other things:</p>
	<p pid="b.84.2/6" class="indent">&quot;This means that I can provide immediate reassurance that you will be funded for your level of recruitment for the coming year discussed with the Learning and Skills Council (LSC) in early March. However, since you last discussed your forecast levels of recruitment with the LSC earlier this year, you may have had further evidence of the likely demand by young people, or you may be in a position to stimulate additional demand to make sure more young people continue in learning rather than becoming unemployed. We therefore need your further advice and information on extra likely demand to meet the September Guarantee.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.84.2/7">So, the LSC was signalling for the first time that schools and colleges could, indeed, come forward for additional funding if they identified additional demand to that identified in February/March.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.85.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1825" speakername="John Hayes" colnum="85"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000466">
	<p pid="b.85.0/1" class="italic"> rose&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.85.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1548" speakername="Jim Knight" colnum="85"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000467">
	<p pid="b.85.1/1">I have almost finished. At the end of last week, in relation to the detailed allocations, I agreed that the <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-02">2 March</phrase> figure could go out to learners, with the exception of four institutions. The reason I have been unable to be absolutely clear on that until now is that there are four institutions that will not get up to the <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-02">2 March</phrase> allocation. I will be talking to the MPs who represent those institutions today&mdash;the hon. Members for Braintree (Mr. Newmark) and for Mid-Norfolk (Mr. Simpson) and my hon. Friends the Members for Basildon (Angela E. Smith) and for Norwich, North (Dr. Gibson). Technical reasons relating to how the formula was worked out mean that those institutions will get less than they thought. In all but one case, significant numbers are not involved and, in every case, I think that the school and college know the situation in respect of those allocations.</p>
	<p pid="b.85.1/2">Finally, before I take a couple of interventions if I have time, it is worth reemphasising that the allocation from the Budget means that we can fund more post-16 learners than ever before. The allocation is up from &pound;1.5 million to &pound;1.55 million. That is on top of the 17,500 additional apprenticeship places to which I referred earlier, and it includes funding 55,000 extra educational maintenance allowance places. A detailed process will now go on until <phrase class="date" code="2009-05-22">22 May</phrase> to agree the very final allocations, including that extra amount for those colleges and schools that are able to stimulate additional demand in order to meet the needs of young people.</p>
	<p pid="b.85.1/3">It is also important for me to say that&mdash;I know that the Opposition will not like this&mdash;we are committed to a September guarantee and, going forward, we are committed to funding places for every 16 to 19-year-old in school and college who wants one and wants to carry on learning. In terms of skills, it is important that we come out of this recession stronger than when we went into it. That is not a guarantee that I have heard repeated by the Opposition, who are so well represented in this Chamber.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.85.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1825" speakername="John Hayes" colnum="85"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000468">
	<p pid="b.85.2/1">I will be very brief. The Minister said that he was not aware of the letter that was sent out on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-02">2 March</phrase>. Were his officials aware of it? In other words, did the Department know because, presumably, he has at least conducted some kind of internal investigation into these matters? Perhaps when answering that point, he will also tell us&mdash;he referred to this glibly earlier&mdash;whether all those colleges that were promised extra capital funding by the LSC will get the money that they were promised.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.85.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1548" speakername="Jim Knight" colnum="85"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000469">
	<p pid="b.85.3/1">Certainly all those schools and colleges that were promised money on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-02">2 March</phrase> will get that allocation, with the exception of the four institutions that I mentioned. The issue of capital is different and continues to be debated in the House with my colleagues from the Department for Innovation, Universities and Skills.</p>
	<p pid="b.85.3/2">In conclusion, we set ourselves the bold ambition of having a world-class education system that brings out the best in every single learner. That means a system that can adapt to the changing world in which we now live&mdash;<i>[</i><i>Interruption.</i><i>]</i> Sorry, on the other question, one official was aware of the letter that went out on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-02">2 March</phrase>.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.86.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1626" speakername="Michael Penning" colnum="86"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000470">
	<p pid="b.86.0/1">On a point of order, Mr. Hancock, is it acceptable for a Minister of the Crown to make a commitment during a debate that he will give way to an hon. Member and then refuse to do so, knowing full well that the time scale means it is impossible for that hon. Member to get in before the debate is terminated?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.86.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1767" speakername="Mike Hancock" colnum="86"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000471">
	<p pid="b.86.1/1">A Minister should not only arrive on time, but, if he gives such a commitment in a debate, he should, according to the conventions of the House, find time to let that hon. Member come in.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.86.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1548" speakername="Jim Knight" colnum="86"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000472">
	<p pid="b.86.2/1">Thank you, Mr. Hancock.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.86.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1626" speakername="Michael Penning" colnum="86"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000473">
	<p pid="b.86.3/1">Give way.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.86.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1548" speakername="Jim Knight" colnum="86"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000474">
	<p pid="b.86.4/1">I will give way for a very brief intervention.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.86.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1626" speakername="Michael Penning" colnum="86"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000475">
	<p pid="b.86.5/1">It is absolutely fascinating that the Minister now gives way because the Chair has lambasted him on the basis that he will not answer the question. Will he answer a simple question and if he cannot do so, will he write to me? Why are some of my schools today telling me that they have not had written confirmation about the shortfall&mdash;in one school of &pound;60,000 and in another of &pound;90,000? They have had nothing at all. Some schools have received something and some have not. Why?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.86.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1767" speakername="Mike Hancock" colnum="86"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000476">
	<p pid="b.86.6/1">You have 20 seconds, Mr. Knight.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.86.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1548" speakername="Jim Knight" colnum="86"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000477">
	<p pid="b.86.7/1">Thank you, Mr. Hancock. There are 1,730 schools and colleges in receipt of the letter. If some have not received it, I shall pursue the matter when I leave this Chamber.</p>
	<p pid="b.86.7/2">Our education system must change. We are responding to a global recession&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.86.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1767" speakername="Mike Hancock" colnum="86"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000478">
	<p pid="b.86.8/1">Order. I would like to thank all Members and the Minister for the courtesy that they have shown to the Chair, and Members for the courtesy that they have shown to each other to enable them to speak in the debate. I request those Members who are leaving to do so quietly, and we will move on to the next debate.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.87.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="87"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000002">
	Government Procurement
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.87.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1833" speakername="David Kidney" colnum="87"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0004.htm#09050659000479">
	<p pid="b.87.1/1">It is a pleasure to see you in the Chair for this debate, Mr. Hancock, and the Treasury Minister who is here to respond to it.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/2">The premise of this debate about sustainable procurement is that the Government have fine policies for sustainable procurement promotion, but there is confusion over responsibility, and some practical guidance is missing. That means that there is not the leadership and direction necessary to make as big a success of sustainable procurement as we should.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/3">For much of my speech, I shall focus on the power of public procurement, but sustainable procurement is the responsibility of every procurer. In fact, in some instances, the private sector is ahead of the public sector, particularly in respect of private finance initiative contracts. Whatever people think about the politics of such contracts, those who bid to construct and then run a building or a series of premises for 30 years are clearly focused on the cost over the whole life of the contract, not just the up-front building costs. In some senses, the private sector is already aware of whole-life costing, which I shall discuss, when the public sector is a bit slower.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/4">The public sector has enormous purchasing power, and it would be interesting to hear whether the Minister has a figure for that. I estimate that &pound;175 billion a year is spent by all public sector organisations on goods, services and utilities. I contend that that purchasing power could be used to lead by example to promote sustainable procurement, which is the procurement of goods, utilities and services in a manner that maximises the environmental, social and economic benefits for all of society over the whole life of the procured asset.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/5">In 2005, the Government set themselves the ambitious goal of making the UK a leader in the European Union in sustainable procurement by 2009&mdash;this year. A little over a year ago, I chaired an inquiry into sustainable procurement which last summer resulted in the report, &quot;Costing the Future: Securing Value for Money through Sustainable Procurement&quot;, which was intended to be a contribution to the debate about how best to achieve the Government's ambition.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/6">Our inquiry took evidence from private sector companies, the public sector&mdash;central Government, local government, the National Audit Office, the Audit Commission, the Office of Government Commerce&mdash;and many others, and we published our report in the summer of 2008. The report states that many of the necessary policies are in place for sustainable procurement but they have not been consistently translated into practice. We found some instances of good practice but many missed opportunities. I shall try later to give some examples of where we felt opportunities had been missed. Since the report's publication, I have been happy to see several further Government initiatives&mdash;for example, the creation of the Centre of Expertise in Sustainable Procurement, which will help to address the issues raised in the report.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/7">What can sustainable procurement achieve? Clearly, there is a great deal of focus today on the dangers to the environment and the urgency of tackling climate change. As a result, there is a focus on environmental sustainability. That is one aspect, and it is one with which sustainable procurement clearly can help. After all, the Government have pledged to reduce carbon emissions by 80 per cent. by 2050, and the whole of Parliament bought into that by passing the Climate Change Act 2008. Just consider the Building Schools for the Future programme, which provides schools that will be used well past 2050, yet so far it is nowhere near making the design changes and reductions in energy consumption that will make a contribution to the tough target that we have set ourselves.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/8">If we want to be at the forefront in leading the world in low-carbon technologies&mdash;both for consumption in this country and as exports that will earn us money&mdash;and resource-efficient economies in the future, we have to be attuned to the potential of global green market opportunities and innovate now. Sustainable procurement policies would help with such innovation.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/9">As well as the environmental sustainability argument, there is an argument for better value for money. We must take into account the medium and long-term costs as well as short-term costs. That is the crucial point of whole-life costing, which I shall come on to. It means sometimes spending marginally more at the outset of a project in order to reduce drastically the whole-life costs throughout the contract.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/10">A project may cost more up front, but if people are mentally attuned to doing things the right way, some features may actually cost nothing extra. For example, orienting a building to be in the right position to catch the maximum amount of daylight and sunshine does not involve more money, but it does involve thinking about the whole-life cost of the procurement, not just the actual building costs.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/11">More sustainable construction can help by drastically reducing energy prices. It would be interesting to hear whether the Minister has any forecasts for future energy costs. We clearly see that gas and electricity prices are on an upward curve. People are talking about investing in a new generation of nuclear power, which will be expensive. Even some renewable energies are expensive, because they are at the beginning of their process. Therefore, we need to attune ourselves to wanting to reduce energy consumption in new buildings and projects where we can.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/12">The same applies to water consumption. We can all see that with an increasing population and greater demands for water, the cost of using water will be higher in the future. We must invest in ways to minimise the consumption of water. Reusing water and harvesting rainwater are ways of keeping costs down over the long term of contracts.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/13">Also on sustainability and better value for money, we could get long-term unemployed people back to work if there were incentives to help people into work as part of procurement contracts. We would reduce social benefit costs in this country and hopefully reduce the social problems associated with long-term unemployment more generally.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/14">That brings me to promoting social cohesion and sustainable communities as an objective of procurement. An example is the Building Schools for the Future programme. It has enormous potential to promote opportunities for small and medium-sized enterprises to bid for parts of contracts, as long as the process is welcoming and open to them. Consider the building of a new school. A traditional procurement approach might simply advocate the construction of a building in which students can be taught. Sustainable procurement would bring an appreciation of how features such as renewable energy technologies offer the potential to minimise the environmental impact of the building. Furthermore, such procurement would be a practical demonstration&mdash;a learning tool&mdash;of environmental sustainability for the school community itself, and, being set in the wider community, for people at large to learn about new technologies.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/15">In addition to that benefit, through the inclusion of social clauses such as requirements in respect of regeneration of the area and using apprentices in the construction process, sustainable procurement could be used to address unemployment, social mobility and social cohesion. For an extended school&mdash;is that not the ambition these days for every school?&mdash;early engagement in the procurement process with community leaders would ensure that the building is designed and constructed to meet the wider needs of the community. That one example of building one school shows that best value for money and environmental, economic and social concerns can be addressed through sustainable procurement.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/16">Correctly made up, the contracts can encourage greater social cohesion by including provisos on using people in apprenticeships or the long-term unemployed, and they can make a difference to the whole community in which the project takes place. Therefore sustainable procurement is not an abstract, idealistic goal, but a practical, achievable objective for government. By using procurement to promote the goals of sustainability, economic efficiency, environmental sensitivity and social justice, the Government can help to foster a better society composed of sustainable communities that are more able to respond to the global economic market. Why is this not happening every time now?</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/17">The first barrier, which I learned of from the inquiry, is affordability. There is always enormous pressure to make short-term cashable savings, yet there is little or no incentive to reduce the long-term costs. Often, that is exacerbated by the split between capital and revenue budgets, meaning that procurers cannot think long term. Three-year settlements have been helpful, but when we are talking about 30-year contracts, as many of the relevant contracts would be, people need to be able to move between revenue-in-the-future costs and capital costs up front to complete a whole-life estimation and a contract built on whole-life costs.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/18">Budget silos are another problem. Sometimes, different people make decisions in different parts of the project. Let me give a simple example from my constituency of Stafford. My local authority wanted to replace an ageing leisure centre and did a deal with a private developer, under which he would build the new leisure centre for free and, in return, would have the site on which the old leisure centre stood. So the developer's ambition was to build a new leisure centre as small and cheaply as could be got away with, consistent with good standards of modern construction&mdash;I have no criticism of my new leisure centre in Stafford, in that sense&mdash;but he was not able to conceive of my argument about including renewable energy technologies in the design, for example, as it was not in his interest. The borough council now picks up the running costs for the next 30 years, which will be higher than they could have been. That is an example of how people dealing with different parts of the project are not willing to work with each other. That is why leadership and guidance is so important.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/19">Although the Treasury procurement green book says that we should not always go with the lowest cost, it does not give sufficient guidance on what sustainable procurement actually means. Despite Treasury guidance stating that projects should be whole-life costed, the public sector does not possess the tools to do that meaningfully, let alone take account of the social and environmental benefits in its calculations.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/20">The solutions are as follows. First, the report strongly advocates whole-life costing to incentivise people's behaviour and get them thinking about the long-term effects of the contract that they enter into, and for them to start to provide an accurate cost for sustainability and see how budgets can be adjusted between the revenue costs and the capital to get the right outcome. Secondly, a stronger theme of the report was commissioning for outcomes instead of just trying to procure outputs. Enabling people to use their own solutions to get to the outcomes that they want helps to promote innovation and allows for additional and unforeseen social and environmental benefits to be weighed in selecting the right bid for the contract. Those desirable outcomes are achievable, but there are barriers to the solutions.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/21">It is difficult to get Ministers to take responsibility and show leadership. That is a not a criticism of my hon. Friend the Minister, but let us consider what happens when I ask the Government who is responsible for leadership. The Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs says, &quot;We're responsible for sustainable procurement&quot;; the Cabinet Office Minister says, &quot;I'm responsible for sustainable procurement&quot;; the Office of Government Commerce says, &quot;But we're responsible for it&quot;; and the Exchequer Secretary is our Minister, so a Treasury Minister is responsible. I keep going round the circuit of the Ministers in those Departments to get somebody to say that the detailed work needs to be done on whole-life costing and that incentives are needed to be able to do the right thing in the procurement process&mdash;and to get something done. Is the Minister the one responsible for this and is she aware, and willing, to do the things that need to be done to achieve this? I hope that we can get to the point at which somebody says, &quot;I am the person who is going to sort this out. What needs sorting out?&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/22">There is a need for standardisation. As we saw when we talked to the bidders for the contracts that I have mentioned, there is a great lack of benchmark data and of standards to work to in presenting a bid that shows a whole-life cost. Benchmark data help everybody to have a common understanding of what the ambition is and they show what things need to be taken, and not taken, into account. For example, the Audit Commission said to us: &quot;If it's a whole-life contract for a building and at the end of its life it's finished, should the whole-life costing, as part of the contract, take into account the decommissioning costs at the end?&quot; Some people do that, but most do not because it ramps up the costs still further. But if people are not bidding with a common understanding, it is like comparing apples and pears.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/23">Some people are working to try to develop helpful standards. The British Standards Institution, for example, has a whole-life costing standard to try to bring uniformity to the process. I am not saying that the BSI is the one and only organisation that can do this. If we can develop standards that everybody applies, at least we are all singing from the same hymn sheet in assessing who wins the bid.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/24">People working in procurement need a greater level of skills to be able to work with the benchmark data and standards, and with the idea of being much more flexible about how to achieve the best contract over a longer period. To some extent, new metrics on standards are needed to standardise the methods of financially valuing things that do not always have a price on them&mdash;for example, the social and environmental benefits that I mentioned.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/25">We found some relevant examples in our inquiry. In a project for eight schools, the bidder wanted to put in biomass boilers instead of natural gas boilers, and although the installation cost of the biomass boilers was &pound;800,000 more, in round figures, than the natural gas ones, over 30 years the running costs would have been &pound;8 million less. But the natural gas option went ahead because it was &pound;800,000 cheaper. A hospital wanted to put in environmental and energy-reducing measures as part of its contract, but those were all removed because it was said that the payback in the benefits of reducing energy costs versus the extra capital costs would have happened over 47 years. When somebody looked at the probable energy costs over 30 years and included a shadow price for carbon, which the Treasury green book says should be done, they saw that there would be payback over 11 years. But by the time that somebody mentioned that, the decision had already been made to cut out all the environmental and energy-saving measures and to go with the lower cost option. So the opportunity was lost.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/26">The message that came across strongly from the report was that everybody feared European Union procurement policy. People might say, &quot;We want whole-life costing. Aren't we breaking EU law on procurement?&quot; or &quot;We want regeneration of apprentices employed under this contract, but are we discriminating in favour of buying local, which is against EU law?&quot; People can use the EU as their whipping boy as much as they like, but mostly the answer to those questions is no. Actually, they can do those things as long as they get the process right. Firm advice and guidance is necessary from the top to ensure that people have the confidence to procure in the right way.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/27">We found good designs and good projects, but too few of them were making it through the process: they were dropped at planning or final-cost stages and did not make it through to become the buildings of the future. It is urgent, for all the reasons that I have mentioned in respect of the environment, social cohesion and social justice for the future. We have had to borrow a lot of money to meet the needs of coping with the greatest economic downturn since the second world war and things will be tighter in future, so it is all the more important today to stand up for good quality buildings and contracts that are going to be with us for the next 30, 40 or 50 years and will, hopefully, contribute to tackling climate change along the way. It is even more important now for us to stand by our standards.</p>
	<p pid="b.87.1/28">Will the Minister be serious about addressing climate change, look for long-term cost efficiency and not just short-term gains, and help to promote more sustainable public sector procurement? To do so, whole-life costing for public sector procurement contracts must be adopted.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.92.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1899" speakername="Angela Eagle" speakeroffice="The Exchequer Secretary to the Treasury"  colnum="92"  time="011:20:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0005.htm#09050659000480">
	<p pid="b.92.0/1">It is a pleasure to respond to the debate and the good and expert points made by my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1833" name="David Kidney">the Member for Stafford (Mr. Kidney)</phrase>. As chair of the Westminster sustainable business forum, he has a long history of involvement and great expertise in the matter. I agreed with almost everything that he said, although borrowing against future revenue streams goes slightly too far in public accounting procedures for now, although we could perhaps consider it in the future.</p>
	<p pid="b.92.0/2">It is clearly important, as my hon. Friend did, to put the necessity for sustainable procurement in the appropriate context. He was right to say that, in the recent Budget, we published three carbon budgets&mdash;the first such budgets in the world&mdash;requiring substantial and stretching reductions in carbon emissions. He expanded his definition of sustainable procurement to encompass other aims&mdash;equality, social issues and innovation&mdash;in addition to green sustainability. I hope that he recognises that the Office of Government Commerce is keenly aware of the re-engineering processes in procurement that will have to feed into society's efforts to cut carbon emissions by 80 per cent. by 2050.</p>
	<p pid="b.92.0/3">At my instigation, we have published a series of pamphlets. &quot;Buy green and make a difference&quot; deals with waste, sustainability and environmental efficiency, but others cover social issues, equality and innovation. It is important to recognise that there has been a change in approach. I was anxious to proceed with that and to get over the default option of a narrow definition of value for money, which is clearly a bane of my hon. Friend's life when considering the potential for reaching targets other than value for money and having a whole-life cost view of what can be achieved with capital expenditure and procurement.</p>
	<p pid="b.92.0/4">My hon. Friend asked about the amount that the Government spend on procurement and he had the right figure: &pound;175 billion. There is enormous potential to achieve more value for money from that expenditure, and I share his exasperation that that does not always happen. He gave some examples. One explanation for the situation is the diffuse nature of the procurement process throughout central Government and the whole public sector, because many of those who are responsible for procurement work in their own areas, often with a narrower view of value for money than we might want promulgated nationally, which is part of the reason behind producing the pamphlets.</p>
	<p pid="b.92.0/5">In expanding the view of what value for money is and embedding a more active and innovative approach to whole-life costs, which my hon. Friend urged me to do, we must ensure that we improve the capability, confidence and professionalism of procurers throughout the whole public sector. My hon. Friend said that some people in the private sector are more confident in this area than those in the public sector.</p>
	<p pid="b.92.0/6">My hon. Friend also mentioned something that crops up whenever I go out and talk to public procurers: the dead hand of EU procurement law. It is often used as an excuse for not doing things differently. There is often, but not always, a tendency for those in public procurement to be defensive about doing that and to take a narrower view of value for money, rather than taking account of the increasing need to take a wider, whole-life cost view and to be innovative about what other value can be achieved when letting a contract. It is all too easy, for a quiet life, to say that nothing innovative can be done with apprentices or equality issues in specific areas because the EU does not allow that. The EU does allow it if the processes are right, as my hon. Friend rightly said.</p>
	<p pid="b.92.0/7">I am sure that my hon. Friend has perused some of the OGC publications, which I wanted out there to get over the refrain, &quot;The EU will not let us do it this way.&quot; Actually, the pamphlets demonstrate precisely how the EU allows public procurement to take account of some important advantages, and I hope that my hon. Friend recognises that we have made progress in getting that fact over.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.93.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1833" speakername="David Kidney" colnum="93"  time="011:20:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0005.htm#09050659000481">
	<p pid="b.93.0/1">I was greedy with my share of the debate, so I should not intervene on the Minister, but will she wave the leaflets under people's noses at the vital times when they are making decisions so that they can overcome their fear of EU laws and apply whole-life costing properly?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.93.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1767" speakername="Mike Hancock" colnum="93"  time="011:20:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0005.htm#09050659000482">
	<p pid="b.93.1/1">Order. The Minister might not be able to do so personally, but I am sure that she knows someone who will.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.93.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1899" speakername="Angela Eagle" colnum="93"  time="011:20:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0005.htm#09050659000483">
	<p pid="b.93.2/1">I am not sure that I could be in so many places at once, which comes back to the diffuse nature of the public procurement process. However, I evangelise about the pamphlets and, as the Minister with responsibility for Government procurement, I wave them around when I attend conferences for professional procurers. I point out that we want innovative procurement and that the Government should lead by example, not trail the field in innovative solutions for the best and most effective use of &pound;175 billion of procurement every year. I assure my hon. Friend that we do that. All the guidance is on the website, and we then evangelise about it.</p>
	<p pid="b.93.2/2">I hope that my hon. Friend recognises that the procurement approach is diffuse and that it is difficult to be present when decisions are made. We must increase the capability, confidence and professionalism of public procurers to ensure that they are confident enough to know that we want them to proceed with that approach. For example, the Green Book requires, as my hon. Friend suggested, the use of a whole-life costing approach to value for money to ensure that sustainability is embedded at the centre of value-for-money decisions. He gave some worrying examples of terrible missed opportunities. Practical guidance for Departments on value for money will be released at the end of the month so that the impact of carbon, water and waste can form part of procurement decision making.</p>
	<p pid="b.93.2/3">The whole area is changing rapidly&mdash;it needs to change so that we can reach our carbon targets&mdash;and procurers must be retrained and updated all the time. It is certainly my responsibility and that of the OGC to ensure that we make our public procurement function much more up to date, confident and professional than it has been, and that we expand the view of value for money from the narrow place where it has been into much wider areas. I am more than happy to tell my hon. Friend that as the Minister responsible for taking that forward, I am happy to work with him to put his ideas, as well as ours, into practice.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.94.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1767" speakername="Mike Hancock" colnum="94"  time="011:20:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0005.htm#09050659000484">
	<p pid="b.94.0/1">Order. I apologise to the Minister, but I will have to interrupt her. I thank Mr. Kidney and her for their courtesy to the Chair and the excellence of the debate.</p>
	<p pid="b.94.0/2" class="italic">Sitting suspended.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.95.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="95"  time="011:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0006.htm#09050659000003">
	Tax Avoidance and Evasion
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.95.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" speakername="David Taylor" colnum="95"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0006.htm#09050659000485">
	<p pid="b.95.1/1">It is a great pleasure to speak under your chairmanship, Mr. Hancock. I am grateful to Mr. Speaker for selecting this vital subject for debate in a long slot, especially as it precisely coincides with this year's Christian Aid week. I shall focus my opening remarks on the international development implications of tax avoidance and evasion and then highlight the impact on the UK Exchequer and our society of the corporate culture of tax avoidance that has taken root in this country.</p>
	<p pid="b.95.1/2">As the Finance Minister of South Africa, Trevor Manuel, has said:</p>
	<p pid="b.95.1/3" class="indent">&quot;the correct spelling of the word 'aid' is 'T-A-X'&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.95.1/4">It should be a source of consensus, or a no-brainer as the tedious phrase goes, that tax is the most sustainable source of finance for development work in poor countries. It promotes accountability and allows Governments to generate revenue from their nations' economic activity to invest in their own infrastructure, health care and education. A broad tax base improves representation and accountability between states and citizens. It encourages good governance, as Governments who depend on their citizens for revenue are more likely to act in the interests of the people.</p>
	<p pid="b.95.1/5">Because promoting economic development for all means greater revenues for the state, Governments have a vested interest in ensuring that economic growth is shared among the population. Progressive taxation also benefits the poor by redistributing wealth through society, and it can limit consumption that has harmful effects on society or the environment through the levying of heavier taxes on products and services. Angel Gurr&iacute;a, the head of that international free market acolyte the OECD, certainly believes that. He has observed that</p>
	<p pid="b.95.1/6" class="indent">&quot;taxes provide the long term financial platform for sustainable development. Taxes are the lifeblood of state services.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.95.1/7">It is estimated that between $500 billion and $800 billion of illicit capital flows from developing countries every year. Of that, $160 billion is lost through commercial tax evasion&mdash;or &pound;20 million during this 90-minute debate. It is about twice the annual bill for global aid from rich countries to poor countries. It is also several times larger than the $40 billion to $60 billion that the World Bank estimates will be needed annually to meet the United Nations millennium development goals, which are intended to halve poverty by 2015. If that money&mdash;that avoided tax&mdash;were allocated according to present spending patterns in poor countries and with the same degree of effectiveness, the additional revenues could, among other things, save the lives of 1,000 children under the age of five every day.</p>
	<p pid="b.95.1/8">There is much discussion about the role of tax havens in facilitating these capital transfers. It is recognised by, among others, the current Pope&mdash;he must be infallible&mdash;that offshore centres play a major role in the imbalances of development, causing a gigantic flight of capital that is the result of tax evasion. Christian Aid estimates that, between 2005 and 2007, &pound;35 billion of illicit capital flowed from non-EU countries to the United Kingdom as a result of trade mispricing&mdash;a practice whereby multinational companies sell goods and services across borders at inflated or sometimes deflated prices to minimise their tax burden. Of that, &pound;5 billion of illicit capital flowed into the UK from the world's 49 poorest countries. That is almost equivalent to the Department for International Development's entire programme budget for 2006-07.</p>
	<p pid="b.95.1/9">The estimable researcher on these matters, Professor Prem Sikka, has pointed out that transfer pricing is used as a &quot;key mechanism&quot; for dodging tax by multinationals all over the world, yet its abuse is scarcely on the political agenda. These are not abstract figures. They represent essential services that the world's poorest people are being denied by merciless and venal exploitation, not just of individual states but through the lack of regulation applied to the global movement of capital.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.96.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2038" speakername="Bob Spink" colnum="96"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0006.htm#09050659000486">
	<p pid="b.96.0/1">The hon. Gentleman mentioned the plight of children between the ages of one and five. He will know that malaria particularly attacks those children, that it affects 40 per cent. of the people in the world and that it infects 500 million people each year. Can he estimate just how much good it would do for mankind if just 5 per cent. of the tax that is avoided were put towards malaria research?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.96.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" speakername="David Taylor" colnum="96"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0006.htm#09050659000487">
	<p pid="b.96.1/1">The answer is in the hon. Gentleman's question. The figures that I have given show the scale of progress that could be made towards achieving the millennium development goals, and the point that he raises is very important. We are considering African countries. Zambia has some of the richest deposits of copper in the world, but it failed to benefit at all from the commodity boom between 2003 and 2008. Why? Because some multinational companies pursued aggressive tax avoidance strategies by pushing for special tax breaks and keeping mining contracts secret. In a country in which just 2 per cent. of people in rural areas have access to clean drinking water, there is an urgent need for more tax revenue. The concept of corporate social responsibility rings particularly hollow in the context of the fact that 98 per cent. of people in rural areas of Zambia do not have clean drinking water.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.96.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1625" speakername="Andrew Stunell" colnum="96"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0006.htm#09050659000488">
	<p pid="b.96.2/1">Does the hon. Gentleman agree that Zambia has a problem not just from the direction that he mentions, but from the purchase of its sovereign debt at a discount by so-called vulture funds, which are also showing a complete lack of social and corporate responsibility?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.96.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" speakername="David Taylor" colnum="96"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0006.htm#09050659000489">
	<p pid="b.96.3/1">I agree with that so strongly that I was on the other side of the River Thames with my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1741" name="Sally Keeble">the Member for Northampton, North (Ms Keeble)</phrase> just 24 hours ago with a vulture on my arm to highlight the issue to which the hon. Gentleman refers.</p>
	<p pid="b.96.3/2">The ability of sovereign Governments in both developed and developing countries to tax effectively is seriously undermined by international tax avoidance and evasion. Under-resourced tax authorities struggle to track the extent to which taxable income from multinationals is moved offshore. Few developing countries can navigate the complexities of multinationals' structures in order to determine tax liability, especially when their people are dying for want of clean drinking water, malaria treatments and sanitation services. Long-term policies in areas such as tax collection and enforcement cannot realistically be adequately supported in crisis and disaster-led circumstances.</p>
	<p pid="b.96.3/3">This is clearly an issue of policy coherence. We cannot continue to spend billions of pounds of UK taxpayers' money only for it to come back to the western world, including to the UK, as illicit money. Trevor Manuel has also said:</p>
	<p pid="b.96.3/4" class="indent">&quot;It is a contradiction to support increased development assistance, yet turn a blind eye to actions by multinationals and others that undermine the tax base of a developing country.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.96.3/5">That is happening on a grand scale. Greater transparency is required globally to ensure that more of those resources stay in developing countries and are used for development. That can be achieved by implementing a new international accounting standard and addressing secrecy in tax havens and offshore financial centres.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.97.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1850" speakername="David Drew" colnum="97"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0006.htm#09050659000490">
	<p pid="b.97.0/1">I thank my hon. Friend for taking up this issue again. One way in which it could be dealt with is through a Tobin tax. That is an idea whose time came five or so years ago, yet lamentably we have made no progress on it. Is there a reason why?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.97.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" speakername="David Taylor" colnum="97"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0006.htm#09050659000491">
	<p pid="b.97.1/1">I genuinely do hope to come to that point at the end of my speech and I hope that my hon. Friend will be able to stay until then.</p>
	<p pid="b.97.1/2">The problems of capital flight and the financial crisis show clearly that the complexity of global financial flows has grown far beyond the ability of Governments&mdash;any Government&mdash;to monitor and regulate them effectively. The fight against poverty demands an end to the secrecy surrounding tax payments made by multinationals to poor countries' Governments. The International Accounting Standards Board provides the framework for regulation in this area and should require multinationals to report the scale of their economic activity and the taxes paid in every single country in which they operate. That would enable sovereign Governments and civil society to ensure that multinationals paid the right amount of tax in the right place at the right time. Many investors are also keen to have that information, which allows a much closer understanding of the risk associated with investments. Such reform of global accounting practices would also promote the concept of ethical investment, which is regarded in many quarters as oxymoronic.</p>
	<p pid="b.97.1/3">Christian Aid and others, including ActionAid, are calling for two key measures of global financial regulation: first, an international accounting standard on country-by-country reporting to provide investors, regulators and tax authorities with a powerful indicative tool to assess risks and highlight abuses; and, secondly, automatic tax information exchange between all jurisdictions, including tax havens, based on a global agreement, instead of a piecemeal approach involving bilateral treaties, which have been shown to have limited impact and tend to exclude developing countries.</p>
	<p pid="b.97.1/4">The London summit not long ago&mdash;the G20 meeting&mdash;delivered significant progress towards financial transparency. Indeed, for the first time, the Prime Minister publicly acknowledged the link between tax evasion and development. Prior to the G20 meeting, he stated:</p>
	<p pid="b.97.1/5" class="indent">&quot;we will also set down new measures to crack down on those tax havens that siphon money from developing countries, money that could otherwise be spent on bed nets, vaccinations, economic development and jobs.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.97.1/6">However, the measures proposed by the G20 are agreements on sharing bilateral tax information between tax havens and wealthy countries that have the economic and political muscle to negotiate. They are rushed measures; they do not help the developing world and will hinder tax investigators in countries such as the United Kingdom.</p>
	<p pid="b.97.1/7">Tax information exchange agreements&mdash;TIEAs&mdash;as proposed by the G20 and the OECD, are of limited value to developing countries. First, only the richest countries have the economic power to negotiate such agreements and gain speedy access to the necessary information. Using a bilateral model, if only UN member countries had fair access to tax information, each of the 192 countries would have to sign 192 information exchange agreements. I know, Mr. Hancock, that you are good at mental arithmetic: 192 squared would mean a total of 36,864 agreements globally. There are between 50 and 72 tax havens in the world, and more than 100 countries with which they could negotiate TIEAs, so that is potentially more than 7,200 bilateral agreements. However, by March 2009, only 49 TIEAs had been signed between OECD countries and secrecy jurisdictions, and only 18 have entered into force.</p>
	<p pid="b.97.1/8">The second reason why TIEAs do not work is that poor countries do not have the power to offer strong sanctions on their own, and thus cannot access the information that they need through that channel. The proposed agreements enshrine &quot;on request&quot; information sharing. If a poor country wants information on a tax payment, it will need to provide significant evidence that criminal activity is occurring, but it simply will not have the resources to conduct such investigations.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.98.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1625" speakername="Andrew Stunell" colnum="98"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0006.htm#09050659000492">
	<p pid="b.98.0/1">I entirely support what the hon. Gentleman says. Perhaps he will take into account the words of <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1673" name="John Battle">the right hon. Member for Leeds, West (John Battle)</phrase>: Africa needs accountants. Many African Governments are not professionally equipped to deal with the kind of challenging financial regimes that confront them. This is a major problem. Even if the partners are willing participants, how will they evaluate the material that they receive and move on to enforcement?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.98.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" speakername="David Taylor" colnum="98"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0006.htm#09050659000493">
	<p pid="b.98.1/1">I agree, and Zambia would be a great example. Soon after I qualified&mdash;it was quite a few years ago&mdash;I was on the point of moving to one of the towns in the copper belt in Zambia to work as an accountant, but it did not happen.</p>
	<p pid="b.98.1/2">Evidence so far shows that TIEAs have produced only a trickle of information. For instance, the TIEA between the US and Jersey&mdash;two of the biggest players in the offshore system&mdash;was used only four times in 2008. States may also maintain or introduce other restrictions on the procedures for obtaining or supplying information. For example, some states consider that before any information is supplied, the person concerned must be notified of the request and given an opportunity to object. That, of course, gives tax evaders ample opportunity to cover their tracks, which highlights again the culture of secrecy and privilege that the activities of powerful multinationals are afforded by domestic and international authorities.</p>
	<p pid="b.98.1/3">The Government must recognise that automatic tax information exchange between all jurisdictions, including tax havens, is the only system that can deliver rightful tax flows to poor countries. The Minister's response to that specific point would be immensely helpful and much appreciated.</p>
	<p pid="b.98.1/4">Of course, some will argue for a bilateral agreement on tax information exchange. Indeed, the Government have argued against automatic TIEAs, saying that developing countries might not have the capacity to use the data that would be transferred and that the information transfer would thus be for nought. That argument is patently absurd and deeply patronising to developing countries. It suggests that they do not have, and could not quickly develop, the ability to deal with large quantities of data of the sort that automatic information exchange would generate. In fact, many developing countries already use international software and data sources to deal with vast quantities of data&mdash;most obviously, when one's passport is scanned at any customs point when entering an airport in almost any country at any income level.</p>
	<p pid="b.98.1/5">At present, no one can tell what profits are made by companies operating in developing countries, or what taxes they have paid there, because companies are obliged to provide only a total profit figure for the whole world. That is an open invitation to avoid or evade tax liabilities&mdash;an invitation that most companies take, given the $160 billion figure for tax evasion and avoidance that I cited earlier. It is critical that the Government actively try to secure an international accounting standard on country-by-country reporting. That would provide investors, regulators and tax authorities with a powerful indicative tool to assess risks and highlight abuses.</p>
	<p pid="b.98.1/6">An international accounting standard for all industries that would require companies operating internationally to disclose the profit that they make and the tax that they pay in each country in which they operate would equip developing countries with the information that they need to target corporate tax abuse. To secure an IAS on country-by-country reporting, the Government, acting in alliance with other leading economies, would need to ask the International Accounting Standards Board to create such a standard. It is important to note that the gang of four&mdash;the four big accountancy firms of Deloitte, Ernst and Young, PricewaterhouseCoopers and KPMG&mdash;are represented on the IASB, so they have a direct say in setting international accounting rules and standards. Interestingly, Christian Aid's proposals for the country-by-country reporting of corporate profits, which are supported by ActionAid, have been rejected by the big four, and no convincing argument has been posted to date to explain why, although we can draw our own conclusions.</p>
	<p pid="b.98.1/7">The IASB is little more than a trade association for international accounting firms that is funded largely by the gang of four and other corporate entities. It might be time to relieve it of responsibility for setting international accounting standards. Perhaps that should be passed to a supranational body such as the UN so that appropriate mechanisms can be developed. I am not sure whether that idea was floated at the recent G20 summit&mdash;perhaps the Minister will tell us&mdash;but the current situation is untenable. It demonstrates, once again, that in spheres as important as global accounting, self-regulation does not work&mdash;it militates against the public interest and the public in the poorest countries. However, G20 Governments should commit themselves at least to approach the IASB in support of a country-by-country profit reporting system. I hope that we will receive an assurance that such an approach will be made today.</p>
	<p pid="b.98.1/8">If implemented, the measures would have the potential to deliver a sum that would have a big impact towards eliminating poverty on a scale never seen before and achieving and embedding the millennium development goals. The Minister, who is a highly regarded, efficient and conscientious member of the Administration, might be able to elaborate on the UK's interpretation of the G20 agreements on the regulation of capital flows to tax havens, and the way in which the impact on developing countries can be reduced.</p>
	<p pid="b.98.1/9">On <phrase class="date" code="1789-05-12">12 May 1789</phrase>, William Wilberforce made his first major speech in the House of Commons on the abolition of slavery. He argued that slavery was morally reprehensible and a matter of natural justice. Tax evasion on the present massive scale has been described as the most harmful economic condition since slavery, as it contributes to the desperate global poverty endured by millions every day. The financial crisis has presented us with an opportunity to reform the economic system and to address global injustices, which are hugely damaging to the world's poorest people. Left untouched, the current system will for ever cast doubt on the legitimacy of profits derived from corporate activity in poor countries.</p>
	<p pid="b.98.1/10">I do not have time to deal with the role of the Commonwealth Development Corporation, which was rebranded as the CDC on privatisation. Why do we allow the corporate culture of &quot;greed is good&quot; to spread into international development policy to such an extent? The Minister will not have time to answer all my questions, but the Government must answer them at some stage, and be forced to do so if necessary.</p>
	<p pid="b.98.1/11">Finally I turn to the impact of tax avoidance in the United Kingdom, which is another area in which reform is overdue. We need to combat the advances made under such a highly dubious corporate culture. It is a tale of merciless profiteering that again features the infamous gang of four. Government borrowing is about to double, but we should not expect private householders alone to bear the brunt of the problems caused by the failure of regulators and the City.</p>
	<p pid="b.98.1/12">I strongly support and applaud President Obama's action to close tax loopholes, including offshore tax havens, that are exploited by US companies, which we read about in the press a day or two ago. The new Administration in Washington estimates that US companies paid an effective tax rate of 2.3 per cent. on the $700 billion that they earned in foreign profits in 2004, so action is long overdue. I hope that there is more to come. I urge the Government to display similar principles and conviction in dismantling the tax avoidance industry in the UK.</p>
	<p pid="b.98.1/13">As we know from a series of excellent articles by the tax gap team of <i>The Guardian</i>&mdash;I referred to it in an early-day motion at the time&mdash;the tax avoidance industry and its clients will go to exceedingly convoluted lengths to avoid their full liability. The evidence of Barclays bank's commitment to stretching Denis Healey's famous prison cell wall that exists between tax avoidance and evasion is not only astonishing, but significant for gaining an understanding of the relative ease with which existing tax laws may be manipulated.</p>
	<p pid="b.98.1/14">There is a compelling argument that complex tax avoidance strategies were a major factor in the collapse of our over-leveraged and indebted financial system. However, the bottom line is that HMRC annually loses a minimum of &pound;25 billion in tax revenue as a result of the tax avoidance activities of the wealthiest individuals and 700 largest businesses. This places an unfair and intolerable burden on working families, small businesses and pensioners at the best of times, but during a recession, when general taxation is expected to increase to meet the Government's higher borrowing, that potentially toxic load that could fuel serious civil unrest.</p>
	<p pid="b.98.1/15">As an accountant myself, I have been studying the special purpose vehicles and other formulae used to channel funds offshore to avoid tax liabilities. We all need to be aware of the damage that such complex instruments wreak on the public purse. We do not let scientists develop chemicals that have a destructive environmental impact, so we should never exempt accountants from the social consequences of their actions, no matter how lucrative their proposals might be in the short term.</p>
	<p pid="b.98.1/16">The Public and Commercial Services Union's tax justice campaign, which builds on the work of its members and that of the Tax Justice Network, focuses on the loss of local tax offices and the consequent problems for HMRC when tackling tax avoidance. Given the Chancellor's Budget announcement just two weeks ago of more resources for HMRC to devote to closing tax loopholes and tackling tax avoidance, it is vital that the programme of so-called efficiency measures does not include the continued closure of local tax offices, as that is akin to tying one hand behind HMRC's back as it tries to deal with the serried ranks of accountants employed by private sector firms to avoid tax.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.101.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1850" speakername="David Drew" colnum="101"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0007.htm#09050659000494">
	<p pid="b.101.0/1">I concur totally with my hon. Friend and pay due tribute to the work of Richard Murphy of the Tax Justice Network. Does my hon. Friend agree that one of the good things that the Government did&mdash;this has been heavily criticised since&mdash;was to shut down advanced corporation tax? Quite simply, that was a major loophole for larger companies and a scam that could be used to hide many things relating to pension arrangements&mdash;not least early retirement problems&mdash;and company pension holidays. Is it not about time that the truth came out about advanced corporation tax? There are too many fables about what it was really about.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.101.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" speakername="David Taylor" colnum="101"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0007.htm#09050659000495">
	<p pid="b.101.1/1">The criticism of that measure in the 1997 Budget is often misplaced. It has been developed and promoted by Opposition parties and demonstrates quite vividly their financial illiteracy&mdash;that is a great pity! I have always believed that although there is a register for tax avoidance schemes, the enforcement of the registration is pathetic. Some organisations fail to register with tax avoidance schemes and accept the relatively small fine incurred as an operational cost. Why do we let people get away with that?</p>
	<p pid="b.101.1/2">Finally, we need to look beyond limited measures, such as a Tobin tax, on regulating the global flow of capital, and to set independently and enforce international accounting standards and equitable tax information sharing agreements&mdash;KPMG is particularly bad in that respect. Accountancy might be boring&mdash;that dreadful suggestion was made in the &quot;Monty Python&quot; series years ago&mdash;and taxation might be seen as a black art, but the devil is in the fiscal detail. We politicians must make a stand against endemic greed and corruption before it infects the values of fairness and equality that bind humanity.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.102.0" speakerid="unknown" error="No match" speakername="Several hon. Members" colnum="102"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0007.htm#09050659000496">
	<p pid="b.102.0/1" class="italic">rose&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.102.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1767" speakername="Mike Hancock" colnum="102"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0007.htm#09050659000497">
	<p pid="b.102.1/1">Order. A number of colleagues want to contribute to the debate. I intend to start the winding-up speeches at 3.30 pm. If people are generous to, and tolerant of, each other, everyone will get a chance to speak.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.102.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1382" speakername="Tony Baldry" colnum="102"  time="014:54:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0007.htm#09050659000498">
	<p pid="b.102.2/1">There is a danger that we might be conflating two separate issues. In a communiqu&eacute; put out immediately after the G20 summit, our Chancellor noted that leaders had agreed to</p>
	<p pid="b.102.2/2" class="indent">&quot;take action to protect the world's financial system and our public finances by cracking down on tax havens&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.102.2/3">His statement made no mention of the need to take action to protect developing countries. Almost all the references in the Library paper prepared for today's debate relate to tax avoidance schemes in developed countries depriving the Exchequers of developed countries of funds. The first paragraph of the first article in the pack reads:</p>
	<p pid="b.102.2/4" class="indent">&quot;UBS yesterday defended itself against attempts by the US Internal Revenue Service to extract names of thousands of American customers holding offshore accounts, telling a federal court that matters should be resolved via talks between Bern and Washington. The beleaguered Swiss bank was responding to a legal challenge by the IRS to reveal the names of up to 52,000 accounts as part of the US administration's efforts to combat tax evasion.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.102.2/5">There is not a scintilla of a quarrel&mdash;I suspect&mdash;between hon. Members about it being right for mature democracies, or indeed all countries, to bear down on tax evasion. However, in none of the briefings that I have been sent have I seen evidence supporting the suggestion that developing countries are losing huge amounts of revenue each year through commercial tax evasion. Not a single article in the Library pack gives any statistics or evidence in support of that suggestion. I am not saying that it is incorrect, but I am bemused. If we are not careful, this will become an article of faith, and the danger of such articles of faith is that they can be used as alibis in other ways.</p>
	<p pid="b.102.2/6">In other words, developed countries can say to developing countries, &quot;Well, you would be in a much better position, and you would not need so much development assistance, if you had in place a better tax system, and if you were properly taxing companies doing business in your jurisdiction.&quot; As times start to get hard, the risk is that countries that signed up to the millennium development goals and increased development funding will seek to find such excuses. If it is to be asserted that developing countries lose large amounts of money through commercial tax evasion, it needs to be much more evidence-based. We then also need to consider how we can strengthen developing countries' tax systems and administrations through increased targeted aid.</p>
	<p pid="b.102.2/7">I find something else bemusing about this debate: I cannot recall having seen, in any of DFID's country plans&mdash;I stand to be corrected&mdash;a reference to enhancing the efficiency of Exchequers and Treasuries in those countries. Much work is being done on good governance, on bearing down on corruption, and on improving the judicial system, courts and general machinery of governance, but very little, as of yet, is being done on improving and strengthening developing countries' tax systems and administrations.</p>
	<p pid="b.102.2/8">As I said, I am slightly concerned that we are conflating two issues. If we are not careful, we will create an article of faith that says that huge amounts of revenue in developing countries are going missing, and we will give an alibi to developed countries to say, &quot;If only developing countries sorted out their tax system better, they would not be in so much difficulty.&quot;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.103.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1850" speakername="David Drew" colnum="103"  time="014:54:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0007.htm#09050659000499">
	<p pid="b.103.0/1">As the hon. Gentleman knows, my knowledge of the Sudan is better than that of any other African country. When the government of southern Sudan were setting up their administration, the British Government paid for a number of people&mdash;admittedly from the private sector&mdash;to go in to help them set up their tax system. Without such a system, southern Sudan had no mechanism to raise revenue. The hon. Gentleman was right to draw attention to the matter but, to be fair, the British Government have a history of trying to help.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.103.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1382" speakername="Tony Baldry" colnum="103"  time="014:54:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0007.htm#09050659000500">
	<p pid="b.103.1/1">As yet, there is no de jure state of southern Sudan. The government in Rumbek are pretty sui generis. We will have to see whether they hold a referendum and decide to go for a de jure state. I am not saying that the British Government have never given funding to help Exchequers, but having read through a large number of plans for developing countries, I cannot recall seeing that they have.</p>
	<p pid="b.103.1/2">The difficulty with such debates is that we approach them thinking about the developed north and the developing south. We need to think about a system that will be effective for Chinese companies operating anywhere, be it in the Sudan or in Kazakhstan. If we are to have a system that is globally transparent&mdash;this is not just about UK banks and companies or US companies&mdash;it must apply to companies throughout the world, or it simply will not stick.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.103.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1885" speakername="Vincent Cable" colnum="103"  time="014:54:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0007.htm#09050659000501">
	<p pid="b.103.2/1">Is the hon. Gentleman aware that he is suggesting that there is a lack of evidence on the subject of revenue loss from tax avoidance in developing countries? Is he aware of the Christian Aid report on death and taxes that seems, on first sight, to be a very serious piece of econometric work? It suggests that somewhere between 10 and 15 per cent. of the revenue of developing countries, and medium and low-income countries, has been lost as a result of systematic manipulation of prices and, therefore, the revenue deriving from them?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.103.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1382" speakername="Tony Baldry" colnum="103"  time="014:54:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0007.htm#09050659000502">
	<p pid="b.103.3/1">If policies are to be taken forward, they must be based on evidence. I am slightly concerned that in the four years that I served on the Select Committee on International Development, very little work was done on that issue. It may well be that Christian Aid is one of the first organisations to have done some work. There is a danger that we create an impression that developing countries would have access to more money than they do currently if only they started taxing more efficiently and more effectively. Ironically, when one visits pretty much any country in Africa, the major concern relates to jobs. Most countries are worried about jobs and employment. Interestingly, most developing countries will offer substantial &quot;tax holidays&quot; to new inward investors. That is true of almost any capital city in Africa. Many developing countries in Africa have free ports and other such mechanisms to encourage investors and job creators to invest in those countries because their primary concern is job creation.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.104.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1625" speakername="Andrew Stunell" colnum="104"  time="014:54:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0007.htm#09050659000503">
	<p pid="b.104.0/1">The hon. Gentleman seems to be developing an argument that poorer countries are giving such incentives of their free will to provide the right business environment to create jobs. Surely the reality is that the multinationals go on a reverse Dutch bidding war to see which country will give them the biggest discounts. One only has to look at copper pricing in Zambia to see how damaging it is to the income stream of poorer countries. Surely the balance of trade in that negotiation is very much with the larger multinational corporations and not with the developing countries' Governments.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.104.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1382" speakername="Tony Baldry" colnum="104"  time="014:54:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0007.htm#09050659000504">
	<p pid="b.104.1/1">There is a slightly 1960s feel about how we describe the multinationals. If the hon. Gentleman goes to Khartoum, Freetown or Dar es-Salaam, he will find that the major new investors seeking the best fiscal arrangements are Chinese or Russian. Most African countries will seek to attract those companies&mdash;whether they be from China or elsewhere&mdash;by giving fiscal incentives.</p>
	<p pid="b.104.1/2">My next point relates to tax havens, but I will try to be brief because I am conscious that others wish to speak. If the UK Government believe that something is wrong with tax havens, they are probably in the best position to sort it out because a large number of them are UK overseas territories. In part, UK overseas territories, such as the Turks and Caicos, the Cayman Islands and Bermuda were encouraged by successive UK Governments to go into banking and financial services as a means of becoming self sufficient. That also applies to the British Virgin Islands and, to a lesser extent, Anguilla, Montserrat and Gibraltar. I have never been entirely clear as to the constitutional status of Guernsey, Jersey and the Isle of Man. None the less, if it is being said that there is something wrong with tax havens, it is within the gift of the UK Government to take action. After all, they managed the constitutions of all of those overseas territories.</p>
	<p pid="b.104.1/3">The Government have decided to return the Turks and Caicos to direct administration under the governor, but that is because of allegations of corruption and nothing to do with it being a tax haven. I am slightly surprised that the Chancellor has proclaimed at the G20 and elsewhere that they will take action on tax avoidance and evasion because many of the tax havens are under UK jurisdiction. Therefore, if action needs to be taken against tax havens, it is within the gift of the UK Government. However, if we are going to take action, it should be based on evidence. We should not put developing countries in a position in which they are being accused of being the authors of their own misfortune. There is a danger of giving an alibi to developed countries to cut back on their assistance to developing countries on the grounds that if only developing countries took the necessary action to increase their own tax yields, they would be in a far better position. If we say that the amount of taxation in developing countries is roughly one and a half times the amount of annual global aid from rich countries to poor, we will see where that argument goes when the developed world is under pressure.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.105.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1692" speakername="Nia Griffith" colnum="105"  time="015:09:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0007.htm#09050659000505">
	<p pid="b.105.0/1">I very much welcome the attention that the G20 is giving tax havens and tax avoidance, which is long overdue. No one can pretend that ruling out the immoral and devious practices that companies use to avoid playing fair and to wriggle out of paying their dues&mdash;in short, to cheat&mdash;will be easy. Those involved defraud the exchequers of the world of billions of pounds, and we all pay for that because we are defrauded as consumers and taxpayers. When we as consumers buy something from a company, we expect a certain amount to go towards legitimate taxation, not towards lining the pockets of millionaires. Similarly, we as taxpayers will pay more or enjoy fewer services if others do not pay their dues.</p>
	<p pid="b.105.0/2">The Government are a big consumer, and procurement can be a powerful tool. My hon. Friend the Minister will be aware that I introduced a ten-minute Bill&mdash;the Public Contracts (UK Tax Requirements) Bill&mdash;last year. Its purpose was to place certain requirements relating to the payment of UK tax on companies bidding for public contracts, to prohibit the transfer of such contracts overseas and to require such companies to provide certain information about tax payments. My hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1600" name="Austin Mitchell">the Member for Great Grimsby (Mr. Mitchell)</phrase> introduced an early-day motion in a similar vein.</p>
	<p pid="b.105.0/3">The problem is that some companies that have won Government contracts, including private finance initiative contracts, can transfer ownership of the company to a tax haven. In that way, they can avoid paying UK tax on their income and profits. I find it particularly outrageous&mdash;and so, I think, do the electorate&mdash;that those untaxed profits come from the public purse and from taxpayers' hard-earned money.</p>
	<p pid="b.105.0/4">The real difficulty is that there is a lack of transparency and that those who award public-private partnerships or PFI contracts are not required to request sufficient explanation and detail about the tax arrangements of the companies that bid for them. We all understand that large companies have projects and businesses in many different countries, but the British public want to be sure that the money that they pay in taxes does not go into schemes that pay companies that do not pay their full UK tax dues.</p>
	<p pid="b.105.0/5">It would be nice to think that we will see the end of tax havens and that we will no longer need a Bill such as mine, but there is still a long way to go and much international negotiation to do. I therefore ask my hon. Friend the Minister to do everything possible to demand much greater transparency from companies that bid for public contracts. In that way, we can ensure that we do not aid and abet some of the practices we have heard about today and that British taxpayers do not pay companies that use tax havens to avoid paying their dues.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.105.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1600" speakername="Austin Mitchell" colnum="105"  time="015:12:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0007.htm#09050659000506">
	<p pid="b.105.1/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" name="David Taylor">the Member for North-West Leicestershire (David Taylor)</phrase> on raising this important subject. He, I and others have been lobbying Ministers and HMRC to do something about it for several years, and we have always received an interested hearing along the lines of &quot;Gosh, we didn't know that!&quot; but no action has resulted. Now that we are in a recession or near-depression, and the manipulations, greed and derelictions of the financial sector have produced their own nemesis, something will clearly be done. When the Minister speaks, and when Ministers do act, however, I hope that they will not just fob us off with the idea that everything is very difficult and that we can act only through international agreement. As my hon. Friend said, there are actions that this country can take at a national level.</p>
	<p pid="b.105.1/2">One of the basic problems that we face is the avoidance of taxation through the formation of holding companies, which can be found around the world. Thirty per cent. of Barclays subsidiaries are in tax havens, Lloyds has 80 holding companies in Jersey and BP has 3,000 holding companies. Such companies are used to manipulate profits. News Corporation is very adept at that. It makes huge profits from <i>The Sun </i>and now from Sky television, which do not pay tax on their earnings in this country as they should, because those earnings are manipulated through holding companies.</p>
	<p pid="b.105.1/3">Google is a classic instance. It must generate between &pound;1 billion and &pound;2 billion of its &pound;7.5 billion worldwide profits in this country. It is headquartered in Ireland, and the money is filtered out through Ireland. It does not pay any tax in Ireland, so the Irish get no benefit from providing the European headquarters&mdash;ultimately, the headquarters are in Bermuda. Google has more advertising revenue than ITV, which produces programmes in this country, but it does not pay tax on that revenue and is making no contribution to production in this country.</p>
	<p pid="b.105.1/4">Last year, in an interesting pamphlet entitled &quot;The Missing Billions&quot;, the TUC estimated&mdash;its estimates are very moderate&mdash;that such practices cost the British taxpayer &pound;25 billion in lost revenue. That will become increasingly important, because we need the revenue to repay the debts that we are accumulating as a result of trying to expand the economy at a time of deflation. Individuals are failing to pay &pound;13 billion in tax in this country, while companies are failing to pay &pound;12 billion.</p>
	<p pid="b.105.1/5">As my hon. Friend said, we can deal with the problem through action in this country. We need not to tax companies registered as subsidiaries, but to view corporations and multinationals as a whole. We need a unitary tax system with formulaic apportionment. Where is the revenue generated? As my hon. Friend said, we need national accounts of what is generated where so that we can tax in this country the revenues accruing from profits, plants and workers in this country. Such a system of unitary tax with formulaic apportionment operates between states in the United States and it could well operate here. Why do we not introduce it? That would put an end to the loss of tax capacity and tax revenue in this country.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.106.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1885" speakername="Vincent Cable" colnum="106"  time="015:12:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0007.htm#09050659000507">
	<p pid="b.106.0/1">Will the hon. Gentleman give way?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.106.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1600" speakername="Austin Mitchell" colnum="106"  time="015:12:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0007.htm#09050659000508">
	<p pid="b.106.1/1">I would rather get through my speech, because the hon. Gentleman will have some interesting opinions to give us.</p>
	<p pid="b.106.1/2">The system that I have set out should be the basis for our tax system given that we need the revenue in the current crisis.</p>
	<p pid="b.106.1/3">A second general principle that this country could and should adopt is anti-avoidance. Why not? It works well in Australia. Under legislation from 1903, Australia does not look at what the law actually says about what is due&mdash;lawyers will quibble about that for ages, and corporations have huge staffs of well-paid lawyers. Instead, it looks at the intention of the legislation. As a result, any structures that are designed to avoid taxation, rather than to improve a company's competitiveness and strength, are struck down. Why do we not have that principle in this country to avoid the manipulations that are going on?</p>
	<p pid="b.106.1/4">The third thing that we can do unilaterally is deal with the tax havens, although <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1382" name="Tony Baldry">the hon. Member for Banbury (Tony Baldry)</phrase> indicated some reluctance to do that. As he said, there are two categories of tax haven. The British overseas territories&mdash;particularly the West Indies&mdash;are mainly of concern to America because of tax avoidance in the United States. The hon. Gentleman was correct to say that we encouraged those territories to develop financial and banking centres as an alternative to paying them aid. We said, &quot;We won't give those West Indian chappies aid. We'll let them develop banks such as we have&quot;&mdash;the same successful banks that have brought this country to its knees. We used that as a substitute for paying them aid because it was cheaper&mdash;that is what it was all about. However, the countries involved are British overseas territories and they can be dealt with as such.</p>
	<p pid="b.106.1/5">The consequence of such development is the corruption that we see in the Turks and Caicos Islands, with its corrupt regimes and inefficiency. It failed to develop the economy's industrial and agricultural potential because it concentrated on financial services, which are skimming off the cream.</p>
	<p pid="b.106.1/6">The second category of overseas territory, as the hon. Gentleman intimated, is the Crown dependencies&mdash;the Channel Islands and the Isle of Man. Those are of more interest because they are escape hatches&mdash;subsidiaries&mdash;which allow finance in the City of London to manipulate its money. We can deal with such dependencies quite effectively. The only inhibition is the constitutional one, which Governments make much of, although they do not hesitate to cross that line on moral issues, equality issues or rights.</p>
	<p pid="b.106.1/7">The Channel Islands are a British concern, and there is not as much of an issue about American companies as there is in the West Indies, so we can deal with the problem by insisting on the principle of absolute openness. All ownership of companies should be on the public record. All the name plates that flourish in Jersey and Guernsey make a fascinating tour; people could think they were touring a mighty industrial empire as they went around looking at those name plates gleaming on the doors of companies there&mdash;but there is nothing behind them. They are just name plates. There should be openness about ownership in the public record; all accounts should be on the public record, so that we would know who was passing the money through, and could deal with that; and there should be full compliance with the European savings tax directive. In other words just paying withholding tax and keeping the accounts secret should not be allowed; full compliance with the directive should be insisted on. That transparency would produce radical change and a substantial reduction in the kind of financial sector that is found in the Channel Islands. It might drive them back to their old basics of tomatoes and tourism, and they might need financial help with that, but we cannot avoid the principle.</p>
	<p pid="b.106.1/8">There is a need to build such measures. We can do it on a national basis without waiting for international agreement, and we should. There is a need to act quickly rather than wait for international agreements, because we are now in a situation of some desperation. We need the companies in question, which do not pay their tax dues or their social rent to this country, to pay.</p>
	<p pid="b.106.1/9">I conclude with an important point, which my hon. Friend did not deal with. We are now concerned about the environment and global warming, and it must clearly be dealt with on an international scale. Global warming and the development, control and management of industries cannot be dealt with unless the financial side of the question, and the management and control of the tax capability of the relevant companies, is dealt with. It must be done, and soon.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.108.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1670" speakername="George Mudie" colnum="108"  time="015:21:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0008.htm#09050659000509">
	<p pid="b.108.0/1">It is with some humility that I take part in the debate surrounded by accountants and international aid experts. I was considering whether to contribute to the debate, but I came to support my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" name="David Taylor">the Member for North-West Leicestershire (David Taylor)</phrase>. He has done us all a service by obtaining the debate; he has also done a great service, to which other hon. Members have added, in what he has said. The scandal has been going on for too long. I am interested in what <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1885" name="Vincent Cable">the hon. Member for Twickenham (Dr. Cable)</phrase> will say.</p>
	<p pid="b.108.0/2">I view the past 20 years as a time when there was urgent need for various actions by the authorities, but, as happened with so many things, no one was prepared to blow the whistle, or to stand up and attempt to stop the over-exuberance.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.108.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" speakername="David Taylor" colnum="108"  time="015:21:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0008.htm#09050659000510">
	<p pid="b.108.1/1">My hon. Friend says that no one has been prepared to stand up. An organisation is nominally charged with that responsibility: the International Accounting Standards Board, which is, as I said, predominantly funded by the gang of four large accountancy bodies. He who pays the piper calls the tune, and you do not bite the hand that feeds you. There are all sorts of sayings that come to mind to explain why the IASB has been so torpid in tackling the problems.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.108.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1670" speakername="George Mudie" colnum="108"  time="015:21:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0008.htm#09050659000511">
	<p pid="b.108.2/1">I have some agreement with that; but there is a larger question concerning Governments and financial authorities. Why have those not been willing to intervene? The picture, certainly in the UK, has been that the City has earned so much money and had such a large part in the economy that I do not think any Governments have been willing to stand up against some of the practices that were current.</p>
	<p pid="b.108.2/2"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1382" name="Tony Baldry">The hon. Member for Banbury (Tony Baldry)</phrase> questioned international aid development, but I do not think that the situation is anything to do with international aid; and the debate is not set out in those terms. It is clear that the credit crunch and the global financial crisis are having an effect on the major developed countries; they are desperate to get their hands on billions that have been lost to them in the past few years, but which, in the eyes of the authorities, they could afford to lose. They cannot afford the loss now, and it is self-interest in Europe, America and the UK that is now the spur to action.</p>
	<p pid="b.108.2/3">The basis on which I came to the Chamber to support my hon. Friend was my hope that the Minister will take a firmer line than has been taken in the past by Ministers, including the Chancellor. Only two months ago, when we were discussing the banking crisis with him in the Treasury Committee, I pressed the Chancellor on <i>The Guardian's </i>excellent articles and could not get him to say a word of praise about <i>The Guardian.</i> I do not think that it was <i>The Guardian</i> that upset him; but he certainly refused to be forthcoming. I wonder about the depth of the Government's commitment, and whether the current issue has been forced on to the agenda by the G20 as part of the political furniture that shows the people that we are taking every action. If that is so, it is outrageous.</p>
	<p pid="b.108.2/4">My hon. Friend raised questions about the OECD standards; we shall all, apparently, be grateful if every country and all the offshore centres meet those. However, there is clear evidence, as my hon. Friend said, that those standards are too low and would not do the job alone. I should have thought that we now have the political opportunity, with a public who face public expenditure cuts and tax increases, and who do not see why big firms, multinationals and banks should not pay their proper whack in tax, to raise the bar and take steps that were not politically opportune in the past. To return to the comments of the hon. Member for Banbury, I wonder whether it is any coincidence, or accident, that the latest adventure of Barclays is to set up an offshore bank in Ghana. If the hon. Gentleman is not alarmed at that, I do not know what world he lives in. Certainly, all the development agencies rightly raise issues of money laundering, drug money and tax evasion. They all see the move as something that should not happen. I want to ask the Minister whether we have made any representations&mdash;such things have been done by Governments in the past&mdash;to suggest that Barclays should not go ahead with the adventure.</p>
	<p pid="b.108.2/5">While I am dealing with Barclays, it would be good to mention its disgraceful record. My hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1600" name="Austin Mitchell">the Member for Great Grimsby (Mr. Mitchell)</phrase> and I grew up&mdash;as did the hon. Member for Twickenham&mdash;in a world where Barclays was rightly considered the villain, when it supported apartheid in South Africa. I thought in my innocence that it had reformed and was a different sort of organisation, until <i>The Guardian</i> drew the curtains aside and we saw what the structured capital markets division of Barclays Capital was up to. Barclays went to court to get a gag and stop the information coming out. Thanks are due to the hon. Member for Twickenham who got a copy and sent it out. We could see what was happening. We ought to mention Rog &quot;the dodge&quot; Jenkins whose annual salary is &pound;40 million, and his colleague, Bob Diamond, who runs the capital division, who has a modest salary of &pound;250,000 a year but an annual bonus of &pound;20 million. It is quite right to ask what on earth they do to earn such money. Barclays engages through offshore banks in activities in which it is the leading international bank, involving firms, banks and individuals avoiding tax&mdash;but that shades into evading tax, and in the event that is what it is. That is what Barclays is up to.</p>
	<p pid="b.108.2/6">When Barclays refused Government help and went to the middle east for more expensive help, we all thought that it did not want Government intervention because of those salaries. Clearly, that might have played a part, but the bigger part in the decision was stopping the Government getting into the firm and seeing what it was up to and putting a stop to those measures. If Barclays is taking Government money in any way, I hope they will go into it and do what they did by agreement with Royal Bank of Scotland, and stop its tax avoidance activities.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.110.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1885" speakername="Vincent Cable" colnum="110"  time="015:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0008.htm#09050659000512">
	<p pid="b.110.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" name="David Taylor">the hon. Member for North-West Leicestershire (David Taylor)</phrase> on securing the debate. This is a very topical issue and he presented the case extremely well. Rightly, the focus has been on tax havens&mdash;the common theme is secrecy&mdash;which my colleague, the noble Lord Oakeshott, called</p>
	<p pid="b.110.0/2" class="indent">&quot;sunny places for shady people.&quot;&mdash;[<phrase class="offrep" id="lords/2009-03-26.772"><i>Official Report, House of Lords,</i> 26 March 2009; Vol. 709, c. 772</phrase>.]</p>
	<p pid="b.110.0/3">People go to the British Virgin Islands or the Caymans not because they want financial expertise but because they have got something to hide, even if there are other reasons why people want secrecy.</p>
	<p pid="b.110.0/4">The debate is on the revenue side. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1382" name="Tony Baldry">The hon. Member for Banbury (Tony Baldry)</phrase> rightly asked for an evidence base. There is fragmentary evidence. Her Majesty's Revenue and Customs estimated three years ago that the British Exchequer was losing something in the order of &pound;10 billion to &pound;40 billion a year&mdash;a wide range&mdash;to tax avoidance and evasion activities of various kinds. Richard Murphy, who has rightly been praised for his practical work on the matter, has estimated that HMRC is losing something in the order of &pound;18 billion specifically through tax havens. High net worth individuals account for about half of that through legal avoidance; &pound;3 billion is lost through corporates; and the rest is lost to illegal evasion. A lot of evidence has come through in the past few years, for which <i>The Guardian </i>has rightly been praised, on corporate tax avoidance, as distinct from evasion.</p>
	<p pid="b.110.0/5">In 2005-06, a third of British companies in the FTSE 100 paid no tax at all on their profits&mdash;none whatever&mdash;and a third paid very little. We have an extraordinary state of affairs. The average corporate tax rate for small companies in Britain is 21 per cent., which is supposed to be concessional, but the average tax paid by big companies is 20 per cent., because the latter have access to the lawyers and accountants that the former do not. That is utterly perverse.</p>
	<p pid="b.110.0/6">Before I go any further, we need to clarify the language. We all use the words &quot;avoidance&quot; and &quot;evasion&quot;, but there is clearly a continuum&mdash;it is not one or the other. On the one hand, there is outright criminal activity, and on the other the form of tax avoidance that all taxpayers engage in when the Government, sometimes rather foolishly, openly give a differential that invites people to take advantage. We had a good example in the Budget: we now have a 50 per cent. top rate tax on earnings, but only an 18 per cent. rate on capital gains tax, which is an open invitation to perfectly law-abiding individuals to turn their income into stocks so that they can pay tax at a much lower rate. We cannot blame people for that. The measure could have been simple incompetence, but it could also have been deliberate.</p>
	<p pid="b.110.0/7">Somewhere between avoidance and evasion is a very grey area, on which the debate has centred. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1600" name="Austin Mitchell">The hon. Member for Great Grimsby (Mr. Mitchell)</phrase> and <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1670" name="George Mudie">the hon. Member for Leeds, East (Mr. Mudie)</phrase> helpfully described the complex structured arrangements in which organisations such as Barclays engage. I believe that Barclays has 110 specialists working on the absolute edge of the margin between evasion and avoidance, so that they stay on just the right side of the criminal law. They nevertheless have the very clear intention of avoiding paying UK taxes, which is our main concern.</p>
	<p pid="b.110.0/8">The big question that the hon. Member for North-West Leicestershire asked was, what do we do about it? It is partly about taking international action and partly about domestic policy. Internationally, the fundamental issue raised by the G20 was transparency, and he raised two of the three key issues, the first of which is the automatic exchange of information. The current OECD white list is very good at creating transparency, but it leaves substantial hurdles when it comes to getting information from tax havens. Information exchange has to be made automatic to be effective. As he mentioned, the Government are resisting such a measure. There are good reasons for resisting automatic exchange in some cases&mdash;one would not want automatic exchange of information with, say, Mugabe's Zimbabwe, for human rights reasons&mdash;but, as a general principle, between countries that have satisfactory human rights, automatic exchange of information should be the norm.</p>
	<p pid="b.110.0/9">The second transparency issue that the hon. Gentleman raised was country-by-country accounting. As several hon. Members mentioned, it is an issue for the IASB. There is a lot of foot-dragging, and political leadership is needed, but that is the way to stop the systematic abuse through transfer pricing, the manipulation of profits and the minimisation of corporate tax payment.</p>
	<p pid="b.110.0/10">The hon. Gentleman did not mention the third transparency issue, namely the identification of the beneficial owners of trusts and companies. A lot of tax avoidance through tax havens takes place by hiding the names of the ultimate owners. The EU savings directive precludes that, but it is not being enforced. One difficulty that the UK has in being righteous about the matter is that our trust system is incredibly opaque. Many trusts are never registered and other countries might reasonably ask, &quot;Why are the British getting heavy-handed about this when their own system of tax law in relation to trusts is so opaque?&quot; Until we deal with that problem, it will be impossible to crack down effectively on the tax haven system.</p>
	<p pid="b.110.0/11">On the specifics, the Prime Minister has now taken the initiative of writing to all our Crown dependencies and overseas territories and challenging them to come up with standards of behaviour that meet the requirements of the G20 and OECD systems. That is a step forward. One could legitimately ask why he did not take that step 12 years ago, but he has done it now. I guess that he did not introduce the measure earlier partly to protect the City, which has sustained many such relationships, and partly because DFID encouraged many of the territories to get into tax haven activities supposedly as a way of making their economies sustainable. That was foolish, as the hon. Member for Banbury pointed out, but we are stuck with it.</p>
	<p pid="b.110.0/12">What action is going to be taken to follow up that initiative? I have two specific questions for the Minister. First, what sanctions are going to be taken against the seven British territories that are on the OECD grey list which do not even comply with the OECD's fairly modest demands? What powers do we have in respect of those territories to which the Prime Minister has written? I suppose that we cannot be too draconian. Fifty or so years ago, when General de Gaulle was annoyed by the tax avoidance activities of Monaco, he cut the water supply off; by the following day, Monaco complied. We are not in a position to do that, but I assume that sanctions against British territories are available. If so, what are they?</p>
	<p pid="b.110.0/13">Secondly, the three United Kingdom Crown dependencies&mdash;Jersey, Guernsey and the Isle of Man&mdash;comply to pretty high standards under the OECD rules, but they do not automatically exchange information. What steps are being taken to make them comply with that higher requirement which, I think we have agreed in the debate, is necessary to make the crackdown on tax havens effective?</p>
	<p pid="b.110.0/14">That deals with the international dimension, and I wish to pose a series of questions to the Minister on domestic policy in my remaining three minutes. First, what resources are the Government putting into HMRC to crack down on avoidance activities such as the complex structured arrangements in the banks that have been described? My understanding is that the budget for the relevant department within HMRC was cut by 5 per cent. for the current financial year. Is that true? What is being done to ensure that HMRC is properly resourced to pursue its activities? Is it true, as I have been told, that HMRC is not yet even so much as investigating the information that came to light as a result of the German crackdown on Liechtenstein? That brought to light a lot of British names. As far as I know, they are not being investigated. Is that true? What will be done following the Government's promise to name and shame companies and individuals who are engaged in systematic tax avoidance? What form will that action take and when will it start?</p>
	<p pid="b.110.0/15">Secondly, as the hon. Member for Leeds, East said, we cannot be in a position in which the Government are guaranteeing banks and simultaneously allowing them to participate in tax avoidance activity. There is a lot of ambiguity about that. It is clear that the Government intended that the beneficiaries of the asset protection scheme comply with British tax rules, but in subsequent statements, including to me, the Chancellor has said that it is a separate issue. How separate an issue is it?</p>
	<p pid="b.110.0/16">On the legislative provisions&mdash;several hon. Members referred to this&mdash;there has been a general expression of belief that we need to move to general anti-avoidance rule processes. What is the Government's time schedule for that, and do they have any specific provisions to introduce a purposive rule in order to ensure that the courts, when dealing with marginal cases, are clearly directed to ensure that companies and individuals seeking to avoid paying taxes are prosecuted?</p>
	<p pid="b.110.0/17">The hon. Member for Great Grimsby correctly described how companies establish subsidiaries for the purpose of avoiding tax. My understanding is that such subsidiaries are required to be disclosed under the Companies Act 2006, but evidence unearthed by newspapers investigating the issue suggests that they are not being registered. They are not compliant with the law. Are the Government investigating the matter? Is action being taken against companies that do not comply with those legal processes?</p>
	<p pid="b.110.0/18">Thank you for your indulgence, Mr. Hancock. I think that we all recognise that raising revenue is now a critical task, given the serious problems with the public finances. We should start by cracking down on the people who do not pay the taxes that they should pay.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.113.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" speakername="David Gauke" colnum="113"  time="015:40:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0008.htm#09050659000513">
	<p pid="b.113.0/1">It is a pleasure to serve under your chairmanship for the second time today, Mr. Hancock. I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" name="David Taylor">the hon. Member for North-West Leicestershire (David Taylor)</phrase> on securing this debate. It is, as others have said, timely and topical, indeed fashionable, although to be fair to the hon. Gentleman, I do not think that anyone would describe him as a slavish follower of fashion, intellectual or otherwise. None the less, it is helpful for us to debate the issue. I know that he has pursued it for some time.</p>
	<p pid="b.113.0/2">There is a clear consensus that secrecy within the financial services sector and various tax jurisdictions is creating great problems. The public mood has shifted, partly because at a time when most people's tax burden is increasing, it is essentially unfair that a wealthy minority can avoid their tax obligations. Also, as <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1670" name="George Mudie">the hon. Member for Leeds, East (Mr. Mudie)</phrase> pointed out, the Government are desperately searching for revenue, we are borrowing a huge amount and debt is increasing.</p>
	<p pid="b.113.0/3">I share the focus of the comments made by the hon. Member for North-West Leicestershire and Christian Aid in its campaign. Secrecy is key. We must find practical ways to improve the exchange of information. In the Crown dependencies and overseas territories, the picture is not all bad. Progress has clearly been made in our offshore financial centres, according to the interim Foot report commissioned by the Prime Minister, on a test of compliance with the Basel Committee on Banking Supervision, the International Organization of Securities Commissions, the International Association of Insurance Supervisors and the anti-money laundering standards published by the Financial Action Task Force. The International Monetary Fund assesses those financial centres as broadly comparable to other jurisdictions and, in some cases, better. It is also worth noting that the G20 assessment for the Crown dependencies suggested that they are substantially implementing the international standards for exchange of information. The overseas territories are committed to doing so, but they have not substantially implemented them yet.</p>
	<p pid="b.113.0/4">We must not be complacent, of course, and there is clearly a great deal of progress to be made, but as <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1885" name="Vincent Cable">the hon. Member for Twickenham (Dr. Cable)</phrase> rightly pointed out, terminology is important. What do we mean by a tax haven? I would argue that a tax haven is not simply a jurisdiction with low tax rates. That is a sovereign right. The Republic of Ireland, for instance, was sometimes accused of being a tax haven for having a corporation tax rate of 12.5 per cent. I think that the focus should be secrecy.</p>
	<p pid="b.113.0/5">Another point of terminology that the hon. Gentleman rightly raised is that there is a spectrum that runs from tax evasion, which is clearly illegal and unacceptable and must be addressed, through tax avoidance to tax planning. I quote:</p>
	<p pid="b.113.0/6" class="indent">&quot;It's perfectly legitimate for people to tax plan. They are only obliged to render unto Caesar what is due to Caesar.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.113.0/7">That comment was made by the Chancellor of the Exchequer to the Treasury Committee in his evidence; I suspect that the hon. Member for Leeds, East will recall it.</p>
	<p pid="b.113.0/8">We must be careful about what we are addressing. There is a danger of confusion in some of the criticisms made about the level of tax avoidance. A number of hon. Members have mentioned the Trades Union Congress report that refers to a tax gap. The work was undertaken by Mr. Richard Murphy, who identifies a &pound;25 billion tax gap caused by tax avoidance. Essentially, he looked at headline tax rates and then at the total tax rate, measured the gap and said that it was caused by tax avoidance, but that fails to take into account that we as a Parliament deliberately introduced measures that mean that entities, individuals and companies are not necessarily paying the headline rate.</p>
	<p pid="b.113.0/9">It appears that half of the &pound;25 billion gap is due to a combination of independent taxation in the UK between spouses and civil partners and the fact that companies can defer taxation through capital allowances. Bill Dodwell of Deloitte put it well when he said:</p>
	<p pid="b.113.0/10" class="indent">&quot;The TUC's report doesn't inform the tax avoidance debate: it seems to be challenging policy choices (independent taxation; the taxation of the self-employed; capital allowance rates) by labelling them as tax avoidance.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.113.0/11">We must be careful not to devalue the terminology. There is such a thing as tax avoidance, which should be addressed, but let us not become confused.</p>
	<p pid="b.113.0/12">Christian Aid has led the argument on the international development element of the issue. I know that it is in frequent communication and contact with my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1862" name="Andrew Mitchell">the Member for Sutton Coldfield (Mr. Mitchell)</phrase>, our spokesman on international development. Christian Aid makes the point made by the hon. Member for North-West Leicestershire: it is better that countries should be self-sufficient and rely on their own tax revenue rather than aid. That is an interesting point for the Minister to answer. How much are the Government doing to assist in that?</p>
	<p pid="b.113.0/13">On a note of caution, my party and I believe that globalisation has many positive effects and that it is good for countries to trade with each other and for multinationals to be active in developing countries. As my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1382" name="Tony Baldry">the Member for Banbury (Tony Baldry)</phrase> pointed out, multinationals go to developing countries and create jobs, which benefits those countries. One reason why they may do so is the lower tax burden. It might be a combination of accident and design&mdash;my hon. Friend referred to tax holidays, for example&mdash; but if the lower tax burden is no longer available, it is legitimate to question whether multinationals would invest in the same way and create the same number of jobs.</p>
	<p pid="b.113.0/14">To what extent do the numbers in the Christian Aid report incorporate a dynamic model? If not for what it describes as the tax leakage from developing countries to developed countries, would there be as much economic activity? I question whether that is the case.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.115.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1692" speakername="Nia Griffith" colnum="115"  time="015:40:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0009.htm#09050659000514">
	<p pid="b.115.0/1">Will the hon. Gentleman give way?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.115.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" speakername="David Gauke" colnum="115"  time="015:40:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0009.htm#09050659000515">
	<p pid="b.115.1/1">I have only one minute, so I apologise to the hon. Lady for not giving way.</p>
	<p pid="b.115.1/2">To conclude, in order to allow the Minister his full time, there should be more transparency and greater exchange of information, and it is right that we should debate the practical ways of developing them, but I have two questions about the UK and anti-avoidance. To follow the comments made by the hon. Member for Twickenham, how much is HMRC investing in enforcement and tackling tax avoidance? There were reports that the amount being spent on those matters increased to &pound;1 billion, although we do not have comparable figures for previous years. Will the Minister put that &pound;1 billion figure into context?</p>
	<p pid="b.115.1/3">Secondly, avoidance activity is likely to increase when tax rates increase. A new 50p income tax rate has just been announced. It was reported that Treasury modelling said that 69 per cent. of those affected by the 50p rate will avoid or evade paying at least some of the tax. Will the Minister confirm whether those reports are accurate?</p>
	<p pid="b.115.1/4">In conclusion, it is right that we tackle this issue in a practical way. We must address secrecy so that those who have to pay a fair amount pay it.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.115.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1554" speakername="Ian Pearson" speakeroffice="The Economic Secretary to the Treasury"  colnum="115"  time="015:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0009.htm#09050659000516">
	<p pid="b.115.2/1">It is a pleasure to serve under your chairmanship this afternoon, Mr. Hancock. The debate has been excellent with well-informed and interesting contributions from <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1382" name="Tony Baldry">the hon. Member for Banbury (Tony Baldry)</phrase> and my hon. Friends the Members for Llanelli (Nia Griffith), for Great Grimsby (Mr. Mitchell) and for Leeds, East (Mr. Mudie), as well as from the Opposition spokesmen, the hon. Members for Twickenham (Dr. Cable) and for South-West Hertfordshire (Mr. Gauke). In particular, I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" name="David Taylor">the Member for North-West Leicestershire (David Taylor)</phrase> on securing this timely debate on tax avoidance and evasion.</p>
	<p pid="b.115.2/2">The Government believe that for any tax system to be effective, everyone must pay their fair share. Tax evasion and avoidance damage the ability of the tax system to deliver its objective of paying for services that we all use and need. It is important to say that the vast majority of people in Britain pay the right amount of tax. It is unsurprising that those who pay are angered by reports of the small minority of people and companies who seek deliberately to evade or avoid paying their fair share. The Government have been consistent in challenging avoidance and evasion through legislation and litigation, and by working closely with other countries, which is increasingly important in the global economy.</p>
	<p pid="b.115.2/3">It is said that businesses that operate internationally can most readily reduce the amount of tax they pay and that globalisation opens opportunities to avoid tax. From the UK point of view, we must keep our rules under review and work with international partners to support our competitive position and protect our tax base. We must also ensure that our partners' systems are not open to abuse. I will shortly say more about the important international agenda that we are pursuing in response to the points made by my hon. Friend the Member for North-West Leicestershire.</p>
	<p pid="b.115.2/4">The Government are also taking strong domestic action to counter tax evasion and avoidance. The Budget set out a further package of measures to tackle tax evasion and avoidance. In addition to closing down a number of abusive and artificial tax avoidance schemes, we announced measures to tackle cross-border tax evasion, including an opportunity for holders of offshore bank accounts to come forward and pay what they owe. The Chancellor announced steps to ensure that large taxpayers take responsibility and accountability for paying tax, including a duty on the senior accounting officers of the largest companies to sign off on tax returns. As hon. Members noted, we are also introducing legislation that will allow HMRC to publish the names of serious tax defaulters. That package of measures will raise more than &pound;1 billion in the next three years and, by 2010, will protect a further &pound;3 billion of tax receipts from evasion and avoidance each year.</p>
	<p pid="b.115.2/5">I mentioned that this problem is international. We are not the only country acting domestically to tackle tax evasion. Earlier this week the US Government released proposals to tackle the problem, which we will watch with interest. The need for international collaboration on taxation has never been clearer. The global financial downturn and the shocks that precipitated it highlight the extent to which our economies are intimately interconnected. The ability of large firms to move large flows of money around the world with ease provides greater opportunity for tax arbitrage through structures designed to minimise tax, as we have heard from hon. Members. As well as leading to a loss of tax revenues at home and in the developing world, such structures add capacity to the financial system and increase uncertainty about the location of risk and value.</p>
	<p pid="b.115.2/6">The Government have long been committed to supporting developing economies. As well as providing aid to the poorest developing countries, we have been clear about the role that tax can play in the development process. I assure my hon. Friend the Member for Leeds, East that that is not a new conversion&mdash;it has been a consistent policy over many years. In effect, we have led G20 discussions on taking action in this area. It was among the key issues discussed in London, where a great deal of progress was made. The G20 leaders agreed to take action against tax havens and noted the published OECD list of jurisdictions that do not meet international standards for exchanging tax information. They are ready to deploy sanctions, if necessary, and I will say more about that in a moment.</p>
	<p pid="b.115.2/7">Tax information exchange agreements play a key role in combating evasion and avoidance by enabling tax authorities to obtain information on the foreign income and assets of their taxpayers for tax assessment and compliance purposes. That makes it more difficult for people to hide income in foreign accounts and to avoid paying tax to their own authorities. Perhaps more so than developed countries, developing countries suffer from flows of capital to tax havens. Tax information exchange agreements provide greater transparency and make it possible to ensure that tax is paid where it is due, meaning that illicit flows of ill-gotten gains are more easily discovered. Transparency has been a key theme of our debate.</p>
	<p pid="b.115.2/8">The Government's priority is to ensure that momentum in this area does not falter and that our G20 commitments are delivered. We are looking to countries that do not meet international standards on exchanging tax information to make swift progress. As the hon. Member for Twickenham mentioned, the Prime Minister has written to all our overseas territories to remind them of their commitments. The hon. Gentleman also asked about G20 sanctions. The G20 is certainly prepared to take counter-measures, and I refer him to the communication annexe of the G20 report, which outlines them.</p>
	<p pid="b.115.2/9">We are talking to countries such as Switzerland and Lichtenstein, which were mentioned, about the implementation of their commitments to exchange tax information with the UK through bilateral treaties. Those steps will not only bring benefits for tax collection in the UK, but help developing nations to improve their tax systems. Rising revenues and sustainable economic growth are important for the strategies of developing countries to move out of aid dependency. With that in mind, we were able to secure the support of our G20 colleagues on ensuring that developing countries benefit from new measures to enhance co-operation on tax. The Prime Minister has written to the OECD to ask it to look at ways to enable developing countries to participate in and benefit from the exchange of tax information. He wrote specifically about extending global forum membership to developing countries. We will continue to explore mechanisms to support developing countries.</p>
	<p pid="b.115.2/10">Transparency is the key to tackling tax evasion. Tax authorities need the capacity to collect the taxes that are due, but they also need to be able to assess the full extent of tax liabilities. The hon. Member for Banbury commented on the measures that we have taken in Sudan. In addition to those, we are exploring the OECD's model multilateral tax information exchange agreement&mdash;perhaps that addresses the 192 squared point that my hon. Friend the Member for North-West Leicestershire made about bilateral agreements. That agreement could be a significant step towards allowing developing countries access to relevant tax information without requiring time-consuming and resource-intensive bilateral negotiations.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.118.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" speakername="David Taylor" colnum="118"  time="015:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0009.htm#09050659000517">
	<p pid="b.118.0/1" class="italic"> rose&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.118.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1554" speakername="Ian Pearson" colnum="118"  time="015:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0009.htm#09050659000518">
	<p pid="b.118.1/1">If my hon. Friend will forgive me, I will not give way because I have precisely two minutes in which to address the other points that he made.</p>
	<p pid="b.118.1/2">HMRC will continue to work closely with other jurisdictions through the Joint International Tax Shelter Information Centre and other international groups to combat avoidance and global tax risks. HMRC deals with all information that is received on a resource-to-risk basis. I cannot comment on individual cases, but it is important to understand the operating efficiencies that have been made by HMRC in recent years. We are also building a better evidence base to underpin our work.</p>
	<p pid="b.118.1/3">The Secretary of State for International Development has commissioned detailed research on the impact of tax evasion on developing countries and the interim review is expected imminently. Between 2001 and 2006, the Department for International Development undertook 101 tax-related projects to support developing countries in improving their tax systems. We are doing a lot with developing countries, not just Sudan, and I could give many further examples of the action we are taking. We are working through the African tax administration forum to share experiences on policy and process.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.118.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1767" speakername="Mike Hancock" colnum="118"  time="015:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0009.htm#09050659000519">
	<p pid="b.118.2/1">Order. I am afraid that I will have to interrupt you, Mr. Pearson. I thank all Members who have taken part for the courtesy that they have shown to the Chair and to each other, and I ask them to leave the Chamber quietly as we progress on to the next debate.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.119.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="119"  time="015:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0009.htm#09050659000004">
	NHS Whistleblowing
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.119.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1949" speakername="Richard Taylor" colnum="119"  time="016:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0009.htm#09050659000520">
	<p pid="b.119.1/1">I am delighted to be having this debate at such an appropriate time, and I am very pleased to see the Minister, with whom I often exchange shots across this Chamber. I am also very pleased to see, behind me, the hon. Members for Stafford (Mr. Kidney) and for Cannock Chase (Dr. Wright), who have been, and are, closely involved in whistleblowing issues.</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/2">The debate is absolutely relevant. First, the country was staggered by the revelations from mid-Staffordshire, after which people inevitably asked why no doctor or senior nurse appeared to have spoken out. Then, at almost the same time, we got the answer with the case of the whistleblower from Brighton. She admitted that she had done wrong in breaching confidentiality, but felt that she was doing good by exposing publicly and effectively the standard of hospital care. She thought that was exactly the right thing to do, but she has been struck off. That has raised an absolute furore in the press, and there has been a petition by the Royal College of Nursing. The letter that I liked best was a short and brief one in <i>The Independent</i> of <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-20">20 April</phrase>, from a lady called Fleur Ball, from Plymouth, who wrote:</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/3" class="indent">&quot;I surely can't have understood this properly. A nurse has been struck off, not for failing to care for elderly, terminally ill patients, but for breaching their confidentiality by revealing how little care they received...And this only after alerting managers to the appalling lack of care given on that ward.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/4">I looked up the Nursing and Midwifery Order 2001 and discovered that the conduct and competence committee has four options of punishment when it feels that allegations that have come before it are well founded. In this case, it elected to give the harshest punishment because, according to the report of the judgment, the panel's view was that</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/5" class="indent">&quot;the misconduct found is fundamentally incompatible with being a nurse.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/6">It is not my place to express a particular opinion about the correctness of that decision, because it could well go to appeal, but one can say that it has been an absolute disaster for anyone in the NHS who was thinking of whistleblowing. Surely, the habit of leaving helpless elderly patients in pain, in filthy beds, without food or fluid, is incompatible with being a nurse, or indeed a doctor, if he or she condones it by not speaking out.</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/7">Recently, the Select Committee on Health had a trip to New Zealand, which was a long way to go, but was extremely useful. I have the Chair of the Committee's permission to comment on one or two things. We met the chair of New Zealand's Quality Improvement Commission, who told us:</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/8" class="indent">&quot;The excuse, 'I'm too pushed to do better,' is rubbish.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/9">The Royal College of Nursing has produced a very useful booklet called, &quot;Dignity at the heart of everything we do: Defending Dignity&mdash;challenges and opportunities for nursing&quot;. It says in the executive summary:</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/10" class="indent">&quot;As one nurse explained: 'I believe there is always a way around obstacles and primarily it is you, yourself, your actions, standards and behaviour that deliver care.'&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/11">So, however pushed people are, it is up to them to get over those obstacles, and that should be possible even on the most stressful occasions. Otherwise, people should at least speak out and say that they cannot do something, and say what they need to be able to do it. Therefore, I ask the Minister an absolutely straight question: is there no way of reviewing or reversing the independent panel's decision to strike that nurse off, other than appealing to the High Court?</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/12">Turning to Stafford, about which much has been said and written&mdash;there was an exemplary debate on it in this place recently, which was led by the hon. Member for Stafford&mdash;several hon. Members have expressed their amazement that there were apparently no staff whistleblowers there. Dr. David Colin-Thom&eacute;, the Government's GP tsar, wrote in the introduction to his review of the lessons learned in mid-Staffordshire:</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/13" class="indent">&quot;What has particularly shocked and disappointed me is that no NHS organisations, staff or representatives of the public reported any serious concerns about emergency services in the hospital. Yet patient complaints and patient surveys all pointed to poor care.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/14">We need to know whether senior doctors and nurses attempted to speak out and whether they were silenced. I know that the Government are against it, but an independent inquiry is probably the only way to find out. I have permission to raise this matter in the Health Committee tomorrow, when I will see if its members will consider taking on an inquiry into whistleblowing. Personally, I am not sure whether that would be the best way of getting at doctors and nurses, and I might suggest, tomorrow, that a small group of Committee members, who are not in any way related, geographically, to the problems in that area of Staffordshire, could go there and meet one or two representatives, completely anonymously, just to talk about what they tried to do, if they tried to do anything.</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/15">My interest in whistleblowing arose after a number of complaints at home about the out-of-hours service that has taken over in Worcestershire. Three staff have talked to me about their concerns, which I quickly passed on to the chair and chief executive of the primary care trust, with whom I have a very close relationship, and I am glad to say that they are taking it very seriously, having ordered an independent review. Already, sources tell me, that service is improving, so I have not had to go to the press about it.</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/16">Why are staff scared? Allegations of bullying in the NHS are rife. If we look at back editions of the <i>Health Service Journal</i>, the editions of <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-02">2 April</phrase>, <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-16">16 April</phrase> and <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-23">23 April</phrase> all had articles about bullying in the service. Thinking about it from the point of view of senior nurses and senior doctors, they are dependent on their managers for their jobs, their mortgages, their advancement, their salary and their salary increments. What has changed from my day? I am often accused of being a dinosaur, and it was some time ago, but in my day a hospital was run by a team that included a senior nurse, a consultant and an administrator. They were all part of the team that ran the hospital, delivering the best care possible for their patients, and there were no secrets&mdash;they knew what was going on. If they had a bad doctor, or if the standard of nursing was appalling, they knew about it and addressed it.</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/17">The Minister probably will not like what I am going to say next, but since the purchaser-provider split, the emphasis has had to be on finances, competition and targets, primarily, other than patient outcomes. A split has occurred between managers and staff, and that can lead to these sorts of disasters. In some cases, but not all, it is noticeable that when a doctor or nurse moves from a purely clinical role to one that involves a large amount of management, their loyalty is tested. Are they fully loyal to the patients and staff, or to the management of the trust? That is where a problem arises. What can be done about that? I have one or two suggestions.</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/18">First, the Public Interest Disclosure Act 1998 is vital. I obtained a copy of a health service circular produced way back in 1999, at the back of which an annex provides a summary of the main provisions of that Act. The most useful paragraph is the one headed &quot;Wider Disclosures&quot;, which is so important I must read it out because I desperately want the Minister to publicise it widely. The circular states:</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/19" class="indent">&quot;Wider disclosures (e.g. to the police, the media, MPs, and non-prescribed regulators) are protected if, in addition to the tests for regulatory disclosures, they are not made for personal gain and if they satisfy a further two provisions. That is the concern must have been raised with the employer or a prescribed regulator, unless, there was reasonable belief of victimisation...there was no prescribed regulator and there was reasonable belief that there would be a cover up, and the matter was exceptionally serious. If one of these preconditions is met and the tribunal is satisfied that the disclosure was reasonable, the whistleblower will be protected.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/20">My first suggestion is that that paragraph be widely publicised.</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/21">The hon. Member for Stafford had two&mdash;he had more, actually, but I refer just to the first two&mdash;board meetings in public. Of course such meetings have to be in public. People must be given a chance to report what is going on and their suspicions. Again, in Prime Minister's questions today, I think the right hon. Gentleman mentioned that there should be stronger patient and public involvement. We have these funny things called LINks&mdash;local involvement networks&mdash;which are very variable across the country. Where were they in Stafford? Presumably, they had not really got off the ground&mdash;in fact, all over the country LINks have been slow to set up.</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/22">I shall mention another point from New Zealand. In one hospital that we visited, it was a strategy for all the staff to ask whether the patient would pass the granny test&mdash; &quot;Would you mind your grandma being in that hospital?&quot; I do not think that I have quoted <i>Private Eye </i>before, but I have a regard for that publication and what it sometimes publishes. In the 17 to <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-30">30 April</phrase> issue, we were reminded:</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/23" class="indent">&quot;In a 2006 Healthcare Commission survey, only 27% of Mid-Staffs staff said they would be happy to be treated in their own hospital&mdash;a powerful indication that standards were unacceptable&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/24">What a condemnation!</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/25">Since this debate was announced, I have had a number of communications. A helpful communication was sent by Dr. Rod Storring, who asked why the question to which I have referred is not still asked. He points out that a number of related questions can be answered by staff anonymously and he suggests that those could be used</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/26" class="indent">&quot;as litmus paper as to whether a Trust is functioning well&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/27">These statements are, I think, still in the staff survey:</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/28" class="indent">&quot;I am able to do my job to a standard I am personally pleased with...I can decide on my own how to go about doing my work...I am consulted about changes that effect my work...Senior managers where I work are committed to patient care...Care of patients is my Trust's top priority...I am able to deliver the patient care I aspire to...Senior managers act on staff feedback.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/29">I agree with Dr. Storring. Those statements should be put to staff anonymously as a litmus paper test of how the trust is doing.</p>
	<p pid="b.119.1/30">Finally, I do not know whether this is possible in the UK, but I shall mention a radical change. In New Zealand, they have a health and disability commissioner who is accessible to patients and staff through outreach work. He believes&mdash;these are not quotes; they are his thoughts on the matter&mdash;that patients must have an independent medical opinion available to them and an easily available advocate, which he regards as his job. He would welcome whistleblowers, provided they have a real case about which to blow the whistle and they are absolutely honest. If the mid-Staffordshire and Brighton cases achieve anything to improve the future quality of care, it will be to blow wide open the fact that there is protection for whistleblowers and that they can speak out without fear of victimisation.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.122.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1580" speakername="Ben Bradshaw" speakeroffice="The Minister of State, Department of Health"  colnum="122"  time="016:16:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0010.htm#09050674000074">
	<p pid="b.122.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1949" name="Richard Taylor">the hon. Member for Wyre Forest (Dr. Taylor)</phrase> on securing this debate on such an important and topical issue. Let me at the outset state unequivocally that the Government support whistleblowing and the NHS is expected to support it too.</p>
	<p pid="b.122.0/2">The NHS exists to serve the needs of patients and the public, not for the convenience of managers or staff. Staff have the right under the law and a professional duty to raise any concerns that they may have about the quality of patient care with their employer. They must feel free to raise legitimate concerns with their line managers, more senior managers or, on occasion, publicly. NHS organisations are required to have policies and procedures in place that support, encourage and celebrate whistleblowing. In well run organisations, it should not get to the stage where staff feel they have to approach their MP or go to the media. Legitimate concerns will be listened to and acted on.</p>
	<p pid="b.122.0/3">Of course, it may not always be easy to distinguish between someone who has a genuine, legitimate concern, and someone with a personal grievance or axe to grind. Good management is about being able to make the distinction in an atmosphere where people feel able and encouraged to come forward. Of course, there is also an onus on the concerned member of staff to act responsibly and professionally. They should go through the correct procedures first and only go public if they feel their concerns are not being listened to or acted upon.</p>
	<p pid="b.122.0/4">Back in 1998, one of the first pieces of legislation passed by the new Labour Government was, as the hon. Gentleman has mentioned, the Public Interest Disclosure Act 1998, which provided statutory protection for whistleblowers for the first time. He described it as a vital piece of legislation&mdash;and, indeed, it is. It came partly in response to a report by the Nolan Committee on Standards in Public Life, which had criticised the fact that people often felt compelled to go public with concerns because of the lack of protection for whistleblowers and the lack of robust procedures in place for organisations to deal effectively with employee concerns. The Government require every NHS organisation to have policies and procedures in place to comply with that Act.</p>
	<p pid="b.122.0/5">Indeed, we have seen a significant increase in the number of successful whistleblowing exercises thanks to the Act, and there have been hundreds of successful uses of the Act&mdash;for example, the case of a cleaner at Charing Cross hospital, who raised concerns about cross-contamination due to unsafe hygiene practices in 2005. She was initially dismissed, but an employment tribunal found that her concerns were well founded and that the 1998 Act applied. She was reinstated and awarded &pound;7,000 compensation.</p>
	<p pid="b.122.0/6">We have also commissioned a charity that specialises in the issue called Public Concern at Work. It provides an independent helpline that is staffed by lawyers with expertise in whistleblowing. That is available to all NHS staff and calls are treated in the utmost confidence. Last year, <i>Nursing Standard</i> magazine, along with Public Concern at Work, asked nurses about whistleblowing. Of those who had been concerned about a serious risk to patient safety in the last three years, 87 per cent. had raised that concern&mdash;43 per cent. did so with their line manager, 18 per cent. with their team leader and 20 per cent. with senior management. Some 232 nurses said that they had successfully blown the whistle and protected patients from harm by doing so. When asked if they would raise such an issue again, 85 per cent. said that they would.</p>
	<p pid="b.122.0/7">Public Concern At Work said:</p>
	<p pid="b.122.0/8" class="indent">&quot;Week in and week out, staff blow the whistle across the NHS...This is a welcome change from the culture that bedevilled the NHS a decade or more ago where staff were too scared to raise concerns and which allowed the scandals of Harold Shipman and the Bristol Royal Infirmary to go unchecked for so long.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.122.0/9">We also know from our staff surveys that more and more NHS staff know about their right to whistleblow and how to go about doing it.</p>
	<p pid="b.122.0/10">The hon. Gentleman raised two recent high-profile cases that have brought whistleblowing to people's attention. Let me deal first with the case of Margaret Haywood. She was the nurse who, in 2005, helped the BBC's &quot;Panorama&quot; programme make a film highlighting poor quality care at the Royal Sussex hospital in Brighton. She was recently struck off by the Nursing and Midwifery Council. I do not intend to go into the ins and outs of the case. The NMC is an entirely independent professional regulatory body and its fitness-to-practise panels operate independently within it. That independence is a vital component in securing public confidence in the system. Hon. Members can read the NMC panel's report at their leisure.</p>
	<p pid="b.122.0/11">It is still open to Mrs. Haywood to appeal to the High Court against the decision. Her union, the Royal College of Nursing, has said that it will support her in any appeal and has made it clear that it thinks that, given the range of sanctions available, the decision to strike Mrs. Haywood off was unduly harsh. Having studied the report myself, and having considered the wider implications of the ruling on our whistleblowing policy, I have to say that I agree with the RCN's position.</p>
	<p pid="b.122.0/12">I can confirm, as the hon. Gentleman asked, that the NMC does not have the power to overturn the decisions of its panels itself. The appeal must be made to the High Court.</p>
	<p pid="b.122.0/13">The second recent high-profile case that the hon. Gentleman raised in connection with whistleblowing was the devastating report by the Healthcare Commission into the standards of care at Stafford hospital. He raised one of the great questions in this case, which was highlighted in the Healthcare Commission report and by others who have looked into events at the hospital in more detail: where were the whistleblowers? Where were the professionals, the royal colleges and the unions?</p>
	<p pid="b.122.0/14">Since the report was published, there have been suggestions that some staff did raise concerns but were not listened to. I urge anyone who has had experience of that or has had it reported to them to bring evidence of such examples forward. But, to be frank, given what we know was going on at the hospital, one would have expected not one or two whistleblows but a cacophony of whistleblowing. One of the things that is clear about how the hospital was run is that there was a closed culture in which the management failed to take public and staff concerns seriously.</p>
	<p pid="b.122.0/15">In response to the two follow-up reports on Stafford hospital that were published last week, the Government announced a range of measures to ensure that NHS organisations fulfil their existing obligations to include the public and staff in decision making, including taking their concerns seriously. We also announced that we will reinstate a question in the annual staff survey asking people what they think of the quality of care where they work. As the hon. Gentleman rightly said, it was one of the measurements that helped alert the Healthcare Commission to the problems at Stafford. I understand that the commission&mdash;it is its survey, not ours&mdash;dropped the question in 2007 because of concern that it might skew results against certain types of provider; for example, a psychiatric hospital where staff may answer when asked whether they would be happy to be treated in their hospital with, &quot;No, because it would mean that I have a mental health problem.&quot; A problem with the wording led the commission to drop the question from its survey, but we strongly believe that asking staff what they think of the quality of care in their hospital is important, and that, done anonymously, it can tell a great deal about the quality of care at a hospital.</p>
	<p pid="b.122.0/16">I hope that I have made it absolutely clear to the hon. Gentleman, both in my general remarks and in what I had to say about the Margaret Haywood and Stafford hospital cases, that the Government fully support whistleblowing. We have provided unprecedented legal protection for those who whistleblow and have emphasised those rights in the new NHS constitution. We will not tolerate management that bullies or discourages whistleblowers. Listening to and acting on the concerns of staff are vital ways to drive up standards and help ensure against poor or unacceptable quality care.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.124.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1833" speakername="David Kidney" colnum="124"  time="016:25:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0010.htm#09050674000075">
	<p pid="b.124.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1949" name="Richard Taylor">the hon. Member for Wyre Forest (Dr. Taylor)</phrase> on securing such an important debate.</p>
	<p pid="b.124.0/2">Recently I was watching the regional television news&mdash;I believe that it was for Warwickshire, not Staffordshire&mdash;and there was a story of a doctor who was celebrating getting his job back seven years after he had been wrongly suspended from work for whistleblowing. It is one thing to say that there is already a law that protects people, but when clinicians read or see that they could have seven years of hell for whistleblowing, it is not that much consolation that the law is as it is.</p>
	<p pid="b.124.0/3">I was at a public meeting in Stafford last night, which I mentioned at Prime Minister's questions today. The room was packed with angry people who had suffered terribly either because of the loss of a relative or because of how they had been treated by the hospital. They told some frightening stories about hospital staff being bullied to make them toe management's line. We need to say that that is totally unacceptable throughout the national health service, and I was pleased that the Minister firmly stated that to be the case.</p>
	<p pid="b.124.0/4">I was interested by the hon. Member for Wyre Forest saying that in his day the hospital was run by the doctor, the nurse and the administrator. I have had a couple of letters since all this blew up in my local media, one from a retired consultant and one from a retired doctor. They both make the same point about the rise and rise of the manager. It is no longer the administrator but the manager who controls the hospital&mdash;the consultant has been pushed aside. One thing that we could say, independently of Stafford, is that Lord Darzi's report last year on quality care and restoring the centrality of the clinician's role in our health service is an important development that we must support and sustain.</p>
	<p pid="b.124.0/5">I am sorry to bring Stafford into the hon. Gentleman's debate, but he was right to say that, in the end, it is the public, the patients and the patients' relatives supporting a caring staff in the hospital, and the dialogue between the two groups, that will eradicate the kind of problems that he described and that I have just described in my brief contribution.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.125.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1478" speakername="Tony Wright" colnum="125"  time="016:27:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0010.htm#09050674000076">
	<p pid="b.125.0/1">I declare an interest, in that I initiated the thought that we might have a whistleblower protection Act more than 10 years ago. It finally became the Public Interest Disclosure Act 1998. I knew that whistleblowing mattered, but I did not realise that we would have a situation such as Stafford, where the absence of whistleblowing was so serious. It is perplexing why that was the case, and we need to do more investigation into it.</p>
	<p pid="b.125.0/2">The Minister referred to a closed culture, and that is what the report clearly said was the fundamental problem. It is all right having general whistleblowing procedures, and what the Government have produced in the years following the 1998 Act is very good. The stuff that the Department has put out is excellent&mdash;it says all the right things&mdash;but the test for guidance is what happens to it on the ground. What happens to it when it confronts, as the Minister said, a closed culture such as the one in Stafford? Is the guidance good enough to convert it into a different culture? Can it break open the kind of closed culture that we saw in Stafford? Clearly not.</p>
	<p pid="b.125.0/3">I urge the Minister to reinforce the guidance, to do all the things that he is doing, to have the helpline and so on, but also to accept responsibility for ensuring that every health organisation in this country not only has words on a piece of paper but puts into practice a robust whistleblowing policy that staff have the confidence to use. If they do not do that, we shall again ask after another incident involving horrors like those at Stafford: why were people not able to speak out in the way that they clearly ought to have done?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.126.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1767" speakername="Mike Hancock" colnum="126"  time="016:27:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0010.htm#09050674000077">
	<p pid="b.126.0/1">The Minister has 30 seconds.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.126.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1580" speakername="Ben Bradshaw" colnum="126"  time="016:27:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0010.htm#09050674000078">
	<p pid="b.126.1/1">I entirely accept what my hon. Friends the Members for Stafford (Mr. Kidney) and for Cannock Chase (Dr. Wright) have just said. Briefly, in response to my hon. Friend the Member for Cannock Chase, I invite him, if he has not already done so&mdash;I am sure that he has&mdash;to study the details of what was announced last week in response to the David Colin-Thom&eacute; and George Alberti reports. Without going through the details, many important new measures and expectations were announced for providers and primary care trusts to ensure that exactly what he is advocating is delivered on the ground.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.126.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1767" speakername="Mike Hancock" colnum="126"  time="016:27:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0010.htm#09050674000079">
	<p pid="b.126.2/1">Thank you. That was good timing. Could those Members who have taken part depart quietly? We now move on to the next debate. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1667" name="Rosie Cooper">The hon. Member for West Lancashire (Rosie Cooper)</phrase> is about to take her place, and the Minister is eagerly anticipating her words.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.127.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="127"  time="016:27:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0010.htm#09050674000001">
	Concessionary Bus Travel
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.127.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1667" speakername="Rosie Cooper" colnum="127"  time="016:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0010.htm#09050674000080">
	<p pid="b.127.1/1">I welcome the opportunity to bring this debate before you, Mr. Hancock. During my time as a Member of Parliament, transport, including the whole gamut of bus and rail services and roads, has been one of my main priorities. Transport is at the heart of many issues affecting the residents of West Lancashire, given the size of its geographical area.</p>
	<p pid="b.127.1/2">I wish to cover two specific issues during this debate. First, some local authorities that are net gainers through the local funding regime are not maximising potential concessionary travel benefits for their local residents. Secondly, some local bus companies are fraudulently issuing tickets, meaning that they are, in essence, overpaid for the journeys taken. Local authorities are thus being overcharged, and pensioners are left worried that the scheme is devalued, that it might not last, and that they might have been involved in fraud.</p>
	<p pid="b.127.1/3">I put on record my support for the Government's national concessionary travel scheme, which has opened up a wealth of opportunities for older and disabled people across the country by removing the cost barrier to public transport. West Lancashire residents rely on public transport to enable them to get access to vital public services, such as their general practitioner or a hospital, to take up employment opportunities, and to take an active part in social and leisure activities.</p>
	<p pid="b.127.1/4">My aim is for pensioners to get a fair deal on concessionary transport. Older people in West Lancashire look on with envy as their neighbours in Wigan and Southport travel for free on buses and trains, often into West Lancashire. They, too, would like the chance&mdash;and the choice&mdash;to hop on a train and visit their friends and relatives and to take full advantage of the social and leisure opportunities in Liverpool, Southport and Wigan. I have taken to the streets alongside local pensioners, and our petition has collected more than 2,500 names, which shows clearly the strength of local feeling. We have met council officials to discuss the issue, and pensioners have protested at the district council's budget meeting, holding posters saying, &quot;We don't want to be Merseyside's poor relations&quot;, but all to no avail.</p>
	<p pid="b.127.1/5">I understand budgetary constraints. However, it is interesting to look at the funding received by West Lancashire district council. In 2006-07, it was estimated to have received an outturn of &pound;295,754. Under the national funding formula, it received an additional &pound;910,000, giving it a total allocation for 2006-07 of &pound;1.2 million. That represented a funding increase of 6.2 per cent., which was the fourth largest in Lancashire, although you would not have noticed it, Mr. Hancock.</p>
	<p pid="b.127.1/6">According to the figures for the concessionary fares special grant distribution in West Lancashire, the district council has been allocated &pound;760,000 for 2008 to 2011. In May 2006, the council agreed to&mdash;as it would say&mdash;prudently set aside a contingency of &pound;210,000. However, I would say that the money was taken away from pensioners and not used, as the Government intended, to help them get out and about on public transport.</p>
	<p pid="b.127.1/7">According to budget figures for this year, the council has a projected surplus of &pound;133,000 before its pooling arrangement with other Lancashire authorities and a post-pooling projected sum of &pound;50,000. It is unfairly using the surplus to offset other council services.</p>
	<p pid="b.127.1/8">For all the funding that the Government have pumped into concessionary travel, my constituents cannot see any great improvement in their access, primarily because of the actions of the local district council. They are still being forced to choose between a form of free travel throughout England or a discounted rail card, and, in areas that are ill-served by the relevant forms of travel, they have to choose travel tokens.</p>
	<p pid="b.127.1/9">The Prime Minister and the Government are, in my local pensioners' views, on the side of the angels by seeking to offer an opportunity for all older and disabled people but, unacceptably, a local Tory administration is pocketing the profit. The local council is wilfully depriving local residents&mdash;and vulnerable groups, at that&mdash;of real transport choices and using the money to prop up other services. At worst, local pensioners would welcome at least the choice between a free bus pass or a free rail pass. At best, they could have the same as their local authority neighbours: free bus and local rail travel. Why not? This local authority is making a profit from the Government's concessionary travel scheme, it has more than &pound;20 million in reserve accounts, and it has spent more than &pound;600,000 demolishing just four homes to make way for its new multi-million pound town hall, yet it refuses to listen to local pensioners and to give them a fair deal on transport&mdash;you really could not make it up.</p>
	<p pid="b.127.1/10">I now turn to fraudulent tickets being issued by bus companies. Such practices genuinely threaten the credibility and viability of the concessionary travel scheme, so any actions that diminish the value of the scheme must be stopped now. This issue has also been highlighted by my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1534" name="Natascha Engel">the Member for North-East Derbyshire (Natascha Engel)</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="b.127.1/11">I am aware that bus companies are issuing tickets to concessionary passengers that do not reflect their journey. In a more reprehensible practice, bus drivers issue tickets from a pre-printed roll. I often joke that, as a new MP, I was not issued with the two things that I would have found most valuable: tarot cards and a crystal ball. However, it seems that that is not so for some bus operators. Are they telling me that they are able to predict each customer's journey in advance, thus allowing them to pre-print their tickets? I would be surprised if that were so. I have complained to local bus operators about these practices and their response has been to change their ticketing policy so that the ticket states the destination. They no longer issue tickets from pre-printed rolls. I have made statements in the local press to raise awareness of such practice and encouraged people to complain if it happens to them.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.128.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1534" speakername="Natascha Engel" colnum="128"  time="016:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0011.htm#09050674000081">
	<p pid="b.128.0/1">In Derbyshire, the bus companies operate on a basis whereby money is reimbursed not on the tickets that are issued, but on an average based on who travels. The people using those tickets&mdash;the over-60s who are travelling on the buses&mdash;are really concerned that if they are issued a ticket with a destination that is much further away than they are travelling, the bus companies are operating fraudulently, even when they are not. That undermines the credibility of the whole scheme, and people are worried that they will lose something that is important to them.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.128.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1667" speakername="Rosie Cooper" colnum="128"  time="016:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0011.htm#09050674000082">
	<p pid="b.128.1/1">I share my hon. Friend's concerns. It cannot be right that people operate a scheme that is not transparent and that people using do not understand, even if it is like that which my hon. Friend outlines. Pensioners are clear that they love and value this scheme. They are really frightened by anything that they think damages the scheme or means that there will not be enough money in the pot at the end of the year. They worry if they hear people complaining that there is not enough money in the scheme at all, because they think that something that is valuable to them might be damaged.</p>
	<p pid="b.128.1/2">The situation needs to be addressed. Even after asking local pensioners to be aware and after speaking to various bus companies, I have recently received further complaints that tickets have been issued to concessionary travellers for a longer journey than the one taken. I complained to Lancashire county council, the travel authority in my area, which told me that 61 per cent. of the complaints that it received would have involved an overpayment to the bus operator. It is clear that if the operator makes money 61 times out of 100, there will be less money in the scheme for proper journeys. I believe that that is just the tip of the iceberg.</p>
	<p pid="b.128.1/3">Lancashire county council's internal audit report on the matter was supposed to go to committee on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-30">30 March</phrase>, many months after the matter was brought to its attention, but there is still no news, no understanding of the scale of the problem, and no idea of the action to be taken or how quickly. The council must act soon to ensure that it gets real value for every pound that it pays, especially if it is underfunded, as it claims. There is no question but that those practices must be stopped.</p>
	<p pid="b.128.1/4">If the bus companies are seeking to make a financial gain through fraudulent ticketing, that is illegal, so action must be taken. Any claim greater than the bus operator's entitlement means that there is less money in the pot for deserving older and disabled people to benefit from the scheme, and that places a greater burden on council tax payers to fill the gap created by ghost journeys. Such practices erode faith in the concessionary travel scheme, as my hon. Friend agreed. Constituents who have contacted me make the case that they do not want to be part of that deception and fraud. There is a growing perception that someone somewhere is on the fiddle, and that does not appeal to the majority's sense of fairness.</p>
	<p pid="b.128.1/5">In conclusion, the national concessionary travel scheme delivers real benefits to thousands of West Lancashire residents, and I want local authorities with a positive grant settlement to maximise and extend the benefits of free concessionary travel to increase opportunities for older and disabled people. Merseytravel allows its older people to travel across its whole network, including cross-boundary travel to Chester and even Ormskirk and West Lancashire.</p>
	<p pid="b.128.1/6">I understand that Merseyside and Greater Manchester passenger transport authorities' arrangements operate differently from those in Lancashire, but why should my constituents not have the same opportunities as their neighbours, especially as the local Tory-run council is making a profit from the scheme? I want a fair deal on free travel for West Lancashire residents. Will the Minister urgently tackle those practices, attitudes and behaviour, because they will seriously diminish the value of the scheme if they are not dealt with soon?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.130.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1594" speakername="Paul Clark" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport"  colnum="130"  time="016:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0011.htm#09050674000083">
	<p pid="b.130.0/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1667" name="Rosie Cooper">the Member for West Lancashire (Rosie Cooper)</phrase> on securing this debate on an important issue, and I take on board her request for my Department to consider the issues that she raised. I am proud, as is she, of the Government's achievements and our commitment to our older citizens and those with disabilities to provide the freedom and opportunities, which did not necessarily exist before, of widening the scope of travel. Indeed, in 2000, for the first time, older and disabled people in England were guaranteed some form of minimum concessionary travel regardless of where they lived. That scheme introduced half-price local travel.</p>
	<p pid="b.130.0/2">In 2006, the Government developed the scheme to provide greater freedom and extended it to provide free local travel within someone's local authority area. At that time, we allocated a further &pound;350 million through the formula grant&mdash;the rate support grant mechanism&mdash;that funds local authorities to pay for that improvement in service. My hon. Friends will remember that in 2006 the then Prime Minister announced that 11 million older and disabled people would be able to use off-peak local buses free of charge anywhere in England from April 2008. That very scheme, to which my hon. Friend referred, is appreciated by the concessionaires who use it. Whenever I visit places in England, I always take the opportunity to ask people who might be using the concessionary fare about their experience of it, the freedom that it has given them, the improvement that it has made to their quality of life, and the inclusion in society that it has provided.</p>
	<p pid="b.130.0/3">To expand the scheme to free local travel England-wide, we allocated a further &pound;212 million through the special grant agreement, which was debated on the Floor of the House, and forms a three-year funding package. There was &pound;212 million last year, and there is &pound;217 million this financial year, and another &pound;223 million for 2010-11. The special formula that we introduced made generous allowance for the number of those 11 million who would take up the option, and the number of journeys that they would make. The formula grant was consulted on widely, particularly with local authorities, and took account of hot spots, so that places to which people might travel regularly, such as tourist areas, shopping areas or areas with a large number of concessionaires aged over 60, received more of the pot than others. Overall, there is &pound;1 billion in the system for the statutory concessionary scheme, to which my hon. Friend referred. It comes from central Government pots, and we believe that it is enough to cover the scheme overall.</p>
	<p pid="b.130.0/4">I turn to some of the options and points that have been raised. My hon. Friend asked why her constituents cannot have the same benefits as people in Wigan, Southport and elsewhere. They can, because the Transport Act 2000 introduced a statutory national minimum scheme, and all local authorities may introduce additions, but they must obviously fund them over and above the &pound;1 billion that we provide collectively.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.130.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1667" speakername="Rosie Cooper" colnum="130"  time="016:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0011.htm#09050674000084">
	<p pid="b.130.1/1">I am grateful for the Minister's comments, and I appreciate that my constituents could have the same scheme if the council were prepared to fund it. The problem is that instead of trying to fund that and to help older and disabled people, it is too busy picking a pocket or two.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.131.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1594" speakername="Paul Clark" colnum="131"  time="016:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0011.htm#09050674000085">
	<p pid="b.131.0/1">It was agreed through the usual channels, principally the Local Government Association, that the special grant arrangement should be separate from the formula grant process that funds the lion's share of local government expenditure, and that it should not be ring-fenced. Indeed, my hon. Friend will be aware that our general ethos is to give more power to local government and elected representatives whom we presume will be responsible in meeting the requirements of their constituents and the people whom they represent and work on behalf of.</p>
	<p pid="b.131.0/2">At the beginning, my hon. Friend asked why those who were gaining did not use the money to improve the service. As the Minister responsible, I say that the powers exist for local authorities to use moneys that are there, whether those moneys have been given through the special grant formula and they have more money than they require or whether they are using their own funds to enhance the statutory minimum that applies throughout the country.</p>
	<p pid="b.131.0/3">Let me talk about the reimbursement process, because that will allow me to go on to the claim that fraudulent tickets are possibly being used as a method of reimbursement. I ask hon. Members to bear with me on the reimbursement process. I am the first to admit that it is complicated. However, it should not be beyond the wit of all of us, and indeed it is not in the vast majority of cases throughout the length and breadth of the travel concessionary authorities.</p>
	<p pid="b.131.0/4">Local authorities have the statutory responsibility to reimburse bus operators for the costs of carrying concessionaires. Therefore, individual authorities need to satisfy themselves that their payments are accurate and need to carry out relevant checks to validate the information passing between them and the bus operators. The underlying principle of the concessionary scheme is that bus operators should be no worse off and no better off. They should not be making a profit out of a national scheme; equally, they should not be making a loss. It is recognised that there are additional costs in carrying people who would not otherwise have travelled.</p>
	<p pid="b.131.0/5">The Department for Transport issues guidance to local authorities and bus operators on how to calculate reimbursement. As I said, the process is complicated, which is why I ask hon. Members to bear with me. Two key factors have to be taken into account. The first is the lost revenue from the people who are now concessionaires but would have travelled anyway. Someone in that group might be, say, 61, still going to work and would have travelled anyway, but they will not be paying now because they have access to the Government's generous scheme. The percentage of people who are travelling under the concessionary bus scheme and would have travelled anyway represent lost revenue to the bus company.</p>
	<p pid="b.131.0/6">The second element is additional costs associated with people who would not have travelled without the free scheme that we have introduced. What are the costs associated with them? There is additional wear and tear from the use of the seats and so on. Additional fuel may be required because of the additional weight. All of those are real things. This is where the tarot cards might have come in useful, because judgments have to be made at local level about who those people are, how many would have travelled anyway and how many would not have travelled.</p>
	<p pid="b.131.0/7">Then there is the issue of reimbursement and how payment is made. The most important factor to note is that the element of reimbursement for lost revenue should be based on the average fare that each concessionary traveller would have paid if there had been no scheme. We are starting to see some of the complications that come into the negotiations that have to be conducted at local level with local bus companies. Generally, the DFT advises that the average fare should be based on a basket of fares, taking into account the existence of commercially discounted and multi-journey tickets that would have been purchased by older and disabled people in the absence of a free scheme.</p>
	<p pid="b.131.0/8">If local authorities are reimbursing bus operators in line with our guidance, it should not matter, for the purposes of reimbursement, what type of ticket is issued to a concessionaire on boarding a bus, because there is no direct correlation between the individual ticket issued and the amount paid to the operator. The most critical issue is where the journey started, because that authority will be charged for the person. Where the person travels to is not a factor in the guidance that we give in relation to the reimbursement to the local bus operator. The key pieces of information that bus operators need to record to facilitate accurate reimbursement are how many concessionary journeys have been made and in which local authority area those journeys began.</p>
	<p pid="b.131.0/9">However, I will take on board this point; indeed, I raised it not long ago in the Department and my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1534" name="Natascha Engel">the Member for North-East Derbyshire (Natascha Engel)</phrase> has raised it. I am referring to the confusion that arises if someone is given a ticket that says that they started at A, which is true, but that they are going to B when they are actually going only to C, which is in-between. People will assume that that is what is being charged for somewhere. The confusion that is caused could undermine the scheme if we are not careful, because people will think that that is what is being charged for and it is fraudulent.</p>
	<p pid="b.131.0/10">I will come to the specific issue of Lancashire in a moment, having outlined how the reimbursement process operates. I share the concern that my hon. Friend has expressed about where the reimbursement is being undertaken using the method that has been described. There is potential fraud but, as I said, the DFT's guidance is that the element of reimbursement should be based on the average fare and that that should be based on a basket of fares.</p>
	<p pid="b.131.0/11">We have discovered through research done by Passenger Focus that 39 per cent. of passholders are making more local journeys by bus now than before they obtained their pass and that 13 per cent. are travelling further than they would have done, because it is free. The DFT guidance is clear. There should not be a correlation between the actual journey taken and the payment, because we would end up with the companies making a profit out of a concessionary scheme.</p>
	<p pid="b.131.0/12">I am particularly concerned about the claims of fraud in Lancashire. As I said, there is no need for any local authorities to base their payments on tickets actually issued. My officials have made that point to administrators of the Lancashire scheme. I am confident that none of the bus companies would condone overcharging by its drivers. However, it does appear that in Lancashire, the scheme is paid for on the basis of tickets issued. That is certainly a cause for concern, because it is not in line with the guidance given by the DFT.</p>
	<p pid="b.131.0/13">I take on board very strongly the issues raised in the debate. That is a reason why I have met a number of colleagues on both sides of the House to discuss issues relating to the concessionary scheme. We are talking about a minority of the 290-odd travel concessionary authorities, but there are some issues to be dealt with. It is one of the reasons why, since April of last year, we have been considering how we can change the administration of the scheme. In the last week or so, we have issued a consultation paper on the administration of the scheme&mdash;on keeping it as it is, taking it to upper-tier levels or even having a centrally based scheme. That is out to consultation. I urge all hon. Members to read the document themselves and consult, and to take the opportunity to get their local authorities to respond as well.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.133.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1667" speakername="Rosie Cooper" colnum="133"  time="016:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0011.htm#09050674000086">
	<p pid="b.133.0/1">Will the Minister undertake to ask his officials to pay particular attention to the situation in Lancashire? It is clear that tickets have been issued for journeys much longer than the journeys actually made. Lancashire is very worried that it may lose money over this. Taxpayers have to fund the difference, yet there is this hole right at the heart of it.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-05-06b.134.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1594" speakername="Paul Clark" colnum="134"  time="016:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090506/halltext/90506h0011.htm#09050674000087">
	<p pid="b.134.0/1">Yes, most certainly we will take that on board. The issues that my hon. Friend has raised must be taken forward, and my officials will raise the matter with officials in West Lancashire and for the Lancashire scheme as a whole. I can confirm that, according to my figures, West Lancashire&mdash;her own authority&mdash;is well funded by the moneys that have gone through the special grant. I understand her campaign to ensure that that money is used for the benefit of the concessionary scheme.</p>
	<p pid="b.134.0/2" class="italic">Question put and agreed to.</p>
	<p pid="b.134.0/3" class="italic">Sitting adjourned.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

