<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="b" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.179.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.179.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.179.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.179.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.179.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.179.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.179.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40652" speakername="Matthew Hancock" colnum="179"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0001.htm#10072737000516">
	<p pid="b.179.2/1">It is a great pleasure to speak under your chairmanship for the first time, in my first speech in a Westminster Hall debate, Mr Williams. I am delighted to have been granted this debate on the economic impact of dualling the A11, and am grateful to the Minister for giving his time. I am also grateful for the cross-party attendance by the many colleagues from all over Norfolk and Suffolk who have come to the debate.</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/2">It is poignant that this is the last day of the parliamentary term, for today Members will return to their constituencies-many of them along the A11. Those hon. Members will follow a now familiar path: steady progress past the M25 and an unencumbered glide past Stansted, before turning right-handed, and making steady progress up to Mildenhall. Then they, like 25,000 others every day, will come to a shuddering halt at Barton Mills. As they grind past the service station, and take their life in their hands getting on to the Fiveways roundabout, they fear they will never go faster than 30 mph again. Is that because it is a built-up area? No. Is it because of the number of pedestrians? Hardly. It is because they have reached the Barton Mills bottleneck. Why does that feature endure? Do the people of Norfolk not need a decent road to the capital? The journey from London to Norwich is 115 miles long. Yet for an inexplicable reason, nine miles in the middle of it have been left as a single carriageway.</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/3">The Minister will today hear many accounts of the extremely high economic returns that would result from finishing that bit of road. He may wonder how a road-widening project can have such high economic returns, but I urge him to think of it not as a road-widening project between Barton Mills and Thetford-although it is that-but more as the long-overdue completion of the road to Norfolk. The first layout of the motorway network, drafted in 1936, included a motorway from London to Norfolk. Proposals for completion of the dualling of the final nine miles of the A11, known as the Barton Mills bottleneck, were first put forward in 1989. After an assiduous campaign by my predecessor, Richard Spring, and my neighbour, my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40136" name="David Ruffley">the Member for Bury St Edmunds (Mr Ruffley)</phrase>-I pay tribute to them both-it became a Government priority in 1999. Public meetings on the plans were held two years ago this week. My constituents, and people all over East Anglia, hope that the new Government will finally give the scheme the go-ahead when the spending review is completed.</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/4">Today's debate focuses on the economic impacts of the road, so I will not dwell on the fact that the reasons for improving that stretch of the A11 are not solely financial. Local people are very focused on the tragic human cost of delaying the scheme. There are serious safety concerns, which were brought into sharp focus by a Road Safety Foundation report in June, which found that single-lane roads were twice as dangerous as dual carriageways. To the real economic cost we must add a cost measured not in pounds, but in lives. Having set out the context, I want to explain, first, the overwhelming local support for the scheme, and, secondly, its clear economic justification. Finally, I shall address head-on the central fact facing the Government: the vast, unprecedented budget deficit that the coalition is addressing.</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/5">First, unlike some transport projects, the scheme commands wide support. The number of fellow MPs here today from all over East Anglia is testament to that fact. Indeed, I am yet to come across an objector. Indicative of that was a petition of some 16,000 local residents presented to the Department for Transport in November 2008 by Daniel Cox, leader of Norfolk county council. Environmental concerns that were raised have been addressed. The project is supported by both Natural England and the Royal Society for the Protection of Birds, which says that</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/6" class="indent">&quot;the road will not harm wildlife in the Brecks&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/7">and that it is</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/8" class="indent">&quot;confident that this is the right deal for nature&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/9">Local businesses are also behind the scheme. The local branch of the Federation of Small Businesses backs the plans, arguing that an efficient road system is &quot;essential&quot;. Giles de Lotbini&#232;re, the managing director of local business Lignacite, says A11 delays are a &quot;hindrance to businesses&quot;. Indeed, international businessman and local landowner Lord Iveagh reflected the general tone adopted by the businesses that I have spoken to when he said:</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/10" class="indent">&quot;the more we can do for the road the better&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/11">The project of relieving the Barton Mills bottleneck is supported not just by local people, safety campaigners, environmental groups and businesses, but by all three political parties. During the election campaign, Lord Adonis, on a last gasp visit to his friend Charles Clarke in Norwich South, said:</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/12" class="indent">&quot;Labour is committed to completing the dualling of the A11 with construction beginning this year.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/13">On <phrase class="date" code="2010-04-23">23 April</phrase>, the Prime Minister and Deputy Prime Minister spoke out in support of the widening. My right hon. Friend the Deputy Prime Minister said that the project was &quot;totally justified&quot;, while my right hon. Friend the Prime Minister said that</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/14" class="indent">&quot;everyone knows it needs to be done&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/15">So from top to bottom, support is widespread.</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/16">What of the economic case? Having done the research, reviewed the evidence, and spoken to the officials at the Department, for whose time I am grateful, I can say that the economic case for finishing the road is compelling. The cost estimate for the scheme is &#163;134 million. Consultants for the Highways Agency estimate that, for that cost, the project will generate &#163;19 million in indirect taxes, and economic benefits of &#163;550 million for consumers and &#163;1.1 billion for businesses; so on the Government's own figures, the benefits are more than 20 times the cost. That is an astonishing figure, which I shall put into context. A return of more than twice the cost is regarded by the Department for Transport as</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/17" class="indent">&quot;providing high value for money&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/18">Hon. Members will not be surprised to find that the Highways Agency reports that</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/19" class="indent">&quot;benefits exceed expenditure costs substantially, demonstrating the economic viability of the scheme&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/20">The report found that there would be productivity benefits in Norfolk, Suffolk and Cambridgeshire, and that they would be concentrated on Thetford, Norwich and Great Yarmouth. It is good to see that MPs representing all those towns are present for the debate. The financial case for completing the road is clearly strong, but the impact would be felt far beyond the balance sheets of the businesses of East Anglia. Completing the road would boost confidence among businesses across Norfolk, generate interest from investors and help to create conditions for new employment. Until 18 months ago, businesses around Thetford routed their lorries away from the bottleneck on a Friday because it was impossible to negotiate. Now they are forced to reroute them every working day. That is the real business cost.</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/21">The Highways Agency report that I mentioned discusses the risks of not proceeding with the work and states that</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/22" class="indent">&quot;future growth aspirations could be jeopardised by the failure to improve the trunk road. Traffic delays would become sufficiently severe that new development would fail to materialise&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/23">I said that the benefits are 20 times the cost; let me put that figure further into context by comparing it with the figures for other schemes on the Department's list. The A13/A130 link at Sadlers Farm has an economic benefit four times the cost; for the A13 passenger transport corridor, the ratio is 2; for the A421 improvements at Milton Keynes, the figure is 1.9; and for the Luton busway it is 1.6. I am told that some schemes in north-east England have an economic return of less than one; I should be grateful if the Minister would confirm whether that is true.</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/24">The reason for that astonishingly high rate of return is clear. We are not talking about a new road project, or even the improvement of a whole road, but the final piece of an otherwise complete jigsaw. The question is why the work has not already been done. I shall not try to answer that question today, although <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40274" name="William Bain">the hon. Member for Glasgow North East (Mr Bain)</phrase> might try to do so. In truth, I find many of the actions of the previous Administration unfathomable, and that is but one of them. Instead, I shall address head-on the hard question that we all face.</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/25">There is no ducking the fact that our nation's finances are in a mess. We have the biggest peacetime deficit on record, and we are borrowing &#163;1 for every &#163;4 that the Government spend. The central task for the new Government in turning our economy around is to deal with the deficit. I campaigned on that platform, and I support it wholeheartedly. We all know that money is tight. The question is how we should deal with the mess.</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/26">The economic evidence shows that fiscal retrenchments are most successful when they are done mostly by reducing current spending. I was therefore delighted when the Chancellor forsook the easy option of further cutting capital spending in the Budget. He said:</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/27" class="indent">&quot;Well-judged capital spending by Government can help provide the new infrastructure our economy needs to compete in the modern world. It supports the transport links we need to trade our goods...There will be no further reductions in capital spending totals in this Budget, but we will make careful choices about how that capital is spent. The absolute priority will be projects with a significant economic return to the country.&quot;-[<phrase class="offrep" id="debates/2010-06-22.170"><i>Official Report</i>, 22 June 2010; Vol. 512, c. 170</phrase>.]</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/28">That policy is right, and the proposed scheme would help make it a reality. I believe that the A11 improvement scheme clearly fits into the class of capital spending that the Chancellor is keen to continue.</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/29">Last week, the Secretary of State for Transport told the <i>Eastern Daily Press</i> that the scheme had achieved &quot;a very high score&quot; under the Whitehall cost-benefit analysis, and spoke of the &quot;very powerful&quot; economic benefits of removing such bottlenecks. Will the Minister repeat those words to the House today? Will he confirm that the evidence shows a compelling case for the road to be completed? Does he accept that there is virtually no local opposition? Will he now tell us that, even in these difficult economic times, removing the Barton Mills bottleneck is at the top of his list of priorities?</p>
	<p pid="b.179.2/30">Lastly, will he accept my invitation to join me, one day soon, in opening the final section of this long overdue road, completing the dream of a highway to Norwich? If he does so, the warm and generous people of East Anglia will give him the hero's welcome that he deserved. <i>[Applause.]</i></p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.182.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.182.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.182.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40560" speakername="Elizabeth Truss" colnum="182"  time="009:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0001.htm#10072737000517">
	<p pid="b.182.0/1">I am delighted that my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40652" name="Matthew Hancock">the Member for West Suffolk (Matthew Hancock)</phrase> has secured today's debate. This issue more than any other is a priority for the people of South West Norfolk; for too long, they have struggled with a difficult situation, given that the road is one of the main thoroughfares into my constituency. The matter should be given serious consideration by Ministers in advance of this autumn's comprehensive spending review. The scheme is long overdue, and it is particularly pressing given the need to generate growth in our economy and to ensure that Britain races ahead.</p>
	<p pid="b.182.0/2">I wish to talk about three things: first, Norfolk's infrastructure deficit; secondly, specific effects of the problem on the town of Thetford; and, thirdly, the wider benefits that the scheme would deliver to our economy.</p>
	<p pid="b.182.0/3">Although the United Kingdom is the world's sixth richest country, it is 34th in the world infrastructure league table. However, Norfolk would rate far behind that. It is the largest county in England not to have a dual carriageway linking to the national trunk road network. We are the only county not to have been included in BT's plans for super-fast broadband. We do not have the train speeds or railway connections that a county with the economic potential of Norfolk truly deserves.</p>
	<p pid="b.182.0/4">Of the missed opportunities to improve infrastructure over the past 13 years, the grossest error was the failure to dual the final stretch of the A11, which I put down to mis-prioritisation by the now defunct regional authorities. They decided that the A11 had a lower priority than other schemes that had a far lower economic benefit.</p>
	<p pid="b.182.0/5">The scheme is readily supported by local businesses. For instance, Jo Pearson of Pearsons (Thetford) Ltd said:</p>
	<p pid="b.182.0/6" class="indent">&quot;Thetford, Norwich and the whole of Norfolk, for too long now has been the poor relation; the difference this upgrade will make in economic prosperity and jobs is immeasurable. We have heard all the talk time and again; this project must be not at the top of the 'to do' list but a distant memory in the completed pile!!&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.182.0/7">People in Thetford and elsewhere in Norfolk are fed up with being told that the project will happen only to find that the digging has not started. I and my colleagues want to see a definite plan for action.</p>
	<p pid="b.182.0/8">My hon. Friend the Member for West Suffolk mentioned the wide support give to the scheme by the local community. I would also mention the Gateway A11 East action group, which is represented here in the Public Gallery and has come to London to show how important the scheme is to them. The <i>Eastern Daily Press</i>, too, is here and listening to today's debate; the paper has featured the problem heavily in its columns over the years. The scheme has extremely widespread support.</p>
	<p pid="b.182.0/9">The problem, as has been pointed out, is that we are now in much more difficult economic times. However, Norfolk is not asking for handouts. We did not receive the national insurance tax holiday for new businesses; and we did not receive the millions of public sector jobs that other parts of the country did. Indeed, 72% of the Norfolk economy is in the private sector. To continue growing and making a net contribution to the tax pot-that is what we do in Norfolk-those businesses need their employees to be able to get into work and their supplies to be delivered to their customers. That is all that we ask.</p>
	<p pid="b.182.0/10">The Norfolk infrastructure crunch is particularly acute in Thetford. Thetford was the ancient capital of East Anglia. It has an amazing number of energetic businesses-<i>[</i><i>Interruption.</i><i>]</i> I think I heard an objection; I am happy to take an intervention.</p>
	<p pid="b.182.0/11">Thetford is a natural hub. We should bear in mind that it is well connected-at least, it would be if the A11 was sorted-to Cambridge, another growing economic area. There is a bottleneck where there should be potential economic expansion. However, although the town may be struggling with the lack of decent road connections, there are plans to build 6,000 more houses over the next few years and many more jobs and businesses will be located there. As a result, what is now difficult may become impossible. There are also plans for a new academy. We have the potential to be a major area of economic growth.</p>
	<p pid="b.182.0/12">I fear that the people of Thetford are in danger of being all dressed up with nowhere to go. Despite the fact that the town is surrounded by some rather nice bits of dual carriageway, further out it peters out into a single-lane highway, which makes it difficult to transit further. Boudicca was thought to have based her operations in Thetford in ancient times. If she was to try leading her insurgency against the Roman army today, she would not get as far as Cambridge, given the state of the roads.</p>
	<p pid="b.182.0/13">The road is important not only to the people of Thetford and South West Norfolk; it is economically vital to the nation. As my hon. Friend the Member for West Suffolk pointed out, the Department for Transport says that schemes with a benefit-cost ratio of more than 2 should be considered highly favourable. The guidance also says that in most, if not all, cases, such schemes should go ahead. The fact that the scheme would return &#163;19 for every &#163;1 invested suggests that it would be of huge economic benefit.</p>
	<p pid="b.182.0/14">The figures suggest that a total investment cost of &#163;100 million would yield tax revenue of &#163;42 million and journey-time benefits of &#163;1.2 billion, and that is before we take into account the extra businesses that might locate in the area when the A11 is dualled. Many companies are currently put off by the poor transport connections, and they are put off not just in Thetford, but in Norwich and all along the A11 corridor. The current Norfolk economy is valued at &#163;16 billion. Between 2001 and 2007, growth in the Norfolk economy outstripped the rest of England by 10%. We could achieve even higher relative growth in our county because the entrepreneurs and the business acumen are there, but we need the infrastructure to support them.</p>
	<p pid="b.182.0/15">Let us consider why the benefit of such a road scheme is so large. The answer is that this piece of road is effectively a ransom strip. It is the final part that has not been dualled. Recent research from the OECD suggests that connecting up networks so that they work is most important and achieves the most value for money in infrastructure investment. It is not about having individual high-value projects; it is about ensuring that we have a network that works, and that is the missing link in the chain. Those who might question the projected high returns-there are not many of them here today-should look at the projections for the A11 Attleborough bypass, which has just been completed. One year after the project, the Department for Transport commissioned a study to consider the return and how it had compared with the projections. The return on that project was a 5.2 benefit-cost ratio, which was only 0.2 adrift from the projections. I commend the Department for Transport for the accuracy of its economic analysis. Given that such a projection is being made on a similar road, I suggest that the high benefit that we would expect from the A11 Fiveways-to-Thetford scheme will be realised.</p>
	<p pid="b.182.0/16">Like my hon. Friend the Member for West Suffolk, I have viewed the other projects in the pipeline. As far as I can tell, the A11 project came out with by far the highest benefit-cost ratio. Most other projects were in the low units and very few projects hurdled into the tens. At a meeting between the nine Norfolk MPs and the Chief Secretary to the Treasury, it was agreed that economic return would be the key criterion, and that it would apply not only within Departments but across Departments. I urge the Minister to ensure that these high-value projects are considered within not only the Department for Transport's budget but in comparison with all capital budgets across Departments. We do not want to see a high-value project stopped just because it falls under the Department for Transport, and Government capital used on a lesser-value project in another Department. In our meeting with the Chief Secretary, we established the important principle that projects with the highest economic returns should go ahead regardless of which Department they are part of.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.184.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.184.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.184.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.184.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.185.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.185.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.185.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.185.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.185.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.185.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.185.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.185.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.185.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40286" speakername="Brandon Lewis" colnum="185"  time="009:57:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0001.htm#10072737000523">
	<p pid="b.185.3/1">I apologise that I have to leave shortly before the end of this debate to attend a Select Committee meeting. I wanted to speak briefly today to show how important the A11 is beyond the corridor of constituencies that it directly runs through. I represent Great Yarmouth and, as was mentioned by my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40652" name="Matthew Hancock">the Member for West Suffolk (Matthew Hancock)</phrase>, whom I commend for securing this debate, the A11 dualling is hugely importance to us. Great Yarmouth has the opportunity to unlock economic growth that could transmute Norfolk, Suffolk and potentially Cambridge with renewable energy and offshore wind farms. They could benefit, too, from our new deep-water outer harbour.</p>
	<p pid="b.185.3/2">When I talk to businesses, whether they are in the chambers of commerce, the Federation of Small Businesses or any other commercial interest, the common comment is about infrastructure. We need high-speed broadband, but, more importantly, we need access by rail and road. The important part of that jigsaw is the dualling of the A11. It would release the opportunity for business to come through.</p>
	<p pid="b.185.3/3">We do not have a motorway in Norfolk. As my predecessors often joked-unfortunately, it is true-the nearest motorway to Great Yarmouth is in Holland. We need the A11 dualled because it releases massive potential for Norfolk, Suffolk and Cambridgeshire. I wanted to be here today to show that there is an understanding across our county that that road is a vital artery that unlocks so much economic potential. I wanted to ensure that the Minister and the Department know that we all share the belief that this is a massively important piece of investment.</p>
	<p pid="b.185.3/4">Again, I fully commend my hon. Friend the Member for West Suffolk for securing the debate. From Great Yarmouth's point of view, we should like to see the scheme go ahead. It is an important part of the jigsaw. In years to come, I and my other hon. Friends, including my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40126" name="Keith Simpson">the Member for Broadland (Mr Simpson)</phrase>, will no doubt argue that the scheme needs to link up with the dualling of the A47 and other roads, but, for now, the A11 is the key to the jigsaw.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.186.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.186.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.187.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.187.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.187.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40126" speakername="Keith Simpson" colnum="187"  time="010:03:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0001.htm#10072737000525">
	<p pid="b.187.0/1">Mr Williams, it is a pleasure to serve under your chairmanship.</p>
	<p pid="b.187.0/2">I warmly congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40652" name="Matthew Hancock">the Member for West Suffolk (Matthew Hancock)</phrase> and my other hon. Friends who are here in Westminster Hall today. We &quot;old lags&quot; from pre-2010-the &quot;Alten K&#228;mpfer&quot;, as our German cousins would call us-stand in awe of their enthusiasm and the fact that they really want to hunt as a pack on behalf of East Anglia.</p>
	<p pid="b.187.0/3">Norfolk has two main trunk roads, the A11 and the A47, neither of which are completely dualled. I have fought long and hard for the A47 to be dualled because, as my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40286" name="Brandon Lewis">the Member for Great Yarmouth (Brandon Lewis)</phrase> has said, it goes through part of my constituency. In terms of priorities, however, I think that everybody in Norfolk-whether they are business people, local councillors or Members of Parliament-has recognised that the No. 1 priority is the completion of the dualling of this nine-mile stretch of the A11. That is the message that I would give to our hon. Friend the Minister-that this dualling work is the key to unlocking a lot of the economic development that we require in the northern part of East Anglia.</p>
	<p pid="b.187.0/4">I hope that I can compare and contrast the reaction of the coalition Government with the briefing that I went to in 1997 with the newly elected MPs at that time. It was a briefing from Baroness Hayman, the Speaker in the House of Lords, who was then a junior Transport Minister. We were told then that roads were really not on the agenda; nobody was really interested in roads at that time. However, the great outcry and bellowing from the then Members for Norwich, North and Norwich, South-Dr Ian Gibson and Charles Clarke respectively-and others proved that even then we recognised that roads were absolutely crucial.</p>
	<p pid="b.187.0/5">If the Barton Mills stretch of the A11 is blocked, perhaps by roadworks or an accident, and if the A47 is blocked at the same time-I think that it happened once that both roads were blocked at the same time-there is no doubt that Norfolk will be totally gridlocked. As I say, that gridlock has actually happened. It is a ludicrous situation that that should happen to one of the largest counties in the country and it obviously has a knock-on effect for our friends and colleagues in Suffolk.</p>
	<p pid="b.187.0/6">In addition, the A11 is criss-crossed by a number of secondary roads. At times, it is almost impossible for people to get across those secondary roads and I believe that that also has a knock-on effect on the local economy.</p>
	<p pid="b.187.0/7">It seems that Norfolk and Suffolk suffer from a double negative. First, we have an inadequate road link between Norwich and London. At this point, I must gently tease my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40560" name="Elizabeth Truss">the Member for South West Norfolk (Elizabeth Truss)</phrase> and say that Boadicea was, of course, heading towards Colchester and not towards Cambridge; I think that Boadicea's old satellite navigation equipment might have been slightly out when she was heading south to our friends in Colchester for a quiet word in their ear and burning down their capital. While I am at it, I also gently point out to my hon. Friend that in Roman times it was Venta Icenorum, which was outside Norwich, that was the capital of East Anglia. Having Thetford as the capital was a later, rather vulgar occurrence under the Anglo-Saxons. <i>[</i><i>Laughter.</i><i>]</i> However, Mr Williams, I will pass that by.</p>
	<p pid="b.187.0/8">As I was saying, the crucial point is that we not only have that inadequate road link but, as my hon. Friends have already pointed out, we have had for years a very inadequate rail link, first run by Anglia and now by National Express. We have all been working to improve that link and I hope that the Minister will pass on to his colleagues who are responsible for the rail network the fact that, when the franchise comes up for renewal, we intend gripping in no uncertain terms, and we will want to interview the various companies that might be thinking of putting in a bid for that franchise.</p>
	<p pid="b.187.0/9">My hon. Friends have outlined the impact on business and economic development of dualling this stretch of road. My experience of 13 years as a Member of Parliament, in a constituency that is north of Norwich, is that there is no doubt that one of the factors-I emphasise that it is only one of the factors, although I think that it is an absolutely crucial one-in getting investment into Norfolk, either from the rest of the United Kingdom or from overseas, is the perception that our infrastructure, including the important road and rail network, is of poor quality. Even in the age of being able to order goods through the internet, when it comes to companies that ultimately rely on shifting quite heavy duty goods by road and rail, I think that Norfolk and Suffolk frequently lose out if those companies are looking for new places to go to. Therefore, it is absolutely crucial that we re-establish that infrastructure.</p>
	<p pid="b.187.0/10">The northern part of our region has always been a poor relation. Parts of Suffolk, Norfolk and Cambridgeshire are poor as measured by every index of social deprivation that one can think of. My own constituency only has small pockets of social deprivation, but in particular I am thinking of friends and colleagues in Lowestoft, Great Yarmouth, King's Lynn and Norwich, where there are major areas of social deprivation. Therefore, getting in new business is crucial.</p>
	<p pid="b.187.0/11">We should also bear it in mind that we have about 2 million to 3 million tourists coming to Norfolk and Suffolk each year to visit our beautiful counties and one of the horror stories that they invariably leave with is that of being stuck on the A11. We want to encourage tourism, so roads are crucial.</p>
	<p pid="b.187.0/12">We should also bear in mind, as hon. Members have pointed out, the importance of the right kind of capital expenditure. I know that the Minister is aware of it; my hon. Friend the Member for West Suffolk has flagged it up. I also pray in aid the support of a colleague who is unable to speak in this debate, although her fragrant presence is before me; I refer to my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40458" name="Chloe Smith">the Member for Norwich North (Miss Smith)</phrase>, who, as a Whip, may be seen but, sadly, never heard, or at least heard only in private. My hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40549" name="Richard Bacon">the Member for South Norfolk (Mr Bacon)</phrase> also sends his apologies, as he is on duty at the Public Accounts Committee. Both my hon. Friends have said that there are two types of capital expenditure. The first, once made, may cost more and more. Such expenditure is important, as it includes schools, prisons, hospitals and so on. The second, apart from the occasional need to repair potholes, produces economic growth after the initial capital investment is made. Roads are one of the most important elements of such growth. I commend my hon. Friends for making that point.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.189.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.189.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.189.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.189.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.190.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.190.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.190.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40396" speakername="George Freeman" colnum="190"  time="010:12:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0001.htm#10072737000528">
	<p pid="b.190.0/1">Thank you, Mr Williams, for the chance to contribute to this important debate, and for chairing it. I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40652" name="Matthew Hancock">the Member for West Suffolk (Matthew Hancock)</phrase> on securing it. I hope that the presence of so many of us from across East Anglia will make the point that the case has huge cross-party and cross-county support, and that the Minister will recognise that the issue has a head of steam.</p>
	<p pid="b.190.0/2">I am conscious of time restrictions, so I will focus on some specific economic benefits. I speak as someone who came to politics after a 14-year career in technology venturing, and who has spent most of his childhood and adult life on the A11 in one way or another. I have some experience of the frustrations involved when travelling within or out of Norfolk.</p>
	<p pid="b.190.0/3">I shall concentrate on three types of economic benefit: local, regional and national. On the local level, as I said in my maiden speech, my constituency is the jewel in the crown that is Norfolk. It is in the landlocked heart of Norfolk and centres on Dereham. My constituency suffers from all the problems relating to marginalisation and detachment from the mainstream economy. Average incomes in Mid Norfolk are less than &#163;20,000, and we have pockets of extreme, often hidden, rural deprivation and of pensioner poverty. Frustratingly, there are many fast-growing small businesses in the constituency that are desperate to grow and spread prosperity, but they are unable to do so because they are cut off and lie in the heart of a county that is also cut off, as Norfolk is the only county not connected to the national dual carriageway system. That serves only to strengthen the perception in Mid Norfolk that we are destined to be either a quaint rural backwater-perhaps not quaint to those struggling to pay their bills, but quaint to those passing through-or, as under the last Government, a giant housing estate, zoned for growth, and described with ugly terms such as &quot;growth point status.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.190.0/4">Neither of those models are what my constituents want. They want a richer and more organic way-dare I say, a Norfolk way, an idea that hon. Members have heard me discuss. It involves a vision of a vibrant rural economy based on jobs in villages, smaller pockets of housing, and entrepreneurship in the countryside. All of that can happen; the only thing holding it back is a lack of infrastructure and a lack of ability to get in and out of the area, whether by broadband, road or rail.</p>
	<p pid="b.190.0/5">My constituency sits between Norwich and Cambridge, two world centres for innovation in technology and enterprise. It is ironic that it languishes in rural poverty and marginalisation, given that to the west and east are growth hot spots struggling to provide capacity when it comes to housing and transport infrastructure. We do not want a handout; we want a way in and out, so that our local businesses can thrive.</p>
	<p pid="b.190.0/6">Turning to the regional argument, anybody looking at East Anglia will find it striking that although over the past 15 to 20 years it has had high growth rates, particularly in and around Cambridge and Norwich, it also contains pockets of extreme deprivation. How can Cambridge, an inflationary hot spot of new technologies, be so close to centres of deprivation in Peterborough, King's Lynn, Cromer, parts of Norwich, Yarmouth, Lowestoft and parts of the Suffolk coast? Anybody coming to the area would think that it must be prosperous. It is as though California had around its perimeter pockets of the extreme deprivation recognisable in bits of the Bronx in New York. The reason is that it is so difficult to get around. Despite having worked in Cambridge for 10 years, I know nobody there who does business with companies in Yarmouth. Companies in Yarmouth should be doing business with companies in Cambridge, but if it reliably takes more than three hours to get there, that will not happen. That key piece of dualling would unlock the regional economy.</p>
	<p pid="b.190.0/7">Additionally, on the east coast of our county there are national assets in the form of container ports, where huge amounts of national trade arrive before setting off on a journey through East Anglia to the rest of the UK economy over a non-dualled section of road-the A47, to which another hon. Member referred. It is ridiculous, from the point of view of national infrastructure and the national economy, that at the heart of the county is a bottleneck holding back so much growth.</p>
	<p pid="b.190.0/8">On the national economic picture, the Government have proposed a clear and important programme for getting the public sector deficit under control and promoting private sector growth through the &quot;open for business&quot; programme. East Anglia can lead in such growth and in rebalancing our economy geographically, as well rebalancing it away from an over-dependence on the City, housing and consumer spending. We can lead in three of the world's biggest growth sectors: biomedicine, clean technology and food science.</p>
	<p pid="b.190.0/9">In the Norwich research park, more than 2,500 scientists work in what is recognised as a global centre of excellence. A team there under Professor Jonathan Jones has just pioneered the world's first blight-resistant potato, an enormous innovation with the potential to transform food growing not just in this country but around the world. How ridiculous is it that when companies come here to inspect that technology and discuss licensing it, they may fly to Stansted and then face an impossible journey to a world-class centre of excellence over a single carriageway? That reality is holding back our potential. All we ask is for the Minister to acknowledge the potential that our economy would have if we had that section of dualling.</p>
	<p pid="b.190.0/10">The section of the A11 that is in my constituency is dualled. However, although that makes it convenient to get around Attleborough, it is not much good if our business people hit a traffic jam when they head south to interact with the national and world economy. We have all made a compelling case on this matter. I thank hon. Members for listening and very much look forward to the Minister's reply.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.191.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.191.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.192.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.192.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.192.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40560" speakername="Elizabeth Truss" colnum="192"  time="010:19:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0001.htm#10072737000530">
	<p pid="b.192.0/1">Is it not the case that, under the previous Government, the economic return of projects was not properly considered or factored into decisions that were made? That is why so many rational projects did not go ahead at a time of unprecedented Government spending. They failed to fix not only the roof, but the road, while the sun was shining.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.192.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.192.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.193.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.193.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.194.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.194.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.195.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.195.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.195.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.195.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.195.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.195.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.196.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.196.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.196.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.196.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.196.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40560" speakername="Elizabeth Truss" colnum="196"  time="010:37:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0001.htm#10072737000538">
	<p pid="b.196.1/1">Is not it the case that even Adam Smith, quite a dry economist, suggested that infrastructure spending was important for the viability of businesses? It is hardly a Keynesian case.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.196.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.196.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.197.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.197.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.198.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.198.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.198.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.198.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.198.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.198.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.199.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.199.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.199.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40308" speakername="Michael Penning" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport"  colnum="199"  time="010:48:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0001.htm#10072737000544">
	<p pid="b.199.0/1">It is a privilege to serve under your chairmanship, Mr Williams, for the first time when on the Government side of the House, under the new coalition.</p>
	<p pid="b.199.0/2">My hon. Friends are hunting in a pack today, as they do regularly in the House. I congratulate them on doing so. It is good that people stand up for their communities, come together to agree what they agree on and move forward on that. I am somewhat trapped, as hon. Members know, by the draft orders that are still in place. I must be slightly careful about what I say so that I do not prejudice any developments. The spending review is still going on and, once it is over, we will announce as soon as possible which programmes will go ahead. That is the right way to proceed-promises broken are not worth anything.</p>
	<p pid="b.199.0/3">The shadow Minister, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40274" name="William Bain">the hon. Member for Glasgow North East (Mr Bain)</phrase>, referred in his short comments to unfunded projects. We know that many of those projects would not have gone ahead unless the previous Government had borrowed even more and given us even more fiscal problems than we have at present.</p>
	<p pid="b.199.0/4">My hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40126" name="Keith Simpson">the Member for Broadland (Mr Simpson)</phrase> said that I have a speech written by my officials. Yes, I do, but, if I tried, I would not be able to read it in the next 10 minutes. Actually, because of the nature of the debate, I think that it would not be right and proper to do that. In the time that I have been in the House, I have often sat on the other side of this Chamber and watched Ministers read out, in good faith, what was put in front of them by their officials, but not respond to comments that were made during the debate.</p>
	<p pid="b.199.0/5">This debate has been excellent, and I shall try to respond to as many questions as possible. If I cannot respond directly today, I shall write to the individuals responsible on the issues that have been raised. So much has been said, and I do not want to leave anything hanging in the air. We will write, talk about the issues and work together to go forward.</p>
	<p pid="b.199.0/6">I have been lobbied by Members of this House-the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs, my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40454" name="Henry Bellingham">the hon. Member for North West Norfolk (Mr Bellingham)</phrase>, and my hon. Friends the Members for Norwich North (Miss Smith) and for South Norfolk (Mr Bacon)-who, because of other responsibilities, were not able today to make the points that they would have liked to make. However, they have made their views known to me in the Tea Room, in the Lobby and anywhere else. My broad shoulders can take the kind of lobbying that I get on roads at present.</p>
	<p pid="b.199.0/7">My hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40652" name="Matthew Hancock">the Member for West Suffolk (Matthew Hancock)</phrase> put the argument for the A11 fantastically well. I am extremely familiar with that part of the world. Until I went into the military at 16, I spent every holiday on the Norfolk Broads, and, since I left the military, I have spent at least one long weekend every year in the area. My children are grown up now-they are 19 and 21-but they will not mind my saying that they loved Center Parcs when they were young. We have sat on the A11 more times than I have had hot dinners, long before air-conditioning for cars was invented, cooked while we waited, and then took our lives in our hands as we tried to cross back on to the A11. That was before the new traffic lights were put in at Elveden for Center Parcs. I know that they caused a great deal of controversy locally when they were put in, but they have saved lives.</p>
	<p pid="b.199.0/8">On saving lives, there were 148 accidents between 2004 and 2008 on this section of the road, 12 of which were serious and two of which were fatal. Our thoughts are with the families and loved ones of the people who lost their lives on that road.</p>
	<p pid="b.199.0/9">The argument is broad. It is about congestion, but what does congestion cause? We have heard today about the economic effects on communities in Suffolk and in Norfolk. I visited many hon. Members during the general election in my shadow Health role, which I had before I moved to my new and exciting role as the Roads Minister. I talk about roads all the time to everyone-I love being the Roads Minister.</p>
	<p pid="b.199.0/10">My hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40286" name="Brandon Lewis">the Member for Great Yarmouth (Brandon Lewis)</phrase> is here today. I went to Great Yarmouth when he was the candidate. I went up the night before because I was petrified about not being there on time for an appointment at 9 o'clock the following morning-I know what that road is like. He was generous and very kind in entertaining me the night before.</p>
	<p pid="b.199.0/11">The argument is not just about business, although the business argument is there, but about other factors that we need to consider such as pollution, and the environmental effects on constituents of that kind of congestion on the road. Investment decisions have to be made not only about businesses but about homes. There is no point building many homes in a part of the world where the road infrastructure is so bad.</p>
	<p pid="b.199.0/12">I will ensure that the points raised by hon. Friends on rail infrastructure, particularly for freight, are taken to my right hon. Friend the Minister of State, Department for Transport, and that she is made aware through my officials of the comments that were made today. I visited Felixstowe only the other day, and I know that investment in rail to get freight out of that part of the country is crucial to such ports. I pay tribute to Hutchison for investing in the railways, not just there but further down the line as well.</p>
	<p pid="b.199.0/13">In many ways, the things that were said today show what is great about this country. Politicians will not give up on this-I am thinking especially about the new generation of younger politicians. I am conscious that I shall have to look at why this section of the road has not been dualled, and whether there is funding for it. Obviously, I will look at why, in 13 years, the previous Government did not do the work. They did some of the preparatory work, and they knew when they came in how important it was.</p>
	<p pid="b.199.0/14">The hon. Member for Glasgow North East said that the project was important, and asked me to give an answer today. He had 13 years to get the previous Government to do that. Actually, because they borrowed so much and did not worry about the country's fiscal situation, the funding was there.</p>
	<p pid="b.199.0/15">The Secretary of State for Transport, officials and I will look at the business case. Projects have gone ahead in the past 13 years with tiny benefit-cost ratios of 1 and 2. Projects with a business case that is a tiny percentage of that for the A11 were started and are going ahead today. All I can say is that, if I had been the Roads Minister then, such projects would not have gone ahead because there was not a local business or environmental case for them.</p>
	<p pid="b.199.0/16">I cannot change the past. I cannot say today that I will stop projects halfway through. We have said that every road project across the country that has not started will stop, and we have stopped the public inquiries. I do not want public money spent on public inquiries, projects and engineers, plans being drawn up and the public worrying even more, if there is a possibility that many of the projects will not go ahead. If we are to make progress, it is right and proper to ensure that the money is there.</p>
	<p pid="b.199.0/17">What are we looking at? The BCR for the A11 project is not 2, 3, 4 or, as alluded to earlier, 19-it is actually 20. I shall not beat about the bush. My hon. Friend the Member for West Suffolk asked me to comment on what the Secretary of State said the other day about the project having a very high BCR. I will repeat what he said: it has a very high BCR. We are waiting for the analysis to be done within my Department to confirm that it is 20. If it is not, I am fairly certain that it will be between 19 and 20, and, if that is the case, it is very high.</p>
	<p pid="b.199.0/18">Can I say today that the project will go ahead? No, I am sorry that I cannot. However, I promise to look at all the environmental, business, community and pollution advantages of each scheme, including the A11 scheme. I most certainly will do that.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.201.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.201.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.202.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.202.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.203.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.203.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.203.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.203.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.204.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.204.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.204.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.204.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.204.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40133" speakername="Andrew Griffiths" colnum="204"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0001.htm#10072737000549">
	<p pid="b.204.1/1">I thank my hon. Friend for his insightful and useful intervention. It is important to consider the effectiveness and efficiency of the court system. As he says, such a backlog of unclaimed fines is unpalatable and uncomfortable for anybody running the court system. I will mention later the impact that the proposals for cuts will have on the future efficiency and effectiveness of the courts.</p>
	<p pid="b.204.1/2">The proposal in the consultation document is that work from Burton will go to either Derby or Stafford, my hon. Friend's constituency. The consultation paper states that Stafford county court is 26 miles away by car, by the shortest route, and that the journey takes 45 minutes by car. Even by car, that is no short journey, and the task of attending court will be much more difficult for the 24% of households in my constituency-almost a quarter of my constituents-that do not have access to a car or van and rely solely on public transport. Many of those households are among the most vulnerable in the area, comprising those on a low income, the elderly and people with disabilities. A third of the wards in my constituency that are covered by the county court are among the 20% most deprived wards in the country; that gives an indication of the kind of vulnerable people who are served by the court. That deprivation brings with it related problems of poverty and increased social and family breakdown-precisely the kind of problems dealt with by the county court.</p>
	<p pid="b.204.1/3">According to the consultation paper, it takes two hours and 23 minutes to get from Burton to Stafford by bus-a journey well worth making, because Stafford is a wonderful place to visit-but the round trip takes the best part of a working day for anybody from my constituency who wishes to attend the county court in Stafford. It takes five hours to travel there and back, not taking into consideration waiting time or the time for the case to be heard. Even the train takes one hour and 40 minutes, with a change, at a cost of some &#163;14.30 for a normal adult return fare. That is simply unaffordable for many on low incomes in my constituency.</p>
	<p pid="b.204.1/4">It is important to remember that the journey times calculated are for a journey from the county court in Burton to the proposed alternative in Stafford. For the many people who do not live right next door to Burton county court, the journey will be significantly longer, because they will have to go into Burton town to get a train or bus to travel onwards.</p>
	<p pid="b.204.1/5">As for constituents who live in areas such as Marchington, which is one of the larger villages in the middle of my constituency, or Rocester, the home of JCB, no combination of trains and buses can get them to Stafford county court in time for a 9 o'clock meeting. I accept that Derby county court is more convenient for some of my constituents than Stafford, and it may seem sensible in principle to say that cases will be transferred from Burton to Derby, but many people have doubts about whether that is likely to happen in practice, and what percentage of cases will be affected. Perhaps the Minister will tell us what he envisages happening, and how many cases he proposes to send to Derby, and how many to Stafford. That would provide a clearer picture of what we may expect.</p>
	<p pid="b.204.1/6">Derby court falls outside the west Mercia and Staffordshire area court services. Derbyshire's courts are subject to a separate review, and I would like an assurance from the Minister that the two reviews will be dovetailed together and considered as a whole. What guarantees can he give that if changes to the county court service in Derbyshire lead to more work being transferred from other courts in Derbyshire to Derby county court, Burton will not fall down the pecking order, with cases ultimately being transferred to Stafford, with the associated difficulties that I outlined?</p>
	<p pid="b.204.1/7">The suggestion in the consultation paper that work could be transferred to Derby has so far done little to reassure my constituents. We must consider the consequences of the vastly increased travel times. I fear that they will result in people not bothering to attend. If witnesses are faced with five hours' travel to give evidence for 20 minutes, they will simply not turn up, and that will further frustrate the court system, delay justice and waste even more money-taxpayers' money. Surely, if the priority is to reduce inefficiency in the court system, our priority should be to tackle non-attendance in court and non-payment of fines, an issue to which my hon. Friend the Member for Stafford referred. That is a problem in the civil courts and in magistrates courts, and it should surely be at the top of our hit list. The problem will be made worse by increasing the inconvenience for witnesses who are called to give evidence.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.205.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.205.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.205.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.205.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.207.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.207.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.208.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.208.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.208.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.208.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.210.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.210.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.210.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.210.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.211.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.211.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.211.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.211.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.211.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40302" speakername="Iain Wright" colnum="211"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0001.htm#10072737000557">
	<p pid="b.211.1/1">It is a pleasure to speak under your chairmanship, Mr Sheridan. The debate is about hospital services in the north-east, but I shall focus on services in North Tees and Hartlepool, so I welcome the fact that I can see here my hon. Friends the Members for Stockton North (Alex Cunningham), for Easington (Grahame M. Morris) and for Sedgefield (Phil Wilson), as well as <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40580" name="James Wharton">the hon. Member for Stockton South (James Wharton)</phrase>. I am also pleased to see a good north-eastern Member in the form of my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40630" name="Ian Lavery">the Member for Wansbeck (Ian Lavery)</phrase>. As I said, I shall focus on North Tees and Hartlepool, but I think that <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40315" name="Guy Opperman">the hon. Member for Hexham (Guy Opperman)</phrase> will wish to catch your eye, Mr Sheridan, and widen the debate so that it has a more regional perspective. I thank him for writing me a note, asking to participate in the debate.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/2">I welcome the opportunity to discuss hospital services in North Tees and Hartlepool again. We had an important but too-short debate on <phrase class="date" code="2010-07-05">5 July</phrase>, initiated by my hon. Friend the Member for Stockton North, in which many hon. Members hoped to contribute so that they could express their concern about, and seek clarification on, the Conservative-Liberal Government's decision to cancel the &#163;464-million new hospital that was to serve the populations of Hartlepool, Stockton, Easington and Sedgefield. I am indebted to Mr Speaker, who, after discussing the matter with me, granted this longer debate so that we could discuss more thoroughly the vital issue of health care and hospital services in my area. We also had a meeting with the Minister in the week following that debate.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/3">The decision by the new Government-one of their first decisions on coming to office-to withdraw the &#163;500-million investment from our area throws the vital issue of health care and hospital services back into complete confusion and mayhem. My constituents and those of my hon. Friend the Member for Stockton North, as well as those of my hon. Friends the Members for Sedgefield and for Easington, are worth much more than that and deserve much better.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/4">It is especially important that there should be excellent health care in Hartlepool and the surrounding areas because the people whom I represent experience some of the worst health inequalities in the country. Much of that is due to our legacy as a former heavy manufacturing town, with industrial diseases and injuries. Much of it is due to the deindustrialisation of the 1980s and '90s, and the failures of Government at that time to put in place an alternative economic model. Economic inactivity and health inequality go hand in hand, and we have in the past 30 years suffered from high levels of deprivation. Much of the health inequality has to do with poor and inadequate investment in primary health care in Hartlepool in the last half-century. For example, we have had a much lower ratio of GPs per head of population than we should have had for much of the time that we have had an NHS. As a result, we have had to rely on hospitals, whereas other areas may have had suitably high levels of GPs and primary health facilities.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/5">Frankly, much of the inequality has to do with people's lifestyles. One third of the population of Hartlepool smoke, as opposed to 24% across England. Some wards in Hartlepool have smoking rates of 40% to 50%. The rate for smoking in pregnancy is way above the national average. The proportion of women who breastfeed their baby in Hartlepool is half what it is across the country. Hartlepool is above the national average for the proportion of people who binge-drink, although I would like to point out that it is below the average for the Teesside area as a whole. Rates of early death from heart disease, strokes and cancer are significantly worse in Hartlepool than the national average, as is life expectancy. Although the gap in life expectancy between Hartlepool and the rest of the country has narrowed in the past decade, it remains the case that a man in Stranton ward has a life expectancy some 11 years shorter than that of a similar man in a more affluent area.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/6">All that history-the lifestyles and the poor health outcomes-means that it is vital that we have the best possible health service for my constituents. Although progress has been made, it will take more sustained help and support, and reconfiguration of services, to narrow the gap still further. We have seen more investment in Hartlepool health in the past 10 years-actually, we have seen more investment in primary health facilities in the past five years than in the previous half-century-but the people of Hartlepool still feel battered and bruised when it comes to the future of hospital services.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/7">Since the 1990s, there has been huge uncertainty about what shape the health services will take, and where they will be located. There has been review after review after review-the Tees services review, the Darzi review, the report from the independent reconfiguration panel-and now there is the decision to scrap the hospital at Wynyard. In that time, other areas have seen a reconfiguration of hospital services; in our neighbouring area south of the Tees, one of the best hospitals in Europe-the James Cook University hospital-has been built. Those of us north of the Tees deserve something similar.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/8">While the uncertainty has continued for my area, the hard-working staff in our local NHS have not been provided with the clear vision and leadership needed. That has compromised their ability to provide world-class health care for our area. The uncertainty has led to a loss of morale and subsequent difficulties in recruitment and retention. The trade union Unison is to be commended in my area for proudly standing up for the people who work in hospitals, but the Government's decision, together with other reforms that they propose, is placing strain on local services and threatening jobs. We need certainty and continuing investment, and the Government, in one of their first acts in office, have provided neither.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/9">It is fair to say that many people in my area might consider the Government's decision to scrap the proposed new hospital to be appropriate-indeed, welcome-and might think that with a hospital not being built in Wynyard, the University hospital of Hartlepool will stay open, and that services will migrate back to it. It surely defies common sense, as I have been told by some constituents, that a town such as Hartlepool, with a population of 90,000, cannot have a fully functioning district general hospital, with all the modern services that hospitals should provide. It is argued that the decision to scrap the proposed new hospital at Wynyard presents an opportunity to provide that, and will mean that the University hospital of Hartlepool will have a secure future.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/10">That is an understandable stance, based on affection for the great service that Hartlepool hospital has provided down the years. The big events of life have occurred in the hospital for many thousands of Hartlepudlians, including me. I am thinking of the births of my four children, the death of my nana and the saving of my son Benjamin's life twice-first when he contracted meningitis at the age of eight, and then at the age of 12, when he suffered a stroke. The dedication of people working in that hospital is second to none, and my family are very much testimony to that.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/11">However, I fear that we will not see the return of hospital services to Hartlepool, and that we will have the worst of all possible worlds-hospital services will move away from Hartlepool and become more inaccessible to the people whom I serve, and we will not have a world-class facility in the borough of Hartlepool to replace them.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/12">I fully accept and embrace the changes in health services. I welcome the technological advances that mean that whereas previously certain medical procedures required extensive stays in district general hospitals, those procedures can now be done safely and more cheaply in a local setting. Just a few years ago, high-quality internet use, for example, could be provided only by bulky and costly desktop computers; now, people can have internet access in the palm of their hand. In the same way, such advances are pushing more and more medical and surgical procedures into the community, into GPs' surgeries and even into people's homes. I welcome that.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/13">We are certainly seeing that trend in Hartlepool. The Momentum programme is reconfiguring more and more services that were once the preserve of the hospital, putting them into the local clinic, closer to people. I met a man in Hartlepool recently who had had his toes amputated. Just a few years ago, that would have required an operation in a hospital and a lengthy stay there for recovery and recuperation. The man I met had had the procedure carried out in the operating theatre of his GP clinic in the Headland surgery, and he was home in a matter of hours. We shall see much more of that.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/14">The newly opened One Life Hartlepool centre, built as part of the Momentum programme, is equipped to carry out minor skeletal surgery and will do orthodontic work that was previously the preserve of hospitals. GP surgeries increasingly take blood samples on-site rather than requiring the patient to attend hospital. Again, that is welcome.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/15">However, we also have to admit that increases in medical specialisation, coupled with a wider and more miraculous range of things that can now be achieved through science and surgery, mean that many surgical procedures are now reserved for doctors and nurses with very specialised skills, as opposed to those in general medicine and surgery.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/16">In preparing for this debate, I have been in contact with the Royal College of Surgeons of England, and I am grateful for its help. As part of its best clinical practice, for acute general hospitals that provide the full range of facilities, specialist staff and expertise for elective and emergency medical and surgical care, the college recommends a preferred catchment population size of between 450,000 and 500,000 people. However, the college estimates that hospitals of that size account for fewer than 10% of acute hospitals in England, and states that there is unlikely to be a significant shift to that size of hospital in the short to medium term. As it is, the majority of acute hospitals have, and are likely to continue to have, catchment populations of about 300,000. That is significantly more than the population of my constituency.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/17">It is essential that MPs and all representatives listen to the professional advice of eminent surgeons. I do not intend to play fast and loose with patient safety and clinical excellence. As a politician, I realise that I do not know better than doctors, and I want the best possible health care for my constituents. I will fight to the last to achieve the best possible services for Hartlepool. They have to be safe and medically advisable, but if something is seen to be clinically essential by surgeons, it is right that my hon. Friends and I should listen. It is also right that Ministers should listen to eminent surgical and clinical advice, and I suggest that the cancellation of the proposed new hospital means that they did not. I hope that the Minister will do so today.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/18">I believe that Lord Darzi's proposals of 2005, under which Hartlepool hospital was to become a centre of excellence for women's and children's services, and the University hospital of North Tees was to become a centre of excellence for emergency surgery, were workable and feasible. Alas, it was not to be, as other parts of Teesside felt that they could not live with that. Although I thought that the subsequent independent reconfiguration panel review was unnecessary, I respect its decision, the quality of its evidence and its professionalism. I cannot argue with the overpowering weight of clinical advice on the matter.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/19">In the IRP report, paragraph 4.8.5, entitled &quot;Clinical views-the need for change&quot;, stated:</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/20" class="indent">&quot;There was a common view across all staff that no change is not an option. Staff are keen to work with the Trust management and to embrace clinically-driven change&quot;-</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/21">&quot;clinically-driven change&quot; is a hugely important phrase-</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/22" class="indent">&quot;that secures the best outcome for patients, staff and the Trust...There was widespread support for a new modern hospital, north of the Tees, concentrating on providing high quality hospital services that cannot be more appropriately provided in local communities&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/23">The IRP also stated:</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/24" class="indent">&quot;This is not simply a matter of recruiting additional staff. Specialist skills can only be acquired and maintained with sufficient 'throughput' of cases. Since safety standards can only be expected to rise in the future, the current model of service provision is unsustainable.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/25">In the concluding remarks in the report, the chair of the IRP-a GP and the chair of an acute NHS Trust in Nottingham-stated in his personal recollections that:</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/26" class="indent">&quot;The clinicians were virtually unanimous in their desire to work on one site. This was not based on their personal convenience but on clinical evidence and a belief that a real and sustainable improvement in patient care would take place.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/27">I want the best possible services for Hartlepool. The ideal situation if I lived in Utopia would be a hospital in the very centre of Hartlepool that provided the widest possible range of specialisms. In the real world, however, I realise that the desire to see a hospital serving the people of Hartlepool, Stockton, Easington and Sedgefield was driven by clinicians, based on clinical evidence and fuelled by a belief that patient outcomes would improve and health inequalities diminish as a result.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/28">To be fair, I think that the present Government recognise that, too. In a recent answer to my written parliamentary question on whether he would implement the recommendations of the Darzi review, the Minister replied:</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/29" class="indent">&quot;The recommendations of the Darzi review of acute health services north of the River Tees were superseded by the advice provided by the Independent Reconfiguration Panel to the then Secretary of State for Health in December 2006. This advice formed the basis of the 'Momentum: Pathways to Healthcare programme' which was developed by the local national health service to provide a new health care system for the people of Stockton, Hartlepool, Easington and Sedgefield.&quot;-[<phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2010-06-28.407"><i>Official Report</i>, 28 June 2010; Vol. 512, c. 407W</phrase>.]</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/30">From that response, it seems that the Minister accepts that clinical pressures were driving and pushing this matter.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/31">In that context, will the Minister confirm that the proposed new hospital entirely meets the criteria set out in a letter of <phrase class="date" code="2010-05-20">20 May</phrase> from the NHS chief executive to Monitor-criteria that are about ensuring that all service changes are led by clinicians and patients, not driven from the top down? Taking that point further, will the Minister explain how the Secretary of State reconciles his policy of clinical-led decisions with the pledge made during the general election campaign that Hartlepool hospital would not close if a Conservative Government were elected and a Tory MP returned for the seat of Hartlepool? What clinical evidence was there to back that pledge? Is that not an example of top-down meddling by politicians, regardless of clinical evidence? Is it now Government policy for the configuration of health services to be contingent on voting behaviour, rather than clinical decisions?</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/32">Will the Minister provide further clarity about his written answer to me, to which I referred a moment ago, on whether Darzi should be implemented? If he believes that Hartlepool hospital should remain open, will he provide additional support and resources to ensure that it can remain open, and that services will return to it? However, this is not just about money; it is about the way in which services are provided and how they are linked.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/33">Since the Adjournment debate of <phrase class="date" code="2010-07-05">5 July</phrase>, and our subsequent meeting with the Minister, the NHS White Paper has been published. It rightly pledges to put patients at the heart of services and decisions regarding services. I welcome that. The phrase used in the White Paper is</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/34" class="indent">&quot;nothing about me without me&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/35">The White Paper also asks for an enhanced local voice; again, that is welcome. However, I would be interested to hear the Minister's view on what should happen if there is a stark difference between what the professionals want and what the public want-if surgeons and clinical teams say that specialism requires a concentration of services on a central site, but local communities say, as they often do, that they like the status quo and that change is unwelcome? How does the Minister envisage such tension being resolved, given that such views are often polar opposites?</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/36">The Minister may say that the independent NHS board will be important when it comes to resolving tensions or contradictions, and that its decisions will be based on clinical views and free from political interference. That would be welcome, but does that mean that the NHS commissioning board will have responsibility for resource allocation? The White Paper certainly suggests so, saying that the board will</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/37" class="indent">&quot;allocate and account for NHS resources.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/38">In that context, I think that &quot;resources&quot; means revenue resources, but does it also mean capital resources? What would happen if the NHS commissioning board recommended that, for hospital services north of the Tees, it was clinically essential that the recommendations of the independent reconfiguration panel were implemented? Would the board's decisions overrule ministerial priorities?</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/39">The Minister may respond along the lines that the independent NHS board will take decisions out of the hands of politicians, but the White Paper contradicts that. It states on page 33 that</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/40" class="indent">&quot;The Secretary of State will have a statutory role as arbiter of last resort in disputes that arise between NHS commissioners and local authorities, for example in relation to major service changes.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/41">In other words, the reconfiguration of hospital services, which can cause bitterness and fear in many communities, as it has in mine, can still be decided by the Secretary of State. That does not take politics out of changes to hospital services at all.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/42">I ask the Minister to address a number of other points. Does he accept that the manner in which the project was assessed within Whitehall-in both the Department of Health and the Treasury-under the Labour Government was entirely in accordance with appropriate procedures? Does he accept that the project was appraised by officials in an entirely appropriate and rigorous manner, and that that was not done a couple of weeks before the general election, but had been planned and prepared for several years? Hartlepool borough council has written to the Secretary of State on the matter. The letter was signed by the chairman of the council and the leaders of the Labour, Conservative and Liberal Democrat groups; they have yet to receive a response, so I would be grateful if the Minister could expand on what he said in the earlier debate.</p>
	<p pid="b.211.1/43">Will the Minister publish the revised criteria and assessment considerations on which the project failed, so that we can see what is to be done to address the matter? Why are Hartlepool and North Tees rejected, when Liverpool and Epsom are not?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.216.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.216.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.216.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.216.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.217.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.217.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.218.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.218.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.219.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.219.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.220.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.220.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.220.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.220.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.220.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.220.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.220.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.220.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.220.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.220.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.220.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40222" speakername="Grahame Morris" colnum="220"  time="014:56:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0001.htm#10072737000567">
	<p pid="b.220.4/1">There seems to be some confusion here with the figures. However, in my mind, perhaps in the minds of other Labour Members and certainly in the minds of the good people of Easington, it only shows what a bad decision it was. I do not believe that it is being made for the stated financial reasons, but instead seems to form part of some type of idelologically-based course of action taken by the coalition Government.</p>
	<p pid="b.220.4/2">It is clear now that the saving of &#163;464 million-the figure that was widely quoted to the media at the time of the hospital's cancellation-is completely misleading. At some point, I hope that we will also get to the bottom of the true costs to the taxpayer of cancelling and pulling the plug on this new hospital development, which, as my hon. Friend the Member for Hartlepool has indicated, has been in the planning since 2005.</p>
	<p pid="b.220.4/3">On <phrase class="date" code="2010-05-02">2 May 2010</phrase>, in an interview with Andrew Marr, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40665" name="David Cameron">the right hon. Member for Witney (Mr Cameron)</phrase> talked passionately about how a responsible society should protect the vulnerable. This is what he said:</p>
	<p pid="b.220.4/4" class="indent">&quot;The test of a good society is you look after the elderly, the frail, the vulnerable, the poorest in our society. And that test is even more important in difficult times, when difficult decisions have to be taken, than it is in better times.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="b.220.4/5">I am sure that many of my colleagues knew at the time, as I did, that that statement lacked substance.</p>
	<p pid="b.220.4/6">Easington is one of the most deprived areas in the United Kingdom. Health inequalities still play a large role in Easington; there is shorter life expectancy and poorer quality of life. Life expectancy in Easington is a full two years lower than the national average. The proposed new hospital was part of a clinically-led strategic reorganisation of health provision for one of the poorest areas in Britain, which would have gone some way to tackling some of the worst health outcomes in the country.</p>
	<p pid="b.220.4/7">The latest figures that I have been able to access are the 2007 statistics on standardised mortality rates per 100,000 population. They show clearly that death from illness that is amenable to health care-that is, deaths that would have been preventable with health interventions-accounted for 256 deaths per 100,000 of the population in the Easington local authority area, compared to an average of only 195 across the rest of England and Wales. For all causes, the figure for Easington is 713, compared to 582 for England and Wales. For coronary heart disease, the figure is 112 per 100,000 in Easington compared to 90 per 100,000 across the rest of England and Wales. For cancer, the figure for Easington is 219 per 100,000 compared to 175 nationally.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.221.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.221.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.221.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.221.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.221.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.221.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.221.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.221.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.222.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.222.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.222.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.222.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.222.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.222.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.222.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.222.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.222.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.222.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.222.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.222.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.223.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.223.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.223.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40521" speakername="Phil Wilson" colnum="223"  time="015:09:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0002.htm#10072737000578">
	<p pid="b.223.0/1">That is absolutely right. Over the past 13 years, the number of apprenticeships in the region has gone up astronomically. In 1997, in my constituency, there were fewer than 30 apprenticeships, but there are more than 700 today. Obviously, anything that curtails the growth of apprenticeships in the future should be frowned on.</p>
	<p pid="b.223.0/2">As far as other jobs are concerned, the hospital would be a catalyst for inward investment and private sector investment. Wynyard Park Ltd worked closely with the hospital, local universities and further education colleges because it realised that high-value medical and other research jobs would come to the area. The company estimated that 12,500 jobs would be created on top of the 3,000 jobs that the hospital would create. There would be 12,500 private sector jobs in the area on the back of the hospital development-just think of the Government's income tax and national insurance take and all the other benefits that they would pick up on the basis of that growth in the local economy. Public sector investment would kick-start growth in the private sector.</p>
	<p pid="b.223.0/3">The hospital would also have become an anchor tenant-a tenant that attracted a lot of other investment to Wynyard. In addition, it would have brought greater investment in infrastructure; the roads and transport networks would have improved, which would have brought more businesses to the park. This is not just about the hospital, as great as that would be. My family and I have used the North Tees and Hartlepool hospitals, and they are great hospitals, but it is time to replace them and to have a new hospital. The credible case put by the new hospital's designers was that the development would be not only a hospital, but a catalyst for growth in the private sector economy in the south Durham and Tees valley area. That case has been completely ignored.</p>
	<p pid="b.223.0/4">I really get annoyed when people try to say that the project was worked out on the back of a fag packet a few weeks before the general election. I have been attending meetings on the issue since I was elected in 2007, and meetings were going on before then. We need the development to happen.</p>
	<p pid="b.223.0/5">The Government's proposals prove what the Prime Minister said during the election campaign when he pointed out that the north-east would feel the brunt of the cuts. He was right to say that we rely too much on public sector jobs, so the Government should give us the opportunity to change that, but that opportunity was taken away from us when the hospital programme was cancelled.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.223.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.223.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.223.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40315" speakername="Guy Opperman" colnum="223"  time="015:09:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0002.htm#10072737000579">
	<p pid="b.223.1/1">The hon. Gentleman asserts that the area should be given the opportunity to address the lack of private sector jobs, but that would not be done by spending more public sector money. We cannot address the deficit on every single occasion by creating private sector jobs through public sector spending, which is surely the basis of the hon. Gentleman's hospital argument.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.224.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.224.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.224.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.224.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.224.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.224.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.224.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40521" speakername="Phil Wilson" colnum="224"  time="015:09:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0002.htm#10072737000582">
	<p pid="b.224.2/1">No, several other Members want to get in on the debate.</p>
	<p pid="b.224.2/2">Figures have been bandied about, such as the &#163;5 billion and the &#163;11,000 difference, which was actually &#163;11 million-the Minister corrected that error, and I noticed it, too, and went up to correct it. That &#163;11 million, over 35 years, means the difference between a new hospital and a hospital that is falling down. Surely we could have found that money somewhere to help to maintain the hospital.</p>
	<p pid="b.224.2/3">I want to end with a question to the Minister. Three or four weeks ago, we brought down the foundation trust's chief executive and the chair for a meeting, and I was pleased that the Minister could meet us. I took away from that meeting the view that the Department would look again at the development if the trust could come up with a credible scheme or initiative to get money from the private sector. If all the figures stacked up, would the Department underwrite such a proposal? We are talking about a foundation hospital. Are we saying that foundation hospitals will be around for ever? Things might change-Governments might change, policy might change-but the hospital must still be funded. Are the Government prepared to underwrite any financial arrangements with the banks and the private sector?</p>
	<p pid="b.224.2/4">On that point, I will sit down and listen to what other Members have to say. The proposed hospital is a missed opportunity for growth in not only the public sector, but the private sector in the region.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.224.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.224.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.224.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40579" speakername="Alex Cunningham" colnum="224"  time="015:19:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0002.htm#10072737000583">
	<p pid="b.224.3/1">I am grateful to have another opportunity to discuss the need for a 21st century hospital to meet the needs of my constituents and those throughout the north-east; however, I shall be briefer than I was the last time I spoke on the matter.</p>
	<p pid="b.224.3/2">It was good to hear my hon. Friends talk about specific issues affecting the health of people in their constituencies, and to hear my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40521" name="Phil Wilson">the Member for Sedgefield (Phil Wilson)</phrase> outline the benefits that the hospital could bring over and above health. I want to start with an outline of the health picture in the borough of Stockton-on-Tees. Things have improved in recent years, but much still needs to be done. According to the NHS health profile for 2010, which has just dropped through my letter box, in Stockton-on-Tees, life expectancy for men living in the most deprived areas is still nearly 12 years less than for men living in the least deprived areas. In relation to early deaths from heart disease and stroke, survival rates have steadily improved over the years: from 160 deaths per 100,000 people in 1998 to about 80 per 100,000 people in 2007. That is half the number of deaths and there is much credit to our hospitals' care and to the local PCTs and health programmes. However, we are still well behind the England average in our progress in relation to early deaths from heart disease, stroke and cancer.</p>
	<p pid="b.224.3/3">What do the decisions made by the coalition Government mean for the north-east and people's health? A new hospital has been scrapped. That is a huge blow, and it is still not clear why our hospital was chosen, while others have been given the go-ahead. We have had years of planning, as other hon. Members described, and that was discussed in detail in my Adjournment debate on <phrase class="date" code="2010-07-05">5 July</phrase>. I accept that the decision has now been made, but it is not clear what will happen. There is also uncertainty for patients in the scrapping of Labour's promises. The coalition have scrapped the 18-week waiting list target and the 48-hour GP access target and downgraded the four-hour accident and emergency waiting time target.</p>
	<p pid="b.224.3/4">There is also great uncertainty for people who work in the NHS locally, who will commission services in the future. I met Dr John Canning, a member of the Cleveland local medical committee, and discussed, among other things, the re-organisation of the NHS and in particular GP commissioning. We await detailed plans, but I am dismayed that the Government, who in opposition promised, &quot;no more pointless reorganisations&quot; are presiding over the biggest structural overhaul of the NHS in 60 years. The NHS needs stability; it does not need to be forced to deal with a huge and unnecessary politically-motivated structural upheaval at a time of significant financial pressure on public services.</p>
	<p pid="b.224.3/5">The new GP commissioners will be responsible for ensuring that their patients get the best possible health care in the best possible facilities. I just wonder how they will make those decisions. Perhaps they will send patients many miles to a new hospital with all the services required by the patient close together and under one roof. Alternatively, will they utilise the services at their local hospital, where the care might be very good but the facilities could be less than first class? Some patients make a positive choice to travel to neighbouring hospitals, which have the most modern and up-to-date facilities, and could be expected increasingly to shun local services because they believe, rightly or wrongly, that in that way they will get better treatment.</p>
	<p pid="b.224.3/6">The strategy outlined by the foundation trust remains the right one. When Stockton-on-Tees borough council met, every member in the chamber voted to ask the Minister to review the decision; that included the Conservative council leader. So can we look forward to a new hospital? The answer could still be yes if it is the true and honest will of the Government. Detailed work on developing a private finance initiative to meet the costs of the new hospital is well under way, but there remains great uncertainty about whether there will be Government support. If the foundation trust completes the work and satisfies Monitor, its financial regulator, that it has a robust project that will work, will the Department of Health approve it and ensure that the people of my constituency and the surrounding ones get the hospital they need and deserve?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.225.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.225.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.226.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.226.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.226.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.226.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.226.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.226.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.227.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.227.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.227.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.227.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.227.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.227.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.227.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40345" speakername="Diana Johnson" colnum="227"  time="015:24:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0002.htm#10072737000590">
	<p pid="b.227.2/1">My hon. Friend makes an important point about the cost over 35 years.</p>
	<p pid="b.227.2/2">My hon. Friend the Member for Stockton North, who I understand is a former non-executive director of the North Tees and Hartlepool NHS Foundation Trust, spoke clearly about the need for a new hospital. I know that he also tabled early-day motion 273, which attracted a great deal of support, to request a review of the coalition decision about the hospital. He, too, made an important case about health inequalities and why the hospital is needed. He also pointed out that structural upheaval in the NHS at a time when we are facing such financial problems is a recipe for chaos. What is the future for the people represented by him and our hon. Friends? Again, I look to the Minister to explain the coalition Government's thinking about what will happen to the needs of communities in the north-east.</p>
	<p pid="b.227.2/3">I do not wish to rehearse the history of this &#163;464 million hospital project-my right hon. Friend the former Secretary of State made it clear that it was a top priority for the NHS, and agreed in March this year that it should go ahead-but it had been in planning for a long time. It was not just signed off close to a general election. As we have heard, the coalition Government decided to cancel the hospital project within the first few weeks after taking up their position in Government. It is clear that the Treasury and other Departments reviewed every significant spending decision made between <phrase class="date" code="2010-01-01">1 January</phrase> and the general election on <phrase class="date" code="2010-05-06">6 May</phrase>. The proposal for the new hospital scheme, which received Government approval only in March, was considered properly during that review, but there are questions about why that particular hospital project was cancelled and others were allowed to proceed when my right hon. Friend had made it clear that the hospital was a top priority for the NHS.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.228.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.228.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.228.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.228.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.228.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.228.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.228.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.228.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.229.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.229.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.229.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40161" speakername="Simon Burns" speakeroffice="The Minister of State, Department of Health"  colnum="229"  time="015:37:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0002.htm#10072737000595">
	<p pid="b.229.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40302" name="Iain Wright">the hon. Member for Hartlepool (Mr Wright)</phrase> on securing this debate. As he and his hon. Friends will know-as the shadow Minister rightly said, they are here in force-we have had one, more brief, debate on this subject, and I have had the pleasure of welcoming most of the Opposition Members present to a meeting at my Department, where we had a useful exchange of views.</p>
	<p pid="b.229.0/2">Before I address the main thrust of most of the contributions, which is North Tees and Hartlepool, I will give a brief overview of the health situation in the north-east and will refer to some of the comments made by my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40315" name="Guy Opperman">the Member for Hexham (Guy Opperman)</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="b.229.0/3">Earlier this month, as hon. Members know, we published our vision for the national health service in the White Paper, &quot;Equity and excellence: Liberating the NHS&quot;, which signals the beginning of the most profound reform in the NHS's 62-year history. By taking power away from Ministers and civil servants in Whitehall and handing it to patients and clinicians, we shall transform the health service from the ground up.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.229.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.229.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.229.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.229.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.229.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.229.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.229.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.229.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.230.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.230.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.230.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.230.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.230.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.230.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.230.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.230.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.230.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40161" speakername="Simon Burns" colnum="230"  time="015:37:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0002.htm#10072737000603">
	<p pid="b.230.3/1">Because, as I will again explain-this is similar to what I said on <phrase class="date" code="2010-07-05">5 July</phrase>-there were a range of criteria determined and, as the hon. Gentleman is aware, we took the decision on the hospital on the grounds of affordability and the foundation trust status of the hospital. If he will bear with me, I will explain that again, so that even if he does not accept the decision, he will, I hope, come to understand the reasoning behind it.</p>
	<p pid="b.230.3/2">On <phrase class="date" code="2010-06-17">17 June</phrase>, the Chief Secretary to the Treasury, my right hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40331" name="Danny Alexander">the Member for Inverness, Nairn, Badenoch and Strathspey (Danny Alexander)</phrase>, announced to the House the decisions made following the Government's review of spending commitments. The review cancelled 12 projects, including the proposed new hospital at North Tees and Hartlepool.</p>
	<p pid="b.230.3/3">The aim of granting foundation trust status is to give bodies, such as the trust in the area represented by the hon. Member for Hartlepool, greater financial independence. As well as being able to keep any internally generated resources, foundation trusts also have greater freedom to borrow from either the public or the private sector. As the proposals required an allocation of public dividend capital from the Department of Health of more than &#163;400 million, they were not consistent with that financial independence. Treasury and Department of Health Ministers, including me, decided that, overall, those factors-affordability within the changed economic climate and the hospital's foundation trust status-weighed against the &#163;458-million scheme for North Tees and Hartlepool more than they did against the other three schemes at Liverpool, Epsom and St Helier, and the Royal National Orthopaedic hospital. For those reasons, the Government withdrew support for the scheme.</p>
	<p pid="b.230.3/4">Following our previous debate, I was pleased to meet, on <phrase class="date" code="2010-07-08">8 July</phrase>, Paul Garvin-the chair and non-executive director of North Tees and Hartlepool NHS Foundation Trust-together with the hon. Member for Hartlepool and many of his hon. Friends now present. At that meeting, we discussed the possibility of the trust putting forward a new proposal under the private finance initiative. As I have said repeatedly, I cannot in any way give any guarantees that such a scheme would, or would not, be approved. Like any proposal, it would have to be considered on its merits and in light of the economic climate at the time it was put forward for consideration and possible approval.</p>
	<p pid="b.230.3/5">However, the advice I would offer the foundation trust is the same advice I would offer any organisation putting forward such a proposal. Any scheme must reflect the changed realities of the national health service, as set out in the White Paper. It would clearly have to demonstrate that it passed the four tests for reconfigurations set out by my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State. That is, it has to have the support of GP commissioners; arrangements for public and patient engagement, including with local authorities, must be strengthened; there must be clear clinical evidence underpinning any proposal; and it must develop and support patient choice.</p>
	<p pid="b.230.3/6">The economic and policy circumstances have changed since the original proposals were put forward. It would be advisable for the foundation trust to make sure that any revised proposals reflect those changes, and can demonstrate that they have the full support of GPs, the public and the local authority. Any new proposal must be realistic, affordable and provide value for money.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.231.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.231.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.232.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.232.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.232.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.232.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.232.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.232.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.232.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40161" speakername="Simon Burns" colnum="232"  time="015:37:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0002.htm#10072737000607">
	<p pid="b.232.2/1">The hon. Gentleman must wait a minute, because I have only 10 minutes in which to answer the questions that the hon. Member for Hartlepool asked. The fact is that the decision was taken on affordability and on the fact that the trust was a foundation trust and so was free to seek other means by which to finance the project, rather than going to the Department for capital funding. Those decisions were taken because of the tough economic situation we inherited after <phrase class="date" code="2010-05-06">6 May</phrase> and the massive deficit the country was left with. My right hon. Friend the Chancellor of the Exchequer rightly believes that that the No. 1 priority for sorting out the economy is to get rid of the deficit as quickly as possible. Regrettably, tough decisions have to be taken in the light of the dire economic situation.</p>
	<p pid="b.232.2/2">I must tell the hon. Members for Hartlepool, and for Kingston upon Hull North (Diana R. Johnson), in the nicest terms possible, that it was their party's mismanagement of the economy and deficit that put us in the current situation. We will have to take tough decisions if we are to have a buoyant, vibrant economy again. <i>[</i><i>Interruption.</i><i>]</i> If I might continue-<i>[Interruption.]</i></p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.232.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.232.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.232.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.232.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.232.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40161" speakername="Simon Burns" colnum="232"  time="015:37:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0002.htm#10072737000609">
	<p pid="b.232.4/1">I will now answer some of the Opposition Members' questions. The hon. Member for Hartlepool asked whether there was an optimum population size for a hospital. I have consulted my officials, who tell me that they are unaware of whether there is an official optimum population size for hospitals, so I will look into the matter and write to him with a satisfactory answer as soon as possible, giving him any information we have.</p>
	<p pid="b.232.4/2">I have already explained, including on 5 and <phrase class="date" code="2010-07-08">8 July</phrase>, the decision that governed the withdrawal of approval for the hospital. On the hon. Gentleman's question about the future of Hartlepool hospital, there are currently no plans to close it, and that will remain the case unless the strategic health authority and the PCT propose closure. There are no such proposals at present, as far as I am aware.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.232.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.232.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.233.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.233.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.233.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40161" speakername="Simon Burns" colnum="233"  time="015:37:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0002.htm#10072737000611">
	<p pid="b.233.0/1">It is perfectly reasonable for the hon. Gentleman to express concern and an interest in finding out what would happen. The answer is that that will depend on a combination of factors, including the national commissioning board that will be created, the GP commissioners and the decision of the local health community. If a local health community put forward any proposals to reconfigure health patterns in its area, it would have to go through all the procedures that are currently in place, and there will also be the changes that my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State will put in place to strengthen the community's input into any proposed reconfiguration. The views and support of clinicians and GPs will be sought, and the focus will be on improving outcomes and affordability, and including the views of local populations.</p>
	<p pid="b.233.0/2">The hon. Gentleman will know from reading the White Paper and the five related documents that have so far been published, which flesh out the details, that local authorities will have a greatly enhanced role in the provision of health services and the maintenance of health care standards in the local community, and will not be restricted solely to their current role in public health.</p>
	<p pid="b.233.0/3">The hon. Gentleman asked whether the Government will implement the recommendations of the Darzi review on acute health services north of the River Tees. The recommendations of that review were superseded by advice provided by the independent reconfiguration panel to the then Secretary of State for Health in December 2006. That advice formed the basis of the &quot;Momentum: Pathways to Healthcare&quot; programme, which was developed by the local national health service to provide a new health care system for the people of Stockton, Hartlepool, Easington and Sedgefield. We understand that NHS Hartlepool and NHS Stockton-on-Tees will continue to work closely with North Tees and Hartlepool NHS Foundation Trust on delivering the wider Momentum programme, and will be discussing the options available with the trust. I hope that that goes some way towards satisfying the hon. Gentleman.</p>
	<p pid="b.233.0/4">The hon. Member for Kingston upon Hull North mentioned the generality of the provision of health care, and new health care facilities, in the region, and I can reassure her by mentioning a number of initiatives that have taken place in the Stockton-on-Tees area in recent years.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.233.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.233.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.233.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.233.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.233.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40161" speakername="Simon Burns" colnum="233"  time="015:37:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0002.htm#10072737000613">
	<p pid="b.233.2/1">Yes, in recent years-there is no point in the hon. Lady sitting there and saying that because, to be frank, anyone who takes a sensible approach to such matters will not try to score cheap party political points. I recognise that for the past 13 years we have had not a Conservative, but a Labour, Government, and I am mature enough and comfortable enough within myself to recognise that during those years advances in health care were made. I am not one of those narrow politicians who say that, because there was not a Tory Government, everything was awful, or that everything done by a Tory Government is wonderful; it is a mixture of the two. One has to be mature enough to recognise that, as I do. The initiatives I will refer to took place in the past few years, so they were under a Labour Government.</p>
	<p pid="b.233.2/2">As the hon. Lady will know, 26 of the 46 Momentum business service change projects are under way as part of the &quot;Momentum: Pathway to Healthcare&quot; programme. They consist of detailed service reviews, a revised pathway based on a map of medicine, a value impact assessment and a service implementation plan. Examples of pathways reviewed to date include those on diabetes, respirology, cardiology and haematology. There are also cross-cutting business service change projects under way in the areas of work force and education, IT, and communications and engagement. There is also an integrated care centre at Hartlepool, with which the hon. Member for Hartlepool will be familiar, and an integrated care centre at Billingham, which I expect <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40579" name="Alex Cunningham">the hon. Member for Stockton North (Alex Cunningham)</phrase> and my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40580" name="James Wharton">the Member for Stockton South (James Wharton)</phrase> will know.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.234.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.234.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.234.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.234.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.234.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.234.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.234.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.234.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.234.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40161" speakername="Simon Burns" colnum="234"  time="015:37:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0002.htm#10072737000617">
	<p pid="b.234.3/1">I thank the hon. Lady for giving me the opportunity once again to tell her that those are all contained in the vision outlined by my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State in the White Paper that was published last week. It is a vision that puts patients at the heart of health care, so that they can have the best health care of the highest quality. It is based on the premise that there should be a local, bottom-up system, rather than one in which politicians and bureaucrats in Whitehall issue diktats and tell local communities with which they are unfamiliar what they should and should not do. That is the way forward for enhancing health care.</p>
	<p pid="b.234.3/2">Our vision is based not on processes that are distorted for party political purposes, but on the need to improve outcomes so that people get better health care. The patient experience, whether in a hospital setting or when a patient visits their GP, should be tailored to their needs, rather than to what the state tells them that they should have. That move will be spearheaded by GPs, through GP consortia, as it is they who are closest to patients, know the health care that they need, and know how patients can best access it. That will all be determined by improving outcomes and the patient experience in order to give the finest quality care that the country can provide-the highest in the world. That is the answer to the hon. Lady's question.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.235.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.235.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.235.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.235.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.235.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.235.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.235.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.235.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.235.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40217" speakername="Thomas Docherty" colnum="235"  time="016:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0002.htm#10072737000620">
	<p pid="b.235.3/1">I reiterate, I do not believe that the Minister was trying to sneak the statutory instrument out by using the form of a written statement. I hope he understands that many Scottish Members of Parliament would have been grateful for the opportunity to have a debate on the subject, perhaps after an oral statement, so I very much welcome today's opportunity.</p>
	<p pid="b.235.3/2">Giving a background to the subject might be helpful. The regulations followed a commitment by the previous Government after my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40239" name="Mark Lazarowicz">the Member for Edinburgh North and Leith (Mark Lazarowicz)</phrase> withdrew his private Member's Bill, the Environmental Protection (Transfers at Sea) Bill. The Bill was itself the result of an outcry in Scotland against proposals by Forth Ports to start carrying out ship-to-ship transfers in the firth of Forth. The Bill followed the introduction of new Scottish regulations, brought in by the Scottish Government in 2007, which dealt with those aspects of environmental regulations devolved to the Scottish Parliament. Significantly, those regulations were supported by all parties in the Scottish Parliament, including the Liberal Democrats and the Conservatives.</p>
	<p pid="b.235.3/3">Let me clear up one myth that opponents of the regulations-the shipping lobby in particular-have been perpetuating, namely, that the regulations have been rushed in some way. The 2010 regulations took the Department for Transport two years and two consultations to produce. They were eventually laid before Parliament in the so-called wash-up in April, to get through which we assume they must have had all-party support. Therefore, further delay and a third consultation are frustrating. It is unclear to us what new, previously unavailable information might be obtained by the third consultation that was not available from the first two processes. I hope that the Minister's reply will clarify that point.</p>
	<p pid="b.235.3/4">May I also make it clear that Labour Members do not oppose ship-to-ship transfers in principle? The Scottish Government and environmental bodies such as the RSPB do not do so either. Furthermore, the Scottish Government cannot be accused of nimbyism when they are championing the use of other Scottish waters. However, because oil spills into the sea are an environmental and tourism disaster, we believe that ship-to-ship transfers must be regulated. We only need to look at what happened in the gulf of Mexico, or closer to home in the Shetland islands with the Braer oil tanker a few years ago, to see what can happen to our environment when things go horribly wrong.</p>
	<p pid="b.235.3/5">Regulations should ensure two things-that ship-to-ship transfers are carried out in the right and safest place; and, secondly, that they meet the current environmental regulations. Therefore, long-standing good practice should be permitted to continue, as in Scapa Flow, which is sheltered, overseen by the harbour authority and in close proximity to pollution control equipment and expert staff. However, potentially hazardous places such as the firth of Forth, which is open sea, uncontrolled and with little if any nearby pollution control, should be prohibited.</p>
	<p pid="b.235.3/6">The 2010 regulations, in our opinion and that of the shadow team before the general election, provided just such an approach. They also provided a means to ensure that the operations comply with current EU regulations, otherwise the Government would be at risk of committing an infraction, as I am sure the Minister will confirm.</p>
	<p pid="b.235.3/7">I do not believe-I suspect that colleagues would not disagree-that the shipping industry should be allowed to pursue the policy of self-regulation for which it is lobbying. Before entering Parliament, I worked at a nuclear power station and on the railways. No one in their right mind would argue for allowing either the nuclear or the railway industries to self-regulate. Given that we require independent, statutory regulation of those two industries, and given the risks involved in the activity that we are discussing, why should the shipping industry believe that it should be allowed to self-regulate? I hope that the Minister will rule out that option today when he replies or, failing that, will expand on his thinking on self-regulation.</p>
	<p pid="b.235.3/8">The shipping lobbyists and their supporters will complain about the cost to them of following the regulations. However, I understand that the cost is only about &#163;9 million a year, and the proposals would add only an extra half-day's sailing to reach Scapa Flow rather than the Forth. I do not believe that &#163;9 million is a price too high for the protection of our environment.</p>
	<p pid="b.235.3/9">As I have made clear, the subject concerns a great number of my constituents. It is rare indeed when the SNP Scottish Government, the Lib Dem and SNP-run Fife and Edinburgh councils, Labour MPs, and Labour, SNP, Lib Dem and Conservative Members of the Scottish Parliament all speak with one voice. That, I hope, demonstrates to the Minister the level of anger felt by many people in Scotland.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.237.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.237.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.237.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.237.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.237.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.237.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.237.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.237.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.237.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40217" speakername="Thomas Docherty" colnum="237"  time="016:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0002.htm#10072737000624">
	<p pid="b.237.3/1">I am grateful to my hon. Friend for those comments. He obviously has particular expertise and knowledge of the mechanics of government from his former life. I would be grateful if the Minister could respond to that point. It might also be worth his clarifying what representations, if any, he has had from either the Secretary of State or the Under-Secretary of State for the Scotland Office. We understand that they are supposed to be Scotland's champions in the Government, and, given that the Scottish Government and the local authorities have raised the matter with his ministerial colleagues, it would be helpful to get an understanding of whether the Scotland Office has been asked for, or has proactively provided, any input to the review.</p>
	<p pid="b.237.3/2">I am conscious that I am beginning to approach the Minister's time, so let me make one final observation. Of course, we would never seek to use early-day motions as a method of gauging the overall strength of feeling in the House. I suspect that the Minister and I would be at one in suggesting that they are not necessarily the best way to make policy. However, it may be worth looking at the two early-day motions that were tabled on this subject.</p>
	<p pid="b.237.3/3">One was from <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40616" name="Sarah Newton">the hon. Member for Truro and Falmouth (Sarah Newton)</phrase>, who I welcome to the debate. I am sure that she will have some thoughts for us in a moment. Her early-day motion, which began</p>
	<p pid="b.237.3/4" class="indent">&quot;That an humble Address be presented to Her Majesty&quot;,</p>
	<p pid="b.237.3/5">asked for the regulations to be annulled, and attracted four signatures.</p>
	<p pid="b.237.3/6">The counter to that early-day motion was early-day motion 308, which was tabled by my hon. Friend the Member for Edinburgh North and Leith and which attracted 28 signatures. Basically, it said that the House welcomed the regulations, and asked for them to be enforced. Curiously enough, however, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40486" name="Mike Hancock">the hon. Member for Portsmouth South (Mr Hancock)</phrase> seems to have signed both motions. Far be it from me to try to establish why a Liberal Democrat might think that he can be both in favour of and against something simultaneously-I suspect that the Minister might have more experience of that than I do.</p>
	<p pid="b.237.3/7">In conclusion, I welcome the opportunity to have this debate. So that we are all clear, I accept the Minister's assurance that he was not seeking or intending to sneak out the announcement. I hope that he can give us some reassurance on the points that we have raised on regulations and other subjects, and I very much hope that he will be able to provide some light on who has made representations to him so far, and on his plans to take further representations from Members on both sides of the House.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.238.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.238.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.238.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.238.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.238.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.238.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.239.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.239.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.240.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.240.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.240.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.240.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.240.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.240.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.240.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.240.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.241.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.241.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.241.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.241.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.241.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40308" speakername="Michael Penning" colnum="241"  time="016:16:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100727/halltext/100727h0002.htm#10072737000634">
	<p pid="b.241.1/1">Not only have I had those findings, but I will look at them after the consultation is concluded.</p>
	<p pid="b.241.1/2">One of my biggest concerns is whether all the regulations are likely to work. That is a point of law. If they are not going to work in law, what is the point of having them? The measures in respect of Scapa Flow, the habitats directive and the environmental consequences will have to happen: that is part of the regulations. I understand that the hon. Member for Dunfermline and West Fife vehemently does not want ship-to-ship transfer in the Forth, but we have to consider whether there is a legal way of ensuring that that does not happen. Although the hon. Gentleman does not want ship-to-ship transfers, ships could move 12.1 miles off the coast and do the transfers legitimately there. Under the regulations, we cannot do anything if they move outside the 12-mile limit. That worries me an awful lot.</p>
	<p pid="b.241.1/3">Ship-to-ship transfers also take place off the Suffolk coast. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40591" name="Therese Coffey">The hon. Member for Suffolk Coastal (Dr Coffey)</phrase>, who is not in this Chamber today, is concerned about whether ships will move outside the controlled environment, where transfers happen at the moment, and go beyond the 12-mile limit. My hon. Friends the Members for Truro and Falmouth and for Waveney (Peter Aldous) have mentioned concerns about jobs being jeopardised.</p>
	<p pid="b.241.1/4">The hon. Member for Dunfermline and West Fife asked whether I would rule out self-regulation. There will be regulation: there is no argument about that. This is about how far regulation goes and whether it is enforceable: that is the crucial thing with any regulation made in the House.</p>
	<p pid="b.241.1/5">My scepticism is not based on my lack of willingness to protect the environment. Anyone looking at my track record will know my views on the environment. I am a fisherman and have fished in many of the coastal areas that the hon. Gentleman represents. We have to consider the risk. The hon. Gentleman mentioned earlier what has happened in respect of BP in the gulf of Mexico. Sadly, that might happen-God forbid that it does-on any of the rigs sitting out there today. There has not been a spillage from ship-to-ship transfer. The regulations are preventive and will put a burden on the shipping business: there is no argument about that, because that will happen. If we put such a burden on shipping, will ships sail up to Scapa and go in and pay their dues, or will they move a few miles out? I am not a shipping person, but I understand that the margins are not huge. That may happen.</p>
	<p pid="b.241.1/6">A lot of ships doing the transfers are Russian. As hon. Members know, the Russians have a large fleet, some of which is not the best quality. I hope that the Russians do not get upset about that, but it is a fact. If we can at least see the ships and control them to some degree within our territorial waters, we stand a chance. If they sit offshore, we will not be able to protect them at all.</p>
	<p pid="b.241.1/7">It is crucial that Parliament sets laws that are enforceable and fit for purpose. I will return to this point. I suspended the regulations because I am concerned that they may not be enforceable and are possibly not fit for purpose. However, I stress that that does not take away the requirement for regulation. I am disappointed that, as revealed in earlier comments, there seems to have been a lack of communication or co-operation between the Scotland Office in the previous Government and the Department for Transport. I assure the hon. Gentleman that that does not exist now and that there is now real co-operation between all the relevant Departments.</p>
	<p pid="b.241.1/8">I will meet as many different people and representative bodies as possible, including the RSPB. I am conscious that I have not had the sort of representation from the RSPB that I should like to have seen, but I expect to receive it during the consultation.</p>
	<p pid="b.241.1/9">Of course, the shipping industry is concerned, but it is not just about the shipping industry, as we have heard from hon. Members from around the country, who are concerned about whether these are the right regulations to protect the environment and jobs and whether they are a sledgehammer to crack a nut. I will consider that matter carefully during the consultation period.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.243.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.243.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.243.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.243.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27b.247.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-07-27c.247.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

