<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;" >
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;" >
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;" >
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;" >
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;" >

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.255.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.255.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.255.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.255.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.255.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.255.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.255.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.255.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.255.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2006" speakername="Alistair Carmichael" colnum="255"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060308/halltext/60308h01.htm#60308h01_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.255.3/1">I am pleased to have obtained this opportunity to debate human rights in central Asia, specifically the former Soviet republics known collectively as the &quot;stans&quot;: Tajikistan, Uzbekistan, Kyrgyzstan, Turkmenistan and Kazakhstan. I acknowledge the valuable assistance that I have received from bodies that have provided briefings for this debate, namely Christian Aid, Christian Solidarity Worldwide and Amnesty International.</p>
	<p pid="a.255.3/2">In many ways, 90 minutes is barely adequate to deal with this subject and the range of human rights concerns regarding this region. Therefore, to allow others to participate in the debate, I shall restrict the focus of my remarks to the situation in Uzbekistan in particular, although I shall touch on Turkmenistan, and on religious freedom, which is of particular concern to me.</p>
	<p pid="a.255.3/3">I shall try also to put human rights concerns into the broader politics of the region, because it seems that human rights problems common to all these central Asian countries are a symptom rather than the disease itself. They are symptomatic of the problem in countries that do not enjoy a great deal of political stability, because there is a tremendous amount of poverty in such countries, which has given rise to a fairly unpleasant class of despot in the region. When discussing human rights, it is important that we see the issue in its full and proper context and do not try to divorce it from the poverty issues in the region. I hope that in this age of joined-up government the Minister for Europe might convey a few of my concerns in that regard to his colleagues in the Department for International Development.</p>
	<p pid="a.255.3/4">There are several characters in the region about whom I am inclined to think that Gilbert and Sullivan would be writing comic operas if were they alive and working today. Those characters are&mdash;I say this in no spirit of levity&mdash;grotesque caricatures of dictators. It is impossible not to find some amusement in a character such as President Niyazov in Turkmenistan, who modestly styles himself as the &quot;father of all Turkmens&quot;, and who renamed the months and days after himself, his mother and various folklore heroes of the country. However, it is easy for me to say that it is impossible not to derive some amusement from such a person because my family are not being persecuted by such people, and my religious freedoms are not being curtailed. It is not me who, as a Christian, is being denied the right to visit and associate freely with other Christians, which is, of course, the situation in places such as Turkmenistan.</p>
	<p pid="a.255.3/5">I move to the situation in Uzbekistan. I have had an interest in that country for several years for a variety of reasons. The Minister may know that I have long been interested in the abolition of the death penalty worldwide; the death penalty has been used as a particularly brutal instrument of oppression in Uzbekistan. It may send shivers down a few spines behind the Minister to know that some of my concerns were first brought to my attention by the former ambassador to Uzbekistan, Mr. Craig Murray, with whom I have been acquainted for 20-odd years since we were both students at different universities in Scotland.</p>
	<p pid="a.255.3/6">I take as my starting point the Government's helpful annual human rights reports. Uzbekistan featured in the 2005 and 2004 reports as being an area of major concern. I love the Government's human rights reports: they have a real talent for taking the meanest grain of progress and embracing it with an optimism that I, as a Liberal Democrat, find truly heart-warming. Optimism should always be encouraged. They note that &quot;some limited steps&quot; have been taken in implementing the UN convention against torture, and highlight a speech made by President Karimov about his aspirations for democracy, but the bleak and depressing truth is that there is no concrete evidence of improvement and plenty of evidence of the continuation of widespread human rights abuses in that country. Torture and other forms of ill-treatment remain routine for those in custody. Indeed, torture is incentivised because confessions are routinely the basis for convictions in trials that are widely recognised to fall far short of any internationally recognised standards for such matters.</p>
	<p pid="a.255.3/7">I shall talk about events in Andijan last May. This issue has been fairly well rehearsed in this place, but probably not well enough. The fact that the events of 12 and <phrase class="date" code="2005-05-13">13 May 2005</phrase> in Andijan have not created more outrage should cause deep embarrassment to all of us in this country. On those nights, a group of armed men attacked an army garrison prison in Andijan, which is part of Uzbekistan's densely populated and impoverished Fergana valley. A number of prisoners were reported to have been released, including 23 men who are currently on trial for belonging to the Akromiya religious movement. Armed men stormed the mayor's office and took police hostages. Reports suggest that a crowd of several thousand gathered in the city on <phrase class="date" code="">13 May</phrase>, initially voicing support for the 23 accused but then calling for jobs, an end to corruption and injustice, and the president's resignation. Eye-witness reports, which have been suppressed by the Uzbek Government and are difficult to come by, suggest that toward the end of the afternoon, Uzbek troops fired indiscriminately on the crowds with live ammunition, using armoured personnel carriers. It has been suggested that about 500 people might have been killed, including women and children. We have no idea how many others might have been wounded.</p>
	<p pid="a.255.3/8">I say in passing that the Minister might wish to consider, in the context of other legislation going through the House, whether those who originally stormed the prison and garrison in Andijan might be regarded as terrorists, and whether those of us who support their quite legitimate case might, at a later stage, be considered guilty of glorifying terrorism. I do not expect him to answer that point today, but I highlight it as something on which he might wish to ponder on another occasion and in another way.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.256.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.256.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.257.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.257.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.257.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2006" speakername="Alistair Carmichael" colnum="257"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060308/halltext/60308h01.htm#60308h01_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.257.0/1">Yes; I am grateful to the hon. Gentleman for that intervention. As a Christian, I have been struck by the theme that runs through virtually all the human rights oppressions in the central Asian republics. The Churches&mdash;not only the Christian Church but other religious groupings&mdash;are at the centre of resistance to the dictatorships. I think back to Malawi in the early 1990s, when the Catholic bishops and the central African Presbyterian Church were instrumental in bringing down Banda.</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/2">The flipside of that coin is that the Churches and religious groups suffer the hardest persecution. That has been a hallmark of events since <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1850" name="David Drew">the Andijan massacre. As the hon. Member for Stroud (Mr. Drew)</phrase> said, it has affected Christian groups, other religious groups, journalists, human rights activists and ordinary citizens of no affiliation at all. Anyone who attracts any suspicion, whether there is any legitimacy to that, seems to be a legitimate target for repression in the eyes of the Uzbek Government. They have tried to close down any discussion or dissemination of any information about events in Andijan. State-run media outlets provided limited coverage of the events as they unfolded, and there was no pictorial representation of them.</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/3">On <phrase class="date" code="">14 May</phrase>, journalists who had been working for western news agencies, including the Institute for War and Peace Reporting and Reuters, were detained and forced to leave the city. Journalists from Russia's NTV and Ren TV were also detained and had equipment confiscated. Given the current relationship between Uzbekistan and Russia, that is even more remarkable.</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/4">Since the events of <phrase class="date" code="">13 May</phrase>, independent journalists and human rights activists have reported a climate of fear in Andijan, with pressure on people not to talk to outsiders. Non-governmental organisations and human rights groups have received reports of detentions and house arrests, including that of Saidjahon Zainabuddinov, the head of Appeal, the human rights non-governmental organisation. He was an eye witness to events in Andijan. We are given to understand that he has been charged with calumny or slander, but again details are difficult to come by. Can the Minister tell us what the current situation is for Saidjahon Zainabuddinov? What progress has been made towards persuading the Uzbek Government to accept an independent international inquiry into the events in Andijan last May?</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/5">Further concerns mentioned in the annual report relate to the restriction on access to prisons; the lack of independence in the judicial system, with judges appointed by the president; widespread corruption; and the continued use of the death penalty. In 2004, Uzbekistan executed prisoners on death row whose cases were lodged with the United Nations human rights committee.</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/6">Also in 2004, I was privileged to chair a meeting in the House of Commons organised by Reprieve, the death penalty abolition group. Among others represented on that occasion was the Uzbek group Mothers Against the Death Penalty and Torture. In particular, Tamara Chikunova was present and her story was one of the most compelling and heart-rending stories that I have ever heard from someone who has been involved with the death penalty&mdash;of course, there are few pleasant ones. Tamara Chikunova's son was arrested, subjected to a mockery of a trial in Uzbekistan and sentenced to death. She visited him regularly in prison. She turned up one day as arranged and was told that she would not be allowed access to him and to come back two days later. She did so and was told that her son had been executed two days earlier&mdash;the very day on which she had been outside, waiting for him.</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/7">I often think that the appalling inhumanity of the death penalty comes from the prevalence of people remaining on death row for 15 or 20 years, as often happens in the United States. However, to use the death penalty at the other end of the scale, only weeks after conviction, takes inhumanity and barbarism, too. That story highlights the nature of the Uzbek regime.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.258.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.258.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.258.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.258.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.258.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2006" speakername="Alistair Carmichael" colnum="258"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060308/halltext/60308h01.htm#60308h01_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.258.1/1">I cannot disagree. The hon. Gentleman has described features of a criminal justice system that breaches just about every internationally accepted norm of criminal justice standards. Justice should be done publicly. People should have a right to know the case against them. The judiciary should be properly independent of the Government. We take those things for granted, but the Uzbek Government in particular&mdash;I take the point about not labelling every &quot;stan&quot; according to Uzbekistan&mdash;almost seem to go out of their way to ignore them.</p>
	<p pid="a.258.1/2">The Government's annual report mentions problems faced by members of Human Rights Watch with regard to the renewal of their visas, but there is not much of an update. Perhaps the Minister can say what the current situation is for NGOs such as Human Rights Watch that seek to operate in Uzbekistan but find themselves constrained in doing so.</p>
	<p pid="a.258.1/3">I am aware that time is moving on, so I shall deal with religious freedom briefly; no doubt other hon. Members will do so in more detail. The reports of religious intolerance and persecution in Uzbekistan cause me significant concern. Discrimination, harassment and criminal prosecutions of Muslims and harassment of religious minorities, most notably Protestant Christians, remain commonplace. The trial of 23 men accused of being members of the banned Akromiya group and anti-constitutional activity led to the Andijan massacre. Can the Minister update us on the policy of critical engagement with Uzbekistan in respect of cases such as that?</p>
	<p pid="a.258.1/4">Another concern that I shall touch on, which is not new, is the suggestion that information derived from torture has been used by this country. Again, I bring hon. Members' attention to the work of Craig Murray. He stated clearly that the Government have used information provided by states that practise torture. Steve Crawshaw of Human Rights Watch told the Foreign Affairs Committee that, in one of her submissions when questioned in the House of Lords on the use of information acquired through torture, Eliza Manningham-Buller as much as said, &quot;We're not going to ask, because that would make things difficult.&quot; I hope that the Government's approach to the use of information from Uzbekistan has moved on from that rather bleak caricature and that the Minister will assure us that they will not use intelligence derived from the use of torture in Uzbekistan.</p>
	<p pid="a.258.1/5">I said in my introductory remarks that I wanted to make the link between human rights abuses and poverty in the region. In doing so, I am again indebted to Christian Aid for its briefing. It is important to understand that the oppression of people in the central Asian republics is an economic as well as a human rights oppression. These are, for the most part, highly resource-rich countries, and that makes the fact that there is such poverty in them all the more appalling. The average per capita incomes in Kyrgyzstan, Tajikistan and Uzbekistan are now lower than in sub-Saharan Africa. The average monthly salary in Tajikistan is $20. Across the region as a whole, life expectancy at birth fell from 68.2 years in 1990 to 64.7 years in 2003. Although some economic progress has been made in the past few years in Tajikistan and Kyrgyzstan, that has not translated into improved living standards for ordinary people. A recent survey suggested that more than half of the poorest households in Tajikistan eat on average only one meal a day. One third of Tajik children are chronically malnourished, and economic migration among the male population of the region is leading to family collapse and increased vulnerability for women and children.</p>
	<p pid="a.258.1/6">In view of the difficult governance issues in the region, will the Minister tell us how he envisages the UK Government's poverty reduction and political objectives there being met? Also, please will he impress on his ministerial colleagues at the Department for International Development the importance of increasing aid to the region, in line with DFID's increasing support to other developing regions?</p>
	<p pid="a.258.1/7">Finally, I shall address changes at the United Nations. In August 2005, the UN General Assembly agreed to establish a human rights council to replace the UN Commission on Human Rights; it was said that the human rights council will assume the mandate of the Commission on Human Rights. It will have between 30 and 50 members, each of them elected on a geographical basis and for a period of three years by a two thirds majority of the General Assembly. Each member will undertake to fulfil human rights standards and face evaluation under the review mechanism. We are told that the United Kingdom welcomes the establishment of the council, but it is of concern that the US ambassador, John Bolton, has said that he is prepared to vote against it. Is the Minister able to give us any insights in respect of why the United States is opposed, what compromises they might be looking for, and what prospect there is for the introduction of the human rights council? Can the Minister also assure us that the system of monitoring human rights worldwide under the UN special rapporteurs will continue and be properly resourced?</p>
	<p pid="a.258.1/8">Much more could be said about central Asia and human rights. I am grateful to hon. Members of all parties for attending the debate. I hope that our words and concerns will be heard outwith this Chamber, and that there might be a little hope for the future of the oppressed people in these countries.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.260.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.260.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.260.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1610" speakername="Greg Hands" colnum="260"  time="009:53:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060308/halltext/60308h01.htm#60308h01_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.260.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2006" name="Alistair Carmichael">the hon. Member for Orkney and Shetland (Mr. Carmichael)</phrase> on securing this important debate. Like me, he has long had an interest in this part of the world, and I am sure that he would agree that, if anything, the debate is somewhat overdue.</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/2">Central Asia is a relatively neglected part of the world&mdash;neglected by policy makers, that mythical body called the international community, and, dare I say it, by Her Majesty's Government, and even by the House. There have, I think, been two oral questions on the region and, perhaps, two dozen written questions in the last year, from, for instance, the hon. Members for Orkney and Shetland, for Stroud (Mr. Drew), for Bassetlaw (John Mann), for Moray (Angus Robertson), and for Leicester, East (Keith Vaz), and from <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1463" name="John Bercow">my hon. Friend the Member for Buckingham (John Bercow)</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/3">I have been to all five of the countries in question, and to Uzbekistan on various occasions. In a general sense, central Asia is not a happy part of the world, and its nations have certainly underperformed in the past 15 years, compared with other ex-Soviet republics not just in Europe, but also in Asia. Twenty years ago, Tashkent was more or less on a par with Novosibirsk or Krasnoyarsk. Since then, there has been quite a severe divergence in the wrong direction for Tashkent and other major central Asian cities.</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/4">The hon. Member for Orkney and Shetland talked in detail about some of the economic statistics; those on per capita incomes and life expectancies are truly alarming. There is also some crazy economics in countries such as Uzbekistan. It is one of the few countries where people can still be seen doing their daily shopping with huge wads of cash. I have seen ethnic Russians showing up at travel agencies with large wheeled hold-alls full of cash to buy their one-way ticket to Moscow; it makes me think of the Weimar republic.</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/5">One issue that has not been touched on so far is the regrettable out-migration of ethnic Russians. That is partly due to Russia's loss of its previous status as the quasi-colonial power, but it is also due to human rights concerns. Depending on one's view on what is going on in Moscow, that journey might smack a little of being a case of out of the frying pan and into the fire. However, that phenomenon is sucking out a lot of the middle classes&mdash;such as they exist&mdash;from these countries.</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/6">Most of the interest that there is in the region in the outside world&mdash;and, indeed, in the House&mdash;is due to energy interests. I am not against there being such interests, but we need also consider human rights, which in many of these countries is awful. Uzbekistan is without doubt one of the five most tyrannical regimes in the world at present. Turkmenistan exceeds even North Korea in its rampant Stalinist personality cult. Tajikistan is still in chaos. Kyrgyzstan still has an uncertain future, and the recent Kazakh election was, at best, questionable.</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/7">I want to focus briefly on Turkmenistan, before concentrating mainly on Uzbekistan. In describing Turkmenistan, it is a shame that we are not allowed visual aids, because it is difficult to get a feel for the country without having seen it. There is a massive personality cult; the hon. Member for Orkney and Shetland referred to it. The leader is Niyazov, the self-styled Turkmenbashi, and his regime is characterised by vanity, control freakery and a habit of fantasy and invention. I have always written him up as TB for short. The phrase &quot;Halk, Watan, Turkmenbashi&quot; can be seen almost everywhere in the country; it means something like, &quot;Praise the leader.&quot; All of us have come across occasional snippets about him. I share the view of the hon. Gentleman. In that country, one spends about a third of the time in a state of bizarre amusement, but for two thirds of the time one is appalled at what is going on. In the centre of Ashkabad, there is a neutrality monument. It is an 8 m high gold statue of Turkmenbashi that revolves on top of a pedestal that is about 70 m high. The leader of the country greets the sun in the morning&mdash;the statue faces the sun&mdash;and then he revolves during the day and says goodbye to the setting sun in the evening. It is incredible to watch. However, the cruel reality in Turkmenistan is that open expression of alternative views is not possible. It can result in imprisonment or forced institutionalisation in a psychiatric hospital. There is no free media, and even most publications from Russia are banned, and means are taken to suppress the use of the internet.</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/8">The hon. Member for Orkney and Shetland rightly focused much of his speech on Uzbekistan. Human rights abuses in Uzbekistan are not new, but on <phrase class="date" code="">13 May</phrase> last year in the city of Andijan there was the world's biggest peacetime massacre of demonstrators since Tiananmen square. I was delighted recently to meet Muhammed Salih, the last Uzbek opposition leader who dared to speak out. He has written an excellent book called &quot;The Opponent&quot;. It starts by describing his unhappy time as a Soviet soldier during the occupation of Czechoslovakia in 1968. Mr Salih spoke movingly of the events in Andijan, and, in response to my questioning, he outlined how the opposition in the country was being much maligned by the Government, who seek to paint its members as Islamists and terrorists, both of which are gross distortions.</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/9">I commend the work of Human Rights Watch which, despite facing great difficulties and some danger to its own people, has managed to put together a credible account of what happened in Andijan&mdash;of tanks rolling through the main square and firing indiscriminately, of snipers picking off their victims, and of soldiers later shooting dead some of the wounded. At the time that they happened, the events of <phrase class="date" code="2005-05-13">13 May 2005</phrase> were somewhat buried under a glut of other international news. That was just after our election, and the French and the Dutch were in the middle of EU Constitution ratification, so the attention of the international community may to some extent have been elsewhere.</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/10">Over the past nine months, I have tabled more than a dozen questions on the Government's response to the events at Andijan, and on what action the UK and the international community are taking. The first response to my very first question on the subject came not from the Minister for Europe, but from the Uzbek embassy in London; its response actually came before the Government's. The embassy sent me what I am sure it thought was a helpful e-mail, a six-page exposition of what it described as the &quot;terrorist&quot; incidents at Andijan, which it bizarrely blamed on Hizb ut-Tahrir. The e-mail had a sinister tone, demanding to know, for example, where I had learned aspects of idiomatic Uzbek, and so on.</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/11">The reaction internationally to the events at Andijan has been very weak, and for no particular reason; there is not even the excuse that Uzbek bases are needed to project coalition power in the region. Energy concerns are not particularly great in Uzbekistan. To the best of my knowledge, Uzbekistan is still a member of the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development and still has a partnership and co-operation agreement with the EU, although I could not ascertain whether that has been suspended. Germany seems quite happy to allow Uzbek Government leaders to receive medical treatment there, claiming that it is being done on humanitarian grounds. I question whether the population of Uzbekistan has the same access to quality medical treatment.</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/12">There is an EU arms embargo, although Uzbekistan is a member of the NATO partnership for peace programme. It must be the first time in history that we have a military ally on whom we have an arms embargo. I pointed that out to the Minister at Foreign Office questions in October, but it seems that no action has resulted. Thankfully, the US has been a little tougher than the EU; it has at least pulled out of its military base, although it is slightly unclear whether that was voluntary.</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/13">The Economist's excellent editorial of <phrase class="date" code="">25 August</phrase> last year said, with reference to Andijan:</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/14" class="indent">&quot;On few, if any, occasions since the cold war has so little been done by so many in the face of such atrocity.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/15">The article goes on to criticise the EU for</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/16" class="indent">&quot;a display of spinelessness worthy of a sea full of jellyfish.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/17">In three months' time, I hope in co-operation with other speakers here, I will be hosting, in Parliament, an anniversary event for <phrase class="date" code="">13 May</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/18">In conclusion, we need a much tougher response on Uzbekistan. It is still not too late. I again draw a contrast with the response to Tiananmen square in 1989. Ironically, at the time that response was criticised in many quarters for not being strong enough, but it was actually quite swift and&mdash;compared to the response to Andijan&mdash;quite strong. Some 17 years on, there are still some sanctions in place against China; yet here we are nine months after Andijan with very little to show.</p>
	<p pid="a.260.0/19">In my time in the region, I often thought that Uzbekistan, Turkmenistan and, to some extent, Kazakhstan were how eastern Europe countries would have been had the Berlin wall not fallen in 1989. One might recall Ceausescu and Honecker in 1989 praising the Chinese authorities after Tiananmen square, and thank God that they were never able to copy those authorities. The regimes that we are talking about, particularly that of Uzbekistan, have copied the Chinese example. Uzbekistan, in particular, and Turkmenistan are worse than the countries of cold war eastern Europe; they are more like the Stalinist days of the early 1950s. Torture is rampant, demonstrators are shot, there are no press freedoms, censorship is complete, and there are roadblocks everywhere on the highways. We need a far tougher response from the western world and from Her Majesty's Government, and I look forward to hearing the Minister's answers.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.263.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.263.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.263.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2002" speakername="Angus Robertson" colnum="263"  time="010:03:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060308/halltext/60308h01.htm#60308h01_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.263.0/1">It is a pleasure to follow <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1610" name="Greg Hands">the hon. Member for Hammersmith and Fulham (Mr. Hands)</phrase>, who is obviously well informed about the situation on the ground in the republics that we are talking about. I commend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2006" name="Alistair Carmichael">the hon. Member for Orkney and Shetland (Mr. Carmichael)</phrase> on securing this debate.</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/2">My interest in former Soviet republics is normally about the south Caucasus&mdash;Armenia, Azerbaijan and Georgia. It is through my interest in that region and my involvement in the non-governmental organisation sector that I have come to understand how much of human rights work is dependent on funding from the UK Government through the global conflict prevention pool. The last GCPP report, &quot;A joint UK Government approach to reducing conflict&quot;, states:</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/3" class="indent">&quot;Activities under the various strategies include . . . .Helping civil society organisations defuse the tensions which can lead to violent conflict. This can include some promotion of human rights.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/4">One NGO involved in the former Soviet republics has outlined its work as consisting of: fostering institutional and legal reform by providing international comparative expertise; engaging in advocacy on a national and international level; the training of key actors&mdash;that is, young journalists, lawyers, judges, specialised NGOs and public officials; the monitoring and auditing of the public's access to official information; and raising public awareness about the practical function of freedom of expression and access to information in a democracy. Those are exactly the sort of efforts that are essential to deal with the shortcomings that have been outlined.</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/5">It may not be well known to some Members present that the Government have slashed their spending on these important efforts by 20 per cent. as a whole. It may surprise them even more to hear that funding to the former Soviet republics has been almost halved; there is a cut of nearly 50 per cent.</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/6">In a Westminster Hall debate last October, to which the Minister responded, I read out a reply that I had received from an NGO, which said that the cuts</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/7" class="indent">&quot;will have negative implications for the democratic transformations in the region. Work cannot be carried out with gaps in time; there should be continuity and an ongoing flow of activities that build on past strengths and existing experiences&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/8">Another NGO said that it would have to</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/9" class="indent">&quot;tap core support and cut back in projects&quot;,</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/10">and said that there are</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/11" class="indent">&quot;obviously other pressures on government spending, but nothing has been made clear as to why the money has gone&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/12">Having worked with many NGOs in the south Caucasus, I am passionate about the subject, and I do not think that the cut in spending there is justified. It would seem extraordinary if the UK Government were to cut spending to the central Asian republics.</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/13">My first specific question to the Minister, together with his colleagues from the Department, is to ask him to run through the cut in spending to Uzbekistan, Turkmenistan, Tajikistan, Kazakhstan and Kyrgyzstan. Will he confirm that there has been a cut in spending through the conflict prevention pools to projects in those republics? Nothing that we have heard today would give anyone confidence to suggest that either the human rights situation or the democratic situation have improved over the past year; if anything, they have become worse.</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/14">The Minister and I have a difference of view on the Iraq conflict, but there is an appreciation that funds, including other budget lines from the conflict prevention pools, have gone from central Asia to Iraq. If the Government have cut funding, now is the time for them to explain why, and to say which projects in the central Asian republics will be affected.</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/15">My second point is about the UK Government and the domestic reaction to the human rights situation in central Asia. Not many citizens of the republics that we are talking about live in the UK. I happen to have a Turkmen citizen&mdash;an ethnic Russian&mdash;in my constituency. He is going through some of the difficulties that the hon. Member for Hammersmith and Fulham outlined. I have raised his case with the Home Office, and I do not expect the Minister to talk specifically about it, but I would like to give him the correspondence on the subject. In that way, he can liaise with the Home Office so that the matter can be dealt with.</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/16">It may not be clear to people outside the region that the Turkmen laws regarding marriage were such that until the beginning of the year $50,000 had to be paid as a fee for registering a marriage with a foreigner. That is extraordinary. I suspect that that was part of the effort to try to stop the ethnic Russian middle classes leaving. Be that as it may, international pressure was put on the Turkmen authorities and changes to the law have been brought about, but it would be a fantasy to think that the problems have disappeared because of that.</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/17">My constituent has appealed against a decision to refuse a certificate of approval for the marriage in the UK. She was granted a visa extension to enable her to have her child in the UK, which has happened, and she has been allowed to remain in the UK for several more months, after which her current visa status requires her to return to Turkmenistan before she can apply for a marriage visa. How extraordinary that somebody who is here in safety and has had a child is having to return to that country. We do not have enough time to read the reports from Human Rights Watch, Amnesty International, the Organisation for Security and Co-operation in Europe and the office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights, etc., all of which are saying that this is an issue of concern.</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/18">For prescience I shall read one paragraph from a document from the Turkmen Initiative for Human Rights, published at the beginning of January. It states that:</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/19" class="indent">&quot;the Turkmen authorities had to cancel this repressive law&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/20">the registration law&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/21" class="indent">yet they were reluctant to offer complete freedom to their citizens, so lists of those who were not allowed to leave Turkmenistan, i.e. 'black lists' appeared in the country. According to various data these lists included between 3 to 5 thousand names. However, most of these people only learnt about their status when they were at the airport about to board a plane. When such cases became known to diplomats at foreign embassies, the Turkmen Foreign Ministry had to demonstrate great ingenuity in order to justify the actions of the border officers and special services.</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/22" class="indent">Consequently, a new law was passed which requires all those wishing to exit Turkmenistan irrespective of the aim of the trip to obtain a new document&mdash;a passport for the citizens of Turkmenistan for going abroad and entering Turkmenistan&mdash;in advance of the trip.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/23">That is not satisfactory. It would be helpful if in time, if not today, the Foreign Office clarified that position. There cannot be hundreds and thousands of Turkmen citizens in the UK; it must be a small group of people. The case has been made by verifiably independent human rights organisations that the current situation is not acceptable. I hope that the Home Office and the Foreign Office will co-ordinate to ensure that people seeking to remain in the UK are treated according to their circumstances and that they are deeply sceptical about the human rights situation in Turkmenistan.</p>
	<p pid="a.263.0/24">The Government have some work to do on this matter and they have some explanations to give on the funding of projects in various central Asian republics. I am sure that the Minister will say that the UK Government have grave concerns and are doing everything that they can. However, if that is so, are they cutting their funding and, if so, why?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.265.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.265.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.265.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1869" speakername="Jeremy Browne" colnum="265"  time="010:13:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060308/halltext/60308h01.htm#60308h01_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.265.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2006" name="Alistair Carmichael">my hon. Friend the Member for Orkney and Shetland (Mr. Carmichael)</phrase> on securing this important debate. The last time that I listened to a speech in the House by my hon. Friend, the outcome was a defeat for the Government by one vote. The Government will be pleased that there will not be a vote on this debate. None the less, I hope that the issues raised are treated with the degree of concern that they warrant.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/2">I congratulate also the two speakers who preceded me&mdash;the hon. Members for Hammersmith and Fulham (Mr. Hands) and for Moray (Angus Robertson)&mdash;particularly the former for making a well-informed and insightful speech based on his experience of visiting all those countries in the region.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/3">I have a degree of sympathy for the Government on such occasions, because it is normal in these debates for everybody to agree that the state of affairs in the given country is deplorable and ask the Government what they are going to do about it. The Government have scope to make headway and progress, otherwise we would have nothing to discuss, but we should not delude ourselves that the Foreign Office or wider Government are able to resolve all the ills of the world from Whitehall. None the less, this is an important debate and I hope that the Foreign Office will not try to be so realpolitik with this region that it will see wider strategic concerns taking too great a precedence over the worrying human rights abuses that have already been chronicled during this debate.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/4">I commend my hon. Friend the Member for Orkney and Shetland on his vigilant opposition to the use of the death penalty around the world, which is a form of sanction that debases humanity. It is a laudable aim for all hon. Members&mdash;I am pleased that there is now a large degree of consensus across parties in Britain&mdash;to say that the death penalty is an inappropriate way to punish people and to send a wider signal to populations of other countries, which is often another of its effects.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/5">We in this country so often take for granted a range of freedoms, including freedom of election, media freedom, freedom of trade union affiliation and religious practice, which has already been touched on, freedom of association and the rule of law and a proper independent criminal justice system. I join those who have already spoken in urging the Minister and the Government not to neglect or too readily forget the events in Andijan only 10 months or so ago. Tiananmen square took place when I was a 19-year-old and a few years have passed since then, but it lingers long in the memory and rightly so, because such events are more likely to be repeated if they are too readily forgotten.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/6">I have four suggestions that are not directly within the remit of the Government but are, none the less, areas where they may have some scope to act. First, this region has a low profile in this country and in western Europe, north America and other parts of the world, and it is easy to neglect it. Few people in this country have ever been there and many of them probably could not locate it accurately on a world map. Few people from the region have visited our country. There is little scope for cultural interchange. As a consequence, countries that are out of sight are often out of mind as well. It would help provoke debate in this country, and raise greater concerns than have already been made apparent by groups such as Amnesty International, if people in Britain had a greater appreciation of the way of life and culture and difficulties faced by people in the region. I do not claim that that is directly in the frame of reference of the Minister, but it is worth us bearing in mind that when opportunities arise to promote understanding of that region, whether through the media or in the House, that is an important factor in bringing international pressure to bear on those who abuse their power in these countries.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/7">Secondly, I should like to talk about poverty, which the hon. Member for Orkney and Shetland mentioned, including widespread hunger, unemployment and reduced life expectancy. Extreme poverty can be a powerful instrument of control for a regime that wishes to use it in that way&mdash;Zimbabwe is as graphic an illustration of that as any country. Such poverty also brutalises a society and means that the human rights concerns of the people who live there are relegated, day to day, below the more immediate concerns of keeping body and soul together. It is always difficult to try to maintain a civilised civic society when people live in extreme poverty and feel that they are willing to complain less about their circumstances, in terms of their liberties, as long as they are able to feed and shelter themselves and their families.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/8">As the hon. Member for Moray said, the Government have scope to make progress on that issue and to try to encourage the Governments in the countries that we are discussing&mdash;in so far as we have relations with them&mdash;to do the same.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/9">My third suggestion is to do with the issue raised about natural resources and energy in the countries of central Asia. Too often, we in the west regard the need to provide for our energy requirements and drive up our standard of living as taking precedence over all forms of foreign relations. I do not wish to be unrealistic; like my constituents, I drive a car and heat a home, and we should guard against being unduly hypocritical. None the less, rather than seeing the need to increase our energy supply as a reason for overlooking human rights, we should regard it more as a lever for change and a way of exercising pressure elsewhere. The Government need to be forceful in that regard.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/10">My final thought is not directly a matter of Government policy, but it is about an issue that they may seek to influence. I do not believe that human rights ever quite come about by Governments signing treaties or forcing them to emerge artificially. The process is more subtle and difficult than that; it is about engendering in people, and those to whom they give their consent to rule, a sense of values that they regard as impossible to violate.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/11">That is more delicate than something that a Foreign Secretary decrees should happen by signing a piece of paper, and it is a worldwide process. I do not regard human rights and civil liberties as the particular preserve of those who happen to be fortunate enough to live in a country in which Government Ministers treat such issues with due concern. That is why I particularly commend the work of Amnesty International, an organisation of which I am a member, and others. They see the issue in a global context, remind us to be vigilant and foster the desire in people throughout the world to live free from tyranny and terror.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/12">I leave those thoughts with the Minister and look forward to hearing his speech and that of the official Conservative spokesman, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1515" name="Geoffrey Clifton-Brown">the hon. Member for Cotswold (Mr. Clifton-Brown)</phrase>. I hope that the Minister will be able to answer many of the concerns raised this morning.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.267.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.267.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.267.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1515" speakername="Geoffrey Clifton-Brown" colnum="267"  time="010:22:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060308/halltext/60308h01.htm#60308h01_spnew8">
	<p pid="a.267.0/1">I am grateful for having caught your eye in this debate, Mr. Cook. I apologise to the Chamber as I have just developed a nose bleed. I am sorry if I look unsavoury; that is the reason why.</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/2">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2006" name="Alistair Carmichael">the hon. Member for Orkney and Shetland (Mr. Carmichael)</phrase> on securing this debate. As he says, not enough attention is paid to central Asia. Some appalling human rights abuses are going on in that part of the world, although as I said during my intervention on the hon. Gentleman, it is wrong to brand all five &quot;stans&quot; in the same way. They have very different populations. Some have greater Russian populations&mdash;for example, 30 per cent. of Kazakhstan's population is Russian, but only 3.5 per cent. of Tajikistan's is Russian. The countries are very different in make-up; they have different languages, different religious beliefs and consequently different Governments. They have varying human rights records. For the sake of completeness, I shall talk about all five countries. I shall end with Uzbekistan and the problems there following the massacre.</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/3">Tajikistan has perhaps the best human rights and democratic record of the lot. It has independent television, allows independent trade unions and permits public assembly, albeit with a licence, and those are all characteristics of the democratic, open state that we would like to see.</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/4"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1782" name="William Hague">My right hon. Friend the Member for Richmond, Yorks (Mr. Hague)</phrase> and I saw the Kazakh Foreign Minister yesterday. Although there are concerns about President Nazarbayev's recent re-election, Kazakhstan wants to do business with the west. The Foreign Minister made it absolutely clear that he was here to promote his country and that it wants to move towards democracy and better human rights.</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/5">We learned one very interesting fact from the Foreign Minister: within four years, Kazakhstan will become the world's largest exporter of uranium. Recently, it signed a memorandum of understanding with the Russians. This is well outside the scope of this debate, but if we could persuade the Iranians to have a system under which the Russians processed their uranium, that uranium would come from Kazakhstan. That is an interesting possibility. Kazakhstan has rich oil and gas reserves.</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/6">Turkmenistan has already been referred to. It is effectively a one-party state; the Democratic party of Turkmenistan is the only registered political party and faces no serious opposition. <i>[Interruption.]</i> Shades of the situation in this country? Perhaps not&mdash;the Opposition here are getting stronger, and we do not want a one-party state.</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/7">Perhaps more worryingly, Kyrgyzstan faces a possible break-up as a country. An article by the Institute for War and Peace Reporting states:</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/8" class="indent">&quot;Kyrgyzstan has been in constant turmoil in recent months, with protests, confrontations and scandals following one another in close succession.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/9">The article goes on to say:</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/10" class="indent">&quot;When it comes to the basic tasks of government&mdash;law and order, resource management, and reform&mdash;the authorities are failing badly, and they are also losing out to their critics in the battle for public opinion.</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/11" class="indent">Given all these circumstances, one hears more and more often the view that the country is swiftly moving towards a tragic finale where it becomes patently apparent that Kyrgyzstan has not developed into a fully-fledged nation, and peace-keeping forces are brought in from the outside.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/12">The article states that the greatest pessimists predict that Kyrgyzstan could break into two.</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/13">That leads me to Uzbekistan, the last of the five &quot;stans&quot;. It will be useful to cite a letter written by the organisation Human Rights Watch that restates the UN's fundamental declaration on human rights, the core principle on which the UN was founded and to which all nations on Earth should adhere. The letter states:</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/14" class="indent">&quot;The United Nations Declaration on the Right and Responsibility of Individuals, Groups and Organs of Society to Promote and Protect Universally Recognized Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms sets forth the standards by which the international community assesses states' treatment of rights defenders . . . Article 1 of the declaration states clearly that, 'Everyone has the right, individually and in association with others, to promote and to strive for the protection and realization of human rights and fundamental freedoms at the national and international levels.' Article 2 stipulates that each state has a responsibility and duty to create all conditions necessary to ensure that all persons under its jurisdiction, individually and in association with others, are able to enjoy all human rights and fundamental freedoms in practice.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/15">As the hon. Member for Orkney and Shetland said, we often take what we have in this democratic country of ours, and in the west, for granted. It is too easy to forget how possible it is to go about one's daily life in an atmosphere of peace and freedom.</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/16">So what happened in Uzbekistan? There have been various descriptions, but the best I have read comes from Human Rights Watch. I shall quote it to show how bad what happened in Uzbekistan on <phrase class="date" code="">13 May</phrase> last year was. The description is very telling:</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/17" class="indent">&quot;In the early morning hours of May 13, gunmen attacked government buildings, killed security officials, broke into the city prison, took over the local government building . . . and took hostages. Towards dawn, they began to prepare for a large protest in Bobur Square, in front of the hokimiat, and mobilized people to attend. By 11.00 a.m., as word spread, the protest grew into the thousands, as people came of their own will and vented their grievances about poverty and government repression. When government forces sealed off the square and started shooting indiscriminately, the protesters fled. Hundreds of them were ambushed by government forces, which gunned them down without warning. This stunning use of excessive force has been documented by the United Nations and other intergovernmental organizations.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/18">Yet we have heard relatively little about that slaughter in Andijan in this Parliament or in <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1610" name="Greg Hands">the world's media. My hon. Friend the Member for Hammersmith and Fulham (Mr. Hands)</phrase> quoted an article from <i>The Economist</i>. During his excellent, fluent speech, which reflected his knowledge of the area, my hon. Friend told us that Uzbekistan is a member of the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development and has a partnership and co-operation agreement with the European Union, so there is some justification in allowing Europe, with its famous common security policy, to take the lead. He also quoted from an article in <i>The Economist</i>, which continues with a wonderful bit of irony:</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/19" class="indent">&quot;If so, the European Union has risen to the occasion as grandly as it did over Bosnia, Iraq and on so many other occasions: with a display of spinelessness worthy of sea full of jellyfish.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/20">Like the hon. Member for Orkney and Shetland, my hon. Friend has tabled questions about the visit to Germany of the Uzbek Foreign Minister&mdash;there is no reason why he should not be held to account for his country's activities.</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/21">I can give many examples from reports on the matters that concern me&mdash;torture; secret trials; people who do not have access to proper lawyers; people who are given long sentences without justification; and, perhaps worst of all, the case of Mutabar Tojibaeva. An article from Human Rights Watch dated <phrase class="date" code="2006-03-07">7 March</phrase> quotes Holly Cartner, its Europe and Central Asia director, who says:</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/22" class="indent">&quot;The trial that led to the sentence of Tojibaeva is so unsound that her conviction cannot be allowed to stand . . . We view Tojibaeva's conviction as part of a pattern of persecution against independent voices and critics within civil society since the Andijan massacre. The ferocity of this pattern is unprecedented even when judged against Uzbekistan's 14-year history of repression since independence from the Soviet Union.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/23">Uzbekistan is a real pariah state, and the world should focus on it.</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/24">In closing, I have a few questions for the Minister. No doubt he will run through all the &quot;stans&quot;. Perhaps he will say a little about what Government representation we have in each. As the Government are in embassy-closing mode, can he reassure us that, in view of the problems in these countries, none of our embassies or consulates there will close. Yesterday we were told by the Foreign Secretary that we recently opened a second consulate in Kazakhstan; that is a good sign, we want to see British representation maintained at the highest level in these countries.</p>
	<p pid="a.267.0/25">There have been alarming reports from Ukraine and other countries that are sending refugees back to Uzbekistan. One can only imagine the fate of such people. In particular, I refer to a report from the Organisation for Security and Co-operation in Europe, on Ukraine's decision to return Uzbek asylum seekers. It says that Mr De Gucht, the OSCE's current Chairman-in-Office, has expressed his consternation at the decision taken by the Ukraine authorities to extradite 11 Uzbek asylum seekers back to Uzbekistan. What representations are the British Government making to Governments who propose to send refugees back to Ukbekistan? They are in grave danger of being persecuted, if not executed, if sent back.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.270.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.270.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.270.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.270.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.271.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.271.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.271.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2008" speakername="Douglas Alexander" speakeroffice="The Minister for Europe"  colnum="271"  time="010:36:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060308/halltext/60308h01.htm#60308h01_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.271.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2006" name="Alistair Carmichael">the hon. Member for Orkney and Shetland (Mr. Carmichael)</phrase> on having secured the debate. Its merit was already proven before I rose to my feet, and I hope that I shall strengthen hon. Members' convictions that the debate is worth while by the remarks that I am able to offer.</p>
	<p pid="a.271.0/2">I welcome the opportunity to underline our commitment to improving human rights in central Asia. I also pay tribute&mdash;I would be remiss to do anything else&mdash;to the longstanding interest in these matters, in particular the abolition of the death penalty, of the hon. Member for Orkney and Shetland, and acknowledge the important work undertaken by non-governmental organisations such as those, including Amnesty International, that he generously recognised at the beginning of his speech. I shall ensure that the terms of this debate are shared with my ministerial colleagues in the Department for International Development, as he requested in the course of his remarks.</p>
	<p pid="a.271.0/3">It is already clear, on the basis of our discussion this morning, that the House is united in its profound concern about the continuing negative trend on human rights in central Asia. Let me assure hon. Gentlemen that the Government continue to place a high priority on trying to bring about improvements. We remain committed to encouraging, cajoling and, where possible, co-operating with the countries in the region, to help to bring about greater freedoms and the development of civil society. We also remain focused on the difficult question, which has been honestly recognised, of how, in practice, the United Kingdom, acting in concert with the European Union and other international partners, can best effect positive change, not least in countries with a record of repression.</p>
	<p pid="a.271.0/4"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1515" name="Geoffrey Clifton-Brown">The hon. Member for Cotswold (Mr. Clifton-Brown)</phrase>, urged me to set out the level of representation at our posts in central Asia. Essentially, we have embassies in all except Kyrgystan; I shall write to him for the sake of completeness. On the matter of the Uzbek refugees, we have made representations to the Kyrgys, Kazakhs, Russian and Ukrainian authorities to allow the United Nations high commissioner for refugees to fulfil its procedures before decisions are taken on extradition. The Government have urged the relevant authorities to continue to abide by their commitments to the United Nations conventions on refugees and against torture, and the Uzbek authorities to treat any returned refugees according to their international commitments. I raised the issue directly with the Kyrgys Foreign Minister when I met him last month.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.271.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.271.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.272.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.272.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.272.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.272.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.272.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.272.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.272.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2008" speakername="Douglas Alexander" colnum="272"  time="010:36:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060308/halltext/60308h01.htm#60308h01_spnew14">
	<p pid="a.272.2/1">The hon. Gentleman raises a timely issue. I was in Moscow only last week, and at my request I met a cross-section of the NGOs, particularly those dealing with human rights in Russia, and heard directly from some genuinely inspiring individuals the difficulties and concerns that they fear in light of the passage of the NGO law through the state Duma. It is a matter of record that through our embassy in Moscow we have raised such concerns directly with the Russian Government and members of the Duma.</p>
	<p pid="a.272.2/2">Given my conversations with the NGOs, our responsibility is to follow closely the implementation of the NGO law. It has been moderated from the original proposals. None the less, I am clear that we will focus considerably on the human rights record and the treatment of NGOs in Russia not only in the immediate weeks and months ahead in anticipation of the G8 meeting in St. Petersburg in July, but after July as well. One of the points put to me by the NGOs was that they were aware that there would be a great deal of international scrutiny in the immediate months ahead, but that their concern was to ensure that that scrutiny would continue once the international focus moved away from the Russian Government's efforts for the G8.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.272.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.272.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.272.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.272.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.273.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.273.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.274.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.274.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.274.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.274.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.274.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.274.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.275.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.275.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.275.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.275.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.276.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.276.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.276.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.276.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.276.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.276.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.276.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.276.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.277.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.277.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.277.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.277.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.279.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.279.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.279.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.279.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.279.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.279.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.280.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.280.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.280.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.280.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.280.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.280.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.280.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1830" speakername="John Pugh" colnum="280"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060308/halltext/60308h02.htm#60308h02_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.280.2/1">My hon. Friend emphasises a point that I wanted to make. Exemplary efforts have been made by local government, occasionally by big firms and even by central Government. In the previous Westminster Hall debate on this issue, which was led by my hon. Friend the Member for North Norfolk, the Under-Secretary of State for Transport, the hon. Member for Halton, pointed to a number of cases Government bodies converting their fleet to LPG or biofuel. That clearly indicates that there is considerable potential, although that potential is, by and large, unrealised.</p>
	<p pid="a.280.2/2">The key question is how we can improve things, given that we all want to do so. We have to differentiate a little between LPG and biofuels. As I understand it, LPG has a 20 per cent. advantage over biofuels. As the maths and the finances stack up, there is every chance that somebody who converts a standard two to three-year-old vehicle to LPG will recover their costs within about two to three years. It would be a blissful day if most of the vehicles that passed us on the roads were LPG powered.</p>
	<p pid="a.280.2/3">However, there are clearly availability issues as regards supply and technology, and there are also technical issues. Therefore, we must look not only at LPG, but at the prospects for biofuels. In one way, biofuels are the easiest things to encourage. Bioethanol can be added to petrol, with no substantial technological modification of the vehicle required. That is the easiest route by which to pursue cleaner and greener fuel. In many parts of the world, bioethanol is commonly added to petrol, and up to about 10 per cent. can be added with no real damage. As hon. Members probably know, the quantities of biofuel used in Brazil are absolutely enormous, and vehicles are modified to run almost totally on biofuels, with little petrol ingredient.</p>
	<p pid="a.280.2/4">If I were in the Treasury, there are two strategies that I would pursue to encourage biofuels. One might be regarded as more laid back than the other and would simply involve relying on the renewables fuel obligation and on finding a mechanism effectively to enforce it so that we hit our 5.7 per cent. target by 2010. If the Treasury did that, I guess that it might relax, and ethanol could go into the mix at about 5 per cent., or perhaps even 10 per cent. or more, and the world would not change markedly. We could visualise a day on which non-ethanol-added fuels had been gradually phased out, in the same way that leaded fuels were phased out. Indeed, I am informed that some supermarkets are already quietly adding ethanol to the fuel pumps and the customers are not noticing any substantial effect.</p>
	<p pid="a.280.2/5">If that was all that happened, there would not be a long-term effect on Treasury revenue, because taxation could gradually change from one sort of fuel to another, almost seamlessly. However, that is not necessarily the most obvious way to make progress. Technological issues may need to bottom out and supply-side issues may need to be addressed. We must accept the point that the Department made in a previous debate on the issue that not all biofuels are equally virtuous. Some are developed at the cost of rain forest, which is intrinsically undesirable. Some biofuels are not as efficient as others and, as was previously mentioned, some have to travel an appreciable distance before they reach us, and not, of course, in vehicles powered by biofuels.</p>
	<p pid="a.280.2/6">A more likely scenario is that ethanol competes head to head&mdash;or pump to pump&mdash;with other sorts of fuel for some time. That is, biofuels will compete with standard fuel and consumers will need to be tempted by a sustained price differential. According to the producers, the current price differential of about 20p is not sufficient to cover their costs or barely does so, although I guess that perhaps they would say that. One could argue that a further, more substantial cut is required. However, if that cut is made and the consumers are tempted to fill up with biofuel rather than other kinds of fuel, a large slice of the &pound;23 billion revenue that the Treasury currently receives from those of us who drive our cars from place to place will be cut.</p>
	<p pid="a.280.2/7">If a further cut was made, there would be another dilemma. Who would be rewarded best and how could the Treasury ensure that they were the right people? Would they be the virtuous consumers who chose to move from one pump to another at the forecourt, or would the oil companies benefit, simply by leaving their prices much the same and welcoming the fact that their profit margins had increased a little more? That is a dilemma for the Treasury that I am sure it will think through fairly carefully.</p>
	<p pid="a.280.2/8">None the less, there is a case for maintaining a price differential between biofuels and other fuels, in tandem with enforcing the renewable fuels obligation, rather than dramatically phasing out the differential, when we simply coerce the petrol companies into providing biofuels or as we approach the target that we wish them to achieve. There is a sound case for saying that a cliff-edge withdrawal of the price differential would not deliver the environmental benefits that we want and would lead to targets being missed.</p>
	<p pid="a.280.2/9">There is also a case for keeping and perhaps developing the system of capital allowances for those who wish to develop a plant necessary to produce the fuel. That point was underlined recently in a radio programme by the managing director of Argent, who said that without such support we might not have biofuels on a proper commercial basis. I should like the Treasury to respond to that point, because in the previous debate on the issue it was mentioned&mdash;not by the Treasury spokesman, obviously&mdash;that the Treasury was giving the matter some appreciable thought.</p>
	<p pid="a.280.2/10">I suspect that to have a truly virtuous outcome we need a combination of carrots and sticks. We need the downward thrust of the renewable fuels obligation and we need the message to go out, loud and clear, to the oil companies. However, we also need the carrot&mdash;the differential tax rates, capital grants and allowances&mdash;to ensure that supply can meet what we hope is the expected demand.</p>
	<p pid="a.280.2/11">There is a holy grail being sought. The ideal scenario from the Treasury's point of view is to secure all the environmental benefits without a slump in the tax revenue, and at the same time not suffer any other adverse economic effects, such as an effect on the balance of payments. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1739" name="Christopher Fraser">The proposal that the hon. Member for South-West Norfolk (Mr. Fraser)</phrase> made, to develop our own bioethanol industry, has an economic benefit as well as an environmental one. As we are going to use the stuff, we might as well home produce it as well. Discovering the holy grail, which I am sure is keenly sought in the Treasury, of securing environmental benefits without a consequent massive slump in revenue will take a degree of clever judgment or a Baldrick-like cunning plan. That is what I would like the Minister to address in this debate.</p>
	<p pid="a.280.2/12">However, I conclude on a slightly techie point that I have raised with the Minister before&mdash;I apologise to hon. Members for being almost wilfully obscure. The process of producing biofuel is known as esterification&mdash;I am glad that I do not have to say that too many times in this debate&mdash;but some manufacturers use a process called filtration to make biodiesel. Nothing in the Hydrocarbon Oil Duties Act 1979 explicitly states that esterification needs to be employed. Producers who use filtration argue that their product satisfies the conditions laid down in the Act and is therefore entitled to the same fiscal benefits. However, the Minister contradicted that in a written answer to me, but did not provide a wholly satisfactory explanation of why biodiesel produced through filtration should be treated differently from biodiesel produced through esterification.</p>
	<p pid="a.280.2/13">I shall leave the Minister adequate time to respond, but I appreciate that the Government have a difficult problem to address. They depend to a great extent on the duty that they receive from fuels and at the same time they have voluntarily embraced the path of environmental virtue. They must pursue both paths&mdash;fiscal probity and environmental virtue&mdash;simultaneously. That probably can be done but, without sharing Treasury modelling, it is not easy to see exactly how. However, if the Minister has a Baldrick-like cunning plan that will do the job, I would certainly like to hear about it.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.283.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.283.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.285.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.285.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.285.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.285.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.286.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.286.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.286.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.286.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.286.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.286.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.286.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.286.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.286.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.286.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.286.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.286.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.287.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.286.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.287.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.286.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.287.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.286.8" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.287.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1570" speakername="Colin Burgon" colnum="287"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060308/halltext/60308h03.htm#60308h03_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.287.2/1">Mr. Cook, I hear your wise words about the coming warm weather and about the length of our speeches. Bearing that in mind, I shall take no interventions during my speech, in the hope that hon. Members will be able to speak later.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/2">The debate is about the changes in Latin America. In this country, we talk about Africa and AIDS, about the middle east and about the growth of economic power in India and China, but Latin America is the one continent that seems to have disappeared from our radar. In talking about Latin America, the word that we should use is change, and that is the central issue of the debate. I am pleased to say that that change reflects a move to the left; Opposition Members might not share my feelings, but there we are. That left movement has many variants in countries such as Chile, Brazil, Uruguay, Bolivia and, of course, Venezuela. Indeed, I was delighted to hear the President of Brazil speak to us this morning. The content of his speech was brilliant, and I shall try to deal with it later.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/3">Latin America is a huge continent, which has always been considered to be part of the United States' backyard, and it is important that the United Kingdom does not neglect it. If we look at American history, we come across the practice of the Monroe doctrine and the idea of manifest destiny. Prior to the civil war, the southern states tried to expand the slave empire into the Caribbean and Latin America to perpetuate slavery. I am pleased to say that Lincoln and the Republicans opposed that, although Lincoln would turn in his grave if he could see his party's performance in the current context.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/4">My desire to highlight the changes in Latin America and to seek a positive response recently motivated me to ask the Prime Minister for his perspective on events in Latin America, but my diplomatic response to his answer is that I found it somewhat disappointing. Indeed, some people in Latin America found it more than disappointing, and it created a minor political tsunami. I am told that, as a result of my question, I am more famous in Latin America than in Leeds. However, like you, Mr. Cook, I am an eternal optimist and I requested this debate to enable the Government to clarify their policy towards Venezuela and clear up any confusion. That is especially relevant given what can only be described as the excruciatingly embarrassing remarks by a junior Foreign Office Minister in the columns of <i>The Times </i>on <phrase class="date" code="2002-04-13">13 April 2002</phrase>. He welcomed the overthrow of Chavez in a coup but, unfortunately for him and fortunately for the people of Venezuela, the coup collapsed one day later, when Chavez was restored to his presidency thanks to popular support. My first question to the Minister, therefore, is what efforts have been made since April 2002 to repair the damage that that comment would obviously have caused? Will he, if possible, clarify the Prime Minister's comments about the international agreements that Venezuela has supposedly not upheld?</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/5">In a general sense, it is worth asking why we should welcome good relations with Venezuela; indeed, that is the question that we are asking today. For those who like to inhabit the world of realpolitik, there is a straightforward answer. Venezuela has the largest proven conventional oil reserves in south America and the sixth largest in the world, at about 77 billion barrels. Only Saudi Arabia, Iraq, the United Arab Emirates, Kuwait and Iran have larger proven reserves. Even in the simplistic sense of having good relations with people who have something that we need, we should encourage the relationship with Venezuela.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/6">Venezuela also possesses huge reserves of heavy crude oil. During the second half of the 1990s, it was the fifth largest oil producer in the world, behind Saudi Arabia, Russia, Iran and the US. It is also a significant producer of gas and has about 3 per cent. of the world's total reserves. Interestingly, those sizeable offshore reserves are being exploited at the moment, and licences are being given to foreign companies. Contrary to the situation with oil companies, the law permits 100 per cent. foreign ownership of projects to exploit non-associated natural gas, so there is an interesting opening for people who are interested in gas, and I am sure that there are a few in this room.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/7">Venezuela is also a significant trading partner for the UK. It is our third largest export market in south America and was worth &pound;187 million in 2004. In the same year, the UK imported &pound;213 million of goods from Venezuela. Several leading British companies have investments in the Venezuelan energy sector, and in tourism, pharmaceuticals, agriculture and finance. My second question to the Minister, therefore, is, bearing all that in mind, can he outline the Government's strategy for enhancing British commercial interests in Venezuela, particularly given the strength of competition from countries such as China in the Venezuelan and wider regional market?</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/8">I would argue, however, that a Labour Government's foreign policy should be driven not just by considerations of economic self-interest, but by a shared system of political values. As I am sure you would agree, Mr. Cook, the Labour party has a long and honourable record of supporting progressive Governments around the world and of siding with movements that seek to govern in the interests of the majority and to involve the masses of people who, historically, have been ignored. Interestingly, Venezuela was the first country in Latin America to begin the process of rejecting the domination of what we call neo-liberal ideas and the Washington consensus and to experiment with ideas of anti-globalisation. Some historians take the view that the upsurge of discontent in Caracas in February 1989, which resulted in the death of roughly 1,000 people, was as important for Latin America as the fall of the Berlin wall in the same year was for Europe.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/9">Whatever the international significance of those events in Caracas, there can be no doubt that they marked the beginning of a domestic political process that eventually led to the victory of Hugo Chavez in December 1998 and catapulted Venezuela into the limelight in Latin America. That was a novel place for Venezuela, because it had previously attracted little interest in terms of its history or politics, other than as the birthplace of Simon Bolivar, although that is fairly important. According to people to whom I spoke at the Foreign Office, Venezuela was never considered an attractive diplomatic posting. The usual take was that Venezuela was an oil-rich country run by a white, Americanised elite, with nearly 70 per cent. of its 24 million people living on the edge of hunger and poverty.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/10">What was the platform on which Chavez came to power and which has caused such ructions on the continent? Given Opposition and US claims about Chavez's democratic legitimacy, it is interesting to note that he had faced the electorate eight times in six years by the end of 2004&mdash;a record that has been matched nowhere else in Latin America and which none of us would like to match. The three central themes of his programme were, first, a radical reform of the economy and, surprisingly, an emphasis on following a third way that was inspired by a certain Tony Blair. That approach was based on what Chavez called a middle road between savage neo-liberalism and failed communism. The second plank was the need to overhaul the country's institutions politically and constitutionally. The third element was the importance of diversifying trading relations away from the dependence on the United States that inevitably and unduly shaped Venezuela's development.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/11">The domestic impact of Chavez's politics is clear. After the dramatic rise in oil prices in 2002 following the failed coup, the Venezuelan Government invested more than $3 billion in social policy reforms in 2005. A series of social investment programmes called missions cover such matters as pre-school education, primary education and literacy, secondary education, vocational worker training, primary health care in the most deprived neighbourhoods and a food distribution programme that covers 60 per cent. of the population. It is estimated that just over 1 million people have acquired literacy skills as a result of those programmes. The poorest in that country have access to medical assistance for the first time ever, thanks partly to the 17,000 medics provided by Cuba.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/12">At international level, President Chavez has attempted to build and broaden links with other countries on the continent. The oil wealth of Venezuela has enabled him to develop regional energy accords with his Caribbean and Latin American neighbours to help with debt problems facing countries such as Argentina and Ecuador, and thereby reduce the influence of the International Monetary Fund in the region. He has even been able to fund regional social programmes such as mission miracle, which enables poor Latin Americans to receive free eye treatment in Venezuela and Cuba.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/13">Venezuela's increasingly active role has met with outright hostility on the part of the right-wing Republican Administration in Washington. As recently as <phrase class="date" code="2006-02-16">16 February</phrase>, Condoleezza Rice called for an &quot;international united front&quot; against Venezuela. In what can only be described as an extremely condescending comment, she said that the State Department was</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/14" class="indent">&quot;working with responsible governments, even responsible governments of the left, like the Brazilian government or the Chilean government, to try and counter these&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/15">Venezuelan&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/16" class="indent">&quot;influences.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/17">Fortunately, both those Governments have strongly rebutted Ms Rice's statements.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/18">There is great danger in the American attempt to isolate Venezuela. The issue that is playing on America's mind at the moment is links with Iran. There is no future in links with a fundamentalist Islamic regime such as Iran. It is up to the UK to use its position to argue for secular politics that unites us all. It would be bad news if Venezuela was influenced by Islamic fundamentalism coming out of Tehran, just as it would be if it was influenced by Christian fundamentalism coming out of Washington.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/19">Central to the debate is the question of who determines our foreign policy on that huge and changing continent. Can the Minister reassure me that our policy is not being subcontracted out to right-wing elements in the US, and will he show me evidence of how our policy is clearly different in this respect? Does he share my view and that of almost 100 of my parliamentary colleagues&mdash;I refer to early-day motion 1644&mdash;that all elected Governments in the region should be treated with equal respect and that the US right-wing fundamentalists should desist from efforts to destabilise the democratically elected Chavez Government?</p>
	<p pid="a.287.2/20">Having listened to President Lula of Brazil this morning, I believe it is clear that fundamental and welcome change is under way in Latin America. Venezuela is at the forefront of that process. How we determine our policy towards that nation will say much about this country. I hope that friendship, solidarity and mutual respect will mark that relationship.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.290.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.290.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.290.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.290.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.290.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.290.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.291.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.291.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.291.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.291.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.292.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.292.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.292.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.292.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.292.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.292.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.292.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1627" speakername="Jon Trickett" colnum="292"  time="014:49:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060308/halltext/60308h03.htm#60308h03_spnew9">
	<p pid="a.292.2/1">Thank you, Mr. Cook; I will try to be brief. I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1570" name="Colin Burgon">my hon. Friend the Member for Elmet (Colin Burgon)</phrase> on securing this debate on an issue that is important strategically for the part of south America that we are discussing. It is also important in terms of the way that the world is developing, given the globalisation that we are all experiencing.</p>
	<p pid="a.292.2/2">The American Administration's position might be more nuanced than is reflected in some of the more extreme and bellicose statements that emerge from time to time. Not so long ago, there were discussions that seemed to be positive between parts of that Administration and representatives of the Venezuelan Government. However, it is also true that many bellicose statements are coming out of Washington, and from very senior sources. The statement about assassinating Chavez came not from someone in the Administration, but from someone on the Republican right&mdash;I think it was Pat Robertson&mdash;but many statements have been made that lead one to be very troubled about what the American Administration's intentions are. This debate provides our Government with an opportunity to clarify their role.</p>
	<p pid="a.292.2/3">I recently read a document produced by an organisation called the Centre for Security Policy in Washington. It is doing some of the outriding&mdash;or some of the more outrageous thinking, some Members might think&mdash;in respect of Venezuela. It states that Venezuela</p>
	<p pid="a.292.2/4" class="indent">&quot;must change. It can change on its own, or it can invite hemispheric forces with the help of Venezuela's broad democratic opposition, to impose the changes. Either way U.S. strategy must be to help Venezuela accomplish peaceful change&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.292.2/5">this year. It is clear that there are extreme right-wing forces in the American Administration that will not tolerate the direction of travel of the Venezuelan Government and the international linkages that they are bringing about.</p>
	<p pid="a.292.2/6">My hon. Friend the Member for Elmet referred to the Washington consensus. I think it is true that one can perceive a world view coming out of the neo-conservative establishment. Many such neo-conservatives are closely associated with George Bush, Cheney, Rumsfeld and their colleagues. The Washington consensus implies a world in which the trade is so-called &quot;free&quot;, capital markets are entirely liberalised, property rights are secured, there is market deregulation, there is a major transfer of assets from the public to the private sectors, the state has a minimal role, and the international alliances that are created are grouped around a Washington hegemonic presence&mdash;a unipolar world. It has been explicitly stated that that is what America aspires to create. The Washington consensus also implies that America has the right to impose what it would describe as a pax Americana on the world&mdash;that it has the right to conduct unilateral and pre-emptive wars, should that be necessary. In respect of building a foreign policy on Venezuela, the question is whether our Government want to construct a set of bilateral relations that are built on the Washington consensus, or whether they will develop, with the European Union and others, a more nuanced approach.</p>
	<p pid="a.292.2/7">One problem with what Washington wants to impose on the world is that it produces an extremely divided form of development for those in what we call the third world&mdash;the developing countries. In Latin America, the richest 10 per cent. control 48 per cent. of the income, and the poorest 10 per cent. share 1.6 per cent. of the income. The Washington consensus&mdash;the neo-liberal project&mdash;produces the most divided societies imaginable. Chavez has attempted to demonstrate that there is an alternative model for development that can tackle poverty, and which, through microcredits and other detailed Government initiatives, can begin to share the wealth. In doing that, Venezuela has been able to take advantage of its oil wealth, but it has also begun to develop a set of international alliances that do not easily fit into the Washington model of a world grouped around a single pole of power&mdash;American power, based on an Republican Administration. Washington regards that as particularly threatening, and that explains the bellicose statements that have come out of elements of the Administration.</p>
	<p pid="a.292.2/8">Chavez and the Venezuelan Government are demonstrating that it is possible to develop a set of international relationships that do not fit into the Washington consensus. What will the UK Government and the EU do? How will they respond to that? I hope that the UK Government are able to establish a line that does not simply support the idea of an unipolar world&mdash;of a single economic and military interest&mdash;and that instead they will develop a much more complex approach to Venezuela and the Latin American continent. I hope that we can play a positive role by sitting alongside Venezuela and the other nations in that region that are following a different strategy for developing and spreading out the wealth than the one that Washington seeks to impose on the world.</p>
	<p pid="a.292.2/9">I notice that I have been speaking for six minutes and 18 seconds, so I shall now sit down.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.293.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.293.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.293.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.293.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.293.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.293.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.294.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.294.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.294.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.294.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.295.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.295.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.295.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.295.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.295.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.295.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.297.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.297.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.297.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.297.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.297.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.297.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.299.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.299.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.299.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.299.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.299.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.299.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.299.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.299.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.300.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.300.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.300.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.300.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.300.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.300.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.301.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.301.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.302.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.302.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.304.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.304.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.304.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1515" speakername="Geoffrey Clifton-Brown" colnum="304"  time="015:32:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060308/halltext/60308h03.htm#60308h03_spnew30">
	<p pid="a.304.0/1">I am glad to respond for the official Opposition for the second time today in this Chamber. I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1570" name="Colin Burgon">the hon. Member for Elmet (Colin Burgon)</phrase> on securing the debate. There have been some excellent contributions, and I hope that the message that comes out of this debate will be that this House is not too polarised about Venezuela. It is clearly in this country's interests to have excellent relations with Venezuela. It is the world's fifth largest oil producer, as we have already heard, there is huge potential for export there&mdash;to which I shall allude in a minute&mdash;and we have a great many imports from it, too.</p>
	<p pid="a.304.0/2">Indeed we have had good relations with Venezuela for a considerable time&mdash;after all, Simon Bolivar visited this country as Venezuela's liberator as long ago as 1810, and President Chavez visited the UK as the guest of the British Government in October 2001. In return, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1616" name="Bill Rammell">the hon. Member for Harlow (Bill Rammell)</phrase>, when he was a Foreign Office Minister, visited Venezuela in 2004, and the Venezuelan Minister for Energy and Mines visited the UK in that same year. It is very much in our interests to maintain those good relations.</p>
	<p pid="a.304.0/3">I am going to pull the leg of the hon. Member for Elmet slightly, because I want to refer to his <phrase class="date" code="2006-02-17">17 February</phrase> article in <i>The Guardian. </i>He referred to the Prime Minister's answer during Prime Minister's questions by saying:</p>
	<p pid="a.304.0/4" class="indent"><i>&quot;</i>The Prime Minister's response surprised many of us on the Labour benches. Skilled diplomat that he undoubtedly is, Blair's response seemingly lacked any nuance of diplomacy.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.304.0/5">We would all say &quot;amen&quot; to that. It was clearly listened to in Caracas, and the unfortunate comments that came from there in response have not been helpful to UK-Venezuelan relations.</p>
	<p pid="a.304.0/6">I almost agreed entirely with the final paragraph of the article. The hon. Member for Elmet stated:</p>
	<p pid="a.304.0/7" class="indent">&quot;It is time that the UK re-engaged with Latin America and offered moral support to regimes intent on social justice and&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.304.0/8">the one bit that I do not agree with&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.304.0/9" class="indent">&quot;redistribution of wealth. In light of our participation in the invasion of Iraq and global perception of UK foreign policy, I believe it is highly advisable to employ constructive language and diplomacy&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.304.0/10">&mdash;which is what I hope we have achieved in this debate&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.304.0/11" class="indent">&quot;so that this country can interact with other sovereign states with an independent, open and progressive agenda. UK foreign policy should not be allowed to be hijacked by other states acting in their own interests, which may not be compatible with our own.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.304.0/12">Perhaps, therefore, some of the comments that have come out of Washington are not helpful either. We obtain&mdash;I learned from a parliamentary answer&mdash;only some 2.2 to 2.4 per cent. of our oil imports from Venezuela, but the United States imports a million barrels a day, so it is a very big customer of that country.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.305.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.305.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.305.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.305.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.306.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.306.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.306.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.306.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.306.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.306.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.306.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.306.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.306.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.306.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.306.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.306.5" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.306.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1515" speakername="Geoffrey Clifton-Brown" colnum="306"  time="015:32:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060308/halltext/60308h03.htm#60308h03_spnew38">
	<p pid="a.306.5/1">I would simply say that I hope that all countries&mdash;particularly oil-rich countries such as Venezuela&mdash;will encourage a climate in which inward investment from foreign countries is welcome. If I have time, I should like to show that inward investment in the Venezuelan oil industry is desperately needed. It could be much more effective if it had such investment, and it would then produce more revenues for the people of Venezuela. What President Chavez did was not necessarily helpful.</p>
	<p pid="a.306.5/2">A lot of comments have been made in this debate about the economy, and it is difficult to know whether it is performing well. With high oil prices, it could do much better. An article in <i>The Economist </i>of <phrase class="date" code="2006-02-16">16 February</phrase> stated:</p>
	<p pid="a.306.5/3" class="indent">&quot;Higher prices have quadrupled Venezuela's annual revenue from oil exports since 1998. Nevertheless, the country's Catholic bishops claimed last month that poverty was 'accelerating rapidly'. Not so, replied Mr Chavez. It has 'begun to decrease slowly and progressively'.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.306.5/4">So we can choose whom we wish to believe. The article goes on to say:</p>
	<p pid="a.306.5/5" class="indent">&quot;In the five years to 2003, Mr. Chavez's performance was disastrous (see chart).&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.306.5/6">The chart does tend to indicate that the oil price has gone up, yet poverty has also increased, so there is something slightly wrong there.</p>
	<p pid="a.306.5/7" class="indent">&quot;The proportion of households below the poverty line increased by more than 11 percentage points. By 2003, a quarter of Venezuelans were living in 'extreme poverty', unable even to feed themselves adequately. It was the first time since data were collected that poverty rose even as the oil price did too.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.306.5/8"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1655" name="Jeremy Corbyn">The hon. Member for Islington, North (Jeremy Corbyn)</phrase> has described the so-called missions, which are President Chavez's personal missions to engage in emergency health, education and welfare programmes. There are conflicting stories about those programmes, but they certainly are not democratically accountable. They do not appear to be as effective as they might be. Indeed, the article went on to say:</p>
	<p pid="a.306.5/9" class="indent">&quot;Whatever the merits of the missions as emergency programmes, they stress quantity over quality. Meanwhile, Venezuela's public infrastructure, such as roads and hospitals, is crumbling. A deficit of 1.5 million housing units is widening. Only a quarter of the 11,000 new houses needed each year are being built, because of the public sector's incompetence and its unwillingness to involve the private sector.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.306.5/10">That may well be. I respect <i>The Economist</i>; it is one of the most respected journals for producing balanced articles. It may be that the person who wrote that had a biased view, but there is no doubt in my mind that the Venezuelan economy could perform better.</p>
	<p pid="a.306.5/11">Another article in <i>The Economist&mdash;</i>it might be by the same author; I do not know&mdash;on <phrase class="date" code="2006-01-31">31 January 2006</phrase> stated:</p>
	<p pid="a.306.5/12" class="indent">&quot;Fiscal profligacy will keep the public finances in deficit, despite high oil prices.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.306.5/13">It continued:</p>
	<p pid="a.306.5/14" class="indent">&quot;Most non-oil investment will continue to be put off by the uncertain legal and regulatory regimes and by price and exchange controls . . . The Ministry of Finance has been overborrowing in recent months, and has built up substantial Treasury cash balances&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.306.5/15">As has been mentioned, President Chavez has taken on other south American countries' debts. For example, Venezuela has taken on &pound;538 million of Argentine debt. The same pertains to Ecuador.</p>
	<p pid="a.306.5/16">The President is trying to use the oil wealth to buy influence. That is not unprecedented elsewhere, provided it is done in a benign way. I hope that we can see that it is done in a benign way. We can see from this constructive debate that it is important that south America should be brought to the fore in this Parliament more often and more positively. We have always had good trading relationships with south America and they are, on the whole, friends of ours. We should maintain good trading and diplomatic links, and the debate has been a helpful and positive step. I hope that we can now reach more normal relations after the unfortunate remarks made in past months.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.307.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.307.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.310.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.310.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.311.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.311.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.311.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.311.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.311.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.311.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.311.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.311.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.311.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.311.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.311.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.311.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.312.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.312.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.312.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.312.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.315.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.315.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.316.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.316.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.317.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.317.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.317.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1472" speakername="Harriet Harman" colnum="317"  time="016:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060308/halltext/60308h04.htm#60308h04_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.317.0/1">I take my hon. Friend's point entirely that if one is exonerated in a quicker and more expedited way, one none the less does not qualify for the section 133 statutory payment. I shall consider that further, particularly as to whether there is a gap such as he has described.</p>
	<p pid="a.317.0/2">I have explained the discretionary scheme. There is also a provision that the Lord Chancellor has been prepared to consider requests for ex gratia payments in cases in which a judicial office holder has demonstrated some sort of personal misconduct. I want to mention also the new scheme for judicial complaints. In the past, Lord Chancellors have taken seriously cases in which Members of Parliament or members of the public have complained to them about judges, but one problem with that is that it has not been visible. Just as when the Court of Appeal makes a complaint about a judge it might be taken up by the presiding judge, the Lord Chancellor might have taken up such an issue with a judge, but nobody would know about it. That is one issue that the Constitutional Reform Act 2005 was introduced to address, so that while assuring the independence of the judiciary, we bring such complaints out of the polite and private world of the Inns of Court and gentlemen's clubs into proper transparency and accountability.</p>
	<p pid="a.317.0/3">The reforms in the Act come into effect in April. A major plank of the reforms is the introduction of a statutory regime governing the investigation of allegations of judges' personal misconduct. The Lord Chancellor and the Lord Chief Justice will have joint responsibility for the scheme and for a new office of judicial complaints, which will be operational from <phrase class="date" code="">3 April</phrase>. The office will support them in that new role and regarding the introduction of proper rules and regulations. Any regulations will be laid before Parliament so that, as with any other important system, one can see what the rules are and which bodies will apply them.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.317.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.317.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.317.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.317.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.319.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.319.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.319.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="319"  time="016:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060308/halltext/60308h05.htm#60308h05_head0">
	Defence Procurement
</major-heading>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.319.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.319.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.320.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.320.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.320.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.320.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.322.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.322.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.322.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1976" speakername="Adam Ingram" speakeroffice="The Minister of State, Ministry of Defence"  colnum="322"  time="016:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060308/halltext/60308h05.htm#60308h05_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.322.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1451" name="Ian Liddell-Grainger">the hon. Member for Bridgwater (Mr. Liddell-Grainger)</phrase> on securing this debate and on providing me with the opportunity to speak on these important issues. I acknowledge the hon. Gentleman's expertise and his involvement&mdash;the role he has played in Her Majesty's armed forces. I also pay tribute to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1715" name="Mark Lancaster">the hon. Member for North-East Milton Keynes (Mr. Lancaster)</phrase> on the role he has played.</p>
	<p pid="a.322.0/2">As the hon. Member for Bridgwater will be aware, we discussed procurement generally in depth in a defence debate on <phrase class="date" code="2006-02-02">2 February</phrase>. We largely dealt with the recently published defence industrial strategy&mdash;the DIS&mdash;and the progress we were making on our major programmes. That, of course, affects the way procurement in this country is managed and run in the future. The hon. Gentleman raised a number of issues and some of them fall within the ambit of the DIS, so I think it is worth setting that out again. He has made some trenchant criticisms of past procurement, and many of the points he made have been taken on board by the present Government. We have learned lessons and we are trying to put in place a new construct to assist us. If I briefly touch on the DIS, I hope that it will give the hon. Gentleman comfort in respect of some of the areas of tangential concern that he raised.</p>
	<p pid="a.322.0/3">We published the DIS on <phrase class="date" code="">15 December</phrase>. It has been well received across industry and by the trade unions. There has been a general welcome for it in this House and the other place, recognising the new partnership between industry and the Government on which it is based. The DIS gives industry, for the first time, real clarity on what we require, how we will go about obtaining that and how we can maintain onshore those elements of industry that are fundamental to our national security. In some sectors, the market is healthily competitive; in others, such as maritime and guided weapons, change is unquestionably required. Industry must make its commercial decisions in responding to the DIS, but we expect companies to show leadership by aligning their businesses to the realities of the future.</p>
	<p pid="a.322.0/4">Maintaining the ability to support and upgrade the significant programme of new platforms and new equipment that we are bringing into service will be crucial. We clearly cannot afford a cradle-to-grave industry in all sectors. However, the higher-value areas&mdash;those that provide the most secure and interesting careers&mdash;are often the very ones in which we need to keep our freedom of military action.</p>
	<p pid="a.322.0/5">We have taken the bold step of setting out the realities, which many would say is long overdue, and we have done so early enough for companies to be able to plan for the transition to a sustainable future while they are well employed. It was John F. Kennedy who said, &quot;The time to fix the roof is when the sun is shining.&quot; I am pleased to report that industry and the Ministry of Defence are wasting no time in implementing the DIS.</p>
	<p pid="a.322.0/6">I think the hon. Member for Bridgwater was seeking to claim the moral high ground and to call into question perhaps not the integrity but the capacity of BAE Systems. May I remind him of some of the history? The royal ordnance factories were vested as Royal Ordnance plc on <phrase class="date" code="1985-01-02">2 January 1985</phrase>, and a major transition took place at that time. BAE Systems took it over in 1987. It is worth bearing it in mind that there have been closures of significant parts of that enterprise over the years. To mention just a few, Enfield closed in 1988; Patricroft closed in 1989, as did Waltham Abbey; and Westcott closed in 1994. That was well before the time of this Administration and well before my time.</p>
	<p pid="a.322.0/7">Was the realm threatened as a consequence? No, it was not. Why was that action required? To answer that, I would have to examine some of the issues, but there was probably a need for rationalisation, a better way of delivering what needed to be delivered. The then Conservative Government understood that that had to be examined and tested, and the decisions were taken. The very fact of closure is no sign of disrespect to those who have shown commitment and delivered a high-quality service in years past. Sometimes, closure is needed to ensure the best delivery. Much of what we are doing now involves taking the same factors into account. We are, of course, doing much more besides.</p>
	<p pid="a.322.0/8">The defence industrial strategy provided clarity on the MOD's thinking in a variety of sectors, including general munitions. In it, we recognised explicitly the military importance of general munitions. I do not believe that there is any difference between us on that. Paragraph B6.3 on page 95 states that</p>
	<p pid="a.322.0/9" class="indent">&quot;quality general munitions, including Small Arms Ammunition, are essential to provide the volumes of fire and the 24 hour, all weather capability required to suppress, neutralise and demoralise enemy forces&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.322.0/10">The hon. Gentleman knows better than I do what that means in practice.</p>
	<p pid="a.322.0/11">The chapter outlined critical capabilities that we want to retain and develop in the industrial base, which included the manufacture of certain munitions&mdash;not all but particularly insensitive munitions and polymer bonded explosives to ensure that the safety hazards inherent in those weapons are as low as is reasonably practicable. We consulted industry throughout the process.</p>
	<p pid="a.322.0/12">The hon. Gentleman will know that BAE Systems provides us with the majority&mdash;80 per cent. of repeat buys&mdash;of our general munitions capability under a long-term framework partnering agreement dating back to 1999. The FPA has provided us with security of supply and contributed to the delivery of an effective general munitions capability that has stood the test of numerous operations since its inception. However, given the particular importance of munitions to our overall military capability, this is an area where we cannot afford to stand still, and we are continually reviewing how best to ensure security of supply&mdash;that is uppermost in our mind&mdash;and the best value for money for the taxpayer. That is no different from the situation in all those years past when the general munitions environment was undergoing such radical change.</p>
	<p pid="a.322.0/13">As part of that ongoing work and coincident with the DIS work, we reaffirmed last September our long-term requirement for general munitions and signed a partnering principles agreement with BAE Systems setting out how we might work together in the future. That was informed by our DIS capability assessments. We set out the assessments and then talked to industry to ascertain whether we could apply that partnering arrangement, which applies to general munitions, consistently across a range of platform and other equipment deliveries.</p>
	<p pid="a.322.0/14">As a consequence of those decisions, BAE Systems made commercial decisions involving the closure of two of its munitions sites at Chorley and Bridgwater&mdash;Bridgwater, obviously, being the hon. Gentleman's constituency. I can well understand his concern about the Bridgwater site, but I should point out that this is a commercial decision for the company as it responds to the wider market place and the DIS, and considers what is best for defence as a whole.</p>
	<p pid="a.322.0/15">I should make it absolutely clear that we have taken steps to ensure that our military capability will not be weakened by this process. We have worked hard with the company and received the assurances that we need about safeguarding the supply of material, which will no longer be directly provided by BAE Systems as a result of its decisions. So we have put all that under test, using the same criteria as were laid down by the hon. Gentleman. The company wrote to the Defence Committee on <phrase class="date" code="2006-02-13">13 February</phrase> this year, elaborating in detail on the safeguards that we have jointly agreed. No doubt that will be given due weight by the Committee when it reports.</p>
	<p pid="a.322.0/16">As part of the guarantee, BAE Systems is establishing a strategic stockpile of Bridgwater-produced material to support our forces for the foreseeable future. That is an important aspect; as well as taking the assurances and guarantees, we also have a stockpile so that we can sustain our needs into the foreseeable future. The company also discussed with us how it will undertake its assessments when sourcing material from overseas, and made it clear that secure sources of supply will be a key factor in any decisions. We strongly support the company's efforts to raise efficiency across its business in general and, in particular, to create a sustainable future for general munitions production in the UK, while ensuring value for money for the taxpayer.</p>
	<p pid="a.322.0/17">The partnering principles also give the opportunity to improve the delivery of military capability to the armed forces. The BAE Systems site at Glascoed in south Wales will become a centre of excellence in the development of insensitive munitions materials such as PBX, which I mentioned earlier. There will be considerable investment at the Glascoed site to allow that to take place. It is not as if we are throwing everything out; indeed, we are satisfied that the company has taken rational decisions, and it is also investing in key capabilities.</p>
	<p pid="a.322.0/18">The hon. Gentleman should be aware that the Department is also in partnering arrangements with other munitions suppliers such as Wallop Defence Systems, based in the UK, and Rheinmetall AG, based in Germany. To sum up on the issue of munitions: our work in this area will provide better capability at better value for money in this important sector.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.325.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.325.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08a.325.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-03-08b.325.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

