<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">

<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >

<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >

<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >

<!ENTITY euro "&#8364;" >
]>

<publicwhip>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.75.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="75"  time="unknown" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm">
	[Mr. John McWilliam in the Chair]
</minor-heading>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.75.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="75"  time="unknown" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_head0">
	Burma
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.75.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="75"  time="unknown" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_head0">
	<p class="italic">Motion made, and Question proposed, That the sitting be now adjourned.&mdash;[Ms Bridget Prentice.]</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.75.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1059" speakername="Iain Luke" colnum="75"  time="09:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spnew0">
	<p>This is a debate that I, and many others, have been trying to secure for some time. It was the reason behind my question to the Leader of the House on 12 June during business questions. In requesting such a debate, I drew his attention to the concerns of 250 Members from both sides of the House, and of people throughout the UK, about the subject of early-day motions 1296, 1311 and 1316, which relate to the taking into protective custody of Aung San Suu Kyi. Since then, the number of Members who have signed those early-day motions has grown to 335, which is more than half the membership of the House. I am therefore grateful that Mr. Speaker has used his discretion to select this topic for general debate.</p>
	<p>It is good to have an opportunity to raise concerns that are held by hon. Members of all parties about the continuing oppressive regime in Burma. In 1990, that regime removed, and has repressed ever since, the legitimately elected Government of Burma, and it stifles and puts in prison anyone who dares to campaign for a return to the democratic ideals that were so overwhelmingly endorsed in elections. Outwith the three early-day motions that I have mentioned, during this Session another five have been tabled, subscribed to by 316 Members. They all give voice to the concerns that we all feel about how the military regime maintains power. Eight early-day motions over a parliamentary Session is testimony to the depth of feeling in the House about the circumstances of Burma.</p>
	<p>Events during the past month have meant that today's debate comes at a crucial time. Since the taking into protective custody of Aung San Suu Kyi, after a year of what could be called relative freedom, we have witnessed a swift return to retrenchment and repression. We need to renew our efforts and commitment both here at Westminster and further afield to sending a message to the regime&mdash;however isolated it is&mdash;that enough is enough. It should now stand aside to allow the country it so severely misgoverns, the people it so brutally represses and the ethnic groups it so viciously attacks and abuses to achieve what they undoubtedly deserve and desire: democratic normalcy.</p>
	<p>I hope that today's debate will give added urgency to the efforts of our Government and of our allies to unite and apply the pressure that they can collectively muster on the military regime that has illegally controlled Burma for such a long time. As the secretary of the all-party group on democracy in Burma, I am especially glad to lead the debate. Unfortunately, the chair of the group, my hon. and learned Friend the Member for Redcar (Vera Baird), who has been active in this field, cannot be with us this morning because of constituency business.</p>
	<p>One of the prime reasons for establishing the all-party group was to act as a focus for parliamentary efforts in a campaign to bring about a peaceful change to the way in which Burma is governed. As ordinary parliamentarians, we want to do all we can to encourage the early establishment of a viable, democratic Government based on parliamentary democracy. That is a cause that Nobel peace prize winner, Aung San Suu Kyi, with her brave long-term commitment to, and consequent long-term imprisonment for, the campaign for freedom and democracy in Burma, has done so much so selflessly to advance. With her release just a year ago from arrest, when she spoke of a new dawn, we all hoped that change was coming. Her recent arrest and imprisonment in the notorious Insein prison, and the crackdown on her party, the National League for Democracy, and other groups campaigning for democratic change show how misplaced those hopes were and make it clear that there is now a need for a trumpet call to further action.</p>
	<p>It is right at this stage, on the threshold of new activity, that I pay tribute on behalf of the all-party group to the many groups and individuals outside Parliament who have done so much in past decades to keep alive the cause of Suu Kyi and her fight for democracy in Burma. I also acknowledge the assistance and stimulus given to the all-party group by the Burma Campaign UK, which has done so much to spearhead a very successful disinvestment campaign in the UK.</p>
	<p>I also publicly thank all those individuals, local Amnesty International groups and Church-based organisations that have contacted me in the past six months to draw to my attention and to that of the group the plight of the thousands of individuals unjustly and illegally imprisoned because of their belief in and support of the ideals of human rights and popular democracy. Unfortunately, they suffer for their beliefs and are jailed in notorious prisons throughout Burma. We hope to draw attention to their situation at the meeting of the all-party group next week to be held jointly with the all-party group on human rights, at which Mark Farmaner of the Burma Campaign UK will lead a discussion on human rights in Burma.</p>
	<p>I wish to make very clear our respect and appreciation of how my hon. Friend the Minister, the Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs, the officials who staff the south-east Asia desk in the Foreign and Commonwealth Office and the ambassador in Burma have handled the current crisis and have attempted during my time as a parliamentarian to bring pressure for change on the military regime.</p>
	<p>I also personally thank my hon. Friend the Minister for intervening to arrange an opportunity for my hon. and learned Friend the Member for Redcar and me to meet the Burmese ambassador. We are now in touch with his office and hope to be able to raise with him directly in the next few weeks our concerns about the plight of all those who are imprisoned in Burma, but specifically Suu Kyi. We also hope to take the opportunity at that meeting to clarify the comments of the Burmese Foreign Minister, U Win Aung, who spoke about Suu Kyi's imminent release at the recent meeting of the Association of South East Asian Nations in Phnom Penh.</p>
	<p>In making these points, I realise that the UK can do little on its own to effect real change, but the Government can follow the good advice given by UN Special Commissioner Rezali to my hon. and learned Friend the Member for Redcar and me when we met him during his last visit to the UK. He said that we must put whatever pressure we can on Burma's major trading partners, the ASEAN countries, to build on the attitudes that they were beginning to display at their last meeting, which, while falling short of direct criticism of Burma, made it clear that they were unhappy about the recent repressive acts embarked on by the Burmese Government.</p>
	<p>In the words of ASEAN's secretary-general, Ong Keng Yong, all ASEAN members would like Suu Kyi to be free to do what she would like to do. She has made it very clear that she would like to bring about democratic change in Burma, and that is something that all members of ASEAN can support, as we do. As an all-party group, we hope&mdash;again, through the good offices of the FCO&mdash;to have an early opportunity to raise our concerns with the ambassadors in London of ASEAN countries. They hold regular meetings to discuss areas of common concern, and we hope to put to them the case for their added involvement in bringing about democratic change in Burma.</p>
	<p>Through colleagues and friends in the European Parliament who are sympathetic to our cause, the all-party group hopes to spread that kind of lobbying through all the member states of the European Union so that MEPs do the same thing to the ambassadors of the ASEAN countries in their countries. That, I hope, will bring about a change of attitude in the ASEAN group.</p>
	<p>I also hope that the Government will take up the matter again with Burma's closest trading partners, India and Bangladesh&mdash;who are not members of the ASEAN group&mdash;with whom, I believe, we have some influence. The circumstances in India and Burma could hardly be more different. They came to independence within a year of each other, but India has prospered from 50 years of stable democracy, while Burma has been stifled and has regressed in 40 years of military oppression.</p>
	<p>In parallel with the initiatives in international diplomacy, the Government should give more prominence to the promotion of the disinvestment campaign being waged by the Burma Campaign UK. In that context, we welcome the Prime Minister's strong reply to a question put to him during Question Time last week by my hon. Friend the Member for Glasgow, Maryhill (Ann McKechin). He suggested that there was a need to take a stronger line with British companies investing in Burma.</p>
	<p>The next target in the campaign is clear: it is the company with the biggest British investment in Burma, British American Tobacco. We need to campaign jointly to persuade that company to disinvest. No one could have put the arguments for disinvestment better than BAT's vice-chairman himself, the right hon. and learned Member for Rushcliffe (Mr. Clarke). He made the point forcefully in a letter to a constituent, in which he said that he</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;sometimes feels uncomfortable about investment&quot;</p>
	<p>in Burma, and that the problem in Burma arises</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;when companies start collaborating with an extremely unpleasant regime which is totally contrary to our notions of civil liberties and democracy&quot;.</p>
	<p>Surely, the events of the past few weeks show that the regime cannot get any more unpleasant; nor can the activities and ideology&mdash;if there is one&mdash;of the Government of General Than Shwe be viewed as anything other than totally contrary to all the notions of civil liberties and democracy that we hold dear in this country. It is now time for the board of BAT and its vice-chairman to do the right and honourable thing, put principle before profit, and take the decision to disinvest from Burma today. Anything that the Government can do to aid us in our campaign will be very welcome.</p>
	<p>I would like to deal with the plight of the numerous ethnic groups, who make up more than 20 per cent. of the Burmese population, and who have faced years of genocide and repression by the regime. As a group, we are being kept closely in touch with the continuing brutal campaign against these groups by the Burmese army&mdash;which is partially being undertaken, it appears, to create the economic infrastructure to enable western industrial concerns to make a profit out of their trading relationships and partnerships within that country. As a consequence, hundreds of thousands of people have been dispossessed, forced to flee and take refuge in the refugee camps just over the border in Thailand. I am sure that some hon. Members who contribute today will be able to give personal accounts of their visits to those refugee camps. Many of the NGOs that attend the all-party parliamentary group meetings are involved in providing aid and advocacy for the refugees and the separate ethnic groupings.</p>
	<p>Whatever happens as a result of our campaign to bring about the restoration of democracy, whether it succeeds or fails, the groups and their welfare must continue to be a priority for ourselves as parliamentarians and for the Government. When change is achieved, as it surely eventually must be, the rights, aspirations, autonomy and welfare of all Burmese people and all the minorities there must be safeguarded and protected by law and by a new constitution for a new Burma, which we wish to see rising like a phoenix from the ashes and the poverty of the present anarchic economic system of military government.</p>
	<p>My first awareness of Burma came from my father's wartime reminiscences, as a Burma Star veteran who fought at Kohima, crossed the Irrawaddy, and ended up in Mandalay, in what was often referred to as Slim's forgotten 14th Army. Burma and its domestic situation continue to be a distant, forgotten area of interest for many in the UK and throughout the world. Having said that, I readily acknowledge the consistent efforts of the present Government to reverse that situation. I hope that they take encouragement from this debate and from the constructive suggestions made on how to proceed, and on how parliamentarians can assist them.</p>
	<p>I am glad to have been able to set today's debate in motion. I look forward to hearing the contributions of the many Members who have come along to take part, and the Minister's considered, concluding reply. The campaign goes on. In conclusion, I ask you, Mr. Deputy Speaker, to thank Mr. Speaker for using his discretion to allow this very important debate to go ahead today.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.79.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1245" speakername="Bob Spink" colnum="79"  time="09:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spnew1">
	<p>I congratulate the hon. Member for Dundee, East (Mr. Luke). He was right to ask for this debate, which is long overdue. I am delighted to be able to contribute.</p>
	<p>I agree with all that the hon. Gentleman said, so I shall try not to repeat it. Much Government and international concern about Burma has been focused on the plight of the pro-democracy movement and the arrest of Aung San Suu Kyi. While those are very important issues, relatively little international focus has been given to the systematic atrocities inflicted by the Burmese military on the Karen, Karenni and Shan ethnic peoples, so I shall focus on that issue.</p>
	<p>The atrocities include summary executions, rape, forced relocations, destruction of villages and crops, and forced labour. More than 650,000 Karen, Karenni and Shan have been internally displaced and more than 200,000 refugees have fled to Thailand. They initially had good treatment from Thailand, but I think that the Thai Government now need to refocus on the treatment given to those groups on the Thai-Burmese border. They should ensure that they are not seeking to extradite them back to the Burmese military regime, where they will suffer atrocities in the border region, and that the international community can get food and medical aid to the internally displaced people there. I thank the Thai Government for what they have done, but I ask them to look at what is happening at the moment. They have lost a little focus, and perhaps they could refocus on the humanitarian problems.</p>
	<p>Many displaced people are hiding in the jungle with little or no food or medicine, and they are sometimes shot on sight by Burmese troops. I can think of no other country in the world where so many displaced people are subjected to a shoot on sight policy, which is utterly unacceptable. The human rights group the Jubilee Campaign believes that the systematic atrocities against ethnic minorities by the Burmese military amount to genocide, crimes against humanity and war crimes as defined under international law. I agree with that assessment. Burma's regime is not only anti-democratic, it is also an evil, criminal regime, which has committed and continues to commit serious crimes under international law. I have visited some internally displaced Karen people in Burma, and was appalled to hear their first-hand witness accounts of the many atrocities that their people have suffered.</p>
	<p>The British Government and European Union have measured progress in Burma mainly by focusing on whatever improvements have taken place in political developments, including the release of political prisoners and progress in democratic reforms. While those are very important, the prisoners represent fewer than 1,000 people and it is deeply disturbing that the British Government are not treating the systematic atrocities against the Karen, Karenni and Shan people as just as important, particularly in view of the hundreds of thousands involved. Those people might not have a voice or international clout in the way that Aung San Suu Kyi and the political prisoners have, but each life is important.</p>
	<p>In the Foreign Office's human rights annual report 2002, the last two lines of the section on Burma state:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;We shall continue to respond proportionately to political developments in Burma. But should progress stall or fail, our policy will . . . harden.&quot;</p>
	<p>There is reference only to political developments and not to the possibility of hardening British policy on Burma because of the military regime's atrocities against the ethnic minorities. Ministers have not been in the Burmese jungle recently, as I have, but they will be aware of witnesses' reports of the atrocities and deprivation experienced by hundreds of thousands of people from ethnic groups in the Burmese jungle.</p>
	<p>The Government have refused to accept that the Karen, Karenni and Shan are facing genocide, but curiously they have never given detailed or clear reasons why. It is not enough for the Government to claim, as they have in the past, that Amnesty International has not called the human rights abuses genocide. Amnesty's researcher on Burma stated clearly only last week that he has not investigated whether it is genocide. Amnesty has simply not addressed the issue. If the Government believe that there is no genocide in Burma, they should give detailed reasons for that conclusion, including reasons for believing that the legal definition of genocide given in the 1948 convention on the prevention and punishment of crimes of genocide does not fit the facts of the Karen, Karenni and Shan situation, which I can testify to because I have seen it at first hand.</p>
	<p>For many years, unarmed Karen, Karenni and Shan civilians have been deliberately killed by Burmese soldiers in what is clearly a blatant breach of common article 3 of the Geneva convention, which specifically prohibits the killing of civilians who do not take an active part in hostilities. Those atrocities have been well documented by the UN special rapporteur on Burma and by several independent human rights groups, including Amnesty International, the Jubilee Campaign, the Karen Human Rights Group and the Shan Human Rights Foundation. It is, therefore, obvious that war crimes are being inflicted on the Karen, Karenni and Shan, and that in itself should be enough to justify the UN Security Council setting up an international criminal tribunal to try Burma's military regime. That would certainly focus the regime's mind. Furthermore, the International Labour Organisation in its report on Burma states that the systematic use of forced labour amounts to a crime against humanity. That gives us yet another reason why an international criminal tribunal on Burma could and should be set up.</p>
	<p>With the detention of Aung San Suu Kyi, the Italian Foreign Affairs Minister, Margherita Boniver, said that the European Union will consider in detail the possibility of submitting the issue to the UN Security Council. The Government should ensure that any such considerations by the EU include submitting to the UN Security Council the State Peace and Development Council's systematic atrocities against the ethnic minorities. While the plight of Aung San Suu Kyi and political prisoners in Burma is grave&mdash;we all know that and want to do something about it&mdash;the situation of the Karen, Karenni and Shan is much worse, with rape, torture and summary executions being typical of what they must endure, not to mention the destruction of their villages, which drives them into a jungle existence without proper food, education for their children or medical care. I spoke to a child who looked about nine or 10, but was 14 and had never had a day's education. They do not even have clean water. I met that child as she was walking two miles to collect water in an old petrol can.</p>
	<p>The solution to the desperate plight of the ethnic minorities is not simply to wait until democracy comes to Burma. No one knows when that will happen, and it may take some time. The ethnic minorities are engaged in a daily and desperate struggle to survive, and they need our help now. Thousands have died as a result of Burmese military atrocities, and thousands more will perish unless the international community acts right now to put maximum pressure on the Burmese regime to stop the killings.</p>
	<p>European Union sanctions against Burma should be linked not only to the Burmese regime's conduct regarding political prisoners and democratic reform, but to its stopping its atrocities against ethnic minorities. It should be given a clear message by the British Government and the EU that unless it stops the atrocities, sanctions will get a lot tougher. Furthermore, the Government should urgently raise the plight of the Karen, Karenni and Shan at the UN Security Council, where they should lobby for a global arms and investment embargo against Burma. The British Government should also ban all new investment by British companies in Burma, as has been done in the US, and call on the UN Security Council to set up an international criminal tribunal to try the Burmese regime for war crimes, crimes against humanity, and genocide.</p>
	<p>The hon. Member for Dundee, East rightly mentioned BAT in his speech. The chairman of BAT, Martin Broughton, told the media,</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;We'll do business in countries if it is legal to do so.&quot;</p>
	<p>That proves the hon. Gentleman's point that nothing short of a legal ban on investment will stop British companies. Exhortations from the Prime Minister will help, but they will not stop those companies, as the chairman of BAT has said.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.81.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1138" speakername="Mike O'Brien" speakeroffice="The Minister for Trade and Investment"  colnum="81"  time="09:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spmin0">
	<p>The hon. Gentleman is talking about British companies, in the plural. From my inquiries, I am not aware that more than one British company&mdash;BAT&mdash;is involved.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.81.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1245" speakername="Bob Spink" colnum="81"  time="09:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spnew2">
	<p>I acknowledge the Minister's point. Premier Oil has withdrawn, but it withdrew because of economic pressures and not because of exhortations from the Government. If the Government had a formal policy to make it illegal for companies to trade with Burma, it would give a clear signal to the international community and to Burma. It would also give a signal to countries near Burma with which we trade such as Thailand. Without strong sanctions, it is difficult to get the Burmese regime to take our concerns about human rights and democracy seriously. Short of military force, the only sanctions are a criminal tribunal or trade sanctions, and I encourage the Minister to think about them carefully.</p>
	<p>The Burmese regime has made great play of the release of political prisoners and the secret dialogue with the National League for Democracy. However, we must focus on what is happening to the ethnic minorities in the jungle as a result of abuses by the Burmese military. Formalised trade sanctions and an international tribunal are the best ways to protect ethnic minorities and to force the military regime to democratise, which would allow us to move forward in Burma.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.82.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1203" speakername="Joan Ruddock" colnum="82"  time="09:58:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spnew3">
	<p>I want to endorse much of what has been said. I congratulate my hon. Friend the Member for Dundee, East (Mr. Luke) on securing this extremely important debate.</p>
	<p>My hon. Friend referred to BAT, and I shall continue in that vein before considering general sanctions. BAT's Burmese subsidiary is Rothmans of Pall Mall Myanmar. As the Minister said, it is the only British company involved in Burma, and it appears to be oblivious to the atrocities. It is a 60:40 joint venture with Union of Myanmar Economic Holdings, which is owned and controlled by Burma's military regime, so the company is directly involved in the most intimate sense in supporting that regime and working in collaboration with it, and its finance is linked with the regime. That is reprehensible, and I was shocked to learn that the deputy chairman of the company is one of our own: the right hon. and learned Member for Rushcliffe (Mr. Clarke). I hope that he will listen to this debate and that, as a right hon. and learned Member, he will have to take account of the seriousness of the need to disinvest in Burma at this critical time.</p>
	<p>BAT pays factory workers just 23p a day. The UN defines anyone living on less than 60p a day as living in extreme poverty. There can be no doubt whatever that the claims that are often made by international companies that they are putting much-needed income into the country just do not ring true. We are talking about slave labour in a country that endorses slave labour, and an industrial zone upgraded in 1996 to involve child labour, which the House has consistently condemned.</p>
	<p>The Burma Campaign UK estimates that the joint venture earns the regime $400,000 a year. Aung San Suu Kyi, the leader of Burma's democratic movement, has called on companies to stay out of the country. She said that foreign investment funds the regime and helps to keep it in power. It is on that point alone that I rose to speak. We can no longer merely threaten Burma with sanctions: we must impose them. The time when we can expect the regime to respond to threats and requests has passed. We know how difficult it has been even for the UN envoy to get permission to see Aung San Suu Kyi in prison.</p>
	<p>I know, and I am sure that the Minister will tell us, that the UK is very concerned and wants to do more than the European Union has been willing to do. Our position has been that we should move within the EU as the most appropriate body through which to impose sanctions on Burma, but we have not been helped by the positions of Germany, France and Italy. I trust that their leaderships are beginning to change their views, given the current situation.</p>
	<p>As we have already heard from the hon. Member for Castle Point (Bob Spink), the EU is far behind the United States. It is not the norm for me to ask for our Government to follow the United States in foreign policy, but I certainly do so this morning. The US imposed sanctions in 1997. All new investments in Burma were banned by the US as long ago as 1997. That was done with what I think was the largest majority vote&mdash;97 to one&mdash;in the Senate. The US has no doubt at all how serious the matter is.</p>
	<p>The US Government have hinted that they will ask the UN Security Council to deal with Burma, but I urge our Government not even to wait for that to happen. I hope that it will happen, but let us not hesitate. Let us agree that the UK, as a permanent member of the Security Council, can refer the matter of Burma for action to that body. Article 39 of chapter 7 of the UN charter permits the imposition of economic sanctions, and has been used to impose them in the past&mdash;for example, in Haiti in 1993 and Southern Rhodesia in 1965. That can and should be done again in Burma.</p>
	<p>As we all know, sanctions can impose great burdens on the peoples of the countries involved. That happened particularly tragically in Iraq. In South Africa, however, the effect of sanctions and all the political pressure certainly bore results over a period. Burma is neither South Africa nor Iraq. The Burmese regime would probably crumple fairly quickly if there were international targeted sanctions. We must certainly try for that, and I believe that the United Kingdom can lead the way. We must bear it in mind not only that BAT is in an appalling collaboration with the Burmese regime, but that many companies that have invested in Burma export their goods into the west. For all we know, many goods are coming into this country that were made in Burma.</p>
	<p>Burmese exports include oil, gas, timber, gems, minerals and garments. Parliamentary questions have been asked in the House without success to find out which goods are imported into the United Kingdom from Burma. Can my hon. Friend the Minister give us any intelligence about that, because it is additional to the fact that a major British company may be collaborating with the regime? We ought to know such information, because retailers and wholesalers who are engaged in the trade should be named and shamed. It is unacceptable that garments and other goods made by slave labour&mdash;by people under the tyrannical regime&mdash;should be coming into this country. I want to know such information, because I do not wish to purchase anything that comes from Burma, and I should like to know that I am not doing so.</p>
	<p>I know of the worries of my hon. Friend the Minister, the representations that he has made and his great commitment to end the horrible situation in Burma. However, we can take steps within the European Union and the Security Council. Should they not produce targeted sanctions&mdash;the result that we hope for&mdash;I urge the Government to follow the unilateral action that the United States has taken and impose an investment ban on Burma.</p>
	<p>I pay tribute to my close friend, Glenys Kinnock MEP, who has done a great deal within the EU. Even now, she is striving to ensure that the matter is placed at the top of the agenda. I also pay tribute to the children at Edmund Waller primary school in my constituency, which I visited recently. They had chosen Aung San Suu Kyi as one of their world heroines. We discussed her and looked at photographs. There are 100 different mother tongues in my constituency. It was extremely touching that girls and boys from all ethnic groups were thinking about an individual who was so far away from them and their experiences, but whom they could identify as an extraordinary woman fighting for the democracy and freedom that we all hold dear in this country. It is a credit to children, especially primary school children, that they can have such a vision and want, as we do, the Burmese regime removed from the face of this earth.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.84.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1174" speakername="John Pugh" colnum="84"  time="10:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spnew4">
	<p>I congratulate the hon. Member for Dundee, East (Mr. Luke) on securing this crucial and timely debate. As a member of the all-party group on Burma, I wish to underline one or two things that have been said and flesh out others that have not been stressed loudly enough. We are debating not only a battle for democracy, but a battle against pure violation of democracy. We must remember that the election was won by the National League for Democracy in Burma in 1990 with 82 per cent. of the vote. I am sure that almost everyone here would regard that as a good democratic victory.</p>
	<p>As has been said, we are witnessing a spectacle of appalling suffering, genocide and abuse of human rights. The hon. Gentleman said that such a situation was, in some ways, remote from our problems. One thing that was perhaps not stressed enough is that this appalling regime is one of the world's major exporters of opium, which ultimately ends up on the streets of our countries. In a sense, its problems indirectly become our problems.</p>
	<p>There seems to be an intractable problem, because the regime has an army of 400,000 people but few external threats with which to deal. One is reminded of the Marcos regime in the Philippines, which had a similar profile, and we know how long that lasted. We ought to be in no doubt that all hon. Members wish for regime change for all the right reasons, as I am sure the Government do. Although that aim is entirely laudable and should be supported by every parliamentarian, the means of achieving it seem rather difficult to identify. The EU has stiffened some of its sanctions and America has pursued a robust path of sanctions. I believe that 20 American states more or less outlaw any firms that have any commercial dealings with Burma. I am sure that the United Nations could be moved further to condemn the Burmese Government.</p>
	<p>However, using the trade lever has a limited effect because Burma's major trading partners are, by and large, not those that stand for a tradition of democracy. It trades with China and the eastern bloc when routes to the west are barred. The House must welcome Japan's move&mdash;it has withdrawn $70 million in aid from Burma, which is no doubt making life more difficult for the Burmese Government. We must do everything we can to endorse such behaviour.</p>
	<p>Sadly, the levers that we can pull to secure regime change, which we all want, are limited. However, that is no excuse for not pulling hard on those levers that we have. We in this country need to point to and praise the attitude of those firms that have, at commercial cost and by virtue of having some conscience, withdrawn from dealings with the Burmese regime. There is a laudable list of such firms, which includes Texaco, Levi-Strauss, Motorola, Heineken, Carlsberg, Amoco, C&amp;A, Triumph International, and so forth. Just as we must point out good behaviour, we must, as hon. Members have done, heavily underline those who have not quite got the message. That applies to British American Tobacco&mdash;not only its board, but its shareholders and anybody who has a stake in the company. If there is to be regime change, for which we all heartily wish, it will be secured not by debate in this place but by a long-term global campaign. If this debate contributes a small amount to that, it will do a lot of good.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.85.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1042" speakername="Oliver Letwin" colnum="85"  time="10:12:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spnew5">
	<p>I enter this debate as a newcomer, without anything like the long experience that some hon. Members have of this subject. Some of my constituents have been coming to me about this matter for some time. Eventually, I decided that it was time to find out what they were on about. I am convinced, partly through receiving tutorials from experts and partly through reading about it, that there is a problem with our approach to the matter. Some element of that has emerged in this debate.</p>
	<p>Two valuable strands have been contributed today. First, there are those who are concerned about how to achieve, or promote and foster, regime change in a country where democracy is being denied and in which a notable proponent of democracy is being treated abominably&mdash;the House considers that to be so. Secondly, we have heard, especially from my hon. Friend the Member for Castle Point (Bob Spink), a powerful account of the dreadful treatment of large numbers of people from the ethnic minorities in Burma.</p>
	<p>When we talk about the pressure that could be exerted, which hon. Members have described most poignantly, I have a dreadful suspicion that we might help to achieve only part of what we desire. I imagine that the pressure being brought, and the greater pressure that might be brought, to bear could succeed in persuading the current regime to make way, gracefully or gracelessly, for a democratic regime, which would be a major advance.</p>
	<p>However, it is not clear to me from what I have been told and what I have read&mdash;perhaps the Minister will offer an analysis that disproves it&mdash;that the result of such a regime change will necessarily be to displace the power of the army so completely that fears about the second strand of concern, the appalling acts against ethnic minorities, will be allayed. There might be an improvement, perhaps even a seismic improvement, in conditions for the Burman population through the achievement of democracy, but if the army retain sufficient control and a vested interest in what my hon. Friend described as genocide, that genocide could continue, notwithstanding its being in a moderated and modified form.</p>
	<p>There is a grave danger that the House and the civilised world will go quietly to sleep about Burma. We will celebrate the arrival of Aung San Suu Kyi as the ruler of a democracy but appalling things may continue to be done against the minority groups for some years, and no one will be paying much attention to them. I exempt hon. Members who are present in the debate. My hon. Friend financed his own trip into the jungle, which he will not forget. I fear, however, that the subject will go off the media's radar. I see the Minister shaking his head and I take comfort from that. I am delighted to sense that the Government are alive to that possibility.</p>
	<p>It is extremely important that the two strands of the debate are brought together to ensure that increased pressure is exerted to achieve both aims, not one at the expense of the other.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.86.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1059" speakername="Iain Luke" colnum="86"  time="10:12:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spnew6">
	<p>I am sorry I did not raise it in my contribution to the debate, but the right hon. Gentleman may not be aware that there is a Government in exile based in America, who are working with the many ethnic groups that have separate representations to consider the post-military government situation. That is relevant to the right hon. Gentleman's point, because it is one step in bringing about military regime change but, as he rightly said, the rights and autonomy of the ethnic groups in Burma are the second strand of the issue. Little attention has been paid to that, but it is on the agenda in other places where the nascent Government of Burma are considering the prospect.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.86.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1042" speakername="Oliver Letwin" colnum="86"  time="10:12:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spnew7">
	<p>That is enormously reassuring. However, although the matter is in the public arena, it is said that the best way to keep a secret is to make a speech about it in the House of Commons and I fear today's debate may show that to be so. I doubt that we will read the observations that have been made today in the headlines tomorrow. Those headlines concern themselves with Aung San Suu Kyi and the fate of democracy in Burma, but there is a discrepancy in the amount of public attention paid to each side. It is enormously heartening if hon. Members and the Government clearly see the need to keep both strands together and to advance on both fronts as in due course it may encourage the media to take an equal interest in them.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.86.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1138" speakername="Mike O'Brien" colnum="86"  time="10:12:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spnew8">
	<p>I have spoken to Aung San Suu Kyi on several occasions in recent months. She is very concerned to ensure that the two issues are linked and to resolve the question of democracy. She is also committed to reaching an accommodation with the Karen and the Shan. There is no doubt that the resolution of the process of reform and democracy should also lead&mdash;Aung San Suu Kyi is conscious of this&mdash;to a resolution of the appalling atrocities that have been committed against ethnic minorities.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.86.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1042" speakername="Oliver Letwin" colnum="86"  time="10:12:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spnew9">
	<p>I am even more heartened by that and I am grateful to the Minister for intervening. I apologise for the fact that I shall have left the Chamber by the time he speaks at the end of the debate.</p>
	<p>I have no reason to doubt what the Minister said about the motive of the Government or Aung San Suu Kyi. It would be absurd for me to pretend that I have the slightest understanding of the intricacies of the relationship between a forthcoming democratic regime in Burma and the military authorities. I do not. My speculation may, therefore, be wholly false. However, I have worked in several countries in that region, and some in sub-Saharan Africa, with and for the Governments of those countries, which were to a greater or lesser extent democratically established.</p>
	<p>On one occasion&mdash;it would be wrong for me to name the country in question&mdash;I took the military secretary to the Prime Minister out for a drink to understand why none of the things that were being decided by the Prime Minister in my presence were happening. Memorably, he told me, &quot;We keep her very busy. We take her from parade to parade. We try to make sure that she never notices that nothing that she says ever happens.&quot; Democratic regimes in countries where there are powerful military authorities that do not have the same blessed relationship with the democratic regime as we experience do not find it easy to deal with that pattern of behaviour.</p>
	<p>For a new, tenuously established democratic regime, there is a risk if the military is sufficiently alienated that the benefits the regime will convey to the country by being democratic will be undone by a coup. That tension is often difficult to resolve. I do not doubt the Minister's motive or that of San Suu Kyi. It is heartening to hear what he said. I hope that if we help to achieve the first step, it will also be the policy of Her Majesty's Government to keep an eagle eye on the matter, and to strengthen the democratic regime against possible military interference.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.87.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1245" speakername="Bob Spink" colnum="87"  time="10:12:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spnew10">
	<p>I support my right hon. Friend's theme. He is wise to raise the spectre of a democratic solution while atrocities by the military against ethnic groups continue. That would not be unprecedented. In Indonesia, there were democratic elections in 1999, but the atrocities against the people of West Papua by the Indonesian military continued for a number of years. In a regime with a strong military presence and strong separatist movements, which then has democratic elections, there are all the ingredients for such problems. My right hon. Friend is right to follow that line.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.87.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1042" speakername="Oliver Letwin" colnum="87"  time="10:12:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spnew11">
	<p>I am grateful to my hon. Friend and to the Minister. I am delighted that there appears to be a considerable degree of consensus on the issue. That is heartening and I hope that the Government will be able to make the media understand the matter in the same terms.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.87.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/716" speakername="John Barrett" colnum="87"  time="10:23:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spnew12">
	<p>I, too, congratulate the hon. Member for Dundee, East (Mr. Luke) on his success in securing the debate this morning. He and I entered this House at the last general election, and from the contributions he has made in the past two years, I know of the interest he takes in international affairs and his commitment to human rights in Burma and elsewhere in the world.</p>
	<p>Like other hon. Members, I have agreed with everything that has been said until now. I will not repeat the issue raised about British American Tobacco. A number of hon. Members agree that it is going to be difficult to have a major impact through sanctions alone because of the relatively limited amount of direct trade that Britain and the US have with Burma. We must increase pressures on neighbouring countries that are trading far more with Burma.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.87.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1203" speakername="Joan Ruddock" colnum="87"  time="10:23:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spnew13">
	<p>Does the hon. Gentleman think that it would not be possible to get UN sanctions, to which China would have to adhere? It is my understanding that China has never voted against proposals concerning Burma. We might be able to persuade it to abstain, and not to stand in the way. What does the hon. Gentleman think of that possibility?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.88.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/716" speakername="John Barrett" colnum="88"  time="10:23:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spnew14">
	<p>The hon. Lady is absolutely right. Exerting pressure on countries such as China and other major trading nations that trade with Burma may be another way forward. As my hon. Friend the Member for Southport (Dr. Pugh) said, it is not only legitimate trade that we should note; it is the impact of opium on our streets. Whether it is products in our shops or opium being traded illegally, we are all affected and we must continue to raise the issue, and today's debate does that.</p>
	<p>When I first saw the title of the debate, &quot;Democracy and human rights in Burma&quot;, I was tempted to suggest that it be changed to, &quot;What democracy and what human rights in Burma?&quot; As the hon. Member for Dundee, East pointed out in his opening remarks, and as we heard from others who have contributed to the debate, there is precious little in the way of human rights in Burma and, by any definition, democracy is non-existent. Gaining 82 per cent. of the vote should be just reason to form a Government and to be in a position of influence; it is no reason for someone to be locked up in a prison cell.</p>
	<p>Our debate serves to highlight the considerable parliamentary interest in Burma, which is shown also by the seven or eight early-day motions relating to Burma that have been tabled since the beginning of the year. Perhaps the most significant is early-day motion 1311, tabled by the hon. and learned Member for Redcar (Vera Baird), which has now received the support of as many as 219 right hon. and hon. Members. They are quite right to be concerned. The story of Burma remains an immensely sad one; not only because of the fact that, despite its rich natural resources, it is a very poor country, but because of the religious persecution that was mentioned earlier, the use of child labour and the other human rights breaches that occur all too frequently.</p>
	<p>It goes without saying that Liberal Democrats totally deplore the detainment of the leader of the National League for Democracy, Aung San Suu Kyi. The Minister is quite right to put as much pressure as he can on the relevant authorities for her release. The idea that she is being held in a two-room hut in a prison just outside Rangoon for her personal protection would be almost laughable if it were not so serious. Some hon. Members have mentioned that she was released from house arrest in May of last year. However, it is important to dispel the myth that she was free to roam as she wished between her release then and her capture one month ago.</p>
	<p>Despite being told that no restrictions would be placed on her, she and her NLD team were faced with the most intense intimidation tactics and harassment as they tried to travel around the country. As others have said, promises of some political reform being made upon her release were broken, although I accept that hundreds of political prisoners were released; perhaps only to be further persecuted outside the prison cell. Nevertheless, as we have heard today, Burma's human rights record remains nothing short of shocking.</p>
	<p>The unprecedented decision of the International Labour Organisation three years ago to take measures against Burma because of its continued use of child labour was a significant step. However, since that decision was taken, the ILO governing board has found little progress, the Burmese authorities being unwilling to tackle the exploitation of child labour and the starvation rates that were mentioned earlier in the debate.</p>
	<p>Perhaps the most disturbing of all the images that we see are those of young children being signed up as part of the Burmese military forces, where they are mistreated. Today, Burma has by a long way the highest number of child soldiers in the world. I strongly recommend to hon. Members the report of Human Rights Watch into child soldiers in Burma entitled &quot;My Gun was as Tall as Me&quot;. It is hardly light reading. It gives a chilling but accurate description of how children as young as 11 are brought into the army, where they are subjected to beatings during training by their commanders and refused contact with their families.</p>
	<p>One story in the report caught my eye. It was by an 11-year-old boy, who said:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;On my journey, there was a checkpoint. The police stopped the car and checked ID cards. I couldn't show one. I was too young to have an ID card . . . the police said: 'You'll have to go to jail for six years for not having an ID card.' Then they sent me to the police station and put me in the leg stocks. They kept saying, 'You have to decide. You can join the army or go to jail.' And then they gave me time to think. They could see I was only eleven but if the police give a boy to the army, they can get pocket money from the army, 3,000 kyat and two tins of rice. They gave me from 8 am until the afternoon to decide. I didn't want to go to jail for six years so I joined the army.&quot;</p>
	<p>Those are frightening and frequent stories; stories that one would not expect to be told in 1903, let alone 2003.</p>
	<p>However, as others have said, it is not just the children who are suffering. Ethnic minorities in Burma have faced the most malicious and violent treatment by the Burmese authorities, forcing cross-border tensions with neighbouring Thailand, to where many of those being persecuted flee. The statement by the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees made clear the international outrage over the way that minorities such as the Karen, Shan and Karenni were being treated, as the hon. Member for Castle Point (Bob Spink) mentioned earlier.</p>
	<p>Again, such outrage is justified. The Shan Women's Action Framework, in conjunction with the Shan Human Rights Foundation, published a report documenting the systemic rape of women and young girls in the Shan state by the Burmese army. The report not only described how most rapes were carried out in front of other officers, but revealed that one quarter of the attacks ended in death. My hon. Friend the Member for Romsey (Sandra Gidley) would have liked to be here this morning to raise this issue, but unfortunately she cannot be here owing to other parliamentary business. Those atrocities may not involve weapons of mass destruction or threaten our security, but we in the international community cannot stand by and allow such shocking attacks to happen.</p>
	<p>As a member of the International Development Committee, I make no apology for bringing into the debate the major humanitarian problems that have been allowed to develop. Burma is gripped in the stranglehold not only of HIV, which has now reached epidemic proportions, but of malaria and tuberculosis. Since I am one of those people who believes that education plays a great part in preventative health care, I am concerned that less than 1 per cent. of gross domestic product is spent on health and education in Burma, one of the lowest levels in the world. I very much welcome the commitment that the Department for International Development has made; some &pound;10 million alone for HIV/AIDS preventative measures.</p>
	<p>However, I wonder if there is still room for the Government to take a greater role on such matters, yet without associating themselves directly with the regime. In DFID's 2003 Departmental report&mdash;a comprehensive 157-page document&mdash;only one paragraph related to Burma. Moreover, Burma got a mere one sentence mention in the Foreign Office annual report, on page 74. Perhaps there is an opportunity for the Government to bring Burma higher up the agenda, although I appreciate the work that has already been done. Without wishing to break the political consensus that has emerged this morning, I think that the Government, who have been so focused on countries such as Iraq and Iran, would do well to focus more on countries such as Burma and Zimbabwe, where people are facing serious breaches in basic human rights.</p>
	<p>There have been a lot of strong statements from Foreign Office Ministers and, indeed, the Foreign Secretary himself. That was reiterated just last week by the Prime Minister in an answer to the hon. Member for Glasgow, Maryhill (Ann McKechin). However, the time for words must be coming to an end and the time for action is long overdue. However, we in the Liberal Democrats very much welcome the action that has already been taken, particularly through the strengthened EU position. Of course, we should not trade in arms or any other equipment that could be used for repression in Burma. Travel bans and sanctions need to be introduced as appropriate but, at the same time, we must ensure that all action that is taken seeks to minimise the impact on the ordinary Burmese people, who have already suffered too much under that terrible regime. Perhaps there is still action that the Government could take, although I regret that there is still not consensus in the UN Security Council on the issue. I hope that the Government will continue to work hard to forge such a consensus, so that the international community can stand united and say that the practices occurring in Burma are unacceptable and will not be tolerated.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.90.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1246" speakername="Richard Spring" colnum="90"  time="10:34:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spnew15">
	<p>I warmly congratulate the hon. Member for Dundee, East (Mr. Luke) on securing this debate, which is very timely. The debate this morning has been extraordinarily good and on an important subject that should concern us all. Recent events in Burma have served to underline what we have known for some time: that the regime is intent on preserving its power, whatever the cost to Burma and its people.</p>
	<p>I have particular memories of Burma, having visited it some years ago. It is a beautiful place, with breathtaking landscapes. Its people practise a particularly peaceful form of Buddhism, which has enriched the landscape with many stunning temples. The Burmese are a gentle, good and proud people, and deserve better than the Government whom they now have.</p>
	<p>I am grateful to the hon. Member for Dundee, East for talking about minorities in Burma. My hon. Friend the Member for Castle Point (Bob Spink) dealt most graphically and powerfully with their tragic problems, and we owe him a debt for his insights.</p>
	<p>Sadly, my right hon. Friend the Member for West Dorset (Mr. Letwin) is no longer present, but he made a valid point about bringing the various strands together. I could not but wryly observe, however, that Potemkin village syndrome can also apply in quite advanced democracies.</p>
	<p>In 1993, my right hon. Friend the Leader of the Opposition&mdash;as he now is&mdash;warned of</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;a brutal and despotic regime that cares nothing for human rights&quot;.&mdash;[<i>Official Report</i>, 30 March 1993; Vol. 222, c. 330.]</p>
	<p>He was talking not about the regimes of Robert Mugabe and Saddam Hussein but about Burma's junta. There was widespread support for his view and for the action taken by John Major's Government in July 1991 to instigate an EU arms embargo on Burma. In 1994, the then Minister of State at the Foreign Office, Alastair Goodlad, said:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;As the situation has deteriorated, the United Kingdom, with our European Union partners, has taken a leading role at the United Nations general assembly and at the Commission on Human Rights, to gain consensus support for tough resolutions calling for the unconditional release of Daw Aung San Suu Kyi and other political leaders and in denouncing the human rights violations reported by Professor Yokota.&quot;&mdash;[<i>Official Report</i>, 21 July 1994; Vol. 247, c. 632.]</p>
	<p>His words demonstrated that the then Government were taking the issue seriously. Unfortunately, the situation continued to deteriorate, and too little was done then or in the ensuing years to resolve the problem.</p>
	<p>We have heard about the democratically elected leader of the Burmese people being imprisoned once again. On 31 May, she and 19 other members of the National League for Democracy were arrested. As the hon. Member for Edinburgh, West (John Barrett) said, the regime's claims that she had been taken into protective custody have been rubbished, and we have learned that at least 70 people lost their lives in the attack.</p>
	<p>As we have heard, Aung San Suu Kyi is being held in a particularly notorious prison. She can be detained without access to her family or lawyers for 180 days at a time, and for up to five years, with no prospect of appeal. That is a grotesque violation of her human rights. Every parliamentarian should find it profoundly shocking that the democratically elected leader of a Government is being denied access to her electorate. I cannot believe that any hon. Member could fail to be moved by the plight of this utterly remarkable woman, by her incredible stand against the forces of tyranny, which constantly rage against her, and by the appalling way in which she has been treated.</p>
	<p>Despite the situation, Aung San Suu Kyi remains an inspiration to her people. In the face of personal hardships, she continues to pursue a peaceful path and she has not been tempted by violence. Unfortunately, the peace process that she and the UN ambassador have been pursuing is failing, despite their good will and sincere efforts.</p>
	<p>On 12 June, Colin Powell wrote that</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;the time has come to turn up the pressure&quot;</p>
	<p>on Burma's junta. I want now to consider how that might best be accomplished, and I freely acknowledge the Minister's efforts in this regard. Foreign investment can undoubtedly have a positive effect in many developing countries, but to be blunt, the opposite appears to be true in Burma. Foreign investment has provided the regime with the money that it needs to cling on to power and has enabled it to double the size of its army. A country of only 47 million people, with no external enemies, has one of the largest armies in Asia. At the same time, the people of Burma have become poorer, as resource allocation&mdash;based on political prerogatives instead of social need&mdash;continues to be debased.</p>
	<p>It has been argued that ending investment will hurt the people of Burma. That must be avoided, as their suffering is already so great. However, it is vital to understand that Burma is a mainly agricultural country, with 75 per cent. of its population living in rural areas. The energy sector benefits the regime and foreign companies. Similarly, the gem and timber trades benefit regional commanders and the regime's business associates. The garment industry is 90 per cent. owned by the regime. The vast majority of rural and urban dwellers are not involved in those industries, so the money that they make is not spent on the people by a benevolent regime but used to prop up a tyrannical one. Though investment flows have dropped dramatically since 1998, future revenue from those ventures will help the regime to neglect and postpone essential reforms. On 19 June, the Minister made a commitment that the</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;international community will not stand idly by while the military regime continues to abuse the democratic and human rights of Aung San Suu Kyi and the people of Burma.&quot;</p>
	<p>If the Government are truly intent on keeping that promise&mdash;I accept the Minister's sincerity&mdash;they must make a concerted effort to limit commerce. Taking up the powerful point of the hon. Member for Lewisham, Deptford (Joan Ruddock), Britain should press for a UN Security Council resolution calling for an end to all investment in Burma so long as the military regime remains in power, and for sanctions on certain Burmese exports, including oil, gas, timber, gems, minerals and garments.</p>
	<p>The Minister will be aware that in opposition his party backed targeted investment sanctions. I make no political point, but can he confirm that that is still its position in government and tell us what steps are being taken to implement that policy in conjunction with others? The United States and Italian Governments have hinted that they will press for a new resolution. Does the Minister agree that if the UK took the initiative now, the added momentum might compel the Security Council to take action on Burma? Should we not use the strength of UK-Chinese relations to achieve such co-operation? What discussions have the British Government had with other Security Council members on the prospect of a new resolution on Burma?</p>
	<p>In the absence of Security Council agreement, we should like to see Britain push for an EU investment ban. I have discussed the idea with representatives of the Governments of other EU member states and there is widespread support for it. Historically, the EU common position has been weaker than the UK might have wanted, and unless recent events have shifted thinking on Burma, the EU will lag behind US policy. Does the Minister share my concerns, and will he confirm that the British Government will be pressing for EU Ministers to put Burma on the agenda of the Asia-Europe meeting, or ASEM, in Bali on 23 and 24 July?</p>
	<p>Burma's military regime shamelessly calls itself the State Peace and Development Council, but it fails US State Department grades on human rights, trafficking in persons and drugs, and international religious freedom. As we speak, more than 1,000 people are detained in Burmese prisons for political reasons. There is hope of strong action. There are signs that the ASEAN countries have had enough of the broken promises and abuses of the regime. As the hon. Member for Southport (Dr. Pugh) observed, last week, Japan cut off aid in a hugely symbolic move. What aid do we give to Burma, if any, and is there scope to copy the Japanese? Wider international pressure would, I hope, lead to the immediate and permanent release of Aung San Suu Kyi. However, we must not be content with that. I am sure that all hon. Members will join me in hoping that the new focus on Burma&mdash;and there is a new focus on Burma&mdash;can be a catalyst for the release of all political prisoners there; for National League for Democracy offices and universities to be reopened; for the SPDC immediately to end extra-judicial killings, systematic rape and political intimidation; and for a genuine democratic process to emerge, leading towards a Government elected by the people and ruling for the people. That is exactly what is not happening in Burma at the moment.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.93.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1138" speakername="Mike O'Brien" speakeroffice="The Minister for Trade and Investment"  colnum="93"  time="10:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h01.htm#30702h01_spmin1">
	<p>I thank my hon. Friend the Member for Dundee, East (Mr. Luke) for providing the opportunity for us to discuss an issue that is very important not only for Britain but for the whole international community. I know of his strong support for democracy and human rights in Burma, from his work with the all-party group. I am also aware of the wide support that the campaign for democracy and human rights in Burma, including the campaign for human rights for ethnic minorities in that benighted country, enjoys on both sides of the House.</p>
	<p>In common with all those who have spoken today, I am deeply concerned about the recent events in Burma. In recent months, the Government have been working hard to encourage dialogue between the regime in Burma and the National League for Democracy. I used to speak regularly to Daw Aung San Suu Kyi about that, but my repeated attempts to speak to her since her detention on 30 May have been rebuffed by the regime.</p>
	<p>We had received information that Daw Aung San Suu Kyi was being detained in Insein jail. We are today picking up reports from a French press agency that she has been moved from Insein jail and is now elsewhere. The reports appear not to know where, and whether they are entirely true, I cannot say. We are attempting to get further information from our sources. Clearly it is a matter of enormous concern that a Nobel peace prize winner who has become a personification of the worldwide campaign for human rights and democracy should be detained by a brutal regime such as that in Burma.</p>
	<p>I am inspired by Aung San Suu Kyi's resolute commitment to the peaceful pursuit of her objectives in Burma. She embodies the hopes of the people of Burma, commanding respect and admiration inside the country and throughout the international community. Large crowds have flocked to her in every corner of the country to which she has travelled. The generals know that those crowds demonstrate the true wishes of the people of Burma. The people want the leaders for whom they voted overwhelmingly in 1990. By its repressive actions, the regime betrays its fear of &quot;the Lady&quot;, as she is universally known in Burma. It says that Aung San Suu Kyi has been detained for her own protection. In fact, she is being detained for the protection of the regime against the people.</p>
	<p>The regime's malign rule in Burma is clear for all to see. The generals have no ideology other than the maintenance of power and the cynical abuse of that power for their own purposes. Human rights abuse against ethnic minorities, as detailed by the hon. Member for Castle Point (Bob Spink), and against the Burmese people themselves, is the regime's chosen instrument for enforcing its position. Ethnic minority groups in Burma suffer the abuses and the destruction of their human rights disproportionately, through extra-judicial killing, forced labour, rape, forced relocation and even the burning of entire communities.</p>
	<p>The British Government have been at the forefront of international efforts to press for an end to human rights violations in Burma. Successive resolutions, co-sponsored by the British, have been passed in the UN General Assembly and the Commission on Human Rights. We also helped to lead the way for the International Labour Organisation to implement measures against Burma because of the scandalous use of forced labour there.</p>
	<p>The regime might seek to sweep such concerns under the carpet by routinely banning foreign reporters and denying international access to large parts of Burma, even by the United Nations. However, we shall continue to draw attention to the harsh reality of its rule. With its litany of other faults, the regime's economic incompetence and ignorance are often overlooked, but it is important to highlight the sheer incompetence of the regime, which is having such a detrimental effect on the people of Burma. My hon. Friend the Member for Dundee, East compared Burma with India, and we see there what damage such a regime can do to the economy, driving its people into poverty. A country that is rich in human and natural resources is being driven towards economic disaster. It is a shocking and unnecessary road to ruin. Why is the old rice bowl of Asia struggling to feed its people? Why has foreign investment dried up? Why are the few companies still investing in Burma voting with their feet? Premier Oil, for example, is withdrawing its support.</p>
	<p>Trade with and investment in foreign countries, even those with democratic shortfalls, is not inherently bad for human rights and democracy in those countries. However, in Burma, the regime cynically manipulates trade and investment to help to support its continued misrule and for personal gain. Those factors are specific to the regime, which is why, as the Prime Minister made clear in the House last week, we do not believe that to trade with or invest in Burma is appropriate while the regime continues to suppress the basic human rights of its people. We are making that clear to British companies, and this morning I shall meet the chairman of British American Tobacco, which was saddled with a problematic investment in Burma as a result of a merger in the 1990s.</p>
	<p>The Government do not encourage tourists to visit or companies to invest in Burma. I shall take to my meeting with the chairman of BAT the views of both Government and Opposition Members who have expressed serious concern about a company continuing to have investment in Burma. I shall be able to report that to the chairman, to whom I shall be speaking within the hour.</p>
	<p>The Government are committed to having serious discussions with BAT and anyone else involved in trade with Burma. I was particularly concerned at the observations of my hon. Friend the Member for Lewisham, Deptford (Joan Ruddock) that some other companies may be purchasing garments in Burma to import to the United Kingdom. I shall certainly look into that and see whether we can find ways of speaking to those companies, if they are British companies.</p>
	<p>In 1998, the late Derek Fatchett wrote to travel associations in Britain explaining why the Government were concerned about their encouragement of travel in Burma. In the light of the deteriorating situation there, I propose to write to all travel organisations with any links with tourism in Burma. There are very few of them, but if any are involved, we shall target them and ask them not to allow, encourage or participate in tourism in Burma. Some people go to Burma for their own reasons, and we want to discourage them from doing so.</p>
	<p>We need a wide strategy to deal with the problem and our approach has been that when Burma has moved towards reform and democracy, we have encouraged it. For a period last year, with the release of Aung San Suu Kyi and the increasing freedom that was being given to her, it looked as though the process was under way, but it then stalled. There was no explanation, and radio silence from the Burmese regime. We did not know why it had suddenly stopped the process, and it was clear in my conversations with Aung San Suu Kyi that she did not know why. However, it did stop and went into reverse, so we must ensure that we send an even clearer message. Over time, the regime will find that the international community will tighten the restrictions on it.</p>
	<p>As a number of hon. Members have said, we must ensure that sanctions do not hurt the Burmese people whom we are trying to help, and are specifically targeted against the regime's leaders, and we will seek to get that balance right. However, if the regime starts to carry out reforms and to move towards democracy, and it enters into discussions and frees Aung San Suu Kyi, we will take that into account as our policy develops. There is a clear strategy of encouragement for reform, if it is taking place, but a clear view that a failure to reform will not be ignored by the international community.</p>
	<p>We have taken a strong EU common position, which contains an arms embargo, and bans on defence links, on high-level visits, on the sale of items that can be used for repression and torture, and on non-humanitarian assistance, as well as an assets freeze and travel ban on the regime, its families and their cronies. Many hon. Members have mentioned action against Burmese exports, and we have already taken some action in that area. The EU has suspended Burma's trading privileges and we have written to all British employers and workers groups informing them of the use of forced labour in Burma and advising them to have nothing to do with Burma.</p>
	<p>As an initial step after the latest crackdown by the regime, the EU strengthened its common position on 16 June. I stress that that was an initial step and that we are actively considering with partners what further action may be necessary if the regime does not see sense soon. UK and EU action to date has been effective, and we must therefore continue to act in partnership with the EU and others around the world. UK diplomatic, trading and investment links with Burma are already very limited, but a collective approach will be needed to achieve a further significant tightening of pressure. We are talking to the Americans about how that can best be done, and we welcome the strong statements by President Bush and Colin Powell. We also welcome the very firm position taken by the Japanese, who have announced that they will cease all economic assistance to the regime because of its recent actions. We are actively consulting them and other major players, including the Chinese and Indian Governments.</p>
	<p>If we were to fail to get a resolution in the Security Council, the Burmese regime would see it as a victory. We must therefore proceed with care by talking to the Chinese and other countries to see whether we can achieve consensus to allow us to take further action in international forums such as the UN. Let there be no doubt that we are seriously concerned about the matter and that we will be making those inquiries. I shall be travelling to China this month, where I shall talk to the Chinese about that and other issues, and I shall also be in Washington in the next couple of weeks, where I shall talk to the Americans about that and other issues. I shall also be going to the Association of South East Asian Nations summit in Bali, where I will talk to Burma's neighbours about the need for them to show that they, too, care about the human rights situation of not only the people who support Aung San Suu Kyi but the ethnic minority communities, which have been subjected to continual atrocities.</p>
	<p>The message must go out from the House that Members of all parties will not allow the issue to die. Aung San Suu Kyi's position will remain at the forefront of our efforts. We will also make sure that the deep worries that exist in the international community are not left as words but are followed up by actions, which means that clear messages must be sent. The way in which the economy of Burma has developed must be addressed, but the regime and its leaders will find that the international community will target them and their cronies for further sanctions.</p>
	<p>Burmese democracy enjoys overwhelming support in Britain and throughout the world because it embodies our, British, core hopes and values, too. The Burmese people want nothing more than what we want for them and have for ourselves: freedom and the ability to determine their leaders, rather than having to rely on a bunch of dictators and old generals. The time for change in Burma is now. We want to use all the pressure that we can to secure that change.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.97.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="97"  time="10:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h02.htm#30702h02_head0">
	National Walking Strategy
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.97.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/728" speakername="Andrew Bennett" colnum="97"  time="11:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h02.htm#30702h02_spnew0">
	<p>I am grateful for the opportunity to raise the issue of the need for a national walking strategy. I should declare that I am a vice-president of the Ramblers Association, although I get no particular benefit from that.</p>
	<p>I want to have a whinge. I almost said a quiet moan, but actually I want a noisy moan. I want to press the Government on why they feel ashamed about walking. More than 12 months ago, there was a document in the Department for Transport setting out a national walking strategy, but for some reason&mdash;whether Ministers were worried that they might be known as the Minister for silly walks or whether the Government were worried that they would be seen as a nanny state if they promoted walking&mdash;the Government sat on it. Now, the document is back as a consultation document: &quot;On the move: by foot&quot;. The Government have not had the courage to take things forward.</p>
	<p>I realise that I am being a little unfair on the new Minister. He has been in the job for two weeks and we cannot expect him to have a grip on the issue. When I saw him this morning tucking into two eggs and some rashers of bacon, I thought that perhaps he was the Minister who would get a grip on walking and make it a success story, rather than a problem story, for the Government.</p>
	<p>Let us be clear. The statistics suggest that people in this country are walking less and less. I have some doubts about the statistics, but they certainly do not show that people are walking more than they did in recent years. My doubt about the statistics is that people are asked to indicate how they travel. If someone goes to the supermarket, drives a short distance in the car and then walks right across the car park, round the aisles of the supermarket, back across the car park to the car and drives back home, that counts as a driving trip, even though the distance covered by walking may be greater than that covered by driving.</p>
	<p>Even if we were to get rather better statistics, they would not show that people in this country are walking more. If the decline is not proven, we know, at least, that we have not reversed the trend. We need to be quite clear that if people walk less and less, they will be born with wheels, rather than feet. The situation is tragic. We have known for so long that encouraging people to walk is good for them.</p>
	<p>What have the Government done? They have had a good document on walking in a pigeonhole somewhere in the Department for 12 months. On Monday, almost by stealth, they put out another consultation document: &quot;On the move: by foot&quot;. Where was the publicity? I understand the difficulties for Transport Ministers. If they talk about airports, there are at least two opinions. If they talk about railways, it is not a particularly good news story. Traffic congestion is not a particularly good story. However, the Government have a good story to tell about walking, if they want to tell it. Why did the Secretary of State not launch the document? Why did Ministers not make a great deal of effort? The current document is somewhat feeble, but the document on which it was based would have made a significant difference. It was a document that the Government could have been proud of.</p>
	<p>Why has it taken so long to produce this little mouse of a document? Surely in the past 12 months, instead of sitting on it, the Government could have introduced something positive. What about a little bit of money? I realise that it is difficult to find money for transport, and in many ways the whole point of the walking document is that we do not need particularly huge amounts of money. We need to ensure that the money being spent by local authorities is spent in a way that serves the primary purpose and encourages walking. It is particularly worrying that there has not been an effort to persuade local authorities to spend more money to make walking more attractive.</p>
	<p>A national walking board would allow us to set standards of good practice throughout the country. Some local authorities have a good story to tell&mdash;some of them are mentioned in the document&mdash;about making walking attractive. What about a national website that shows what good practice could be? &quot;Talking Walking&quot;, the sixth national walking conference, is being held on Friday. I can understand why the Minister cannot go to the conference, but someone from the Department could have gone and sent the clear message that the Government believe that walking is a good idea.</p>
	<p>Why is walking a good idea? First, it is fundamental to improving the health of the nation. It is crazy to spend large amounts of money on the national health service to remedy the problems of heart conditions and the like, when we could make a big reduction in the number of people suffering from such problems by encouraging them to walk for 10 or 15 minutes a day. Certainly, two periods of walking of 10 to 15 minutes a day make a significant improvement to people's health. That would be good value for money. One of the achievements of the Government has been to ensure that money that was being spent on problems such as unemployment has been saved to be spent on positive things. Why is the Department for Transport not doing the same thing? If it spends a bit more money on walking, it will improve people's health and reduce the bill to the NHS.</p>
	<p>The Government should be hailing how enjoyable walking is, in the countryside and the urban setting. One can leave this building and walk around the streets of Westminster, as many MPs do, and there are some fantastic buildings to look at. The paving and the views make it an attractive environment to walk in. It gives people a sense of place, and it lifts their spirits, provided that when they are walking around they do not have to dodge traffic, and their safety is not at risk.</p>
	<p>Not only is walking good for individuals' health, and enjoyable, but it makes a significant difference to the environment. The more people walk, the less they need to use their motor cars, or even public transport, which reduces emissions and the problems of global warming. It is a clear environmental plus for the Government.</p>
	<p>That takes us to the question of social cohesion. It is sad that in many places one sees only the odd person walking, which does not give one that sense of community. If one walks out of the house to the local shops, one is more likely to communicate with neighbours, even if it is just a nod to them. That gives people the feeling that they belong to a community. It is a social action, as opposed to getting into a car&mdash;a cocoon in which people travel individually.</p>
	<p>We know that the more people walk, the safer the streets become, because crime tends not to occur if there are lots of people, or witnesses, about. It makes sense to encourage people to walk. It makes the environment more attractive and safer.</p>
	<p>The key question is why the Government do not have more enthusiasm for walking. Why are they not getting on with the promise they made to the Select Committee on the Environment, Transport and the Regions in 2001 that there would be a national walking strategy? It is amazing that more than two years later the Government are still asking questions. The questions in the document are nice, but we already know the answers. We need courage and boldness from the Minister to stop consulting and take action. We need clear guidance for local authorities on what good practice is. There are some examples of that in the document. However, one need only leave this building to see appalling examples of walkers being almost herded into cattle pens, and of zigzag crossings where pedestrians can only cross half the road because priority has been given to the motorist and not the walker. The motorist travels quicker, so why not give priority to the group of people who move slowest: the walkers. That makes common sense.</p>
	<p>There is the question of road surfaces. In most local authorities, money tends to be put into keeping roads, not footpaths, in a good state of repair. I have the crazy situation where constituents demand that a road be improved and made smoother and that potholes are filled in, and a week later they are asking for traffic-calming measures. It would be much better to spend that money on making footpaths attractive for people to walk on.</p>
	<p>There are also planning issues. The Government have a good record, and the Deputy Prime Minister has worked hard to get across the concept of regenerating city centres. I approve of all of that. However, a key to that must be to encourage people to walk from their homes to their places of work and leisure. That means that more town centres must give priority to walking. I was once told that if Trafalgar square were pedestrianised, it would cause chaos. As far as I can see, it caused a lot of difficulties while the work was being done, but has produced an attractive space where people can walk. My only disappointment is that the whole of Whitehall was not turned into a pedestrian area. That might have encouraged the Prime Minister and other Ministers to walk across to the House, rather than shoot across in vehicles that do not get there any quicker.</p>
	<p>My hon. Friend the Minister should be talking to other Ministers. In Stockport, walking is being put on prescription, so to speak, because it is clear that walking is good for people's health. If a doctor, rather than a Minister or an MP, tells them to do it, people take more notice on the whole. We must get the message across that walking is good for people. I ask the Minister to make walking his crusade. He has an opportunity in a difficult Department to come up with some wins. I do not expect him to stroll down from Harrow into the centre of London, but I should like to see him walking around&mdash;coming out of his Department to champion walking.</p>
	<p>Finally, I want the Minister to give a short message to the &quot;Talking Walking&quot; conference&mdash;the sixth national conference. He should say something to allay the disappointment resulting from this document, make it clear that the Government take walking seriously and think it plays a part in our transport strategy, and also make it clear that very soon a national walking strategy will be in place.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.100.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1082" speakername="Tony McNulty" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport"  colnum="100"  time="11:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h02.htm#30702h02_spmin0">
	<p>I congratulate my hon. Friend the Member for Denton and Reddish (Andrew Bennett) on securing the debate, not least on the day when Trafalgar square has finally been opened in all its pedestrianised glory. While it is still in my mind, I should like first to respond to my hon. Friend's last point: I will try to ensure that I, or another Minister, will get a message to the conference on Friday to show our support for this endeavour.</p>
	<p>I have to say that I have known my hon. Friend for a long time, and I have never heard him whinge or moan. When we are talking about the supposed lack of progress, or otherwise, on a particular policy, that would be a clear and legitimate reason for complaint, but I have not heard any whingeing or moaning. I denounce as silly those people who see this debate or any serious discussion about walking as some latter-day manifestation of John Cleese and the ministry for silly walks, because walking as a key means of transport is an important subject. Therefore, to those who say that it is Pythonesque, I say that such a comment says far more about them and their stupidity than it does about a very important matter.</p>
	<p>I would gently part company with my hon. Friend on the comment that the Department for Transport sat on the document for 12 months while nothing much happened. The Government are wedded and committed to a comprehensive walking strategy but want that strategy to be, precisely as I said, comprehensive. The document may have been with the Department, but to do the job properly and achieve a detailed walking strategy, the work by its very nature must cross Departments. That is what has happened in the past 12 months.</p>
	<p>My hon. Friend will know that more than 700 people attended 11 seminars on the matter between June and November last year. Those meetings inform much of what is in the discussion paper &quot;On the move: by foot&quot;, which is not feeble or a mouse of a document. That is what has been happening to develop the specifics of the strategy, but he will know&mdash;I certainly do, not least because I was party to much of it in a previous incarnation&mdash;that much has gone on across Departments to set the groundwork for proper development and improvement of the lot of pedestrians and walkers. One thinks particularly of the Government's liveability agenda, with which I had much to do in my previous position.</p>
	<p>There have been discussions with the Department of Health on objectives for improving health, preventing disease and increasing physical activity among disadvantaged groups; with the Office of the Deputy Prime Minister and the Home Office to ensure measures to improve personal security; and with the Department for Culture, Media and Sport, which has developed policies to improve the quality of urban walking routes for tourists and to promote Britain as a destination for those who enjoy walking. In addition, the Departments for Education and Skills and for Transport have been working to improve the safety and sociability of journeys to school, many of which should be by foot rather than by road, thereby cutting out congestion caused by the school run. My hon. Friend was entirely right to mention urban regeneration, social inclusion and other dimensions of the subject.</p>
	<p>We believe that issuing a single document that addresses current barriers to walking and sets out all the relevant policies and initiatives to help to get them over will greatly assist all those who seek to improve the quality of the local environment and to promote a greater willingness to walk more. We want to ensure that the walking strategy that emerges fully reflects much of the cross-governmental work, not least the ODPM's liveability agenda. The discussion paper complements many of the aims and initiatives of that agenda, and people travelling on foot will benefit from the substantial funding that the Government have committed to improving the quality of local communities and public spaces. Surely, it is not sufficient to exhort and encourage people to walk more often if they have to walk through battle zones or areas that are entirely pedestrian-unfriendly, whether urban or rural.</p>
	<p>My hon. Friend asked about a national walking target&mdash;or perhaps he did not, but I shall discuss it anyway. There are two reasons why the Government remain of the opinion that there is no need to adopt national targets. First, we consider it difficult to relate them to everyday life&mdash;for example, walking 250 miles per person per year. Secondly, our aim is to improve conditions. We want people to decide for themselves whether to take advantage of the improvements. As was underlined by much of what my hon. Friend said, at present people do not have that choice. We must address the problems if an area is a battleground, if it is a real hardship simply to walk to the local shops or school or if physical barriers put people off walking.</p>
	<p>We are finalising arrangements with Transport for London, the London Walking Forum, Living Streets and the Centre for Alternative and Sustainable Transport to fund and develop the partnership website for walking, which will provide comprehensive information on walking, including news on publications, conferences and training, good practice, job opportunities, and a forum for advice and an exchange of views. It will target mainly practitioners but also provide a valuable resource for the public.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.101.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/728" speakername="Andrew Bennett" colnum="101"  time="11:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h02.htm#30702h02_spnew1">
	<p>When?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.101.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1082" speakername="Tony McNulty" colnum="101"  time="11:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h02.htm#30702h02_spnew2">
	<p>Imminently, I am told, or very shortly. We would prefer to see how the website evolves before making a commitment to national or regional forums. My predecessors met representatives of the walking lobby at regular intervals to discuss this and other matters and I am more than happy to continue to do so.</p>
	<p>On funding, the substantial increase in investment made available to local authorities through the Government's 10-year plan will enable a major expansion of schemes to make conditions easier and safer for pedestrians. All local traffic authorities have been asked to develop a local walking strategy as part of their local transport plans, which should identify gaps in the local infrastructure and improvements needed in footway networks.</p>
	<p>In the first LTP annual progress reports, many authorities identified progress on providing more pedestrian routes and improving safety and integration with other transport modes. Over the five-year period of the first LTPs, local authorities estimate they will deliver 650 km of improved footways, walking routes and pedestrianisation schemes, and 91 km of new footways or footway improvements were established by local authorities in 2000&ndash;01. I am keen to ensure that what local authorities say they will deliver by means of the local transport plans is actually put in place. I am equally keen to work with colleagues across the Government to ensure the integration of the other elements that feed into the process. It does not always mean a lot of money, as my hon. Friend suggested, but care and thought, for example about the design of street furniture, traffic signage and so on, to improve conditions and fundamentals such as the friendliness of walking in urban streets and townscapes.</p>
	<p>We will work closely with the Department of Health. The discussion paper emphasises the benefits of regular walking for improving personal health and fitness. Evidence of its effectiveness in improving general health and preventing disease is compelling, as my hon. Friend said. Walking is the easiest way to meet the recommended half hour of exercise each day. Last year, the Department supported a series of regional seminars for transport and health professionals on the health and environmental benefits of walking. As an aside, I say that eggs and bacon are part of the Atkins diet, which is working very well for me. All I need to do now is to take exercise too and I shall be the fitter for it.</p>
	<p>In respect of road safety and traffic management, walking close to fast traffic can be a frightening and unpleasant experience as well as being potentially dangerous. Many of the measures that are needed to improve the quality and convenience of the walking environment should also have a positive effect on improving safety. Conversely, in order to get more people walking, roads and footways must be made safer and more welcoming.</p>
	<p>It is a constant battle, but we must recognise that there should be a better balance between the needs of pedestrians and those of vehicles, which the future design, construction and management of roads must reflect. We plan revised guidance on measures such as reduced traffic flows, lower driving speeds and road space allocation, which can all play a part in improving conditions for pedestrians. Our discussion paper seeks views on what works and what does not.</p>
	<p>My hon. Friend may well be right to say that the answers to much of what is in the document are apparent. However, we need to discuss matters one more time with key groups and individuals to ensure that we have things right and that our role at the Department for Transport dovetails with the extensive work being done by Departments across the piece.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.102.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/728" speakername="Andrew Bennett" colnum="102"  time="11:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h02.htm#30702h02_spnew3">
	<p>I am not very happy about the extra consultation. When will it be over? When will a national walking strategy be published?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.103.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1082" speakername="Tony McNulty" colnum="103"  time="11:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h02.htm#30702h02_spnew4">
	<p>I cannot give my hon. Friend specific dates, but given where it starts from, the previous documents and the work done throughout Government in the past year, I hope that this round of consultation will be swift and that a better and more comprehensive strategy will emerge more quickly because of it. If, subsequent to this debate, I can respond with greater clarity, I shall write to him.</p>
	<p>My hon. Friend made an important point about land-use planning and the planning system, which I spent much time dealing with last year. Our discussion paper emphasises the importance of good planning and urban design. It takes account of the latest policy developments.</p>
	<p>Planning policy guidance note 13 on transport seeks to ensure that new developments and basic facilities are within easy walking distance, and that development patterns encourage walking. PPG6 on town centres and retail developments advises on the location of retail and leisure facilities, and workplaces in town centres. PPG3 on housing gives guidance on increasing housing density, so that access to shops and other services is easier. Those guidance notes are being reviewed in detail by the ODPM.</p>
	<p>Over the past four months since the publication of &quot;Sustainable Communities: Building for the Future&quot; on 5 February, we have increased the profile of public realm, public space and liveability. They are crucial to enhancing the conditions in which pedestrians and walkers must operate. We are aware that successful and sustainable communities are those that are characterised by clean, safe, attractive streets, parks and open spaces&mdash;areas where people want to live, work, play and walk. My hon. Friend will know that the ODPM has committed &pound;201 million over three years to improve the quality of parks and public spaces. That will include a new liveability fund to replace some of the resources that local authorities have lost over the past few years, details of which are in the &quot;Living Places&quot; report that the ODPM published last November. Several schemes under the public space and liveability heading are of real concern to those interested in walking.</p>
	<p>Following on from my hon. Friend's exhortation about speaking to other Ministers, there is an intergovernmental group on public spaces, as part of the living places initiative. It broadly encompasses many themes in respect of public realm parks and open spaces and will recapture much of the urban realm for those who want to walk. The group meets for the first time on Monday. It will draw in a range of different Departments to which he alluded. There are some excellent schemes in the liveability pot, not least a new unit, CABE Space&mdash;the Commission for Architecture and the Built Environment&mdash;which will deal specifically with the public realm and environmental issues. It was launched on 12 May&mdash;by me, I hasten to add.</p>
	<p>The sum of &pound;30 million has been committed to a community enablers scheme entitled &quot;Living Spaces&quot;. It was launched on 29 May&mdash;again by me, but in a previous incarnation. Groups such as the friends of parks and open spaces can place bids from &pound;1,000 to &pound;100,00 to regenerate, recapture and reinvigorate public spaces. That is important for walkers because, given its present state, the public realm&mdash;a cemetery, a space of some description or a park&mdash;may inhibit walkers. We are keen to see how the &quot;Living Spaces&quot; programme unfolds. It will be headed by Groundwork and the ODPM. It will mean that many of the pedestrian walkways that are currently degraded will be brought back into the public realm, and thus back into use by walkers.</p>
	<p>We are serious about developing a walking strategy. As I have outlined, we want it to be key and central to all that we do. I hope that people take the discussion paper and the truncated consultation period seriously, so that we can all work together in partnership to ensure a walking strategy that is needed and desired for the betterment in health of everyone in the country.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.103.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="103"  time="11:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h02.htm#30702h02_spnew4">
	<p class="italic">Sitting suspended until Two o'clock.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.105.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="105"  time="11:29:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_head0">
	Schools Funding
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.105.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1036" speakername="David Laws" colnum="105"  time="14:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew0">
	<p>I am pleased to have secured this important debate on schools funding. It will mean a lot to many people, not least given this year's funding settlement, which has caused problems in schools throughout the country. I welcome the Under-Secretary of State for Education and Skills, the hon. Member for Enfield, Southgate (Mr. Twigg), to the debate. I am slightly disappointed that the Minister for School Standards is not present. He gave a widely reported speech yesterday in which he promised to be &quot;self-critical&quot; when examining the causes of this year's schools funding crisis. I should have liked him to be here today to be self-critical and to admit the source of some of the problems experienced by schools this year. However, I am sure that the Under-Secretary will explain the Government's position excellently.</p>
	<p>Before I raise some of the more uncomfortable points, I wish to welcome the fact that it was announced yesterday that two schools in my constituency, Holyrood school in Chard and Wadham school in Crewkerne, have been granted specialist school status. I welcome the additional money that will, as a consequence of that, go into the two schools. I congratulate their head teachers and staff on the hard work that they put into the bid, especially Mr. Maurice Hicks, the head teacher at Holyrood school and Gillian Gee, the head teacher at Wadham school.</p>
	<p>On a gloomy note, I talked this morning to other head teachers in my constituency, among them Mr. Jones, the head teacher of Preston secondary school. If the Under-Secretary has been especially well briefed for today's debate, he will certainly know that Preston secondary school and Westfield school were awarded specialist school status last year. Preston secondary school was tremendously enthusiastic about that because it means that additional capital and revenue funding comes on stream. The school was optimistic, anticipating that this year it would be able to expand budgets, spend more on capital projects and deliver better education as a consequence. We can imagine the disappointment felt at that school now, after discovering that its budgetary position means that it has to implement staff cuts, such as four teacher redundancies this year and the non-replacement of several staff who may be retiring. In addition, some of the school's plans for expansion have had to be put on hold, and &pound;50,000 of capital funding has had to be taken out of the budget to protect this year's budget for the other teaching staff. Moreover, a &pound;50,000 deficit on the school's budget this year will create carry-forward problems into next year.</p>
	<p>The problems experienced by Preston secondary school, in spite of the new money received as a consequence of gaining specialist school status, have been experienced by many other schools throughout the country this year. Those problems will have a real impact on the delivery of education. However, this debate is not designed primarily to focus on the problems created by this year's funding difficulties. It is designed to enable us to consider the effects of the spending review for the next two financial years, 2004&ndash;05 and 2005&ndash;06, and to find out what the Government will constructively do to deal with the problems in schools.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.106.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/754" speakername="Annette Brooke" colnum="106"  time="14:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew1">
	<p>Does my hon. Friend agree that it is essential that in their funding plans for the next two years the Government deal with issues relating to the lowest-funded authorities, such as Poole and Dorset, to make sure that the base funding per pupil is sufficiently high that the teacher and classroom assistant to pupil ratios are restored?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.106.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1036" speakername="David Laws" colnum="106"  time="14:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew2">
	<p>It will not surprise hon. Members to learn that I entirely agree with my hon. Friend. She makes powerful constituency points in the same robust way as she always does. I hope that the Minister has heard her comments and takes them on board in the funding settlements for the next two years.</p>
	<p>Before we consider the funding problems facing the Minister in 2004&ndash;05 and 2005&ndash;06, we must examine the impact of this year's financial problems if we are to understand the nature of future challenges. I shall touch upon the problems in finances of many schools, and explore some of the causes of those financial difficulties.</p>
	<p>When the issue of funding first arose, the response of Ministers was intriguing. Initially, their response was to deny that there were any funding difficulties in schools; then, it was to blame local education authorities; at least now there seems to be some degree of acceptance by Ministers that it is the way in which they allocated funding and did not understand the pressures on school budgets that led to difficulties. In what is likely to be a pre-election year next year, we hope that Ministers will pay attention not only to the head teachers and school governing bodies complaining about the funding settlement, but to the impact on public opinion of the downturn in school budgets this year.</p>
	<p>The Minister is no doubt as aware as anyone of recent opinion polls, such as that in <i>The Guardian </i>on 25 June this year. The article stated:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;Labour has dramatically lost its reputation with voters for improving schools and education in the past three months . . . Back in March, when the Guardian carried out its annual public services survey, education was the only area where the voters said they could see real improvements coming through. But the results of this month's ICM survey show that the impact of the schools funding crisis and the row over tuition fees has led to a sudden loss of confidence in the government's record on education.&quot;</p>
	<p>I hope that that, combined with representations from head teachers, will help to concentrate the Government's mind on schools funding over the next year. I expect that most hon. Members who have similar experiences to mine in their constituencies would agree that the widespread perception in schools and among the public is that the Government have made a mistake with schools funding this year and lost some of their reputation for improving funding.</p>
	<p>I dare say that in the time that the Minister has been at the Department for Education and Skills, he has visited a good many schools. I, too, have visited some, although they have mainly been in one part of Somerset. I suspect that the Minister has been further afield&mdash;I certainly hope so. My experience of visiting schools since the Labour Government came to power is of head teachers and teachers saying two things: first, that there is too much bureaucracy in the Government's education reforms; and, secondly, that the funding position is gradually moving in the right direction. This year, however, they are not saying that. The change is reflected in today's press, in which I read that one Labour MP has been forced to donate one day's wages to ease the financial crisis at his local primary school. One article states:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;The staff of Ashby Primary in Leicestershire said the plan had started as a joke but had taken hold when it emerged that there was no money for school library books.&quot;</p>
	<p>This year that school faces a &pound;38,000 shortfall.</p>
	<p>Those types of problem are reflected throughout our constituencies. Preston secondary school in my constituency is having to make redundancies. It is not the only example&mdash;its problems are reflected in other secondary schools in the constituency. I shall briefly quote from a letter that I received from Mr. Glynn Ottery, the head teacher at Stanchester community school in my constituency; he has also been chairman of the Somerset Association of Secondary Heads. In the letter, dated 28 April&mdash;as the crisis in schools funding was beginning to emerge&mdash;Mr. Ottery wrote:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;The situation in Somerset is very poor indeed&mdash;the worst school budget I have had in 12 years of Headship! I would estimate that two thirds of secondary schools in Somerset are in real difficulties.&quot;</p>
	<p>The letter continues:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;There will be some teacher redundancies in the secondary sector in Somerset this year . . . many schools are avoiding redundancies by raising class sizes&mdash;often above 30.&quot;</p>
	<p>Mr. Ottery goes on to explain that the effect of this year's financial problems is not being felt in terms of reductions in teacher numbers alone. Many schools are trying to cushion the effects of this year's crisis: in the hope that the Government will resolve the situation between now and next year, they are cutting other items of the budget. Mr. Ottery's letter describes some of the cuts at his school. He says that there will be less money for books and equipment in some departments, significant cuts in teacher professional development and training, a reduction in learning support assistants for children with special educational needs, and cutbacks in other capital expenditure, including on ICT.</p>
	<p>Mr Ottery's letter continues:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;This year's budget is desperate, and for the first time I simply do not have enough money to run my school. There is no doubt we will significantly overspend by the end of the financial year. More worrying is that the Government's budget is for a further two years.&quot;</p>
	<p>He worries greatly about how schools such as Stanchester will make up next year for the deficit that has been created this year.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.107.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/973" speakername="John Horam" colnum="107"  time="14:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew3">
	<p>One problem that exacerbates the difficulty is the number of centrally funded schemes&mdash;many of which are important to a school, such as support for exclusivity problems&mdash;that have suddenly ended so that there is no longer any central funding. If they come to an end when a school is struggling for the reasons that the hon. Gentleman is outlining, that is a double difficulty.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.107.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1036" speakername="David Laws" colnum="107"  time="14:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew4">
	<p>I entirely agree. I will describe later what I believe to be the sources of this year's funding problem. I wanted to start by identifying some of the impacts that that has had on the education sector.</p>
	<p>Let me quote from another letter, which I received from a primary school in my constituency, to show that these problems are reflected not only in particular sectors such as secondary education, but right across the board. The problems at South Petherton Church of England infants school are very similar to some of the problems identified in the secondary sector in Somerset. The effects of the school's financial problems are that it is having to balance its budget by cutting teaching assistant time by 15 hours immediately, decreasing the amount of time the head spends on activities in which the head would normally take a leadership role, cutting back on training and supply cover, and putting on hold capital plans for the school. Many schools are having to cut their capital expenditure and use that money to plug the gap. Mrs. Grazette, the head teacher of South Petherton infants school, explains at the end of her letter:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;The reality in our School is quite different from the rhetoric in the National Agreement and it is my experience, in talking to other Headteachers, that this is their reality too.</p>
	<p class="indent">I am a dedicated educationalist and went into Headship because I believed I could make a positive difference to children's learning. I believe that teaching can be the best job in the world but my dedication and conviction are being sorely tested at the moment!&quot;</p>
	<p>The letters I have quoted offer examples from a couple of schools. There will always be schools that lose out in particular budget rounds, but if we look at the situation in the schools right across Somerset, we find that those that were able to respond to a survey by the National Association of Head Teachers a couple of months ago provided evidence that in Somerset there had been 28 full-time teacher redundancies, that teachers were not being replaced&mdash;another problem that schools are facing&mdash;equivalent to almost 28 full-time posts, that there were 14 redundancies among support staff and a reduction in support staff hours equivalent to 895 hours. That is happening even though schools are taking action this year to try to minimise the staffing impact of the funding problems. Many schools are running down their reserves and transferring capital funding from other projects to cushion the blow this year, hoping that the Minister will produce a resolution to this problem by next year. That is why it is vital that Ministers consult over the next few months and resolve the problem, including making up the deficits, before we find ourselves facing much worse problems next year.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.108.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/950" speakername="David Heath" colnum="108"  time="14:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew5">
	<p>Does my hon. Friend agree that, particularly in smaller schools, one of the results of teacher redundancies or not filling posts is a dramatic increase in class sizes, which is contrary to the Government's stated policy?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.108.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1036" speakername="David Laws" colnum="108"  time="14:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew6">
	<p>My hon. Friend is, as ever, right. We will see the effects of this year's financial pressures not only in teacher redundancies but in rising class sizes, which cannot be good, especially as our country already has high primary school class sizes compared with other countries.</p>
	<p>If we are to address the problems next year, we must understand what caused them this year. I think that the Government are now willing to accept that there is a serious funding problem this year, which has set back the improvements that they seek in the education system. However, it has taken a long time for them to acknowledge the cause of the problems&mdash;their first effort, after trying to pretend that there were none, was to blame the LEAs. The Minister for School Standards attended one of the teachers' conferences a couple of months ago and said that the problems arose because the LEAs were squirrelling away &pound;500 million, not spending it. He said the Government would chase that matter up and discover which authorities were irresponsibly holding on to the money. Having considered the matter, the Government have backed away from that explanation. The Minister for Schools Standards wrote to me on 15 June. Having implicitly criticised Somerset county council for its policy and having blamed its financial mismanagement for locally created problems, he wrote:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;we did not set out to give the impression that LEAs were holding back funding from schools.&quot;</p>
	<p>He could have fooled a few of us. That was the impression the Government gave. I am, however, glad that they have now acknowledged that that is not what has happened.</p>
	<p>There were various reasons for the funding problem this year, the main one being that the Government completely miscalculated the higher costs coming to bear on the sector, especially pay costs. The increase in national insurance contributions should have been easy to anticipate and build into the calculations. It would perhaps have been less easy to build in the higher threshold payments, which many schools had to fund, the increase in pension costs and the teachers' pay award, which was not anything special in relation to inflation, but that should have been possible.</p>
	<p>The NAHT provides a clear summary of the main reasons why this year the Government misjudged so badly that only a few hundred million at most of the &pound;2.7 billion extra cash that they put into the education system is getting through to schools after the cost changes. The NAHT lists the areas in which the Government have misjudged things this year:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;An under estimate of teachers, and support staff, pay increases over the 3-year period . . . An under estimate of the cost of the pension increase this year . . . An under estimate of the losses from the Standards Fund over the 3 year period . . . An inappropriate inclusion of Standards Fund money in the third year . . . An under estimate of Performance Related Pay increases not covered by Government grant&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p>which is important for many schools with more senior teachers&mdash;</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;No allowance for the cost of shortening the main scale over the 3 year period . . . Inflation calculations pitched&quot;</p>
	<p>at the wrong level, and incorrect assumptions about the leadership incentive grant. I see the Minister shake his head, but I assume that the Government have accepted that some of those items were among the causes of this year's problems. I hope that he will deal with that on summing up. It is time that we moved on from the matter of who to blame for this year to what our schools are interested in, which is how we are going to sort things out next year, but if we cannot figure out a common position on what has caused the problems, we will never get anywhere next year.</p>
	<p>I am grateful to staff at Somerset county council&mdash;the director of education, Michael Jennings and his group manager, Susan Fielden&mdash;for providing a note about other pressures facing LEAs and schools, some of which are dealt with in the NAHT paper. There are other matters outside the domain of pay&mdash;inclusion, for example, is a growing cost for schools. Although we welcome the efforts that the Government are making to enable children to attend mainstream schools, there is often a significant capital cost in getting such programmes off the ground. There are transport costs, not least in rural authorities throughout the country, many of which have lost out under the new funding formula for schools introduced by the Government this year. Somerset county council tells me that</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;inflation in this sector continues to run considerably higher than average levels&quot;.</p>
	<p>Therefore, the Government's assumptions about transport costs may not always be borne out in practice. There is a growing responsibility on LEAs to provide a wide range of early-years education support, and many authorities will need an increase in provision as a result. In Somerset, that will come to some &pound;500,000 in 2003&ndash;04.</p>
	<p>There are falling rolls in many primary schools, but often school budgets will not decrease as fast as Government funding; a large and increasing gap will be generated, because although the pupil-related funding may fall off, schools will still have to meet teacher costs and operational costs, which are easy to ignore in national formulae. Also, of course, there are issues relating to standards funds, work force reform, performance pay and ICT, all of which were mentioned by the NAHT and all of which are serious problems to many authorities and schools across the country.</p>
	<p>Schools funding is a major challenge for the Government. This year, there has been a change in the national funding formula and responsibility for standards funds and threshold payments has shifted. There have been several changes to other formulae as well as a national insurance increase. I therefore accept that what might initially have appeared to the Government to be a generous increase for schools has turned out, at best, merely to meet the higher costs that schools now face. We hope that the Government will now engage in an active debate with LEAs and the teaching profession to make sure that next year they get the judgments right, not only for the education system as a whole, but for particular parts of the country. Even though most parts of the country have had real problems this year, there is no doubt that there has been considerable diversity of experience between regions and counties, and even within counties. That is probably one of the factors that have made it so difficult for the Government to address the problem this year.</p>
	<p>What are the Government saying about the measures that they will take to tackle the problem? The Minister for School Standards, in response to a written question asked by my hon. Friend the Member for Harrogate and Knaresborough (Mr. Willis) about the funding problems caused to schools, set out the Department's position on how to address the difficulties. He wrote:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;My Department is working with representatives of local government and schools to consider what changes to the schools funding system are needed from 2004&ndash;05 to ensure that every school receives a reasonable per pupil settlement next year.&quot;&mdash;[<i>Official Report</i>, 23 June 2003; Vol. 407, c. 554W.]</p>
	<p>We want the Government to acknowledge the funding problems that have been caused this year, to identify why they were caused, and to work seriously with LEAs and the teaching profession to make sure that they do not happen again. We would also like to know the Government's objectives for next year in terms of the impact of the funding settlement. What does &quot;reasonable&quot; mean? Does it simply mean that the higher costs will be covered by next year's settlement? Does it mean that the higher costs that will affect next year's budgets will be met but the deficits that are being created this year will not be tackled? If so, there will be real problems and schools will not even be able to maintain the teaching staff that they have this year. Does &quot;reasonable&quot; mean what most schools and most of us want it to mean&mdash;that the Government are planning for expansion in the schools system and that they intend to get it back on course next year? Will schools be able to recruit new teachers and teaching support assistants and expand capital programmes? I am sure that the Minister would agree that for a Government who aspire to improve education a reasonable settlement would not be a standstill settlement that simply covers the higher costs and makes good one year of problems.</p>
	<p>Those are some of the issues that the Government must address seriously today. I hope that the Minister will acknowledge that there are many other problems with the schools funding system that we simply cannot touch on in the time we have today. Such problems relate to the distribution of funding across different parts of our country and the difference between deprived communities and those that are not deprived to such a significant degree. There are also issues connected with the funding of special educational needs and the necessity of long-term funding in the education system. Instead of experiencing every year ridiculous funding uncertainties that mean that teachers do not know what will happen next, we should follow through the logic of the comprehensive spending review, so that not only do the Government wisely set three-year targets centrally, but schools have a better understanding of their budgets for two or three years ahead.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.111.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/853" speakername="Andrew Dismore" colnum="111"  time="14:24:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew7">
	<p>I congratulate the hon. Member for Yeovil (Mr. Laws) on securing this debate on such an important subject at such an opportune time. I am sure that my hon. Friend the Minister will think that I sound like a broken gramophone record because of the number of times I have made these representations to him and to his departmental colleagues. However, I can assure him that neither I nor my head teachers, parents and governors will go away until the problem goes away.</p>
	<p>We in Barnet have very good schools. Since the Labour Government came to power, we have had consistently improving results at all key stages and in GCSEs and A-levels. I pay tribute to the very good work that head teachers, staff and teaching assistants do in our schools to achieve those continuing improvements. However, I am very concerned that unless we do something dramatic to tackle the funding crisis this year and in future, the prospects for our being able to continue to maintain that improvement year on year will become remote.</p>
	<p>The starting point for the problems that we are experiencing in Barnet was the 2001 census, which showed a 9 per cent. decrease in population. Those of us who live in the area find that incredible and unbelievable, bearing in mind the amount of building work that is taking place in the area. It seems that every time one turns a corner, a building has been knocked down and a bigger block of flats is going up. Even if the census is correct for the adult population, there is certainly no sign of any fall in school rolls. The number of children we must educate remains the same, but the amount of money we have has been dramatically reduced.</p>
	<p>We have also been significantly affected by the general changes in the funding regime, particularly the changes in the standards fund. In terms of funding, the changes translate as follows: the Department for Education and Skills said that we should passport 7.8 per cent. of funding into schools' budgets&mdash;that equates in cash terms to &pound;14.5 million. However, somewhere along the line, the Department cannot have been talking to its colleagues in the Office of the Deputy Prime Minister, or not communicating as effectively as it might, because Barnet, which was on the ceiling for DFES passporting, was put on the floor for cash. We received only &pound;7 million for the whole council&mdash;only half of what we had been told by the DFES to passport to schools. We have had a major increase&mdash;24 per cent.&mdash;in council tax and it is not realistic to expect local taxpayers to pay any more.</p>
	<p>The LEA has been able to passport the 7.8 per cent. to schools, but significant budgeting problems remain because of rising costs, which the hon. Member for Yeovil identified. They include national insurance contributions increases, pension increases, the teachers' pay award and other rising costs that we know about. The problems are having a serious and deleterious effect on a number of secondary schools in my constituency. Only yesterday I received a copy of a letter sent to my hon. Friend the Minister for School Standards from St. James' school. Mr. McSharry, the head teacher, writes:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;We are a very good school.&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p>I agree&mdash;</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;Our students come from a corridor of deprivation including Burnt Oak, Grahame Park, West Hendon, Cricklewood and Kilburn&quot;</p>
	<p>but the</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;deprivation is not reflected in the appearance&quot;</p>
	<p>or</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;behaviour of the students, or . . . their examination results.&quot;</p>
	<p>It is a high-achieving school given its intake. Mr. McSharry continues:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;I would be the first to applaud what this Government has done for education.&quot;</p>
	<p>He makes some nice comments about me which modesty forbids me to read out, then points out that</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;this financial crisis is having a deleterious and corrosive effect on morale and will undermine, indeed wipe from the collective memory what has been achieved.&quot;</p>
	<p>He comments on the &pound;451,000 budget deficit facing the school in the current year, even after a staffing reduction of five teachers. That has probably been achieved by natural wastage, but part of the problem is caused by the need to employ agency staff to fill vacancies, which is a common problem in London&mdash;I am sure that my hon. Friend the Under-Secretary has the same problem in his constituency&mdash;and which has a major impact in terms of increasing costs. Mr. McSharry also makes a point about the standards grant, which for St James' school was reduced by &pound;114,000. The recruitment and retention element, which was included in that amount, was reduced by more than &pound;30,000. That is why the school is facing serious problems.</p>
	<p>The deficit goes beyond that, because the school is trying to obtain specialist school status in science. It is very good at science, maths and ICT, but the Mr. McSharry and I understand that a school in deficit cannot apply for specialist status. I hope that when my hon. Friend the Under-Secretary replies to the debate, he will make it clear that schools that are facing a deficit this year will not be penalised in applications for specialist status, which might actually help them to get out of their difficulties.</p>
	<p>The DFES has reviewed Barnet's education budget&mdash;as have I, during many long, tortuous meetings in which I had a wet towel wrapped around my head to assist my efforts to understand the figures. We have come up with various ideas and solutions about what should be done. The DFES talked about the centrally retained element of the education budget. I met my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Education and Skills at the beginning of June to discuss the matter. He felt that there was no need for the Department to revise the central budget corrections that had been made for the current year. The budget includes, for example, &pound;1.1 million that has been retained as a contingency. It will be disbursed to schools during the current year, mainly to primary schools, which have very little scope to deal with this year's budget problems. The pupil referral unit, which the DFES approved, should be transferred from the adolescent psychiatric unit to the education budget&mdash;that is &pound;700,000&mdash;and there is an increase in the SEN budget of &pound;750,000. Last year's deficit of &pound;900,000 was a historic overspend caused primarily by the substantial increase in costs for non-maintained schools. Those costs have skyrocketed: last year, they increased by an average of 15 per cent., with some increases of up to 25 per cent. Day schools' costs are up by 6.8 per cent. in the current year, and residential schools' by 10.1 per cent. Although there are only 112 statemented kids in non-maintained schools&mdash;almost the same number as last year&mdash;the costs have increased dramatically; something must be done to correct that.</p>
	<p>I was very pleased that my hon. Friend the Under-Secretary wrote to Barnet's cabinet member for education in these terms:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;We recognise that you have not deliberately withheld money from schools and that centrally held budgets can be justified and/or were agreed with schools through the forum.&quot;</p>
	<p>That argument has been addressed, but the problem remains. There is no central money left that can be passported that is not already earmarked for schools.</p>
	<p>We have been told that schools can consider the revenue use of capital funds, but there is very little money of that type available. I shall give an example of that shortly. We are told that schools can consider licensed deficits, but I understand from the education authority and head teachers that licensed deficits can be achieved only through redundancy programmes. By the end of the calendar year, Barnet faces between 15 and 20 teacher redundancies, with a similar number of teaching posts not filled and, of equal importance, similar numbers of redundancies and unfilled teaching assistant posts. I fail to see how we can implement the agreements on work-life balance in schools that the Government have made with the various unions against a pattern of unfilled vacancies and redundancies for teachers and teaching assistants.</p>
	<p>Barnet would have to deal with a licensed deficit of between &pound;3.5 million and &pound;4 million, which would have a significant impact. No doubt my hon. Friend the Under-Secretary remembers Copthall school, which he visited to present A-level certificates to sixth formers. A very high-achieving school, it was ranked the highest performing girls' comprehensive in the country in <i>The Guardian</i> value-added league tables. It has just won specialist status as a business school. My hon. Friend wrote to me when I raised the case of that school and suggested that the head teacher and the governors would need</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;to fully consider the flexibilities&quot;</p>
	<p>that the Secretary of State had announced on 15 May. They have done that, but they are getting nowhere in dealing with the problem. They have already implemented a cut of &pound;200,000, which is equivalent to 3 per cent. of the budget. They have considered using capital, but they have only &pound;85,000 of capital this year, and that has already been committed to fixing leaks in the roof and windows. They are left with a deficit of &pound;200,000.</p>
	<p>The head teacher and governors are happy to set up a deficit budget and, in effect, that is what they have done. However, they cannot agree with the education authority on a licensed recovery plan, because such a plan would inevitably mean redundancies. A letter from Barnet's deputy chief education officer to the head teacher states that</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;a licensed deficit in the order of &pound;200,000&quot;</p>
	<p>would have to be on the back of</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;a recovery plan which the LEA agrees is viable . . . over three years. The school should plan on the basis that future years increases in the School Budget Share will cover pay awards and inflation on other goods and services.&quot;</p>
	<p>The letter states that</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;The cost of staff at the moment&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p>after the 3 per cent. cut&mdash;</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;is 107 per cent. of the school budget share&quot;.</p>
	<p>and that</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;the key to a viable recovery plan lies in making sufficient redundancies or other staff reductions in 2003&ndash;04 which give a saving in that year but give a significant saving in 2004&ndash;05 and future years for the school to save what is initially a cumulating deficit.&quot;</p>
	<p>The importance of that is that the cut might balance the books for this year, but will have an impact on staffing in future years unless we get the budget right for next year and subsequent years. The letter also comments on capital funding, but I have already referred to that. Therefore, for the school to get a licensed budget, the education department is demanding proposals for redundancies,</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;including numbers and stage of process&quot;,</p>
	<p>as part of the outline recovery plan.</p>
	<p>Mrs. Gadd, the head teacher, has indicated that she and her governors are not prepared to set a budget that would be licensed because of that requirement of the recovery plan. She says that there is no slack available in the school and that it now faces several appalling options. By the end of the year, the school will either be sending all the children home one day a week, or it will have to send all the children in year 11&mdash;the GCSE year&mdash;home permanently after Christmas, to let them study for themselves. The problem is now starting to become serious. Who is going pay staff wages by the end of the year?</p>
	<p>The two examples I have given illustrate the significant problems facing schools. Our head teachers have worked very hard to come to terms with the problems. They have not pressed the nuclear button and started to send kids home, but have worked responsibly to try to balance the books. St. James' school has made significant cuts and lost five teaching posts, yet still faces a shortfall of &pound;450,000. Copthall school has made a 3 per cent. reduction in its budget, but still faces redundancies. That will undoubtedly have an impact on the schools in the current year and future years.</p>
	<p>I can say to my hon. Friend the Under-Secretary, as I said to the Prime Minister during Prime Minister's questions the other week, that parents in my constituency are not interested in apportioning blame; they want the problem sorted out. We are not going to be able to sort the problem out with the remedies that have so far been offered by the Secretary of State. We have to have more money if we are to avoid education meltdown in Barnet&mdash;in the schools in my constituency&mdash;at the start of the next calendar year. We must have something to offer them to sort the problem out.</p>
	<p>Significant cuts in spending have been made this year. Will next year's budgets for schools be sufficient to catch up the ground lost this year? If licensed budgets are set for the schools that have been able to achieve the requirements, will next year's budget provide enough to catch up that licensed deficit, so that we will not see year-on-year cuts as the schools run to stand still or to make up the budget deficit? What will happen when the schools standards fund changes, as was proposed last year? That has had a disproportionate effect in my constituency, with some schools losing significantly larger amounts of money than others, and the effect throughout the country has been patchy. Will my hon. Friend the Under-Secretary also tell us what will happen to specialist school applications, given the present position? That is the question raised by Mr. McSharry, the head teacher of St. James' school.</p>
	<p>I am not crying wolf; this is a serious problem. My local education authority, Conservative controlled though it may be, has worked responsibly with the Department to try to get to the bottom of the story. The Department has worked responsibly with the education authority to look at various options, and my heads and governors have also worked well together. There has been a team effort to try to work through the problems, and I have done what I can to bring people together and hold the meetings needed to get to the bottom of the problem and sort it out. However, I think that we have now got to the bottom of it. The problem is that there is simply not enough money in the pot. Something has to be done.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.116.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/724" speakername="A J Beith" colnum="116"  time="14:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew8">
	<p>I am glad that my hon. Friend the Member for Yeovil (Mr. Laws) has secured and introduced this debate, which he has done from a background of constituency experience and also from a grasp of the Government's public expenditure plans that is unusually good among Members. In doing so, he has given me the opportunity to refer to the situation in Northumberland, which is particularly bad and desperately needs attention in the next two years. The problems in Northumberland have built up over a considerable period of time. They consist of not only the current problems of the standards fund losses, the additional expenditure on pensions and the pay settlement, but the impact of a decade of bad local government funding settlements.</p>
	<p>I have gone with a mixed delegation of Members of Parliament from three different parties to both the previous Government and the current Government because year after year the formula, which was established by the Conservative Government and continued by this one, left Northumberland with less expenditure on local government services, particularly education, than other parts of the country. That has not been remedied by the changes so far made to the local government funding system and the effect has been severe.</p>
	<p>Although the decision emanates from the Office of the Deputy Prime Minister, the Department for Education and Skills must have been closely involved in the decision and discussions. It should recognise the severe impact of a bad local government settlement on a local authority, the largest single responsibility of which is education. The situation in shire counties has been severe.</p>
	<p>Northumberland has had significant setbacks in obtaining funds from the Department for Education and Skills, particularly by way of private finance initiative schemes. The authority has twice put up and twice had rejected PFI schemes for the Ashington area, which includes schools in my constituency, and for the Berwick area. On each occasion, it picked up hints that it was not far short of the conditions required for the approval of a scheme. It was suggested that if the authority put this or that right, it could hope to secure approval at a later stage. It has been through that experience twice and groups of schools, which desperately need investment, have been unable to secure it because of successive decisions on PFI schemes.</p>
	<p>In the case of the Berwick area, the county is proposing a massive reorganisation of schools&mdash;the amalgamation on to one site of a high school and two middle schools&mdash;with no confidence whatsoever that PFI funding can be obtained for the conversion and construction of buildings. The county authority finds it difficult to convince anyone in Berwick of the merits of the scheme because everyone says, &quot;You'll never find the money.&quot; Even if we put up with the loss of the existing schools&mdash;the middle schools are doing a particularly good job&mdash;we cannot have any confidence that a great new campus will have the necessary funding for it to have major compensating advantages.</p>
	<p>The cost pressures have been so serious that the education authority had to ask head teachers to stop making people redundant because it could not afford the redundancy payments. The director of education sent a letter to heads earlier this year pointing out,</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;There are 12 schools where normally we would approve the voluntary redundancy of permanent staff over 50. The cost of those redundancies . . . would be in the region of &pound;3,000,000, yet the amount of budget available to fund redundancies is only &pound;1,000,000. Over the last ten or so years a large amount has been spent on redundancies in schools, and we are still paying for this from the education budget. Rather than funding redundancies, we would prefer to provide more resources for schools.&quot;</p>
	<p>The council scraped together &pound;500,000 from its PFI funding and &pound;1 million from elsewhere to put forward a proposal to stop the redundancies and keep the posts. The whole process was cost-driven. One or two teachers had probably hoped that they would get voluntary redundancy and were denied it, and the story illustrates the desperate snatching at one fund or another to deal with immediate cost pressures.</p>
	<p>The pressure to close down village schools is largely derived from those cost pressures. Major reviews are taking place in two areas of the county and they will be followed by reviews in other areas. The proposals for the Ashington area are likely to include closing Linton school in my constituency. The school has massive and remarkable community support to which I pay warm tribute. I have watched how the community has cared for its school. In the Berwick area, a whole series of schools face the possibility of closure or amalgamation. They are Horncliffe, Norham, Scremerston, Cornhill-on-Tweed, Ford, Milfield, Lowick and Holy Island. That large group could be reduced to two or three schools. Village after village would lose its school, contrary to the Government's statement that there is a presumption against village school closures.</p>
	<p>Two factors are driving the proposals: the county's educational problems and the surplus places argument, which the Government are fond of using. The county administration fears that the surplus places argument works against it in its PFI bids. In seeking approval for major capital investment in schools, it has to meet the argument that it has too high a quota of surplus places.</p>
	<p>What are surplus places in village schools? They arise primarily from two things. First, in a village school a teacher could be teaching 15 children of a wide age range. Theoretically, the teacher could teach 20 or 25 children in that class, but there may not be that number of children between the ages of five and seven in the village that year. It is in the nature of schools in small communities that teachers may take two-year groups, or, in some cases, all the year groups in the school, as happens in my constituency. Despite the versatility that teachers show, the problem remains. When surplus places are viewed in that way, the impact is to put under pressure of closure schools in villages that are active in their support and where it is certain that there will be pupils in future years.</p>
	<p>The second factor in the surplus places policy is the fact that many of the schools were built to accommodate children between the ages of five and 15, or in some cases, five and 11, whereas the only children that they actually have are between five and nine, because the county has a three-tier system. That does not mean that the accommodation is wasted. In almost every case, spare classroom accommodation in schools is used for nursery classes or playgroups, which are often independently run, or for other community purposes that are welcomed in the communities that are served. It ought to be a sensible part of any rural policy to use community assets, such as village schools, as ambitiously and flexibly as possible to meet the various social needs of the community.</p>
	<p>What is the process by which policies on education funding for the next two years, and the surplus places policy, are subjected to rural-proofing? How is it that that objective, which the Government and the Countryside Agency have set for themselves, is applied to policies that appear to have the opposite effect and work directly against rural areas?</p>
	<p>Let us consider the village first schools that are threatened and those that will be threatened when the review moves on to other areas. The atmosphere in the first schools is positive. My description of the funding situation would not be readily apparent to someone who just went into a class in which young children were being taught because of the dedication of staff in our small schools. There is huge community support for the schools and they can rely on the community to fill some of the gaps by fundraising and coming in to help with activities. Great successes are achieved, but all that could be thrown away in the closure and amalgamation process.</p>
	<p>The impact of the financial problems is more immediately obvious in middle and high schools. Subjects can no longer be taught and activities that were being developed have had to be abandoned or greatly reduced. The impact is severe. There has also been a serious impact on high schools, which include schools that are trying to invest in staff and facilities to raise standards that are not high enough at present. Berwick high school is trying to acquire the status of business school. Doing so against the current background and the PFI refusals seems a Herculean task. It is battling the tide of funding, which is going against it all the time.</p>
	<p>When the Minister deals with the wider issues of education funding for the next two years, I want him to apply rural-proofing to those policies and examine their impact on village schools and smaller schools. I also want him to recognise that in rural and urban Northumberland the impact of a decade of school underfunding is making it virtually impossible for schools to tackle the problems that they want to resolve, which the Government are urging them to resolve. Northumberland's situation is serious and I ask the Minister to give it some special personal attention</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.118.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/950" speakername="David Heath" colnum="118"  time="14:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew9">
	<p>I, too, congratulate my hon. Friend the Member for Yeovil (Mr. Laws) on securing the debate. I express my surprise that more hon. Members are not here to represent the views of their schools. If that gives the proceedings a slight Somerset bias it is no bad thing as far as we are concerned. I shall not rehearse the arguments that my hon. Friend has already made. My right hon. Friend the Member for Berwick-upon-Tweed (Mr. Beith) faces almost exactly the same problems in his constituency as I do in mine. Our constituencies have a similar, rural outlook.</p>
	<p>We have been here so many times before. Throughout the last Parliament we almost had a monthly repertory company talking about the worst funded local authorities in this country and making the case on behalf of our educational authorities. It was nearly always the right hon. Member for Birmingham, Yardley (Estelle Morris) who was deputed to answer our questions, and we knew each other's speeches off by heart. We knew exactly what we were going to say, and once we had finished the debate, we would agree that there was a serious problem that needed to be addressed, but could not be entirely addressed within the Department for Education and Skills. We have always understood that.</p>
	<p>The holy grail that was before us was always the funding review and the change in funding formula. That was going to make the difference and end the decades of underfunding of the worst funded authorities in the country. I have to say that we are bitterly disappointed at what has happened this year, overall and in specific terms, to Somerset schools. We do not seem to have made the quantum leap that will take our children into the same funding league as those elsewhere in the country.</p>
	<p>I often cite the fact that our children annually receive from Government &pound;1,500 per child less than those in some London suburbs. I accept the points made by the hon. Member for Hendon (Mr. Dismore) as that clearly is not the case in his constituency, but that sort of disparity is impossible to justify. It is the root cause of everything else that flows from it. Until we have a genuine entitlement for our children we will be robbing Peter to pay Paul and making do in our education systems. We are not providing the level of funding that is appropriate for our very good schools, teachers and governing bodies, which are doing a superb job with the little that they have.</p>
	<p>The inequity in the funding formula used to be dealt with by the standards fund, which was used as an unofficial DFES slush fund. Even that has now been cast into confusion, and as a result, schools face serious problems. There is no hope of a further review that will deal with the underlying deficit. We hear much from Ministers about the need for stability in education funding, and we absolutely agree. We have argued for that for years. We want there to be the certainty, at least in the medium term, of a three-year rolling programme of education funding. What we do not want is stability in deficit, which makes it impossible to plan effectively for the future, to make the necessary investments and to set aside funds. That applies both to revenue and to capital.</p>
	<p>Somerset has a huge backlog of temporary buildings. At one point, well over 800 temporary classrooms were in regular use. Not only had some of them been put there 40 years ago, but they were being used for the education of children whose grandparents had been taught in them as children. That is a disgrace; it should have been dealt with years ago.</p>
	<p>I accept that, because there is such an enormous requirement for resources and funds, it cannot be met overnight and the Government are making a start. However, that means that there is limited scope for progress on all the other things that schools should be doing. My right hon. Friend the Member for Berwick-upon-Tweed spoke about wider community use. That is one of the things that get lost when schools have no capital fund, because they do not have spare buildings to put to such use.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.120.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/901" speakername="Mark Francois" colnum="120"  time="14:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew10">
	<p>Without wishing to deny anything that the hon. Gentleman has said about Somerset, is he aware that Essex had the worst grant settlement in the country? In both our counties, many are concerned that this year is not a one-off. The title of the debate signifies that it is the beginning of a process. Unless the Government can be persuaded to amend that process the problem will be magnified, for both pupils and teachers, in Somerset, Essex and many other counties.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.120.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/950" speakername="David Heath" colnum="120"  time="14:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew11">
	<p>Obviously, I cannot speak for Essex, but I know that at least 40 local authorities face the situation every year, and have done for decades. Because it is recurrent, problems are exacerbated rather than getting better. On top of the root cause of the problem, we are now experiencing the immediate issues set out so clearly by my hon. Friend the Member for Yeovil. They affect schools in my constituency, such as Bruton primary school, which I visited last week. It is a superb school; it received a wonderful Ofsted report, is doing everything right and has an enthusiastic head and other staff. It also has very enthusiastic governors who had gone about financial planning in a sensible way: they knew that the roll would fall over the next year and then recover, so they set aside money in order to maintain class sizes and ensure that staff remained. However, they now face the unhappy prospect of reducing their staff numbers and massively increasing class sizes&mdash;and it is not their fault. They do not blame the local education authority&mdash;they have worked closely with it&mdash;but they do blame the Government. Bruton primary is not the only school affected; there are Nunney first school and Horsington school and I could list many more.</p>
	<p>If the situation is not dealt with at source, at Government level, it cannot be dealt with by the local authorities. As the hon. Member for Hendon says, there is a limit to the tolerance of our electorate for council tax increases. They cannot continue paying more and more and, by the gearing effect, receiving less and less. They cannot keep on cross-subsidising education out of social services and roads maintenance and all the other things that a county council funds.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.120.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/724" speakername="A J Beith" colnum="120"  time="14:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew12">
	<p>Let me give an illustration. Northumberland county council found that, even with a council tax increase of 12.8 per cent., it could not achieve the level of education spending presumed by the Secretary of State.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.120.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/950" speakername="David Heath" colnum="120"  time="14:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew13">
	<p>That does not surprise me. If there has been one recurrent theme over many years, it has been that whatever the Department for Education and Skills wants to happen, the Department for the Environment as was, now the Office of the Deputy Prime Minister, does not allow the system enough elasticity for it to work. Education authorities that are committed to education and people in the schools system who are committed to schools find themselves the losers. That must not persist. The education system reminds me of a dangerous road where somebody is required to die before an improvement is made. One feels that our schools will have to fail before anybody is prepared to acknowledge that there is a funding problem. I am not prepared to see our schools fail. They are good schools and deserve our support. They should not have to support themselves through jumble sales and raffles. They should have the education service funding what they need.</p>
	<p>Last Thursday, at Education questions, I asked the Secretary of State why he had not found time to discuss the immediate problems with Somerset education authority. He replied, I believe, that he would be happy to do so. Will the Minister confirm that so that a meeting can be arranged? Although officials from the authority and the Department are to meet, I should still like to sit round a table with the Secretary of State, my hon. Friend the Member for Yeovil and the authority's representatives so that we can thrash out the issues. I hope that we can co-operate on finding solutions.</p>
	<p>Finally, I invite the Minister and his colleagues to visit Somerset. During my time as an MP, no Education Minister has ever visited the schools in my constituency. It is about time that Ministers came to see the excellent work that is done in our schools and the problems that they face. If they will not do so, we shall continue to have Adjournment debates about Somerset's education funding every year, if not, as my hon. Friend suggests, every month. The Minister can be assured that we will not let up until we have a fair deal for our children.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.121.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1174" speakername="John Pugh" colnum="121"  time="15:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew14">
	<p>I congratulate my hon. Friend the Member for Yeovil (Mr. Laws) on securing the debate and on his excellent introduction. I also commiserate with the Minister, who seems to have been set upon by posses of Liberal Democrats. When he and his colleagues drew straws on Monday morning, he must have got the short one, because there can be no subject that the Government would less like to talk about at the moment than school funding. At the very least, it is a public relations disaster. At the worst, it suggests that the Government are guilty of provoking a major redundancy crisis across the land. The problem is not confined to Somerset, Essex or London. Indeed, school after school, and LEA after LEA, have identified such problems. By and large, the ministerial response has been first to deny that there is a problem and then to distribute blame elsewhere. That has set LEAs against the Government in a rather unfortunate way.</p>
	<p>I am glad to say that the Government seem to have backtracked, but they are still vulnerable to two charges. The more serious is that they are guilty of deceit because they have presided over underfunding while appearing to be generous. The lesser but more convincing charge is that they are guilty of incompetence because they intended to increase school budgets wholesale this year but provoked a financial crisis in some, although not all, schools and LEAs. In that respect, it is noticeable that those who have done well are always the slowest to complain.</p>
	<p>I find the lesser charge more convincing, because I am sure that the Government genuinely do not want the flak and that the Minister does not want to be here answering questions on the issue. The Government do not want to resort, as they did earlier this year, to knee-jerk reactions, such as allowing schools to use their capital for purposes that were not previously intended. They do not want to put a strain on their partnership with LEAs.</p>
	<p>The remarks of the Government's advisers before the Select Committee on Education and Skills last week also convince me that Ministers did not want to get into this mess in the first place and that they did not foresee it. Those advisers did not say that the Government had failed to listen to their advice, but that there was a problem with the modelling of school budgets. However, I think that there may have been a failure of anticipation and that it would be plausible to talk about a failure of modelling only where certain data could not have been foreseen. Most of the events that have caused schools problems this year have, however, been perfectly foreseeable. The increases in national insurance and teachers' pay were known, and the effect on school budgets of restructuring salary scales should have been. Pension contributions were also a known factor. The DFES certainly knew about the phasing out of the standards fund; indeed, it inspired the programme. The second-year effects of pay increases for non-teaching staff were known, as were overall pupil numbers.</p>
	<p>The DFES advisers' only defence against the accusation that they should have taken account of such information was to say that they knew about it in general terms. They said that they knew the global figures, but that one could surely not expect them to work out specific outcomes. For example, they made play of the fact that they did not have their finger on the exact fluctuations in pupil numbers; and the extent to which LEAs would passport the funds was not easily identified, although they could have gone by previous practice, as most LEAs used to passport all that the Government asked them to do. Floors and ceilings may not come within the provenance of local authorities; and every local authority has a different distribution formula when handing out the money to schools.</p>
	<p>Coming from the Department's advisers, that is a fairly feeble defence. They are not charged with not knowing exactly which schools would have problems; they are charged with failing to anticipate, because LEAs have different distribution formulae, different attitudes to passporting and different positions on floors and ceilings, that many schools would be seriously underfunded. If the advisers' modelling could not pick out a general failure, the Department needs to do one of two things. It should either scrap the model, as it clearly does not work; or it should sack the modellers.</p>
	<p>The question is how the Government will progress out of that mess. I accept that next year will not be a repetition of this year in every respect. Certain variables will be better known. For instance, the local government settlement is stable for three years, although I understand that many hon. Members are deeply unhappy about that. Many costs, such as national insurance, are already factored into school budgets. The issue of school balances and of schools holding money unnecessarily will be addressed, and I hope that the switch in the standards fund will have started to bed down. However, I should like the Minister to say something about how it will be dealt with next year, and whether money taken from the standards fund will be returned to the general pot.</p>
	<p>There are still imponderables. It is difficult to calculate the effect of regradings&mdash;wage negotiations are always an uncertainty on the horizon&mdash;and there is always the possibility that the new freedoms being given to local authorities will affect what they do with their funds. However, because it is an easier proposition for them, the modellers should look at the matter in the round. The figures shown to the Select Committee suggest that if we strip out the ongoing costs, there could be something like a 1.4 per cent. real-terms increase in school budgets next year.</p>
	<p>Two questions remain&mdash;whether that sort of figure, which is relatively comforting, incorporates all the real costs that schools will incur; and whether the general figure lacks significant local variation. In order to prevent local variations presenting a different picture against the background of general increases, the DFES has a responsibility to try to firefight in advance. It needs to engage in significant consultation with schools, unions and heads. As the Select Committee said, it needs to liaise effectively, or more effectively, with the ODPM. It needs to clarify the position with regard to the standards fund in general, and to consult the Local Government Association, which still says that an extra &pound;1 billion will be required.</p>
	<p>Above all, the DFES needs to ensure that no initiatives are adding further costs to the school budget. I take what my hon. Friend the Member for Somerton and Frome (Mr. Heath) said about stability in deficit, but schools need stability in funding and in practice. That may not be an attractive prospect for a hyperactive Minister, but I suggest that it is a good one.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.123.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/749" speakername="Graham Brady" colnum="123"  time="15:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew15">
	<p>I warmly congratulate the hon. Member for Yeovil (Mr. Laws) on securing a debate on school funding not only because it is a matter of particular importance today and this year&mdash;we are in the midst of a major crisis&mdash;but because he picked a debate that looks forward. One of the biggest worries faced by schools throughout the country is that the funding problem is not one for this year only. The much-trumpeted stability and predictability in funding sounded attractive when that sounded like an increase in funding, but now that we have school deficits and teachers facing redundancy, it seems a much less attractive prospect.</p>
	<p>The hon. Gentleman has therefore done a good job, not only for his constituents, but for the House, in bringing the right debate before us. He commented on the sadness caused by the absence of the Minister for School Standards. I was tempted to observe that it is infinitely better to have the Under-Secretary of State for Education and Skills, the hon. Member for Enfield, Southgate (Mr. Twigg), here with us in person than to have the Minister for School Standards appearing by videolink, which appears to be his habit at the moment&mdash;he addressed the governors' conference and the foundation and aided schools by videolink. Perhaps that is an indication&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.124.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1086" speakername="John McWilliam" colnum="124"  time="15:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew16">
	<p>(Mr. John McWilliam): Order. The hon. Gentleman is suggesting something that I doubt Standing Orders will ever allow in my lifetime.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.124.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/749" speakername="Graham Brady" colnum="124"  time="15:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew17">
	<p>You have been in the House far longer than I have, Mr. Deputy Speaker, but in the six years that I have been here so many things have happened that I hoped that I would never see that I wish that I could share your certainty.</p>
	<p>Perhaps the Minister for School Standards is being self-critical somewhere else. Perhaps he is now absorbing the responsibility that he must bear personally for the problems that are being experienced in schools throughout the country. I have said before that I believe that the problem is the grossest betrayal of trust of which the Government are guilty, because they promised so much in education. People in the world of education, parents and children feel bewildered and let down by the sorry pass to which we have come due to the Government's education policies.</p>
	<p>The hon. Member for Yeovil started by welcoming the successes of some of his local schools. I, too, could pay tribute to many successful schools in my area, but the tragedy is that such schools are now succeeding not because of, or even with the support and help of, but in spite of the Department for Education and Skills. It is important to consider briefly what the situation is now. It is easy to pluck examples out of the air. For instance, an example from my constituency is that the head of Bollin primary school, a colleague, has been pushed into not only organising a f&ecirc;te or auction&mdash;I think that another hon. Member referred to something similar&mdash;but jumping out of an aircraft in a sponsored free-fall parachute jump to raise money for the school budget. That should certainly not be necessary in any school in this country.</p>
	<p>We have also all read in our newspapers today about the splendid example being set by the hon. Member for North-West Leicestershire (David Taylor), who, in common with the head, teachers and support staff at one of the schools in his constituency, is giving up a day's pay to contribute to that school's shortfall of &pound;38,000. We read too of a Coulsdon high school in Croydon, where parents were warned on Friday that every pupil will lose one afternoon's school a week from September due to its &pound;300,000 shortfall.</p>
	<p>The Conservative group on the Local Government Association, which is now the majority group, has been surveying local education authorities and has received some worrying replies on the current funding crisis. About 67 per cent. of the replies from LEAs indicated that there would be some redundancies in local schools, while 22 per cent. of replies reported that teaching posts were being left unfilled owing to financial pressures. Croydon reported between 100 and 130 posts left unfilled, Leeds did not fill 78 teaching posts, and more than 35 contracts on the Isle of Wight will not be renewed. About 97 per cent. of the replies reported that at least one school in those LEA areas had been forced to set a deficit budget, which is a serious problem for those schools. If the Minister does not want to trust the Conservative group on the LGA&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.125.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1296" speakername="Stephen Twigg" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Education and Skills"  colnum="125"  time="15:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spmin0">
	<p>Perish the thought.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.125.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/749" speakername="Graham Brady" colnum="125"  time="15:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew18">
	<p>Perhaps the hon. Gentleman will trust his old friends in the National Union of Teachers, which has also been surveying schools and LEAs. It has found that two thirds of the respondents in its survey reported that there would be reductions in staff due to loss of teaching or support staff posts. About 60 per cent. of respondents reported that teaching posts would be lost. There are serious problems not only in one or two localities, but throughout the country.</p>
	<p>We have heard several good contributions to the debate. The hon. Member for Somerton and Frome (Mr. Heath) made some telling points about the problems faced by his local schools and said that no Minister in the present Government had visited one of his local schools. I do not know whether the Minister will respond to that comment in due course, but if he does not, I am happy to assure him that a Minister in the next Government will. Such a visit will be high in the list of priorities. The hon. Member for Hendon, North&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.125.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/950" speakername="David Heath" colnum="125"  time="15:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew19">
	<p>The sad fact is that, when I was chairman of the education authority at the time when there was a Conservative Government, the only school that a Minister visited was a public school.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.125.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/749" speakername="Graham Brady" colnum="125"  time="15:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew20">
	<p>Well, there we are. We used to hear about Punch and Judy politics from the former leader of the hon. Gentleman's party. Perhaps that was what was in mind. I give my personal assurance that we shall put matters right.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.125.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1036" speakername="David Laws" colnum="125"  time="15:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew21">
	<p>Will the hon. Gentleman give way?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.125.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/749" speakername="Graham Brady" colnum="125"  time="15:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew22">
	<p>I shall in a moment, but I want first to refer to the remarks made by the hon. Member for Hendon, North.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.125.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/853" speakername="Andrew Dismore" colnum="125"  time="15:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew23">
	<p>It is just Hendon.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.125.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/749" speakername="Graham Brady" colnum="125"  time="15:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew24">
	<p>The whole of Hendon? The people of Hendon have great good fortune.</p>
	<p>The hon. Member for Hendon (Mr. Dismore) referred to the danger of educational meltdown. His remarks are especially important because of the quality of schools in the borough of Barnet, which has some of the best schools in the country. It is a tragedy that that area is one of the places that has been hit the hardest during the current crisis.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.125.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1036" speakername="David Laws" colnum="125"  time="15:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew25">
	<p>As Lord Ashdown's successor in Yeovil, I am certainly not engaging in Punch and Judy politics, nor was my hon. Friend the Member for Somerton and Frome (Mr. Heath). We are having a constructive debate about education funding in future years and the distant possibility of having a Conservative Government. Under the Conservative party, there were two decades of the slowest growth in education budgets in the post-war period. It was only about 1.4 per cent. per year in real terms. If the Conservatives ever get back into power, will the hon. Gentleman make a pledge today that he will stick with the big increases in education funding that are in the current comprehensive spending review?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.126.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/749" speakername="Graham Brady" colnum="126"  time="15:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew26">
	<p>During the 18 years of Conservative Governments, we had sustained real-terms growth in education funding. The hon. Gentleman has already accepted that. What is unprecedented is what is happening now. Admittedly, the Government have put large sums into the budget, which is lifting large sums out of the pockets of our constituents supposedly to pay for the local services. However, the Government are still forcing schools and LEAs to fire teachers, which is taxing more and delivering less.</p>
	<p>We have heard some telling points about why such problems have occurred. As I said at the outset, it is most important to look to future years, the problems that our schools will face and how we can solve them. I know that the Minister realises the importance of that. The first issue that schools that are being forced either to set deficit budgets or to spend their reserves this year are having to consider is how they will get out of that situation and recover their deficits. I am sure that they will be interested to hear the Minister's advice on the matter. The second problem is how they can deal with the black hole in capital funding, which is now being opened up. I do not like praising the Government but, in all fairness, I give them credit for increasing capital funding for schools in the past couple of years. However, the fact that schools are now being told to take the money that they were given for capital and spend it on teacher redundancies has left them utterly bewildered.</p>
	<p>As Doug McAvoy of the NUT put it, what are we to do? If our boiler breaks down in the middle of the winter, should we sack the deputy head? Schools throughout the country are grappling with such problems. They will want to hear the Minister's views. Above all, there is the ticking time bomb of the teachers' work-load agreement. That will be introduced in September this year, and the biggest costs and increases in responsibilities for schools, particularly in staffing terms, will kick in not this September but next. Against a background of stable funding and stable deficits, that leaves the Minister with serious questions about how schools are to reduce teacher work load as the Government have promised they should be able to do. How are they to increase staffing levels against the backdrop of schools throughout the country either having to make staff redundant or facing an inability to replace staff who are leaving?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.126.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1296" speakername="Stephen Twigg" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Education and Skills"  colnum="126"  time="15:20:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spmin1">
	<p>I am pleased to have this brief opportunity to respond to what has been an important and constructive debate. I am delighted to hear that my hon. Friend the Minister for School Standards has undertaken to be self-critical, and I shall do my best to match him either in person or via videolink.</p>
	<p>I congratulate the hon. Member for Yeovil (Mr. Laws) on securing this important debate. I thank him in particular for his comments about the specialist schools in his constituency. I join him in congratulating the two schools in his constituency on yesterday achieving their specialist status. I am also delighted to be able to inform him and the hon. Member for Somerton and Frome (Mr. Heath) that I shall be in Somerset next week, attending in person&mdash;not via videolink&mdash;two primary school conferences in Weston-super-Mare. At those events, about 500 primary head teachers will have the opportunity to raise all sorts of issues with me.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.127.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/950" speakername="David Heath" colnum="127"  time="15:20:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew27">
	<p>We are gladdened in the extreme to hear that the Minister will be visiting the historic county of Somerset, but would he like to visit the current county of Somerset as well? Weston-super-Mare lies in a different local authority area.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.127.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1296" speakername="Stephen Twigg" colnum="127"  time="15:20:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew28">
	<p>I am suitably humbled. I checked in &quot;Dod's&quot;, and the address for the hon. Member for Weston-super-Mare (Brian Cotter) is North Somerset, so I thought I was on firm ground. I accept the kind offer from the hon. Member for Somerton and Frome to visit his constituency at a suitable opportunity. I can also confirm that my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State would be happy to meet the hon. Gentleman with a delegation. He should write to my right hon. Friend and an undertaking will then be made.</p>
	<p>In his opening speech, the hon. Member for Yeovil said that when he visits schools the improvements of recent years are pointed out. I shall briefly refer to those. The hon. Member for Altrincham and Sale, West (Mr. Brady) acknowledged some of the progress on capital that we have made in the past six years. It is worth reflecting on the figures for Government support for capital investment in school buildings. During the three years in the run-up to Labour coming to power, the figures were &pound;0.6 billion in 1995&ndash;96, &pound;0.7 billion in 1996&ndash;97 and &pound;0.8 billion in 1997&ndash;98. The figures for this year and the next two years are &pound;3.8 billion, &pound;4.5 billion and more than &pound;5 billion.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.127.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/749" speakername="Graham Brady" colnum="127"  time="15:20:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew29">
	<p>I am intrigued about why the Minister has given figures for only the last three years of the previous Conservative Government and three years of the present Government. Surely, it would be more accurate and realistic to compare the whole six-year period of this Government with the six years leading up to 1997.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.127.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1296" speakername="Stephen Twigg" colnum="127"  time="15:20:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew30">
	<p>I am happy to do that and I shall write to the hon. Gentleman with those figures. I simply point out that the figure for every single year of this Government is higher than the highest of the three Conservative figures in front of me, but I am happy to write to him with further information.</p>
	<p>The figures demonstrate that we are taking seriously the challenge, to which the hon. Gentleman rightly referred, of buildings that should frankly have been invested in by Governments of both parties for decades. It will take a long time to achieve that investment. During this Government, we have seen an increase of approaching 25,000 in the number of teachers in schools, and an increase of 80,000 in the number of support staff.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.128.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/749" speakername="Graham Brady" colnum="128"  time="15:20:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew31">
	<p>I am anxious that the Minister should not give any partial information. Would he acknowledge that the increase of 25,000 in teaching staff is closer to 1,000, if that is taken as full-time equivalents?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.128.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1296" speakername="Stephen Twigg" colnum="128"  time="15:20:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew32">
	<p>I do not believe that that is the case, but I am happy to check it and to include the information in the letter that I have already undertaken to write to the hon. Gentleman.</p>
	<p>I will move on to some of the specific questions that hon. Members asked. I will write to them if I am unable to respond to all of the matters that they raised during the debate.</p>
	<p>My hon. Friend the Member for Hendon (Mr. Dismore) has pursued a vigorous campaign in defence of the schools in his area and in the London borough of Barnet. He raised a number of matters, which included schools applying for specialist status. The new guidance that was published last month states that the specialist money cannot be used to cover budget shortfalls, but there is nothing to stop a school with a deficit from applying for specialist status. I hope that that provides my hon. Friend with the reassurance that he sought.</p>
	<p>The right hon. Member for Berwick-upon-Tweed (Mr. Beith) raised several issues around rural-proofing. As he is aware, the Countryside Agency has praised the Department for Education and Skills as the Government Department with the best record on rural-proofing. I have direct responsibility for that area and I have convened a rural schools group, which goes through a whole range of issues, including funding issues. In addition, the Secretary of State regularly meets with ministerial colleagues from the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs and with the Countryside Agency to consider the full range of DFES priorities, including funding and how those can be effectively rural-proofed. The right hon. Gentleman also raised a number of other issues relating to PFI, about which I undertake to write to him.</p>
	<p>On the central question of our debate, nobody disputes that there is significant extra money in the system from this financial year&mdash;a &pound;2.7 billion increase&mdash;or that that coincides with a significant increase in the cost pressures that schools face. Taking everything into account, including inflation, we estimate that that sum adds up to about &pound;2.45 billion. Therefore, there is about &pound;250 million of extra money in the system. The impact of the changes this year has been variable because we have had so much change: in the mode of self-criticism, we failed to anticipate fully the combined impact of many different changes taking place at the same time. We are now learning lessons from that.</p>
	<p>The hon. Member for Orpington (Mr. Horam), who is no longer present, raised an important issue, which he has raised with me before, about the ending of standards fund grants. My hon. Friend the Member for Hendon also referred to it. One of the difficulties with regard to that is that in the school system&mdash;as in other public services&mdash;people are against ring-fencing in general but are in favour of it in the particular. The shift from standards fund to mainstream funding has a huge differential effect. Some schools in some parts of the country have significantly lost out as a result. In tackling the funding challenges for the coming year, one thing we must do is try to ensure that there is not that type of differential effect in different parts of the country.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.129.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1036" speakername="David Laws" colnum="129"  time="15:20:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew33">
	<p>The Minister for School Standards said that there would be a reasonable settlement next year. Before the hon. Gentleman finishes, can he say what a reasonable settlement means?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.129.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1296" speakername="Stephen Twigg" colnum="129"  time="15:20:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h03.htm#30702h03_spnew34">
	<p>In my remaining two minutes, I shall attempt to deal with that issue. I have not been able to cover as much ground as I would have liked. However, I wish to make one point. We have to face up to the shared responsibility of central Government and local government to get this right. We are working with our partners in local government to address the issues for the coming years, having learned the lessons from this year. Our key priority is to ensure that all schools receive the reasonable per pupil settlement to which the hon. Gentleman referred. We are sitting down with colleagues in local government and the teachers' associations&mdash;including the head teachers' associations&mdash;to ensure that we can get a definition of what that reasonable settlement will be that will work across the country. These are the sorts of things that we are taking into account in defining that: the need to get a sufficient education funding increase for every LEA; the importance of striking the right balance between support through the general grant and through ring-fenced and targeted grants, and between in-school and out-of-school provision; and, the need to ensure that there is confidence that schools and pupils will receive the money that is intended for them, that there are fair and appropriate variations in the budget increases received by different schools in the same LEAs, and that work force reform, in line with the national agreement, can be sustained. That is an important priority for our partners and for us.</p>
	<p>This has been a year of significant change. We want to secure the longer-term development of schools and the wider education service. That is about giving schools and LEAs more predictability and certainty. I welcome the opportunity, albeit briefly, to air some of the thinking in Government about how we can learn the lessons from this year to get things right next year and in the longer term.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.130.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="130"  time="15:20:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_head0">
	Rail Links (Shrewsbury)
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.130.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1348" speakername="Paul Marsden" colnum="130"  time="15:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spnew0">
	<p>I am delighted to have the opportunity to raise the important matter of the standard of rail links to Shrewsbury. According to the computer records in the House of Commons Library, there has not been such a debate for at least 25 years, and possibly longer.</p>
	<p>I am pleased that some of my Welsh colleagues, including my hon. Friends the Members for Montgomeryshire (Lembit &Ouml;pik) and for Brecon and Radnorshire (Mr. Williams), led a delegation today to the Secretary of State for Wales to discuss the condition of the railways connecting with Shrewsbury. I hope that that will be considered jointly with this debate, that Ministers will begin to work together closely to enforce a better understanding and that that will start to bring about real improvements for rail links.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.130.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1143" speakername="Lembit pik" colnum="130"  time="15:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spnew1">
	<p>Is my hon. Friend aware that we called primarily for the support of the Secretary of State for Wales in creating an hourly service from Shrewsbury to Aberystwyth and integrating the rail and bus links? Will he support a campaign to consider integrated rail transport from Shrewsbury to the west?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.130.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1348" speakername="Paul Marsden" colnum="130"  time="15:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spnew2">
	<p>Absolutely. We have, over the centuries, had our differences with the Welsh, but now we are working closely on a range of different issues, especially on the local hospital in Shrewsbury, which serves the people of mid-Wales. Similarly, the Shrewsbury to Aberystwyth line is important but under-resourced and does not provide enough services for local people.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.130.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1279" speakername="Simon Thomas" colnum="130"  time="15:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spnew3">
	<p>The hon. Gentleman said that that line was under-resourced but he will know that the National Assembly for Wales has pledged a considerable sum to it. The difficulty seems to be somewhere in the Strategic Rail Authority. I am sure that he will join me and other hon. Members in ensuring that what the Assembly has pledged comes through, so that his constituents, and mine, get the better service that they deserve.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.130.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1348" speakername="Paul Marsden" colnum="130"  time="15:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spnew4">
	<p>I agree with the hon. Gentleman. In fact, I was going to deal with that in my speech. I understand that the Welsh Assembly, which is putting its money where its mouth is, pledged &pound;2.5 million, yet the problems seem to reside more on the English side. I am a regular user of rail services; I have seen them at their best and worst. On Monday of this week, I travelled down on a Virgin Trains service that was some 35 minutes late into Euston, which was not untypical. That is the heart of the matter. People want fast, efficient and cost-effective services, but they are not getting them at the moment.</p>
	<p>National Statistics has demonstrated that train travel has risen by 20 per cent. in the past decade&mdash;that is great&mdash;but there has been no significant track expansion, train passengers are typically being delayed on one in five trains and the length of those delays has increased. That information comes from the Strategic Rail Authority. Although the cost of motoring is proportionately the same as it was in 1974, the cost of rail services has risen by some 80 per cent. All in all, British rail users are paying some of the highest fares in Europe, but they are not receiving the services that they should have.</p>
	<p>I am a great fan of history. I was interested in finding out where the first railways went in Shrewsbury and throughout Shropshire. In 1835 the small Ffestiniog Railway proposed an alternative port in Morfa Nefyn for Irish-bound traffic from Wolverhampton. Shrewsbury was one of the obvious stopping-off places on the way to that peninsula. Unfortunately, the Admiralty in London decided that the new port was not required and Shrewsbury did not get its important station.</p>
	<p>In 1839 there was another proposal to run a line from the west midlands to the Mersey. That line would have gone through the town. By 1844, there was still no agreement, as the North Wales mineral railway thought that any new scheme would affect rail traffic on the Wrexham to Chester line. So it went on, until Royal Assent was eventually given to a link between Chester and Shrewsbury on 30 June 1845. A year later, links to Wolverhampton, Hereford and Stafford were agreed to.</p>
	<p>It is curious that, throughout history, there is a certain repetitive theme. I looked back at the report of the proceedings of the Select Committee on the Shrewsbury, Oswestry and Chester Junction and North Wales Mineral Railway Amalgamation&mdash;I am sure hon. Members will be familiar with them&mdash;and found that the Select Committee had discussed a proposal for such a railway. Mr. Ellicombe, the agent for the Bill, was cross-questioning Henry Robertson, who went on to become a Liberal Member of Parliament for Shrewsbury in 1862.</p>
	<p>The questions that were posed included:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;Do you consider that the proposed consolidation of the Companies would be of great advantage to the public?&quot;</p>
	<p>Mr. Robertson said:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;I think it would be a great advantage to the public . . . it would be much better in the hands of one Company than in the hands of two&mdash;it would produce a quickness and greater regularity and would tend to the advantage of the public.&quot;</p>
	<p>The question was then asked:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;Would a considerable expense be saved by working one line in connection with the other?&quot;</p>
	<p>The answer was:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;No doubt great expense would be saved.&quot;</p>
	<p>There are echoes through time, but clearly we have not learned from what has gone before. Then, as now, there was great competition between companies, and that means that we do not always get the services that we should have.</p>
	<p>Later, the Beeching reforms devastated the branch line. Then, British Rail was privatised by the Conservatives and was smashed into 120 pieces. That ended the strategic planning of our railways and destroyed the precious knowledge and expertise of local British Rail staff. In short, Shrewsbury has been an important railway hub for the Marches and mid-Wales for more than 157 years. Local people are proud of that history, but they despair of the current situation.</p>
	<p>Recently, Liberal Democrats in Shrewsbury and Atcham carried out a survey. We asked 200 people at Shrewsbury railway station what they thought of the services. Some 90 per cent. thought that privatisation had had a negative impact on the railways and that, in particular, rail services had got worse under Labour since 1997. Some 58 per cent. thought that there simply were not enough trains running.</p>
	<p>There is a bureaucratic nightmare of responsibility and accountability that means that we fail to bring about the improvements that we desire. To give a small example, an argument has raged about who is responsible for lights on the footbridge over Welshpool station. The platform belongs to Wales and Borders Trains and the footbridge belongs to Powys council. The two cannot agree. The Welsh Assembly has earmarked &pound;2.5 million to improve the Cambrian line; however, we cannot get the Strategic Rail Authority to agree to that work, so nothing has happened.</p>
	<p>As the chairman of Shrewsbury-Aberystwyth rail users association, Gareth Marston, said:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;What we have had since privatisation is a fragmented and dysfunctional system which is cost inefficient. What we need is a vertically integrated system like most other European Countries have, who manage to run much more efficient services than our own. What we must be looking to do is undo the damage that the 1993 railways act did.</p>
	<p class="indent">We are not looking for a blank cheque, we are just looking for existing funds to be spent on improving services rather than an inefficient structure and legal wrangles.&quot;</p>
	<p>As the rail regulator said in a recent report, Network Rail's spending is out of control. There are fewer and less reliable trains, yet passengers have to pay a lot more. I shall take the example of the journey from Shrewsbury to London. I am pleased that the price of a saver return ticket has been held down. Since 1997, it has gone from &pound;30.50 to &pound;33.70, a rise of just 11 per cent. That is good. However, that ticket is very inflexible and, for business people, getting that ticket at short notice is totally impractical. However, a standard return has risen from &pound;70 to &pound;115, a 64 per cent. rise. The first-class fare has risen from &pound;97.50 to &pound;184, a whopping great rise of 89 per cent. in the past six years.</p>
	<p>I accept that performance has improved on some services and that since the various train disasters, there have clearly been some improvements. Nevertheless, Wales and Borders Trains has a punctuality rate of only 84 per cent. against a target of 92 per cent., and Central Trains has a punctuality rate of 82 per cent. against a target of 91 per cent. If we look behind the arbitrary targets, we realise that they distort what the public and the passengers desperately want. One interesting fact is that only 35 per cent. of people think that Central Trains deals satisfactorily with the delays. The poor commuters have been rewarded with the worst train performance, endless delays, cancellations and a deteriorating service.</p>
	<p>I should like to have the Intercity routes back. It would be a great challenge to any Government to agree to that, but they are very symbolic. We briefly recaptured them in a Virgin Trains experiment, but they immediately died a death. We need vision, better management and cash put into the railways to make them succeed; to get people out of cars and back on to the trains. It amuses me slightly that the Deputy Prime Minister said way back in 1993 that Intercity was being cut back to maximise revenue. He lamented that Blackpool and Shrewsbury might be next, and that several areas might be removed from the network service. He said that that was wrong. He was right then. What are the Government going to do about it now?</p>
	<p>My office has received a number of submissions from the different rail users associations. The Shrewsbury to Chester rail users association has made various points. It wants to see improved connections by advancing the time of northbound trains; to have more accurate information from Network Rail and real-time train information; to re-open stations at such places as Baschurch, Whittington, Weston Rhyn and Rossett; and to include the Shrewsbury to Chester link as a trans-European network route to give it the strategic designation that it deserves.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.133.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1153" speakername="Owen Paterson" colnum="133"  time="15:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spnew5">
	<p>The hon. Gentleman has touched on some stations in my constituency. Is he aware that I have had numerous meetings with the various authorities, and with Councillor David Lloyd of Gobowen who is celebrating 10 years of the re-opening of Gobowen station next Friday? All that we are asking for on our patch is an hourly clock-face service running from Shrewsbury up to Chester so that people know when the trains go. More trains will get people off the roads. We saw a 20 per cent. increase in users last year because of the improved timetable.</p>
	<p>I entirely agree with what the hon. Gentleman said earlier. We are exasperated by the bureaucratic delays. The Welsh franchise was promised to start on 1 March 2002, but it is still not up and running. Through the hon. Gentleman, can I ask the Minister when that will happen? Is the hon. Gentleman aware that we had a promise of &pound;250,000 to get the Wolverhampton to Shrewsbury link up to 90 mph five years ago, and that that still has not happened?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.133.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1348" speakername="Paul Marsden" colnum="133"  time="15:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spnew6">
	<p>Because of the shortness of time, I shall simply say that I totally support what the hon. Gentleman has said. I hope that the Minister will address those specific points.</p>
	<p>Other rail users associations have reiterated key points. Mr. G. Atkinson from the Shrewsbury to Wolverhampton rail users association has said that there are</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;no through services from the local stations direct to Birmingham New Street except the 07.10 from Shrewsbury, which means passengers having to change at Wolverhampton on an important commuter route&quot;</p>
	<p>and vice versa on the way back, where there are no direct trains through except the 21.07. Why would people take the train when they do not have the basic flexibility to get on to railway services that they want? The association calls for:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;A co-ordinated timetable between the two operators&quot;</p>
	<p>and says:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;Timetable posters at stations are incomplete and difficult to relate to&quot;</p>
	<p>each other. Further, there is no proper consultation on timetable changes:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;This year bus times at Telford were six minutes too early to meet the first train&quot;.</p>
	<p>So it goes on. Gill Wright from the Heart of Wales Line travellers association has highlighted the under-utilisation of the rail services from Shrewsbury to Aberystwyth, and has called for:</p>
	<p class="indent">&quot;1. Devolved government for the West Midlands to assist in the management and strategic overview of the railways.</p>
	<p class="indent">2. Vertically integrated franchises operating on a not for profit basis</p>
	<p class="indent">3. Need to replace unsuitable rolling stock not designed to be run on a scenic, tourist route&mdash;poor visibility, and lack of space for cycles and bulky luggage.&quot;</p>
	<p>There is a need to increase Sunday services, which are now down to one a day. The demand is there in a tourist area, but it is simply not being met. There are so many knowledgeable and willing people, constructive in their approach, who want to help to make the situation better. I hope that the Minister will take that spirit on board when he addresses those points.</p>
	<p>The Minister should appreciate that there is criticism but above all people have affection for the railways as a symbol of the success of the country and believe that we could have a great railway system once again. We need timely and reliable train services through capped investment costs, value-for-money services, an integrated approach to information from operators and helpful, friendly staff who want to exceed customer expectations instead of coming up with excuses for trains being delayed or cancelled.</p>
	<p>Liberal Democrats will reduce the number of franchises to increase efficiency. We will cap costs through in-house contracting. We will introduce a national railcard to give a third off fares, and introduce minimum standards for stations to increase security. We will increase integration with other public transport options such as the successful pilot scheme &quot;plus bus&quot; in Birmingham and invest an extra &pound;2.3 billion above what the Government have pledged. The money will produce line-speed improvements from Shrewsbury to Aberystwyth and reduced journey times on the Shrewsbury to Chester line. Investment of &pound;4.5 million is pledged under the Liberal Democrat national plans.</p>
	<p>I hope that the Minister addresses my points in a good, constructive spirit. Is he willing to meet a cross-party delegation of Conservative, Labour, Liberal Democrat and nationalist Members to find a way forward? There is a lot of good will, and many people are prepared to make the process work. I thank the Minister for his time.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.134.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1082" speakername="Tony McNulty" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport"  colnum="134"  time="15:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spmin0">
	<p>First, I congratulate the hon. Member for Shrewsbury and Atcham (Mr. Marsden) on securing the debate and on the level of detail he has gone into on the assorted railway lines that go in and out of Shrewsbury. As he said in his little history lesson, Shrewsbury remains an important hub in that part of the country. I am not surprised to find that this is the first debate on Shrewsbury rail links for some years, if not the first ever. Until the hon. Gentleman said that Shrewsbury was represented by a Liberal in the 1840s, I was going to say that it had been represented by Tories for ever and a day because they could not care less about railway links.</p>
	<p>I appreciate the spirit in which the hon. Gentleman has made his remarks. I should be more than happy to meet an all-party delegation to discuss those matters. I have no difficulty with that. I was a little confused as to whether the supposed &pound;2.3 billion is to be spent in Shrewsbury, or whether it was a national figure. Perhaps he can explain that to me afterwards because I do not remember seeing it in the last Liberal Democrat shadow Budget.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.135.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1348" speakername="Paul Marsden" colnum="135"  time="15:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spnew7">
	<p>First, I thank the Minister for agreeing to meet the cross-party delegation, and it would be nice if he met representatives of the rail users associations in that area. Secondly, the &pound;2.3 billion is pledged nationally, and &pound;4.5 million is pledged for Shropshire.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.135.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1082" speakername="Tony McNulty" colnum="135"  time="15:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spnew8">
	<p>I assume that that will be in the next shadow Budget from the Liberal Democrats because it certainly was not in the last one.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.135.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1348" speakername="Paul Marsden" colnum="135"  time="15:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spnew9">
	<p>It was.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.135.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1082" speakername="Tony McNulty" colnum="135"  time="15:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spnew10">
	<p>Not in that detail.</p>
	<p>As the hon. Gentleman said, Shrewsbury is currently fairly well served by regular direct trains to a variety of destinations including Wolverhampton, Birmingham, Crewe, Liverpool, Manchester, Chester, Cardiff, Swansea, Hereford and the Cambrian coast, including Aberystwyth. There is also one train a day in each direction providing a direct service to London Waterloo. In addition, Shrewsbury acts as an interchange between rail services and local bus services. I take the hon. Gentleman's point, and I know that many local authorities wish to pursue that. It is not just a question of money; it should not be beyond the wit of the operators to ensure that, when the train arrives, the bus is about to leave just outside, as in the more traditional European model, which sometimes works.</p>
	<p>Having said that, I caution people against thinking that everything in Europe is tickety-boo, that everything in the garden is lovely, and that it is only the British rail system that is somehow defunct or deficient. Once one is off the TGV lines in France and crossing the country on provincial or local district lines, one finds that the service is far worse than the worst lines in the British network.</p>
	<p>Regular, twice-hourly off-peak services to Birmingham enable passengers travelling from Shrewsbury to interchange with a wide variety of services. The cross-country network is centred on Birmingham and offers links to nearly all areas of the country. Fast, regular and comfortable journeys to London are possible with a change at Wolverhampton. The interchange is simple. Many London trains leave from the same platform at which Shrewsbury trains arrive and are timed to make good connections with rail services to Shrewsbury.</p>
	<p>I am not saying that everything in the garden is rosy. It is clear from what the hon. Gentleman said that things can and should improve, which is why I am happy to meet a delegation. I am pleased that he said that, on the whole, the service is reasonable.</p>
	<p>The Wolverhampton to London section of the journey is provided by Virgin West Coast, using air-conditioned, comfortable rolling stock with full catering facilities. The hon. Gentleman will know that brand-new Pendolino trains are gradually being introduced on the route and will provide enhanced comfort and reduced journey times. He will also know that at least &pound;9 billion will be invested in the west coast main line.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.136.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1143" speakername="Lembit pik" colnum="136"  time="15:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spnew11">
	<p>Will the Minister give way?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.136.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1082" speakername="Tony McNulty" colnum="136"  time="15:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spnew12">
	<p>With respect, I will not. I am a bit of a parliamentary purist and if Back Benchers have not done me the courtesy of giving me notice that they want to intervene, I will not let them. I am more than happy for the hon. Gentleman to whisper to the hon. Member for Shrewsbury and Atcham and for him to intervene.</p>
	<p>The direct service from Shrewsbury to London Waterloo is provided by Wales and Borders Trains and travels via south Wales, Bristol and Woking. I fully accept that, although direct, the train takes significantly longer to reach London than travelling via Wolverhampton to Euston.</p>
	<p>The service is not part of the passenger service requirement of the Wales and Borders franchise and the SRA has no plans to include it in the passenger service requirement of the new franchise, which it hopes to let later this year, because passenger levels on it are low. In inviting bids for the new franchise, the SRA has sought to protect the existing passenger service requirement, as well as those services in the existing timetable that appear to offer value for money. In addition to passenger service requirements, bidders will be expected to retain the current level of overall mileage. There is no specific requirement to continue providing the Shrewsbury to Waterloo service, although bidders for the franchise may wish to do so.</p>
	<p>On a point that the hon. Member for Shrewsbury and Atcham did not go into in detail, electrification from Wolverhampton to Shrewsbury has been considered, but is not included in the SRA's latest strategic plan. Studies have shown that the case for electrification of railways on a national basis is weak. Previously, it was considered that electrification brought numerous advantages, such as reduced fuel and maintenance costs, as well as rail vehicles with better acceleration, higher top speeds and quieter operation. In the current climate, that is no longer the case. Diesel fuel is much cheaper, so the fuel cost differentials are largely eliminated. The performance characteristics of modern diesel trains are at least as good as equivalent electric units, and although the maintenance costs of electric trains are slightly less than those of diesel trains, when the cost of maintaining overhead line equipment is added, the case for electric trains, as opposed to diesels, is not sustained.</p>
	<p>The priority is to provide additional capacity for both passenger and freight demand while improving the network to enable train operators to deliver significant improvements in the quality and reliability of their services, as passengers expect. Electrification is not necessarily the only way of achieving that. The SRA is much more concerned with outputs and inputs. It intends to ensure increased service standards for passengers.</p>
	<p>The notion that there is a bureaucratic nightmare may have been fair in the immediate post-privatisation period but, with all that the SRA has done, it is no longer entirely fair. I suspect that the example that the hon. Gentleman quoted about the footbridge being owned by Powys, with Wales and Borders owning the station&mdash;or whatever the configuration was&mdash;probably reflects a situation that has existed for a long time; British Rail may once have been involved instead of Wales and Borders. There has always been that degree of bureaucracy at a local level.</p>
	<p>The entire purpose of the SRA is to get the strategic overview and strategic planning, to which the hon. Gentleman referred, back into the equation. I admit that it is early days, but since the SRA's inception it has pushed things back in that direction compared with the disparate, disintegrated, bodged job of privatisation that he mentioned.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.137.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1348" speakername="Paul Marsden" colnum="137"  time="15:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spnew13">
	<p>I accept the Minister's point on the bodged privatisation. It would be helpful if we had a micro-franchise to take Wales and the Marches back into a single unit, and I wonder whether he is prepared to review that situation. A single entity, possibly under the auspices of the Welsh Assembly&mdash;although the details would have to be worked out&mdash;would mean better co-ordination and management of rail services.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.137.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1082" speakername="Tony McNulty" colnum="137"  time="15:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spnew14">
	<p>I will undertake to pass that point on to the appropriate authorities. I could review the matter until the cows come home, but given my responsibilities and the way things are, it would not matter. I shall pass that point on because other Members have raised the issue&mdash;this is not meant disrespectfully&mdash;of peripheral-type areas outside the core inter-city routes. The Shrewsbury area falls betwixt and between the west coast main line and routes in south Wales, and I shall pass on those concerns. I suspect that micro-contract means a macro-substantial subsidy, which may be another dimension to the equation. The point is fair and I shall pursue it and examine it in greater detail.</p>
	<p>I contend that the SRA is about drawing the strategic dimension, which was regrettably completely absent in the immediate post-privatisation era, back into the equation.</p>
	<p>There are two elements to integrated timetables. First, we must ensure that there is ample publicity and information. The hon. Gentleman knows as well as me that for many travellers, whether they are in the town or whether they are in the city, reliable information is key. Secondly, I also take his point, which is similar to the one about the interface between buses and trains, that the confluence of two franchises and the peripheral nature of Shrewsbury, which I mentioned, means that the timetables should be integrated or, at the very least, that the assorted information from the assorted franchises should be integrated.</p>
	<p>I take that point to heart and undertake to examine it in some detail in terms not only of the published timetables at Shrewsbury station but of the timetables that provide information about the other areas that one can get to by a direct service from Shrewsbury, not least of which are Manchester airport, Birmingham airport and London Euston. Many rail franchises hide their light under a bushel because one can readily get from one place to another but nobody knows about it. That is certainly true of overland services in London, and I am sure that it is true in Shrewsbury.</p>
	<p>Shrewsbury is an important junction not only between a number of train services but, as the hon. Gentleman has suggested, between trains and buses to non-rail destinations. Birmingham, which is at the centre of the cross-country rail network, is accessible by half-hourly services throughout most of the day and allows onward connections. However, I accept the points about some of the difficulties. Passengers travelling between Shrewsbury and London can look forward to an increased service because of the Pendolino fleet&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.138.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1086" speakername="John McWilliam" colnum="138"  time="15:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spnew15">
	<p>Order. I must suspend the sitting for a Division in the House.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.138.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1082" speakername="Tony McNulty" colnum="138"  time="15:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h04.htm#30702h04_spnew16">
	<p>If I can just speak for 20 seconds more, I will have finished, Mr. Deputy Speaker. The debate has been important and I wish the hon. Gentleman well in pursuing the improvements that he seeks. I undertake to help him in the ways outlined in my speech.</p>
	<p class="italic">Sitting suspended for a Division in the House. </p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.139.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="139"  time="15:59:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h05.htm#30702h05_head0">
	Syria
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.139.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/976" speakername="George Howarth" colnum="139"  time="16:07:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h05.htm#30702h05_spnew0">
	<p>I am most grateful for this opportunity to debate the important subject of Syria. Together with nine other right hon. and hon. Members, I was fortunate enough to be part of a delegation sponsored by the Syrian-British Society that visited Damascus, Palmyra and Aleppo at the end of May. I wish to take this opportunity to thank the society for its kind sponsorship of our delegation and to thank the Syrian Government for their generous hospitality. I would also like to express gratitude for the support of the ambassador and his staff.</p>
	<p>In order to give others an opportunity to contribute to this short debate, I intend to confine my remarks to two issues that are of key importance; first, the economic links between our two countries and, secondly, the important position that Syria occupies in the politics of the middle east.</p>
	<p>Despite recent difficulties that we all know about, Syria and the UK are already engaged in significant trade. In 2002, the UK exported &pound;83 million worth of goods to Syria and imported &pound;117 million, representing increases on the previous year of 26 per cent. and 33 per cent. respectively. As a delegation, we were united in urging the Syrian Government to continue and, indeed, to speed up the process of economic reform. They already have powerful incentives to do so through their association agreement with the European Union and, of course, programmes of the IMF and the World Bank.</p>
	<p>We recognise that liberalising banking is crucial to the process of wider economic reform. In that context, we welcome the work in which the Government and the British Council are engaged to help bank employees with training and to provide English language training through the British Council. That is crucial to the expansion of trade. However, I firmly believe that there is greater scope for that source of co-operation and assistance and that in economic and trade terms the mutual benefits are great.</p>
	<p>The serious political importance of the relationship to the long-term stability of the region should not be understated. The strengthening relationship between the two Governments is welcomed in Syria, particularly the warm relationship that has developed between my right hon. Friend the Prime Minister and President Bashar. As a delegation, we made it clear to those we met, including the President, that obstacles must be overcome, certainly if Syria is to maximise its influence. Human rights and the need for political reform are two issues on which we pressed very hard. I know that my hon. Friend the Member for Wirral, South (Mr. Chapman) has some comments to make on human rights, so I shall not say too much about that. However, as the Syrian Government are aware, there is a problem with their image.</p>
	<p>In the wider world, whatever the merits of President Bush's classification of Syria as part of the so-called &quot;axis of evil&quot;, it cannot be ignored. Whatever reasons groups such as Islamic Jihad and Hamas may have for operating in Syria, the fact that they are there inevitably leads to suspicion and mistrust.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.140.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1164" speakername="Michael Portillo" colnum="140"  time="16:07:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h05.htm#30702h05_spnew1">
	<p>As part of the delegation, I endorse the opening comments and warm thanks expressed by the hon. Member for Knowsley, North and Sefton, East (Mr. Howarth) to the parties involved.</p>
	<p>On the offices of Hamas and Islamic Jihad, perhaps the hon. Gentleman recollects that we were given three arguments. First, the offices had already been closed by the organisations concerned, so there was no need for Syrian Government action. Secondly, the offices were largely involved in humanitarian work. Thirdly, they were not really terrorist organisations because, in the context of occupation of the occupied territories, they were regarded as freedom fighters. Whatever the truth of the first two arguments and the merits of the third, which I do not accept, does the hon. Gentleman agree that they were not convincing for a British delegation? Does he agree there has been a continued missed opportunity, particularly in view of the progress that is now being made with the road map negotiations? Will he urge his right hon. Friend the Prime Minister to use his good offices with President Bashar with regard to this matter? I believe that it would be to Syria's advantage if it made an important move in that direction.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.140.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/976" speakername="George Howarth" colnum="140"  time="16:07:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h05.htm#30702h05_spnew2">
	<p>I agree with everything that the right hon. Gentleman said. I simply make the point that whichever of the three arguments are employed, the fact is that the continued presence of groups such as Islamic Jihad and Hamas in Syria&mdash;whether they are in offices or elsewhere&mdash;inevitably leads to suspicion and mistrust. I accept entirely that my right hon. Friend the Prime Minister has a powerful role to play in persuading the President and the Government that they must be seen to act. Being seen to act is almost as important as the action itself.</p>
	<p>As the right hon. Gentleman said, we were told that efforts are under way to deal with the issue, but it continues to have a corrosive effect on international perception of Syria. Addressing such issues is essential for two reasons. First, as the right hon. Gentleman said, these issues inevitably damage Syria's reputation in some important parts of the world. Secondly, it acts as a serious barrier to the role that I believe Syria can play in the peace process and in taking part positively to deliver the road map.</p>
	<p>Shortage of time limits the ground that I can cover, but I leave my hon. Friend the Minister with one clear message. The UK is a constructive but at times critical friend to Syria, and we have a pivotal position to play in encouraging and supporting economic reform and in supporting and encouraging Syria's potential as a political force for good, particularly in the middle east. I know that the Syrian-British Society is able to help, and I urge the Government to work with it so that our bilateral relations can continue to develop in a friendly and mutually beneficial manner.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.140.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/813" speakername="Tony Colman" colnum="140"  time="16:07:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h05.htm#30702h05_spnew3">
	<p>Does my hon. Friend agree that the warm welcome given to the delegation&mdash;as a member, I thank all those who helped us on our visit&mdash;included a welcome to the idea of the BBC opening a permanent office in Damascus? That would be another excellent way to deal with the problem of perception. Will he suggest that our hon. Friend the Under-Secretary encourage the BBC to open in Damascus, as it would be able to give a true picture of what is going on in Syria instead of the distorted perception that we often receive?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.141.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/976" speakername="George Howarth" colnum="141"  time="16:07:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h05.htm#30702h05_spnew4">
	<p>My hon. Friend has made his point well, and I support him. There are many misconceptions about Syria. In many ways, it is a religiously tolerant country. We were all hugely grateful for the warmth and friendliness of the people of Syria. The more that that side of Syria is exposed to the media, and thus to the wider world, the better it will be for Syrian relations with others.</p>
	<p>I conclude by saying that, as was demonstrated in their interventions, many hon. Members stand ready to help the Government in their efforts to improve relationships. I urge my hon. Friend the Minister to make use of us whenever he thinks it could help the Government in their wish for better understanding.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.141.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/791" speakername="Ben Chapman" colnum="141"  time="16:16:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h05.htm#30702h05_spnew5">
	<p>I congratulate my hon. Friend the Member for Knowsley, North and Sefton, East (Mr. Howarth) on securing this important debate. I thank him for allowing me some of his time, as I wish to make a few points on human rights. I, too, was privileged&mdash;I use that word advisedly&mdash;to be part of the delegation. Perhaps I should not say so, but I thought that it was an excellent delegation with an excellent mix of Members. I am delighted to see the hon. Member for West Suffolk (Mr. Spring), the right hon. Member for Kensington and Chelsea (Mr. Portillo), my right hon. Friend the Member for Southampton, Itchen (Mr. Denham) and my hon. Friend Member for Putney (Mr. Colman) in their places today. I thought that they made a substantial contribution to the political dialogue while we were in Damascus and elsewhere in Syria.</p>
	<p>It is clear that there is much potential in our bilateral relationship with Syria, and that the UK has many friends and much influence in Syria. As my hon. Friend said, we need to make more of that. Just as our talks in Syria were characterised by frankness on both sides, so do I want to be candid when considering the issue of human rights. In that subject, as in a number of others, Syria, as my hon. Friend said, must to address the reality and perception. In my view, the overseas perception of Syria does not facilitate its advancement in the global community.</p>
	<p>It has to be said that Syria's record on human rights is poor. In my view, it has not done enough to address the concerns that we and others have on the subject. For example, there are widespread reports on the use of torture in prisons, and Syria has yet to sign up to the convention against torture. That and the security services' lack of accountability give cause for concern.</p>
	<p>I am a little saddened that the pro-democracy civil society groups that were established following positive initial moves after the accession of President Bashar have since stalled and that many of them have been closed. Two members of Parliament and eight other high-profile civil society advocates who subsequently continued their activities were arrested this year. All were sentenced to periods of between two and a half and 10 years imprisonment on charges of illegally trying to change the constitution, weakening national unity and increasing sectarian strife.</p>
	<p>Of course, I welcome the release&mdash;at about the time when we were in Damascus&mdash;of Ibrahim Hamidi, who was accused of disseminating false information. To a degree, however, the damage has already been done. Nevertheless, there have been some positives since Bashar became President: the release of up to 600 political prisoners, mostly as the result of a presidential amnesty; the fact that diplomats were allowed to attend the trial of the two members of Parliament; the granting of licences to independent publications; the accession to the convention on the elimination of all forms of discrimination against women, and a number of other things.</p>
	<p>I remain concerned about the overall human rights performance. We missed no opportunity to raise that point when we visited. Dozens of people were arrested during the year on political grounds and hundreds of political prisoners, including prisoners of conscience, continue to be held.</p>
	<p>We, and our EU partners, have continued to lobby over recent cases but with little success. The continued arbitrary arrests, unfair trials, detention of political prisoners and torture run contrary to human rights norms. Syria is, in many respects, a tolerant society; exceptionally so in respect of religious freedoms. I urge the Syrian authorities to act on human rights now&mdash;I did the same in Damascus&mdash;and to understand that their practices in that regard damage their standing. They must work to improve both their human rights and their image overseas. There is much good will and friendship towards President Bashar and the Syrian people. In Britain, there is a diaspora of considerable power and force. Let us work together to increase understanding of Syria.</p>
	<p>In conclusion, I pay tribute to those who accompanied us on our visit to Syria; Dr. Fawaz Akhras, Mr. Wafic Said, Mr. Gayth Armanazi and, of course, the ambassador, who was with us throughout. It would be remiss of me if I did not thank also the late Fouad Takla. I had not met him until our visit, but in that short time, I came to know him as a man of great humour, character and integrity. He was a man of Homs and a man of considerable achievement. I hope that my friends will join me in sending condolences to his family.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2003-07-02.142.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1179" speakername="Bill Rammell" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs"  colnum="142"  time="16:22:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200203/cmhansrd/vo030702/halltext/30702h05.htm#30702h05_spmin0">
	<p>I start by endorsing those last comments.</p>
	<p>I congratulate my hon. Friend the Member for Knowsley, North and Sefton, East (Mr. Howarth) on securing the debate. I get the sense that he did it not only on his own behalf, but on behalf of his colleagues who took part in the visit. Such visits are constructive and useful and can only help to improve and secure relations between Syria and the UK, and help the development of that country and the middle east in general. In response to his specific point, I would say that the Foreign Office welcomes the work of the Syrian-British Society and wishes to see it enhanced.</p>
	<p>The United Kingdom and Syria certainly do not see eye to eye on a number of issues. The Syrian Government would be the first to acknowledge that. However, we are fortunate in having a relationship that allows us to discuss our concerns and disagreements frankly and openly, without preventing the UK from assisting Syria, when it can, in its attempts at reform. We recognise that there is much that we can do with Syria, and we are keen to develop the relationship; at its heart is the fervent support of both the Prime Minister and President Bashar, who have a strong working relationship, as my hon. Friend said. The President's visits to the UK last December as a guest of this Government underlined and reinforced that relationship.</p>
	<p>I want to say a few words about our relationship in general. Some people might ask why we are dealing with a country that some people believe is a former ally of Saddam Hussein, a state sponsor of terrorism and an occupier of Lebanon. If we are to make progress in our relations with Syria, we must acknowledge that Syria has made mistakes and that its image is badly tarnished. That does not mean, however, that Syria cannot change or that it does not matter; in fact, it means the complete reverse. Syria still strongly influences Arab opinion. It has a seat on the United Nations Security Council, and is central to our efforts to secure a comprehensive peace between Israel and the Arab countries. In a sense, to say that Syria does matter is to state the obvious. It is up to us to convince Syria and President Bashar that change is fundamentally necessary.</p>
	<p>It is also a statement of the obvious, although I believe it to be true, to say that, in many ways, Syria is at a crossroads, and that there are important decisions to be taken and hard choices to be made. We hope that President Bashar and his Government will choose wisely and that they will make a decisive break with the policies of the past. We hope that they will contribute to a better future for Syria and the region. Through dialogue, we hope that we can help Syria to make the right choices for herself and her people. It is down not only to us. Syria, too, must act and move forward. A willingness to continue to co-operate on the key questions of Iraq and of reining in the Palestinian rejectionist groups is most important.</p>
	<p>It would be remiss of me not to point out another problem, to which several hon. Friends referred; the important failing of Syria's public diplomacy. In the past, Syria deserved its reputation, but much of the bad press is self-generated. Syria has failed to present its policies more clearly and to take a more constructive approach to international issues. We want to continue to discuss those matters with the Syrian Government. Nevertheless, Syria has a good record on women's rights, and stands out in the middle east for the harmonious relations between Christian and Muslim communities. That record stands strongly in its favour, and we should do everything that we can to support it.</p>
	<p>I want to examine more closely some of the key aspects of our relationship. I shall start by talking about the positive ones. Most importantly, our relationship with Syria is two-way. Both sides are genuinely willing to listen to each other and to place an importance on developing that relationship. We are committed to continuing to increase high-level contacts. This year alone, the Minister for Trade and Investment, my hon. Friend the Member for North Warwickshire (Mr. O'Brien), visited Damascus twice. The Prime Minister and President Bashar speak on the telephone, most recently at Syria's request, and the Foreign Secretary speaks to his opposite number. That relationship is enhanced by often candid exchanges and a sense of trust rather than animosity; an essential ingredient of any continuing relationship.</p>
	<p>It is all very well to talk in those terms, but what practical results have our relationship brought? There have been encouraging signs. As hon. Members have said, Syria is changing, albeit slowly. Economic reform, to which my hon. Friend the Member for Knowsley, North and Sefton, East referred, is fundamentally necessary after four decades of a command economy, and is essential to Syria's long-term aspirations. Those changes and reforms are, at long last, picking up pace.</p>
	<p>New legislation has seen the granting of three licences that allow foreign banks to operate in Syria for the first time, which is a very welcome development. We hope to encourage further liberalisation in the financial sector through the visit next week of the Lord Mayor, Gavin Arthur, who will be accompanied by a delegation of British business men and representatives from the Bank of England. Such exchanges can only help this process.</p>
	<p>We are working with the Syrians on another key area of reform; public administration. The UK has helped to design an IT strategy specific to Syria's requirements. We hope that IT will form an important part of Syria's attempts to reform its administration. The strategy was recently adopted by the Syrian Cabinet and has the President's full support. The British Council plays an important role through its assistance with the IT strategy and capacity building in universities. Education is equally important to Syria's future, so it is important that we also help in that sphere. As I said, there is much that we can do with Syria. Equally, there is much that Syria can do for itself.</p>
	<p>Let me move on to the more difficult issues. It may be sensible to start with Iraq. We welcomed the strong Syrian vote in favour of Security Council resolution 1441 in November. However, Syria's support for the Iraqi regime, through the supply of weapons, support for the recruitment of volunteer fighters and the harbouring of regime figures&mdash;whether or not that has been sanctioned by the President&mdash;has, to say the least, been regrettable. That left the Syrian Government needing to rethink their policy and quickly realign themselves following the conflict with Iraq. Encouragingly, Syria looks to be doing that. I believe that Syria is attempting to put past misjudgments behind it.</p>
	<p>As a close neighbour, Syria is naturally concerned about Iraq's future. We understand that and have sought to involve Syria in planning for Iraq's future. We have shared our vision with the Syrians, and Syria has, in general, been receptive to our thinking. More positively, the Syrian Government have sought to remain engaged with us on the subject, offering thoughts, suggestions and contributions. I very much welcome that.</p>
	<p>The significant changes in the region following the Iraq conflict may have had a positive impact on Syria's thinking and attitude, on its stance on the peace process in the middle east generally and on its position on the quartet's road map for peace in particular. Syria suddenly found itself almost alone among its neighbours, which were fully supportive of the latest peace initiative. We and others encouraged it to take a more constructive approach, and there is strong evidence that that is happening. Syria has said that if the road map is acceptable to Palestinians&mdash;I remind hon. Members of the commitment of Prime Minister Abbas&mdash;it is acceptable to the Syrians. Syria still has reservations, primarily about where its own concerns on the Golan refugees fit in, but it is showing more interest and calling for a detailed road map specific to those concerns. That is a positive development. We should build on that co-operation and that increase in understanding.</p>
	<p>However, a continuing concern involves the Palestinian rejectionist groups and Hezbollah. My hon. Friends referred to that in detail. There is no real evidence to suggest that Syria directly provides funding, weapons or training to those groups, but allowing them to operate out of Syria and openly providing ideological support serves only to damage the peace process. As a candid friend, we should be able to say that. We have called on Syria to temper its rhetoric and to shut down rejectionist offices. The right hon. Member for Kensington and Chelsea (Mr. Portillo) rightly referred to that.</p>
	<p>More recent utterings from Damascus have been more encouraging. We urge people to continue that process, because curbing the actions of rejectionist groups is crucial to the road map's success. We have repeatedly told the Syrians that they have a key part to play in bringing an end to the violence in the occupied territories. I hope that that role will continue.</p>
	<p>This issue was not referred to in the debate, but is worth highlighting. Some would argue that the Syrians occupy Lebanon and that the Lebanese Government are merely puppets of the Syrian Government. I think that that is a distortion of the truth. Lebanon has a thriving free market, a large measure of freedom of expression and a functioning, albeit idiosyncratic, democracy. Although Syria has a degree of influence in Lebanon, its presence has the support not only of the Lebanese Government but, significantly, of the majority of the electorate. Hon. Members would support that process.</p>
	<p>My hon. Friend the Member for Wirral, South (Mr. Chapman) also referred, quite properly, to concerns about human rights. It is worth highlighting the fact that Syria has made only limited progress in that regard, despite being repeatedly urged by our EU partners and us to move in that direction. My hon. Friend referred to the 600 political prisoners who have been released over the last three years, which we welcome, and to the key release late last year under the presidential amnesty of the prominent civil rights activist Riad al-Turk. However, there is a considerable degree of further progress to be made. The continued practices of arbitrary arrests, unfair trials, the detention of political prisoners and torture run fundamentally contrary to international human rights norms. In that regard, the comments that my hon. Friend made about the need for Syria to sign up to the convention on torture is an argument that is effective and well made. There is no excuse not to address those human rights concerns and we shall certainly continue to push Syria on such issues.</p>
	<p>My hon. Friend the Member for Knowsley, North and Sefton, East raised two key points, the first of which was about the Foreign Office looking both to work with the group in question and to see its work helping the work that we do. I should like to give assent to that proposal; perhaps we can discuss it in another forum. His other point was about the BBC office in Syria; I make it clear that that decision is for the BBC to take, but we would be supportive, because that could help to open up the process.</p>
	<p>Where do we go from here? We take the view that our approach and our policy of critical engagement can be worth while and we wish to continue with that. Syria has, admittedly, got a lot to do, but it is moving in the right direction. It is important that Syria continues to work on these issues; in particular, an EU association agreement and membership of the WTO will help in that regard. However, it is important that we remain critically engaged with Syria. If we continue to do that and Syria continues to respond, things can develop in a positive direction. Debates such as this one, which follows what I can see has been a successful visit, can only help in that regard. Once again, I congratulate my hon. Friend on securing this debate.</p>
	<p class="italic">Question put and agreed to.</p>
	<p class="indent">Adjourned accordingly at twenty-three minutes to Five o'clock.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

