<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">

<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >

<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >

<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >

<!ENTITY euro "&#8364;" >
]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.73.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="73"  time="unknown" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_head0">
	[Mr. Eric Martlew in the Chair]
</minor-heading>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.73.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="73"  time="unknown" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_head1">
	Iran (Nuclear Programme)
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.73.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="73"  time="unknown" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_head1">
	<p pid="a.73.2/1">Motion made, and Question proposed, That the sitting be now adjourned.&mdash;[Gillian Merron.]</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.73.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" speakername="David Gauke" colnum="73"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.73.3/1">I am grateful to have the opportunity to initiate this timely debate on what is an important matter. It is timely because the five permanent members of the United Nations Security Council and Germany met earlier this week and agreed on a specific course of action, and because the board of the International Atomic Energy Agency meets tomorrow to discuss what action needs to be taken. It is important because of the nature of the Iranian regime and the steps it has taken to acquire nuclear weapons. That is a threat to the entire world, and particularly the middle east. Of course, if there is one country that is most concerned, it is Israel. In that context, I should declare that I recently travelled to Israel, courtesy of the Conservative Friends of Israel.</p>
	<p pid="a.73.3/2">We must understand the nature of the Iranian regime. Its human rights record is truly appalling. It has been censored 52 times by various organs of the United Nations. It has treated minorities&mdash;such as religious minorities, homosexuals and women&mdash;appallingly. In the interests of time, I will not dwell on specific examples, but, if necessary, one could recount many tales of minors being executed, women being stoned to death for committing the crime of adultery, and many politically motivated executions. If hon. Members wish to find specific examples, I recommend the website <a href="http://www.abfiran.org">www.abfiran.org</a>, which is a memorial to more than 9,000 people killed by the regime.</p>
	<p pid="a.73.3/3">Iran also has an appalling record of exporting terror. It has committed many assassinations overseas, including three in London in 1987. It was behind the bombing in Argentina that killed 85 people in 1994. The revolutionary guards were believed to have been involved in an attempted coup in Bahrain in 1996. In Afghanistan, there is evidence of the revolutionary guards forming a fifth column, which has attempted to undermine Hamid Karzai. They also worked closely with the Afghan warlord, Gulbuddin Hekmatyar, who has also attempted to destabilise the Karzai regime. In Iraq, there is widespread concern that Iran has been backing elements of the insurgency, and there is evidence that Iranian technology, including roadside bombs, has been used to kill British soldiers. Unfortunately, there have been two tragic examples of that this week, and I pay tribute to the brave troops who are out in the Gulf.</p>
	<p pid="a.73.3/4">There are conflicting messages about the relationship with al-Qaeda. There are al-Qaeda sympathisers who are in jail in Iran, but there is also evidence of some degree of collusion; it is an uncomfortable relationship, but there is evidence of that. The clearest relationship with a terrorist group is with Hezbollah&mdash;effectively a proxy organisation of the Iranian regime which has caused enormous difficulty in Lebanon, and continues to this day to launch rocket attacks on northern Israel. On my recent visit to Israel, we met members of the Israel Defence Forces who could recount tales of that. There is concern regarding Hezbollah terrorist raids into northern Israel in attempts to kidnap Israeli soldiers. However, there is not just Hezbollah in that part of the world. In the west bank and Gaza, Iran has developed relationships with Hamas and Palestinian Islamic Jihad, and it has given support through funding, helping the families of suicide bombers and providing extensive training.</p>
	<p pid="a.73.3/5">It is notable that a Shi'ite regime is working so closely with Sunni extremists, but they are united by a hatred of Israel. The attitude of the Iranian Government&mdash;particularly in recent months, but also going back many years&mdash;is truly horrifying. The entire world has been shocked by the comments of President Ahmadinejad about his intention to wipe Israel off the map and his calling of the holocaust as nothing more than a myth, but he is not alone. The supposedly moderate Ali Rafsanjani has contrasted the &quot;devastation&quot; of Israel by a nuclear bomb with the mere &quot;damage&quot; that would be inflicted if there was a response from Israel against the Islamic world, given the far greater population of the Islamic world. Supreme leader Khamenei has stated that the only way to solve the middle east crisis is to &quot;destroy the Zionist regime&quot;, which he describes as a &quot;cancerous tumour&quot;. In 2002, the Israeli Government produced a dossier of public statements by Iranian officials that identified 150 threats to the very existence of Israel. The strategy of the Iranian regime&mdash;given that it represents a Shi'ite nation, and therefore a minority in the wider Muslim world&mdash;is to advance its cause as the lead state in the Muslim world by being the most vociferous opponent of Israel. That makes it all the more dangerous for Iran to have a nuclear bomb.</p>
	<p pid="a.73.3/6">We must also remember that it is not just Israel that the Iranian regime hates; it hates the west as a whole. President Ahmadinejad has talked of a world</p>
	<p pid="a.73.3/7" class="indent">&quot;without the United States and Zionism&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.73.3/8">and of the world of Islam being in the process&mdash;I emphasise that phrase&mdash;of an historical war with the world of arrogance, by which he means the west.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.74.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1661" speakername="Philip Hollobone" colnum="74"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.74.0/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend on securing this timely debate. He is giving us a real tour de force description of the evils of this abhorrent regime. Does he agree that although the international community has come together quickly to condemn recent developments in Iran, we should be doing far more to encourage internal opposition to the Iranian regime?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.74.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" speakername="David Gauke" colnum="74"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.74.1/1">I entirely agree with my hon. Friend, and I will return to that point.</p>
	<p pid="a.74.1/2">Given the nature of the Iranian regime, its enormous hostility to the west, and the clear instability of the Iranian leadership&mdash;mental instability, I mean&mdash;the thought of the Iranians acquiring nuclear weapons is terrifying. I have no doubt that that is what the regime is attempting to do, despite its repeated denials and claims that its nuclear programme is purely for the generation of electricity. The case for that is overwhelming. First, there is the secrecy of the programme. Until 2002, we knew very little about the Iranian programme. Then the Iranian resistance revealed the existence of the nuclear enrichment site at Natanz and the heavy water plant at Arak. When the Lavizan-Shian site was exposed in the spring of 2004, the entire site, including the top soil, was removed. That is not the action of an innocent state merely wishing to develop civilian nuclear energy. It is also the case that Iran has one of the largest oil and gas reserves in the world. Therefore, why would it seek to develop nuclear power, which is relatively expensive? The IAEA visits have been highly restricted, and more evidence of that came out only yesterday. The nuclear programme is under the control of the revolutionary guards&mdash;not some department of energy&mdash;partly because that conceals the programme from the IAEA, and partly because the revolutionary guards are the most hard-line and extreme organisation within the Iranian leadership.</p>
	<p pid="a.74.1/3">We also know that Iran has been in contact with A. Q. Khan, the renegade Pakistani scientist who was heavily involved in the nuclear programmes in North Korea and Libya. Evidence of highly enriched uranium has been found on centrifuges in Iran&mdash;too enriched to be necessary for nuclear power, but appropriate for nuclear weapons. The Arak 40 MW reactor is designed to produce plutonium, but most experts believe that the quantities it will produce are too small to generate electricity and too big for purely scientific or experimental purposes.</p>
	<p pid="a.74.1/4">There is evidence of attempts to develop internally, or to smuggle a large range of material or equipment necessary to create, a nuclear bomb. That includes: nuclear warheads; gyroscopes and guiding devices; polonium 210, which is used as bomb detonator; tritium, which is used to increase the explosive power of a bomb; maraging steel and ceramic matrix composites, both used for encasing nuclear warheads; and beryllium, which reduces the amount of enriched uranium or plutonium required in a nuclear bomb.</p>
	<p pid="a.74.1/5">There has been enormous expenditure on missile technology and on various classes of the Shahab missile, which is capable of travelling to not only Israel but much of southern Europe. Just this morning, we learned from an interim report by the IAEA that Iran has obtained designs for building the core of a nuclear weapon. Rightly, the international community has dismissed any idea that Iran is purely seeking to acquire nuclear energy.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.75.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1382" speakername="Tony Baldry" colnum="75"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.75.0/1">My hon. Friend rightly describes a complete pariah state, but we have to recognise the reality: some major players in the region do not see Iran in that way. Iran exports 420,000 barrels of oil a day to China, and a number of us from the Conservative Parliamentary Friends of India had a meeting with the Minister of Power in India, who made it clear that India needed to be engaged with Iran in order to access gas and oil supplies for India. He said, in terms, that India would not oppose Iran, because it could see that it would be hypocritical of India, which is developing an expansionist civil nuclear power scheme, to oppose a neighbouring country that was seeking to do the same. Although we all see Iran as a pariah state, within Asia the picture is much more complex, and we will have to address that.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.76.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" speakername="David Gauke" colnum="76"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.76.0/1">I agree. The Chinese, the Indians and, indeed, the Russians have been much more reluctant to take action against the Iranian regime than we would like. There is perhaps some movement in the right direction, but there is no doubt that the world community has been very restrained in the action that it has taken, for reasons that have been outlined. I acknowledge that, and will perhaps return to those points.</p>
	<p pid="a.76.0/2">It behoves this country, and the international community as a whole, to take strong action against the Iranian regime, simply because of the consequences of Iran having a nuclear bomb. There are a number of reasons to think like that. First, and most obviously, given President Ahmadinejad's nature and his recent comments about the coming of the 12th imam, it is just possible that he would use the bomb. It would be the first time that nuclear weapons were in the hands of somebody just crazy enough to use them. It is very difficult to see how the concept of mutually assured destruction would work with someone such as President Ahmadinejad.</p>
	<p pid="a.76.0/3">Even if the bomb is not used, if it is acquired by the Iranian regime it will undoubtedly help to raise its prestige both internally and externally. It will strengthen its position within Iran so that it can continue to abuse the human rights of its people, and it will also assist Iran in becoming a lead state in the middle east.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.76.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1946" speakername="Mark Pritchard" colnum="76"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.76.1/1">Is my hon. Friend aware of reports coming from the United States this week that the Iranian regime has offered to arm other Arab states if it obtains nuclear weapons, thereby arming the whole middle east with weapons of mass destruction?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.76.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" speakername="David Gauke" colnum="76"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.76.2/1">I am grateful to my hon. Friend for that intervention. His description of events confirms my concern about Iran becoming a lead state within the middle east. Of course, any country armed by Iran will owe it a degree of allegiance; it will not act in such a way unless there is benefit to its own regime. That would further strengthen its position and further weaken the security of the middle east.</p>
	<p pid="a.76.2/2">Even if Iran does not arm other states in the middle east, there has to be some concern that its actions will result in proliferation. Certainly, if Iran had nuclear weapons, I have no doubt that the Saudi Arabian regime would seek to acquire nuclear weapons. That in itself causes concern, not so much because of the current regime in Saudi Arabia, but because, given the instability of the house of Saud, one would be concerned about who might ultimately get their hands on those nuclear weapons.</p>
	<p pid="a.76.2/3">Also, if Iran acquires nuclear weapons, it will be seen as an act of defiance against the west&mdash;it will be seen as sticking two fingers up to the Americans and Europeans. I have no doubt that such an act of defiance would encourage further acts of defiance of significant proportions against the west. It would also act as a deterrent to western involvement in the middle east. Not everybody supports the engagement in Iraq, but nearly everybody supported the involvement in Kuwait. However, it would be very difficult for the west to take any action in the middle east once Iran had nuclear weapons.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.77.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1588" speakername="Mark Harper" colnum="77"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.77.0/1">That is particularly worrying at this moment, given that we are proposing to send a significant deployment to Afghanistan, a neighbouring country. We know that Iran is interfering and supplying improvised explosive devices in Iraq, causing the death of civilians and members of our armed forces. Given the picture that my hon. Friend paints of Iran's interference overseas, it is worrying that it may well do likewise in Afghanistan.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.77.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" speakername="David Gauke" colnum="77"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew8">
	<p pid="a.77.1/1">That is an excellent point. The concern about Iran acquiring nuclear weapons is that it may pass them on, not simply to other states, but to terrorist organisations&mdash;I outlined Iran's links with such organisations earlier&mdash;and so further destabilise much of the middle east. We talk about missile technology, but given the unconventional means by which certain middle eastern terrorist groups act, the concern is not purely about missiles. If nuclear weapons get into the hands of proxy groups such as Hezbollah, perhaps the concern will be more that a nuclear weapon may be held in a container ship arriving at Tel Aviv or&mdash;who knows?&mdash;Felixstowe. We have to be desperately concerned about that.</p>
	<p pid="a.77.1/2">That brings me to the response of the west. After the exposure of the nuclear programme in 2002, the lead was taken by the EU3&mdash;France, Germany and the UK. The exposure of the nuclear programme coincided with a policy of greater engagement and dialogue with Iran. There was a time when the EU3's approach was seen as a success; on <phrase class="date" code="2005-02-03">3 February 2005</phrase> the Foreign Secretary used the engagement of Iran as an example of the advantages of the EU working together on foreign affairs. However, in reality, the period of negotiation with the EU3 simply allowed Iran to proceed, albeit disrupted, to develop its nuclear programme.</p>
	<p pid="a.77.1/3">Two deals have been made with the EU3, one in late 2003 and one in late 2004. In October 2003, Iran agreed to suspend uranium enrichment activities. In June 2004, however, it reneged on that deal and renewed construction of its uranium conversion facility in Isfahan and, probably, of its enrichment facilities. In November 2004, Iran again agreed to suspend enrichment processes. The suspension agreement was not very comprehensive. For example, it did not include construction of the Arak research reactor. Between June and November 2004, there are claims that some 37 tonnes of uranium yellow cake were converted into gas at Isfahan, despite the fact that Iran was required not to do so in October 2003. Indeed, Iranian officials have been boasting about how, during that period, they were able to develop their nuclear programme.</p>
	<p pid="a.77.1/4">Iran has consistently evaded or delayed meeting its obligations and, despite doing so consistently, it blamed the EU for failing to meet its obligations. Given that during that period Iran's nuclear programme continued to develop, and that the Iranian Government have become more hard-line, the EU3's policy of engagement cannot be judged a success, to put it mildly.</p>
	<p pid="a.77.1/5">The EU, along with the US, has for some time called for Iran to be referred to the UN Security Council. On Monday night, the five permanent members of the Security Council, plus Germany, agreed that the IAEA should report Iran when it meets tomorrow, although no action will be taken until the IAEA report is completed on <phrase class="date" code="">6 March</phrase>. That is a step in the right direction, but we cannot be overly optimistic that any action will be taken. As <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1382" name="Tony Baldry">my hon. Friend the Member for Banbury (Tony Baldry)</phrase> said, China and Russia have been reluctant to support action against Iran, and even the agreement on Monday has merely meant reporting Iran, rather than making a referral, which is more likely to lead to sanctions. We have a month's delay, without any great likelihood of any action at the end of it. At best, this is a small step in the right direction, but after three years of diplomatic failure, the Government are being hopelessly complacent if they believe that the softly-softly approach in itself will bring results.</p>
	<p pid="a.77.1/6">I hope that I am wrong. I hope that simple diplomacy is enough, but it is unlikely, in all honesty, to resolve the problem. The Iranian regime has not negotiated in good faith and it will not do so. The next step, presumably, should be sanctions, although, as we have heard, there will be resistance to that. We have heard of the enormous commercial relationships with China, India and Russia that may prevent us from making our position as clear as we would want.</p>
	<p pid="a.77.1/7">It must also be accepted that the effect of sanctions can be unpredictable. Will they cause disillusionment with the regime among the Iranian people, or will they rally behind their leadership? Will sanctions be enforced? Our experience in Iraq is that sanctions do not always prove effective and are often evaded. However, that is the right next step, because it would be a clear signal of the world's disapproval of the Iranian regime.</p>
	<p pid="a.77.1/8">Even so, we need to go fur<phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1661" name="Philip Hollobone">ther. My hon. Friend the Member for Kettering (Mr. Hollobone)</phrase> referred to assistance to the internal opposition within Iran. One example, in the face of the Iranian regime, has been the treatment of the mullah's internal resistance. In 2001, the People's Mujaheddin of Iran was proscribed. Many serious and distinguished lawyers, such as Lord Slynn of Hadley, have concluded that that organisation does not belong on the list because it has never attacked the west or its interests and has not undertaken any violent activity since 2001. It is hard not to reach the conclusion that the PMOI is on the list in part to please the Iranian regime. The de-listing of the PMOI would send a clear signal that we are on the side not of the Iranian Government, but of the Iranian people.</p>
	<p pid="a.77.1/9">There is growing unrest in Iran. In 2004, according to Iranian Government figures, there were 1,300 demonstrations during the entire year. The number of demonstrations that took place in November and December 2005 alone almost reached that figure. We must do what we can to encourage the internal opposition to the Iranian regime, not discourage it by prohibiting the one organisation that can provide an alternative voice.</p>
	<p pid="a.77.1/10">I am under no illusions about the enormous undesirability of ever taking military action in Iran. There are enormous practical difficulties. This is not Iraq; the nature of the terrain and internal organisation is such that there is no comparison whatsoever. There are great practical concerns about a surgical strike succeeding in destroying Iran's nuclear programme. Indeed, as we speak, there are reports of Russian-made anti-aircraft defences being installed in Iran. Having said that, however, as a last resort we should not dismiss military action.</p>
	<p pid="a.77.1/11">In this context, people often talk about Israel. Having met many officials and politicians in Israel recently, I know that there is no desire to take military action. There is certainly no desire to take symbolic military action. However, Israel faces an enormous threat, with nuclear weapons potentially pointing in their direction. With Iran under a leader who has pledged to wipe Israel off the face of the map, Israel may decide to take action. If it does, I have no doubt that much of the world will condemn it in the most forthright terms. I have no doubt that most Governments will condemn it strongly, that many hon. Members will do so, too, and that Kofi Annan will be very concerned. However, Iran poses an enormous threat to the Israelis and were they to take action, we should be slow to condemn them, given the extraordinary circumstances that they face. Having said that, I do not think that the world should try to leave the problem to Israel.</p>
	<p pid="a.77.1/12">If Israel, rather than anybody else, acts, it would make the matter much worse because it would damage the middle east peace process and to some extent inflame the Arab street&mdash;although sometimes predictions on that can prove unreliable. It would, undoubtedly, worsen the position of Israel. It would be a catastrophe were Israel to act on this. Unfortunately, however, there may be a bigger catastrophe if it does not act. We should show some understanding to the Israelis on the matter.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.79.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1506" speakername="David Jones" colnum="79"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew9">
	<p pid="a.79.0/1">Is not the difficulty that in order for Israel to attack Iran, it would be necessary for Israeli planes to fly over either Iraq or Turkey, which would necessarily imply that the United States would have to be at least aware of the attack? That being the case, is it not more appropriate for NATO to get involved, rather than to leave it to Israel to carry out that work?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.79.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" speakername="David Gauke" colnum="79"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew10">
	<p pid="a.79.1/1">My hon. Friend makes an essential point. I agree that it should not be left to Israel. Indeed, should Israel act, the entire west would be implicated. The responsibility rests on the entire world. Israel's bombing the Osirak nuclear site in Iraq in 1981 was condemned by most of the world, but most of the world has benefited enormously as a consequence. None the less, we should not rely on, and should not expect, Israel to have to take that action.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.79.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1488" speakername="Bob Spink" colnum="79"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew11">
	<p pid="a.79.2/1">My hon. Friend is making a balanced speech and is approaching the issue with sensitivity and understanding. Does he feel that the world community has something to learn from the action that Israel had to take against Iraq in the 1980s, and that looking at that lesson should galvanise the world community in ensuring that Israel does not, on this occasion, have to come forward to rescue the region?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.79.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" speakername="David Gauke" colnum="79"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew12">
	<p pid="a.79.3/1">My hon. Friend makes his point well. There is a lesson to be learned from what Israel did in 1981. Such action should be a last resort, but under some circumstances we reach the last resort. We did in 1981 and we may well do so again, soon.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.80.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1742" speakername="Brian Binley" colnum="80"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew13">
	<p pid="a.80.0/1">We do Israel and the concept of world peace a total disservice if we create the situation in which it thinks that it needs to take action because we are not doing so. That creates a great danger in the middle east which we all need to recognise and face up to more positively than we have done to date.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.80.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" speakername="David Gauke" colnum="80"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew14">
	<p pid="a.80.1/1">My hon. Friend makes an excellent point. Israel will take desperate measures if it is in a desperate circumstance. The west should not allow Israel to find itself in such desperate circumstances.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.1/2">The Foreign Secretary has described military action as &quot;inconceivable&quot;. He has said that that is not on the table and is not something that we should think about. That is hopelessly naive. We need to maintain the leverage&mdash;as John McCain referred to it&mdash;of having that option available to us. It is an appalling action to take, but it may be the least worst alternative and we should continue to consider that as a possibility.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.1/3">Time is running out to stop Iran acquiring nuclear weapons. If we think we have a problem now, how much greater will it be when Iran acquires nuclear weapons? There have been occasions when this Government have been bold and courageous in taking action in the belief that they were stopping a rogue state acquiring weapons of mass destruction. The Prime Minister has shown great leadership on this type of issue in the past, although that is, perhaps, an unpopular view, at least in his own party. None the less, it is time that this Government recovered some of that courage and prepare to take bold action to defend our interests and those of the world community as a whole. We face an enormous challenge. I hope that the Government show that they are up to that challenge.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.80.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1620" speakername="Iain Wright" colnum="80"  time="010:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew15">
	<p pid="a.80.2/1">I should like to point out to the Chamber my position as chairman of Labour Friends of Israel.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.2/2">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" name="David Gauke">the hon. Member for South-West Hertfordshire (Mr. Gauke)</phrase> on securing this debate on a vital, extremely timely and fast-moving issue. I was pleased to have been able to hear his contribution to the debate on Israeli policy in the Palestinian territories a couple of weeks ago. He spoke with experience and wisdom about the security threat facing Israel, and did the same again today, with astute analysis and thoughtfulness.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.2/3">This is the most profound and important issue affecting international relations today. It has an impact not only in the immediate region, but throughout the world. It affects relations between and with the European Union, the United States, China, Russia and India&mdash;a subject that I shall come back to, if I may.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.2/4">The internal nature of Iran is not particularly encouraging. By and large, since 1979, religious extremism has been at the top of the Iranian Government, interpreting Islamic teachings as anti-western, anti-capitalist and anti-Semitic. The election of Mahmoud Ahmadinejad as Iranian President in June 2005 fortified decisively the position of the extremist clerical elite at the heart of Iranian Government policy.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.2/5">Thus, as the hon. Gentleman said, we see a denial that the holocaust ever took place: last month, Iran announced its intention to sponsor a conference to examine the scientific evidence supporting the holocaust. There have been calls for the death of the western world. Soon after he became President, Ahmadinejad was quoted as saying:</p>
	<p pid="a.80.2/6" class="indent">&quot;Thanks to the blood of the martyrs, a new Islamic revolution has arisen and the Islamic revolution of 1384 will, God willing, cut off the roots of injustice in the world.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.80.2/7">As the hon. Gentleman also said, there is a direct threat to the existence of another state; the comments last year about wishing to see Israel wiped off the face of the earth were both offensive and disturbing. Only last week, the Iranian Defence Minister was quoted as saying that</p>
	<p pid="a.80.2/8" class="indent">&quot;Zionists should know that if they do anything evil against Iran, the response of Iran's armed forces will be so firm that it will send them into external coma, like Sharon&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.2/9">I find it absolutely astonishing that one member of the United Nations should be permitted to express a wish to obliterate another. That cannot be tolerated. It is therefore vital that all of us&mdash;particularly the Foreign Office and my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs&mdash;should support the work this week by the international community to ask the International Atomic Energy Agency to report Iran to the UN Security Council.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.2/10">The hon. Gentleman mentioned Iran's expansionist and aggressive foreign policy, which has been backed up by Iranian support for terrorist groups. As he pointed out, Iran has strong links with groups associated with violence and terrorism, such as Hezbollah, that wish to undermine the middle east peace process. Iran supports Palestinian Islamic Jihad, which claimed responsibility for the attack at Hadera in Israel in October 2005.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.2/11">Given that context&mdash;a demagogic religious extremist President, support for terrorist groups and a wish to wipe out Israel&mdash;it appears likely that Iran is attempting to back up its foreign policy through an acceleration of its nuclear programme. That would completely derail the middle east peace process, increase tension in the region to crisis point and have profound repercussions throughout the world.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.2/12">As I mentioned earlier, the Iranian nuclear issue is affecting, and will continue to make its mark on, relations between EU states and with the United States. The attitude of the emerging economic superpowers of the world&mdash;China, India, Russia&mdash;to the Iran nuclear question could shape global politics for decades. For example, Iran provides about 15 per cent. of China's oil needs, a percentage that is becoming ever higher and more lucrative, given the expansion of the Chinese economy. For its part, Russia is building a nuclear power station for Iran. Both nations are very dependent on Iran, so their support for the United States and the EU three on reporting Iran's nuclear programme to the Security Council this week is welcome.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.2/13">I disagree slightly with the hon. Gentleman's interpretation of that support. I think it a sign of greater decisive action that shows an encouraging element of almost universal support from the international community in requesting that Iran complies with its non-proliferation treaty obligations.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.2/14">It is extremely important that negotiations go well when Russia meets with Iran on <phrase class="date" code="">16 February</phrase> to discuss the Russian proposal to enrich uranium outside Iran.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.82.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1437" speakername="Tobias Ellwood" colnum="82"  time="010:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew16">
	<p pid="a.82.0/1">The hon. Gentleman raises an important point about the relationship between Iran and Russia. Russia provides a lot of the uranium used by Iran and could be in a pivotal position to slow&mdash;indeed, stop&mdash;any nuclear advancement on the part of Iran. Russia should be taking bolder steps. Does the hon. Gentleman agree?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.82.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1620" speakername="Iain Wright" colnum="82"  time="010:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew17">
	<p pid="a.82.1/1">I agree to some extent. Russia's meeting with Iran on <phrase class="date" code="">16 February</phrase> will be vital. There are not many grounds for optimism at the moment, but that meeting is a chink of light that I hope will expand.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.1/2">It is difficult to be hugely optimistic at the moment. Iran has deceived the rest of the world about its nuclear research for close to 20 years. Its posturing President seems hell-bent on securing nuclear weapons to assert domination in the region and threaten the security of Israel. Yet I should like to end on a positive note. I am convinced that Iran has a vibrant and positive role to play in the international community. Its vast oil reserves will ensure that it becomes a major economic player with a strong say in international politics; the country would be able to play a role on the world stage without recourse to aggression.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.1/3">Its demographic pattern&mdash;there is a young, large and increasing population&mdash;gives Iran huge potential in economic, social and cultural matters in future decades. The hon. Gentleman said that we should be extraordinarily critical about the Iranian Government but not the Iranian people, and that was very valid. A moderate Iranian nation would be strong, proud and able to fulfil its potential both internally and internationally. There is hope, but it is vital that the international community should stay together in its condemnation of Iran's leaders.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.1/4">I am grateful to the hon. Gentleman for giving us the opportunity to express our views at such a timely moment&mdash;the next few days and weeks are of huge importance. I sincerely hope, and think it essential, that the United Nations should show real leadership when the issue is reported to it.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.82.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1726" speakername="Patrick Mercer" colnum="82"  time="010:07:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew18">
	<p pid="a.82.2/1">I am extremely grateful to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" name="David Gauke">my hon. Friend the Member for South-West Hertfordshire (Mr. Gauke)</phrase> for securing this debate on an extremely important subject, and I am privileged to follow <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1620" name="Iain Wright">the hon. Member for Hartlepool (Mr. Wright)</phrase>. Many of the points made have shown that all parties feel that the issue is the most serious that we have faced during the past several years.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/2">I should like to draw attention to two pieces of rhetoric that everybody in the Chamber will have heard and that contrast starkly with some words on the &quot;Today&quot; programme this morning. First, we heard President Ahmadinejad spewing forth a series of appalling, irrational statements of hatred and loathing that emphasise the point made by both my hon. Friend the Member for South-West Hertfordshire and the hon. Member for Hartlepool: our argument must be with Iran's Government and not with its people. Secondly, President Bush recently talked in his state of the nation address about the serious view that he takes of the situation. However, both those pieces of rhetoric contrast starkly with the words of Mrs. Spicer on the radio this morning. She talked about her young son Leon, who was killed outside Basra just before Christmas.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/3">I am sure that many hon. Members remember the BBC documentary &quot;Last Night Another Soldier&quot; from the 1980s, about the steady drip of military casualties in Northern Ireland. Let us spare a thought this morning for the parents of Lance Corporal Allan Douglas of the Highlanders and Corporal Gordon Pritchard of the Royal Scots Dragoon Guards. Two families in Scotland have been shattered by events in Iraq which are directly related to what is going on in Iran. Anyone who doubts that the technology that killed those soldiers came from anywhere other than Iran needs to consider carefully the words of the free press in the west, the less-than-free press in the east, our ambassador in Baghdad and our general officer commanding Multinational Division (South East). They all make it clear that wherever this kit is coming from, it is destined to destabilise, kill and distract the west from Iran's nuclear programme.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/4">My hon. Friend made said that it was possible that destabilisation by Iran had already started or that it would start in the near future in Afghanistan. Precisely the same sorts of weapons&mdash;exactly the same manufacture and design&mdash;that have been used to kill our soldiers in southern Iraq are appearing on the Pakistan-Afghanistan border. It does not take a rocket scientist&mdash;that might be a bad pun&mdash;to work out where this stuff is coming from. It is instructive to see how the pernicious influence of terrorism spreads from Tehran through Pakistan, to the border of Afghanistan and through to Iraq. Precisely those same routes will be followed in the event of Iran gaining a nuclear weapon.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/5">It is worth bearing in mind the exact Iranian position. We have no need to emphasise the fact that Iran's support to Shi'a extremists via the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps and Lebanese Hezbollah has killed, and continues to kill, people throughout the middle east. Iran plays host to a powerful group of al-Qaeda operatives. As far as we aware, those people are confined; they are contained somewhere in Tehran. The influence that comes from the fact that those men exist, albeit under Iranian civil and police control, continues to allow powerful groups of Sunni extremists to operate inside the borders of Iran.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/6">The conflict between Sunni and Shi'a inside Iran does not need to be emphasised, but we should not underestimate the influence on President Ahmadinejad of those particular strengths and feelings in his country. He is trying to balance Shi'a against Sunni and is having to play host to the world's most dangerous terrorist organisation. People such as Abu Mussab al-Zarqawi are using their influence through Iran to operate inside Iraq and Afghanistan. Anyone who underestimates the pressure on Iran at the moment is clearly wrong.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/7">We would all condemn the continued support of Palestinian terrorists by Iran. There is no doubt that the fingerprints of the IRGC and of Lebanese Hezbollah are seen every day in the middle east. Any moves that Iran is likely to make can serve only further to destabilise the middle east peace process. If we allow Iran further to develop its ability to produce nuclear weapons, albeit under the umbrella of nuclear power, and if we allow the Government in Iran further to exercise their stranglehold on the people of Iran, we will have only ourselves to blame.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/8">Anyone who cannot see the comparison between the situation in Iran and the situation in Iraq more than 10 years ago, and who does not feel the same lurch in his or her stomach when we discuss this subject, is blind to the lessons of the past three or four years in Iraq. If the west wishes to avoid another situation like the one that we face today, which is killing our soldiers day on day, we must understand that this is the most serious threat that we have faced for some years.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/9">I despair when I read that the Secretary of State for Defence has said:</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/10" class="indent">&quot;Elements within or connected to the Iranian system&mdash;I put it no more strongly than that&mdash;seem to be encouraging violent opposition to multinational forces.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/11">Here is the rub, however, because he continued:</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/12" class="indent">&quot;That is a risky way for anyone to behave, so we hope that it does not continue.&quot;&mdash;[<i>Official Report,</i> <phrase class="date" code="2005-10-10">10 October 2005</phrase>; Vol. 437, c. 34.]</p>
	<p pid="a.82.2/13">What words are those to try to salve the consciences of the families of dead soldiers? What words are those to go forward to oppose the dangerous Government in Iran? We need less empty rhetoric and more action by the Government to ensure that we provide the right gestures, not just the right words.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.84.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1484" speakername="Eric Martlew" colnum="84"  time="010:07:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew19">
	<p pid="a.84.0/1">May I again ask for short speeches? I would like to start the wind-ups at about half-past 10.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.84.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1875" speakername="Andrew MacKinlay" colnum="84"  time="010:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew20">
	<p pid="a.84.1/1">I am sensitive to the fact that we are time-limited, Mr Martlew. Both <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1620" name="Iain Wright">my hon. Friend the Member for Hartlepool (Mr. Wright)</phrase> and I look forward to hearing the views of other Labour Back-Bench Members, so we must make time for them. It should not be left just to us to support the Government on this occasion.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.84.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1905" speakername="Edward Vaizey" colnum="84"  time="010:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew21">
	<p pid="a.84.2/1">On that point&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.84.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1875" speakername="Andrew MacKinlay" colnum="84"  time="010:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew22">
	<p pid="a.84.3/1">If the hon. Gentleman will restrain himself, I might say some other things that will prompt him to ask me to give way.</p>
	<p pid="a.84.3/2">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" name="David Gauke">the hon. Member for South-West Hertfordshire (Mr. Gauke)</phrase> on securing the debate. Although I know that it tends to become a matter of rubric to congratulate people, he does need to be congratulated on that, on the way he prosecuted the case and on how he illustrated the concerns of many Back-Bench Members across the political spectrum about the situation and how we have reached it in terms of our international diplomacy.</p>
	<p pid="a.84.3/3">I share concerns about the gravity of the international situation. I do not think that it has been so grave since the fall of the Berlin wall. What surprises me is that that has not been picked up by some of our colleagues in Parliament or by the media. Put in a nutshell, we know that Israel cannot, and will not, tolerate Iran getting anywhere near having the capacity to develop a nuclear weapon. The clock is ticking.</p>
	<p pid="a.84.3/4">The situation requires the maximum amount of international agreement, particularly among the five permanent members of the Security Council, and all our diplomatic skills to prevent Iran from having nuclear weapons. Otherwise, even the most moderate Israeli Government will feel compelled to intervene. As Israeli Governments have repeatedly reminded us since the founding of the Israeli state, Israel cannot afford to lose one war. For that reason, the situation is extraordinarily grave.</p>
	<p pid="a.84.3/5">I take heart from the fact that the Russian Federation and China have joined the other permanent members of the Security Council at least in contemplating reporting Iran to the Security Council. That is significant, because although reference has been made to Russia's commercial interest in Iran and to Iran's aspirations to having nuclear energy and/or a nuclear weapon, both the Russian Federation and China probably recognise the gravity of the situation. They realise that the potential for a major conflict or a conflagration is consequent on Iran's approach to nuclear power and nuclear weapons, which, if not arrested, would have consequences that are in no one's interests. Moscow and Beijing now realise how serious the international situation is in relation to the Tehran regime.</p>
	<p pid="a.84.3/6">I am surprised that the Minister for Europe is present, because it seems as if a different Minister responds on these issues each time. I am not sure whether he is the jobbing Minister or the Minister who has responsibility for this matter. I do not say that sarcastically&mdash;I would like to know the answer. There seems to be a shifting of the sands, which is indicative of how our Foreign Office works&mdash;I deliberately say &quot;Foreign Office&quot; and not &quot;Ministers&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.84.3/7">I do not think that the Foreign Office has been very skilled in relation to Iran, and that eventually permeates through to the ministerial team, whose sincerity and diligence on this matter I do not question. Disappointing advice and counsel has been given by our diplomatic professionals and that has worked its way through to the ministerial team over a number of years. That is shown by the three wasted years when the EU3, with the best of motives, pandered to, and appeased, the Tehran regime. They have nothing to show for it. History shows us that when we take the advice and counsel of the Foreign Office and follow appeasement, we pay a heavy price later.</p>
	<p pid="a.84.3/8">As a member of the Foreign Affairs Committee in the previous Parliament, I remember how we were coaxed and encouraged by the Foreign and Commonwealth Office to visit Tehran. I refused to go. My colleagues were well motivated, but the visit bolstered the regime. It sent all the wrong signals. The visit was made under the encouragement, advice and counsel of the Foreign Office. I say in all seriousness to the Minister that the Government need to listen more to Back Benchers. On some occasions, their prudence and wisdom might surpass that of the mandarins at the Foreign Office. If they listen to Back Benchers, especially across the political spectrum, it might occur to them that perhaps there has been a misread in the Foreign Office about the nature of the regime in Tehran and its intentions.</p>
	<p pid="a.84.3/9">Reference has been made to people, both in Iran and in painful exile, who are boldly standing in resistance to the regime in Tehran. We must recognise that those who have given the west the greatest indication of the full nature of the threat of developments in Iran and the technologies that it is pursuing in its nuclear programme are members of the Iranian resistance, yet we treat them as pariahs. That is not only unacceptable, it is bad politics.</p>
	<p pid="a.84.3/10">Many of us consider that the constituent organisation of the national council's resistance, the PMOI, has been listed with a terror tag to placate and appease the dreadful people in the regime in Tehran. That must stop as a matter of justice. It must also stop out of our naked self-interest. We need to send a signal that we stand by people who stand for freedom. We have a rich tradition. In 1940, some people thought that we should not recognise Charles de Gaulle. Whatever we might think of him, he was a brave man and also a correct man. As Churchill said, &quot;Here is the constable of France.&quot; He was the flame flickering. There were some who would have tallied and bargained with the Vichy regime. It now comes round full circle. The Minister needs to take account of those who support freedom, and who will also helping him to find out what is really happening in Iran.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.86.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1506" speakername="David Jones" colnum="86"  time="010:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew23">
	<p pid="a.86.0/1">The hon. Gentleman mentions the important continued proscription of the People's Mujaheddin Organisation of Iran. I have no doubt that he is aware that, next week, there is a hearing in the European Court of Justice at which the continued proscription of the PMOI will be considered. Does he share my feeling of utter shame that the only Government of a European Union nation who have intervened in those proceedings to retain the proscription are the British Government?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.86.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1875" speakername="Andrew MacKinlay" colnum="86"  time="010:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew24">
	<p pid="a.86.1/1">That is a good point. My feeling is not one of shame, but one of dismay. The British Government do not read the tea leaves properly. They do not understand, first, that they will ultimately lose in the courts and, secondly, that they are sending all the wrong signals to Tehran. Going to court to resist the legitimate attempts of the PMOI and others to get the terror tag lifted is sending all the wrong signals. The Minister might find my remarks irritating, but if he pauses and reflects on matters, he might find a scintilla of truth in what I say. He might go back to the guys in the Foreign Office and say, &quot;Well, perhaps Mackinlay has a remote point&quot;, and that might alter the course of history.</p>
	<p pid="a.86.1/2">The United Kingdom representative of the National Council of Resistance of Iran, Ms Dowlat Nowrouzi, announced in January that the Iranian regime has successfully procured two types of equipment&mdash;the hot isostatic press and the hot press&mdash;to shape enriched uranium as part of nuclear weapons production at the materials and energy research centre near Karaj, 40 km west of the Iranian capital. Both machines are banned. That the National Council of Resistance of Iran is helpfully giving more information to the west is indicative of what happened as recently as a week ago and is a pattern of how it is revealing the true nature of what is happening in Iran. On behalf of hon. Members across the political spectrum, I make the case that for that reason plus others, the Government should reassess their position in respect of the National Council of Resistance of Iran and the PMOI.</p>
	<p pid="a.86.1/3">Separately from that, I have tabled parliamentary questions about the EU's export licence regime. By inference, some criticism has been made of Russia when dealing with Tehran, but we in the European Union and the United Kingdom still do not have a sufficiently rigorous regime to stop exporting materials to Iran which have a dual use.</p>
	<p pid="a.86.1/4">I have tabled a series of questions about zirconium silicate. It is used in ceramics production, but it has a dual use. To their eternal credit, the Bulgarian authorities recently intercepted a lorry load of zirconium silicate in transit from the United Kingdom to Iran, but eventually had to let it go through because of a bureaucratic and not up-to-date European Union schedule on dual-use exports. I hope that the Minister will consider such matters.</p>
	<p pid="a.86.1/5">Many of us want to tell the Minister that, thanks to the negotiations with Europe, the Iranian regime gained another year in which to complete its project in Isfahan. It needed 12 months to complete the work on the centrifuges. Although I have described that in my own words, I am referring to the words of the chairman of the Iranian supreme national security council's foreign policy committee. He bragged that the negotiations with the EU3 bought it more time. An Iranian daily Government organ stated that Tehran had benefited greatly from the talks with the EU3 in advancing its nuclear programme. I am describing the pattern of our failing to send the right signals early enough to potential adversaries so that we make it clear that we will not tolerate and continue such a course of appeasement.</p>
	<p pid="a.86.1/6">The Foreign Office Minister has been questioned about the Lovers of Martyrdom Garrison, which has been encouraged by the acolytes of the so-called President of Iran. The regime is encouraging young men and women to prepare themselves for martyrdom not in Iran, but abroad, where they should go as the ultimate export of terrorism, to sacrifice their lives in the cause of the regime. Yet again, there has been an embarrassing silence from the United Kingdom Government and the European Union in the face of the declaration by the Tehran regime that it is encouraging young men and women to prepare themselves for the ultimate martyrdom.</p>
	<p pid="a.86.1/7">Colleagues throughout the House will wish to draw to the attention of the Government that 430 Members of Parliament and peers have now requested them to revisit their attitude to the National Council of Resistance of Iran and the PMOI. Yesterday, 2,000 distinguished lawyers signed a similar declaration. Those involved are not fringe people; they are not made up of the hon. Member for Thurrock. They have had stewardship in this country of both justice and national security. Lord Waddington, who was Home Secretary, is among them, as is Lord Archer of Sandwell, Harold Wilson's Solicitor-General. People from throughout the political spectrum in large numbers are urging the Government desperately to rethink their attitude as a matter both of justice and of plain common sense.</p>
	<p pid="a.86.1/8">In the interests of the United Kingdom, we should recognise those who are bravely resisting the terrible regime that denies human rights, persecutes people internally, and exports terrorism, as the Prime Minister alluded to a few weeks ago when the deaths occurred of coalition soldiers in Iraq, which have been mentioned. Again, on that occasion we received confusing signals. The Prime Minister, to his credit, was robust, the Foreign Secretary said something similar, but slightly different, and the Secretary of State for Defence said something different again. We need a coherent indictment from our ministerial leaders about Iran's role in funding, facilitating and giving equipment to the irregulars in Iraq who are trying to attack the coalition forces and undermine its work and that of the Iraqi Government.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.88.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1905" speakername="Edward Vaizey" colnum="88"  time="010:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew25">
	<p pid="a.88.0/1" class="italic">rose&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.88.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1875" speakername="Andrew MacKinlay" colnum="88"  time="010:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew26">
	<p pid="a.88.1/1">I would like to give way to the hon. Gentleman, but there is no time, so I shall conclude my peroration by saying that I hope that the Minister will make a name for himself by saying that the Government will reflect on what has been said.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.88.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1869" speakername="Jeremy Browne" colnum="88"  time="010:31:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew27">
	<p pid="a.88.2/1">I will be brief, because I know that there is enthusiasm in all parts of the Chamber to hear the Minister's response to what has been an interesting debate. We owe a debt to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" name="David Gauke">the hon. Member for South-West Hertfordshire (Mr. Gauke)</phrase> for securing this opportunity to discuss such an important subject.</p>
	<p pid="a.88.2/2">There is a widespread consensus about the nature of the problem, although there may be somewhat less of a consensus about the solution. We should start by acknowledging that our disagreement is not with the Iranian people. I know that that sounds like a general point that is almost not worth making, but it is important, because the Iranian regime is keen to portray the British Government and the British Parliament&mdash;and for that matter the British people&mdash;the Americans and others as innately hostile to Iran, its people and its way of life. We must be sure to reject that and say emphatically that our argument is not with the people. I have been to Iran on a number of occasions and can recommend it on many levels to others who might wish to visit. The people there have a great appetite for many of the points of common humanity that we would recognise and share with them.</p>
	<p pid="a.88.2/3">Another important point, which has not been made&mdash;or at least not at length&mdash;is that we should try to understand the mindset of people in the middle ground in Iran, rather than that of the most extreme people. To take the view of an Iranian person, on the west is Iraq, which is occupied predominantly by the United States but by the United Kingdom as well, while on the east is Afghanistan, which is also subject in large parts to, as an Iranian might see it, occupation by the United States, the United Kingdom and other countries that might not be entirely sympathetic to Iran. Further east are India and Pakistan, which have been discouraged from developing nuclear weapons, but appear not to have paid any great price for having done so. In fact, to the contrary: Pakistan's unelected leader and India's elected leader both seem to enjoy pretty good relationships with the United States, the United Kingdom and others.</p>
	<p pid="a.88.2/4">I would therefore urge caution to hon. Members who think that people in Iran are unaware of how absurd their regime is being. A lot of them are more open-eyed about the situation and have come to a more rational decision. After all, the President of Iran was elected, albeit in an imperfect election, which caused complications for people who wished to argue that everybody had been hoodwinked. In fact, the Iranian people were more clear about the choices that confronted them than we sometimes give them credit for. That makes the problem more complex than we in Parliament would wish.</p>
	<p pid="a.88.2/5">Despite that, the backdrop to the development of Iran's nuclear capacity is extremely worrying. Iran has a deeply repressive state that by any liberal standards is one of the worst in the world, with routine restrictions on speech, the media and religious expression, and foreign policy statements from its President that lurch between the alarming and the deranged. Nobody should be in any doubt that the threat is a great one. The Government are therefore right to be pleased that the matter has been reported to the United Nations. That is an important step and we should not be dismissive of it. The threat of sanctions and other activity ought be real. Iran needs to realise that there are economic, political and cultural consequences to being isolated.</p>
	<p pid="a.88.2/6">When it comes down to it, most people can accept most of those points; but what happens if Iran does not respond to those promptings, however energetic and however firm the consensus among leading world powers? That is the big question that the Minister needs to address. I do not detect any enthusiasm for conflict, and the hon. Gentleman rightly pointed out that, leaving aside the political considerations, there are enormous practical and military questions that lie between where we are now and intervention of that sort. However, we need to realise the seriousness of the situation and make it emphatically clear to the Iranian regime that it needs to think through the full political and other consequences of the action that it is taking. The Iranian Government have to be extremely careful about brinkmanship and seeing how far they can push the good will and tolerance of western countries, or for that matter of countries around the world.</p>
	<p pid="a.88.2/7">As in any negotiations, we perhaps also need to recognise that the Iranian Government need to be able to tell their people that they have reached a politically manageable solution, in terms of Iran's internal dynamic. However, as has been said before, ultimately, no Government can afford to rule out any option altogether. I will be interested to hear the Minister expand on what consequences he thinks will follow if the United Nations route does not prove to be successful, as we all hope it will be.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.89.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1735" speakername="Keith Simpson" colnum="89"  time="010:37:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew28">
	<p pid="a.89.0/1">I, too, congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" name="David Gauke">my hon. Friend the Member for South-West Hertfordshire (Mr. Gauke)</phrase> on introducing this important debate on Iran's nuclear programme. Like him and other hon. Members, one has the sense that this is a serious moment and that the next few months and years will be important not only for the international community but for Britain. As somebody who is by nature a reasonably sunny personality&mdash;at least politically&mdash;I am pessimistic not only about the situation in Iran but about the connected situation in Afghanistan.</p>
	<p pid="a.89.0/2">Hon. Members have spoken passionately and I should like to congratulate Labour and Conservative Friends of Israel on some most effective lobbying. Perhaps one day, when the regime has changed, we shall have a debate in which Labour and Conservative friends of Iran will be represented.</p>
	<p pid="a.89.0/3"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1875" name="Andrew MacKinlay">The hon. Member for Thurrock (Andrew Mackinlay)</phrase> seemed to speak on behalf of a number of my colleagues who were unable to get in. He is, of course, the voice of Lady Thatcher, in that when she was Prime Minister she believed that the Foreign Office existed to represent the interests of foreigners inside the United Kingdom. As a shadow Foreign Office Minister, I am not here to defend the Foreign Office&mdash;I am sure that the Minister will do that&mdash;but I should like to point out a factual error that the hon. Gentleman made. The most malign advice that Prime Minister Neville Chamberlain was given did not come from a Foreign Office official. Sir Horace Wilson was of course from the Treasury, and we should all know where our real enemies lie in Whitehall.</p>
	<p pid="a.89.0/4">Our policy is simple. We welcome Monday's decision by the five permanent members of the Security Council to report Iran in March. We recognise that we must work hard to prevent Iran from acquiring nuclear weapons, for all the reasons that have been succinctly argued by colleagues. However, like other colleagues, I have a number of concerns. It seems that Iran has had numerous opportunities to change course and address international concern about its nuclear intentions, yet the seven resolutions that the International Atomic Energy Agency has passed on Iran since 2003 represent a litany of Iran's failures to declare its activities and the deficiencies in its co-operation with the agency.</p>
	<p pid="a.89.0/5">After more than three years of inquiries, the IAEA has not been able to establish the details of the full genesis of Iran's programme. Iran has failed to provide transparency and has followed a deliberate policy of concealment. In early January, it removed IAEA seals from its nuclear installations and made preparations to begin enrichment. It has violated its safeguard agreements and there is a long litany of its saying one thing and doing the exact opposite. That is a difficulty for both the Foreign Office and the international community. They are hoping for the best but preparing for the worst. There is no guarantee that any commitment made by Iran, whether individually to the United Kingdom or to the international community, will every be carried out.</p>
	<p pid="a.89.0/6">A number of hon. Friends and colleagues, including my hon. Friend, put forward the dilemma for any democratic country and the international community. That is what happens when every element of diplomacy has been used, an attempt has been made to bring pressure to bear and sanctions have ultimately been introduced but the country at the receiving end has failed to respond. That leaves a great chasm and some form of military action may then be inevitable.</p>
	<p pid="a.89.0/7">A number of hon. Friends and colleagues pointed out their concern that if Iran fails to respond and the international community fails to persuade it, Israel might ultimately decide to take military action. If I follow the logic of the arguments of my hon. Friends and colleagues, that puts even greater emphasis on the international community to think about taking the full rack of sanctions. As we know from the United Nations charter, that does not rule out the international community's use of some form of military action.</p>
	<p pid="a.89.0/8">I want to flag up for the Minister a number of the Conservative party's concerns. We are worried that we seem already to have moved away from the outcome that our Government, the United States and our allies were seeking&mdash;an early referral to the UN Security Council. The Government's original response to the Iranian ending of suspension was, rightly, very strong, but are we able to deliver on our threat? Have the Government received assurances from Russia and China that they will support tougher action if necessary and if Iran continues its course of intransigence and confrontation? To my mind, Russia and China are the key. If they decide to sit on their hands and not go the full course, I greatly fear that someone&mdash;I am sure that the Government are attempting to point this out to them&mdash;will take what most of us would consider to be unacceptable action, which would ultimately be the military option.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.91.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1588" speakername="Mark Harper" colnum="91"  time="010:37:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew29">
	<p pid="a.91.0/1">Will my hon. Friend give way?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.91.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1735" speakername="Keith Simpson" colnum="91"  time="010:37:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew30">
	<p pid="a.91.1/1">I will not give way because I shall be only one more minute and other hon. Members, rightly, want to hear the Minister.</p>
	<p pid="a.91.1/2">We are also concerned that in expressing interest in Russia's compromise proposals and then reportedly offering access to the Lavizan site in Iran, the Iranian Government are employing delaying tactics by doing the absolute minimum to give the impression that they are interested in compromise. That has been their track record over the past five or six years. What is the Minister's assessment of the Russian proposal and Iran's commitment to exploring it?</p>
	<p pid="a.91.1/3">Finally and crucially, the Foreign Secretary said&mdash;this has been touched on by a number of colleagues&mdash;that military action against Iran is not an option. The Prime Minister said that all options are on the table. What is the Government's real position on the calls from some quarters to contemplate military action against Iran? I hasten to say that I am not advocating the use of military action, but I do not believe that in any international dispute, either now or in the past, when faced with an intransigent Government, the international community or a nation state can exclude the use of military action. That must always ultimately be in the background and available under not only the UN charter but international law. The Iranian Government should be only too well aware that ultimately that is an option. No one in this Chamber, and certainly not the Government, wants that option to be exercised, but the Prime Minister, the Foreign Secretary and the Defence Secretary need to come up with a form of words to encompass that. If we do not persuade the Iranians that we in the international community are serious, they will develop nuclear weapons and sooner rather than later one country in the middle east will actively intervene to prevent them. The consequence of that is too horrendous to contemplate.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.92.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2008" speakername="Douglas Alexander" speakeroffice="The Minister for Europe"  colnum="92"  time="010:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.92.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" name="David Gauke">the hon. Member for South-West Hertfordshire (Mr. Gauke)</phrase> on securing <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1875" name="Andrew MacKinlay">the debate. I have, as my hon. Friend the Member for Thurrock (Andrew Mackinlay)</phrase> urged me to do, listened carefully to the contributions from hon. Members on both Back Benches, which included a number of powerful speeches, and from the Front-Bench spokespeople for the principal Opposition parties who offered considered and measured contributions to this important debate.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/2">In his characteristically mild, supportive and gentle way, my hon. Friend the Member for Thurrock asked on what basis I, as the Minister for Europe, was appearing before the Chamber this morning. Perhaps I might clarify that the Minister for the Middle East is meeting Ministers from the region who are in London attending the Afghan conference, and the Foreign Secretary is meeting the Iranian Foreign Minister this very morning, so I speak on behalf of my Foreign Office colleagues.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/3">There have been a number of powerful and measured contributions from both sides. However, perhaps not for the first time in recent days, Labour is not as well represented as the Opposition. That was a source of concern until I heard the contribution from my hon. Friend the Member for Thurrock, which made me revise my view on whether more contributions from the Labour Back Benches would be entirely helpful to the Government.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/4">I acknowledge at the outset, as did the hon. Member for South-West Hertfordshire, that the debate is exceptionally timely. Before I explain the significance of that, I must echo the tributes that have been paid, and the sentiments that have been expressed by hon. Members on both sides of the House, to the families of the service personnel who lost their lives in Iraq in recent days.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/5">The debate is timely because tomorrow the International Atomic Energy Agency's board of governors will meet in special session in Vienna. For the board's 35 members, there will be just one agenda item: Iran's challenge to the international non-proliferation system and how to respond to it.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/6">I have a certain sympathy with <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1869" name="Jeremy Browne">the contribution of the hon. Member for Taunton (Mr. Browne)</phrase>, who acknowledged that there is a fairly broad consensus among the parties on the nature of the problem facing us. However, with the greatest of respect to hon. Members, I struggled to find clarity in their contributions of the details of the prescription, as distinct from the description, in the face of the problem. I shall try to set out for the record the Government's position and how we will take matters forward.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/7">Let me explain why the Government, with France and Germany, as part of the E3 process and supported by the European Union, believe that the time has come to involve the UN Security Council, to which a number of hon. Members referred. Two and a half years ago, Iran was forced to admit to the IAEA that it was building secret installations to enrich uranium and to produce plutonium which could be used to produce material for nuclear weapons. Iran was and still is building missiles that could carry nuclear warheads. Subsequent investigations showed that, in the IAEA's words,</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/8" class="indent">&quot;Iran's policy of concealment has resulted in many breaches of its obligation&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/9">A series of IAEA reports identified serious grounds for concern that Iran's nuclear programme might not be, as Iranian leaders claim, solely for peaceful purposes. Then, and now, our aim has been to persuade Iran by building broad international support&mdash;that relates to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1735" name="Keith Simpson">the point made by the hon. Member for Mid-Norfolk (Mr. Simpson)</phrase> about Russia and China&mdash;and working through multilateral bodies in order to take steps to guarantee that its nuclear programme will not be used for military ends. Under the IAEA's statute, Iran should have been reported to the Security Council two years ago. The UK, with France and Germany, decided to look for a way forward, through negotiation. The IAEA board agreed to delay involving the Security Council to give that initiative a chance.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/10">At the heart of our initiative was a proposal that Iran should suspend all enrichment-related and reprocessing activities that could be used to produce fissile material for a nuclear weapon while we discussed mutually acceptable long-term arrangements. The IAEA board adopted successive resolutions asking Iran to suspend those activities. In November 2004, Iran finally agreed to move ahead on that basis. The Paris agreement set out the framework for talks and offered the prospect of not just a long-term solution to the nuclear issue, but a stronger relationship between Europe and Iran, including co-operation on political and security issues and in economic and scientific fields. We have pursued the process in good faith, but Iran has rejected all constructive attempts to find a solution.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/11">Last August, Iran unilaterally restarted uranium conversion at its plant in Isfahan, in violation of the Paris agreement and contrary to IAEA board resolutions. The same month, without serious consideration, it rejected our detailed proposals for long-term arrangements. Those were the most far-reaching ideas for relations between Iran and Europe that have been presented since the 1979 Iranian revolution and they offered the possibility of an improved relationship based on co-operation.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/12">The IAEA board confirmed the legal basis for involving the Security Council under articles XII.C and III.B.4 of the IAEA's statute. However, at the request of our partners, we agreed to propose that the board again delay involving the Security Council, to enable more time for diplomacy. In December, European and Iranian officials met to explore whether we could find a basis for resuming talks. We made it clear that it would be essential for Iran not to resume further the suspended activities. With our support, Russia also sought a way forward by proposing that, as part of a final agreement, Iran might have a financial-only stake in an enrichment joint venture based in Russia. Such an agreement would have helped to assure Iran that it could rely on a supply of fuel for its nuclear reactors without acquiring technologies that could be used to produce fissile material for a nuclear weapon. The Russians also made it clear that Iran would need to continue suspension of all enrichment-related activities if such ideas were to be discussed further. We were prepared to endorse that idea, as long as no enrichment took place inside Iran. We understand that the Russians presented it in those terms as well.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/13">Since then, the Iranian position has been contradictory and deliberately confusing. At its request, European political directors agreed to meet one of its negotiators, Javad Vaidi, in Brussels on <phrase class="date" code="2006-01-30">30 January</phrase>&mdash;this past Monday&mdash;but Vaidi indicated no room for flexibility.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/14">Iran's resumption of uranium enrichment-related activity three weeks ago was a clear rejection of European and Russian efforts to get back to talks. Its actions have shown no respect for IAEA resolutions or for the commitments that it made to us and to Russia. Iran has portrayed its activities as harmless research, but they involve the development of technologies that would enable it to produce fissile material for a nuclear weapon. What Iran claims is a small step is, in fact, fundamental.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/15">Therefore, the backdrop to tomorrow's IAEA board meeting involves not just Iran's 18-year history of concealment, to which several hon. Members referred, and its failure to take steps that would give us confidence about its nuclear intentions, but also its policy towards Israel and Iraq, its attitude towards terrorism and its human rights record. I echo some of the sentiments that have been expressed. We have all been appalled by the comments of President Ahmadinejad, his denial of the holocaust and his calls for the destruction of the state of Israel, which my right hon. Friend the Foreign Secretary, who has not received universal support in this debate, described as sickening, horrific hostility to the Israeli people. In Damascus just 10 days ago, President Ahmadinejad met leaders of Islamic Jihad while its bombs were killing and injuring civilians in Israel.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/16">The consequences of Iran acquiring nuclear weapons are unthinkable. Central Asia and the middle east&mdash;two of the world's most volatile areas&mdash;would be destabilised. Other states might seek to enhance their own capabilities, prompting a regional arms race. The non-proliferation treaty&mdash;the very bedrock of international efforts to prevent the spread of nuclear weapons&mdash;would be badly damaged, as would the goal of creating a zone free of weapons of mass destruction in the middle east, a cause to which we are committed. Iran's latest actions are a challenge to the multilateral non-proliferation system and a rejection of the diplomatic track. We must respond firmly.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/17">On Monday, Foreign Ministers from the UK, France and Germany, together with their counterparts from the United States, Russia and China, agreed that in Vienna tomorrow we should work with the IAEA board, which should</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/18" class="indent">&quot;report to the Security Council its decision on the steps required from Iran, and . . . report to the Security Council all IAEA reports and resolutions&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/19">I welcome that decision. There is strong emerging consensus that it is time for the Security Council to become involved.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.0/20">Several hon. Members asked whether it had been appropriate to follow the diplomatic track. The efforts have not been in vain, as we are closer to securing genuine international consensus than we have been at any point in the preceding two years. For some of the reasons that have been outlined, it is vital that we secure such agreement. The Iranian regime fears genuine international consensus. What would be more to its advantage is a position from which it would be able to divide and seek to exploit the international community, thereby guaranteeing the continued potential for developing nuclear weapons.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.95.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1437" speakername="Tobias Ellwood" colnum="95"  time="010:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew31">
	<p pid="a.95.0/1">There is an irony in what happened with Iraq&mdash;IAEA representatives made it clear that they did not believe that there was a threat, yet we still ended up going to war&mdash;and in today's situation with Iran, which IAEA representatives have not been allowed to visit and which definitely involves a threat. I am concerned that, as a result of what was learned from Iraq, the Government and the international community may be more wary of dealing with the situation in Iran. They may go too softly and appease the country. Our approach must be more robust.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.95.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2008" speakername="Douglas Alexander" colnum="95"  time="010:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew32">
	<p pid="a.95.1/1">I listened carefully to that point and would argue respectfully that reporting to the Security Council is a necessary step, given where we are now. In that sense, notwithstanding some of the direct queries made by hon. Members, I would not wish to prejudge the outcome of the report to the Security Council. Further steps can be taken thereafter, but it is important at this stage to support the IAEA's efforts, and to sustain and uphold the importance of the IAEA board in dealing with the issue. We have reached the point at which it is necessary for a report to go to the Security Council.</p>
	<p pid="a.95.1/2">The agreement of the six countries to which I referred&mdash;and, indeed, many others&mdash;will send a powerful signal of the consensus that is emerging in the international community. The debate echoed the fact that international concern about Iranian activities has grown during the past two years of diplomatic discussion, and I fully accept that. The process led by European countries has done much to increase awareness of the problem and to build international consensus that Iran must take steps to build confidence. Regrettably, Iran's actions preclude the diplomatic solution wanted by the international community. It is now necessary to involve the Security Council to increase the political pressure on Iran to respect the wishes of the IAEA board.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.96.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1484" speakername="Eric Martlew" colnum="96"  time="010:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew33">
	<p pid="a.96.0/1">I call Mr. Amess.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.96.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1829" speakername="David Amess" colnum="96"  time="010:57:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew34">
	<p pid="a.96.1/1">You have taken me by surprise, Mr. Martlew.</p>
	<p pid="a.96.1/2">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1633" name="David Gauke">my hon. Friend the Member for South-West Hertfordshire (Mr. Gauke)</phrase> on the splendid debate. I concur with all the speeches, but I take a different opinion on many things that the Minister said. A lot of hon. Members are defence experts and could put the case more eloquently than I can. Unlike some people who purport to be Churchillian figures, I am one of the few Members of the House who have consistently raised the subject. If only we had been listened to much earlier.</p>
	<p pid="a.96.1/3">The Minister completely ignored the point about the People's Mojaheddin Organisation of Iran and what was said about the disgraceful thing that will happen shortly. The Minister owes the House the courtesy of addressing that. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1661" name="Philip Hollobone">My hon. Friend the Member for Kettering (Mr. Hollobone)</phrase> and I feel so strongly about how the gentleman who calls himself the President of Iran is conducting himself that a few weeks ago we addressed a crowd of 30,000 people outside the United Nations headquarters in New York.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.96.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2008" speakername="Douglas Alexander" colnum="96"  time="010:57:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew35">
	<p pid="a.96.2/1">I would not wish the House to believe that I intended any discourtesy by that omission, which the hon. Gentleman rightly identified. With the forbearance of hon. Members, I shall write to him about the PMOI.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.96.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1829" speakername="David Amess" colnum="96"  time="010:57:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew36">
	<p pid="a.96.3/1">That would be very useful. Many hon. Members and I are in favour of jaw-jaw rather than war-war, but we are angry because there has been too much seduction of the present regime. I listened carefully to the state of union address last night&mdash;what a sad figure I am, I stayed up for it&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.96.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1484" speakername="Eric Martlew" colnum="96"  time="010:57:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h01.htm#60201h01_spnew37">
	<p pid="a.96.4/1">Order.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.97.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="97"  time="010:57:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h02.htm#60201h02_head0">
	East Timor (Indonesian Invasion)
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.97.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1391" speakername="Don Foster" colnum="97"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h02.htm#60201h02_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.97.1/1">I am delighted to have this opportunity to debate the important issue of the deaths of those called the Balibo Five in East Timor in 1975.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/2">In 2002, East Timor celebrated its official independence as Timor-Leste. This followed two and a half years of United Nations administration and a 24-year illegal occupation by Indonesia, in which, according to a recent report, up to 180,000 people died. Today, I want to concentrate on just five of those deaths: the deaths on <phrase class="date" code="1975-10-16">16 October 1975</phrase> of five journalists, now known as the Balibo Five. They were a New Zealander, two Australians and the two Britons, Brian Peters and Malcolm Rennie.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/3">When Britons die abroad we anticipate our Government doing all they can to help the relatives. We expect the Government to seek as much information as possible and to share it with the relatives. Sadly, in this case, the opposite happened. From 1975 until 1995, there was almost complete inaction. The Government were involved in a disgraceful cover-up. Thirty years on, information is still being withheld from the relatives of Brian Peters and Malcolm Rennie, and from the relatives of the other three journalists. Hence, this debate concerns the release of documents relating to the Indonesian invasion of East Timor in 1975.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/4">With the help of many former and present Members of both Houses, the relatives have sought to prise open the store of documents about events surrounding the deaths of the Balibo Five. Success to date has been limited. This debate is designed to persuade the Government to make more information available, especially in time for the inquest of Brian Peters, due to take place this year in Sydney.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/5">What do we know? Following a civil war from July to September 1975, East Timor was in the control of a left-wing movement, Fretilin. Thousands had died and there remained instability and unrest. Into this situation flew Brian Peters and Malcolm Rennie. They were working for the late Kerry Packer's Channel Nine network and arrived in the East Timorese border town of Balibo on <phrase class="date" code="1975-10-13">13 October 1975</phrase>. There they met the other three journalists who were working for the rival Channel Seven network. Three days later all five were dead. How and why they died is what the relatives want to know.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/6">As we get closer to answering these questions it is increasingly clear that the reluctance of our Government to find out more&mdash;or to reveal more&mdash;about the deaths is because to do so would reveal even more than we now know about Britain's sorry role in Indonesia's war on East Timor. We are finding out more about that sorry role because, under intense pressure, both our Government and the Australian Government have released various documents. A selection of the released British official documents&mdash;compiled by my constituent Hugh Dowson&mdash;now appears on the website of the national security archive of George Washington university.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/7">From those and other documents we now know, for example, that the Australian Government were told in advance by Indonesia that it intended to invade East Timor. A briefing to the Australian Government on <phrase class="date" code="1975-10-13">13 October 1975</phrase> finally gave them the invasion date of <phrase class="date" code="">15 October</phrase> and the invasion route, which went through Balibo. It took 25 years before even that information was officially shared with the relatives of the Balibo Five.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/8">While we do not yet know the precise nature of our own Government's understanding of what was about to happen, we know that they knew enough to anticipate an attack. In effect, the British and the Australians gave a green light to Indonesia. Indeed, it was later to be said by our ambassador to Indonesia that the Balibo Five</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/9" class="indent">&quot;were in the war zone of their own choice&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/10">When the British selection was published last November, it prompted <i>The Times</i> to run a story with the headline &quot;Government lied to cover up war crimes in 1975 invasion of island&quot;. The Asia editor, Richard Lloyd Parry, began his article in equally stark terms:</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/11" class="indent">&quot;The British government knowingly lied about Indonesian atrocities in East Timor, including the killing of British journalists in 1975, according to newly released diplomatic documents.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/12">I should, however, point out that most of the documents were not newly released. Most were made available in 2002 and just the analysis was new, but that does not alter the starkness of the point made. The article continued:</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/13" class="indent">&quot;In a startling insight into foreign complicity in Indonesia's invasion of the former Portuguese colony, the documents show that Britain used its position as chair of the United Nations Security Council to 'keep the heat out of the Timor business' in the UN.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/14">Despite frequently telling the relatives of the dead men that the full facts of their deaths were unknown, British documents released in recent years indicate a rather different story. The documents show that our ambassador to Indonesia at the time, John Ford&mdash;now Sir John&mdash;sought to persuade the Australians not to press the Indonesian Government for information about the deaths. He wrote:</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/15" class="indent">&quot;We have suggested to the Australians that, since we, in fact, know what happened to the newsmen it is pointless to go on demanding information from the Indonesians which they cannot, or are unwilling to provide.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/16">This is in stark contrast to what relatives and parliamentarians have been told over the years. This was shown, for example, in the answer to a parliamentary question of <phrase class="date" code="1994-03-07">7 March 1994</phrase>, which stated:</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/17" class="indent">&quot;We pressed the Indonesians for information at the time.&quot;&mdash;[<i>Official Report</i>, <phrase class="date" code="1994-03-07">7 March 1994</phrase>; Vol. 239, c. 20W.]</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/18">The documents also show that while the full invasion of East Timor by the Indonesians did not begin until <phrase class="date" code="1975-12-07">7 December 1975</phrase>, incursions involving Indonesian troops did begin, as the Australian Government were warned, in October. In a confidential memo dated <phrase class="date" code="1976-03-15">15 March 1976</phrase> to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, the ambassador describes how attempts were made to destabilise the Fretilin movement by providing support, training and resources to the anti-Fretilin forces. The memo continues:</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/19" class="indent">&quot;Increasingly, Indonesian troops were used clandestinely to stiffen the Timorese guerrillas or replace them under the anti-Fretilin banner. In one of these actions on 15&ndash;<phrase class="date" code="">16 October</phrase> five journalists from Australia (two of them British by birth) were killed at Balibo near the border when reporting on the fighting from the Fretilin side.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/20">Thus, while the full-scale invasion was to come later, Indonesian troops were in action in East Timor at the time of the deaths.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/21">I would argue, therefore, that the answer to a parliamentary question on <phrase class="date" code="1994-03-14">14 March 1994</phrase>, which claimed that</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/22" class="indent">&quot;The deaths occurred over seven weeks before the Indonesian invasion&quot;&mdash;[<i>Official Report</i>, <phrase class="date" code="1994-03-14">14 March 1994</phrase>; Vol. 239, c. 473W.]</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/23">may be technically accurate, but it certainly evades giving a true reflection of what actually happened. This is especially so when we now know that the action, which was codenamed Operasi Flamboyant, involved a mixed force of 3,600 Kopassanda&mdash;Indonesian commandos&mdash;and anti-Fretilin Timorese. We also know that the second report on the deaths, published on <phrase class="date" code="1999-02-16">16 February 1999</phrase> by Australia's Minister of Foreign Affairs, Tom Sherman, said that the attack on Balibo came at the start of a general offensive by Indonesian military forces to annex East Timor.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/24">Given this cavalier approach to the truth both at the time and since, it is no surprise to read that when the Indonesian invasion resumed and the capital, Dili, was seized in December 1975, our ambassador to Indonesia sent a Christmas eve message to the FCO, saying:</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/25" class="indent">&quot;Once the Indonesian forces had established themselves in Dili they went on a rampage of looting and killing . . . . if asked to comment on any stories of atrocities I suggest we say that we have no information&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/26">So, the situation is clear. There was a cover-up of the invasion and of the atrocities that took place during it, including the deaths of the Balibo Five. As Richard Lloyd Parry's piece in <i>The Times</i> put it:</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/27" class="indent">&quot;In the Cold War atmosphere of 1975, after the US defeat in Vietnam, Indonesia's status as a pro-Western, anti-communist leader was far more important to Britain than justice for tiny and obscure East Timor&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/28">But the relatives want justice and to know what happened. They have been given various accounts of what might have happened, including that the five journalists were killed in crossfire during the civil war or, more recently, that they were accidentally killed during the invasion, or precursor to an invasion, by Indonesia. Indeed, although Indonesia's Government have yet to admit that their troops were involved, Indonesia's special forces have admitted that they killed the newsmen. We even know the names of some of those involved in the attack, including Yunus Yosfiah and Dading Kalbuadi.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/29">However, many believe that this was no accidental killing, but murder to prevent evidence of Indonesia's covert war on East Timor from being broadcast to the outside world. We, and the relatives, still do not know which is the correct version. More needs to be done to help them find out and to find out whether more could have been done to warn the Balibo Five of what was about to happen. However, to be fair, more recently more has been done. In 1998, for example, the then new Indonesian President was asked by our Government to look again at the deaths of the Balibo Five. He agreed to do so, but others more powerful than him blocked that investigation.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/30">Since then, many British and other official documents have been released. Bodies other than our Government have sought to make progress. The UN itself tried to carry out an investigation. The Indonesians refused to co-operate. What that investigation revealed is in the UN police files, a point to which I shall return in a moment. Most recently, East Timor's reception, truth and reconciliation commission has, among many thousands of other issues, considered the deaths of the Balibo Five. Its final report is expected to be made public later this year and may shed further light.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/31">However, this debate was intended to see whether our Government could do more. The Minister and his officials will, by now, have studied in detail the analysis on the national security archive website of documents released by his Department. Will he either now, or in writing in the near future, respond to that analysis? Will he acknowledge that for most of the past 30 years relatives of the deceased, hon. Members representing the interests of the relatives, and both Houses of Parliament have been misled? In a face-to-face meeting with the Minister's immediate predecessor, relatives of British citizens Malcolm Rennie and Brian Peters asked for help in ensuring that the evidence collected by the UN police is not contaminated. The letter of June 2005 from <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1554" name="Ian Pearson">the Minister for Trade, the hon. Member for Dudley, South (Ian Pearson)</phrase> to those relatives failed to allay their concerns about this urgent matter. Will the Minister now undertake to address those concerns?</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/32">Given the forthcoming inquest in Australia into the death of Brian Peters, will the Minister guarantee to provide full co-operation to the coroner? In particular, will he agree to release the documents referred to in my letter to the Secretary of State of <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-15">15 November 2005</phrase>? Once the final report of the reception, truth and reconciliation commission has been published, will the Minister establish high-level discussions with the Indonesian, Australian, New Zealand and East Timorese Governments? The purpose of such discussions would be to identify and put in place the further action needed to provide comprehensive information about the deaths of the Balibo Five and to bring to justice any persons identified as potential wrongdoers.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/33">I acknowledge that back in 1975 the UK Government were extremely anxious to keep what was happening in East Timor out of the news. The memo of <phrase class="date" code="1976-03-15">15 March 1976</phrase> from our ambassador to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office states</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/34" class="indent">&quot;that East Timor was an area in which Britain was no longer directly involved and that Britain's interests indicated a low profile&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/35">It continues:</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/36" class="indent">&quot;Dr Kissinger did likewise. This policy has so far paid off handsomely. The lack of involvement has largely kept Timor out of the British and US headlines and away from becoming a major public issue&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/37">Our Government, along with others, sought to hush up what was happening in East Timor and even to give political support to Indonesia. In the UN General Assembly vote of <phrase class="date" code="1975-12-12">12 December 1975</phrase>, which</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/38" class="indent">&quot;deplored the Indonesian military intervention in Portuguese Timor&quot;,</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/39">Britain abstained. We did what had been recommended, which was to</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/40" class="indent">&quot;keep our heads down and avoid siding against the Indonesian government&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.1/41">Many suggest that the reason for that approach was because Indonesia was a major international arms buyer, but, whatever the reason, our Government have some responsibility for the deaths of thousands of people. They certainly have a responsibility to come clean on all that they know about the deaths of the Balibo Five and to help the relatives find answers and obtain justice.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.101.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2008" speakername="Douglas Alexander" speakeroffice="The Minister for Europe"  colnum="101"  time="011:15:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h02.htm#60201h02_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.101.0/1">I welcome the opportunity to discuss the points raised in today's debate. The death of the five journalists in Balibo in East Timor on <phrase class="date" code="1975-10-16">16 October 1975</phrase>, and the suggestion, made subsequently, that they were deliberately killed, has naturally led to great distress for their relatives. I would like at the outset to address the suggestion that there has been any cover-up by the Foreign and Commonwealth Office or that it knows, or has withheld, any information that would shed further light on how the journalists died.</p>
	<p pid="a.101.0/2">A telegram from the Foreign Office to our embassy in Jakarta dated <phrase class="date" code="1975-10-16">16 October 1975</phrase> reports that Indonesia intended soon to intervene covertly in strength in support of anti-Fretilin elements in East Timor's civil war. A second telegram from our embassy in Jakarta on <phrase class="date" code="">24 October</phrase> records that Indonesia's stepped-up clandestine operations in East Timor appeared to be succeeding. It is clear from these telegrams that the Foreign Office was aware only of covert interventions by Indonesia prior to Indonesia's invasion on <phrase class="date" code="1975-12-07">7 December 1975</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.101.0/3">Papers released early in 2002, and available at the national archive since September 2002, show that our embassy in Jakarta reported the deaths of the five journalists on <phrase class="date" code="1975-10-24">24 October 1975</phrase>. The telegram from our embassy in Jakarta recorded that five journalists from Australia had been killed in an anti-Fretilin attack on Balibo and said that the Australian embassy had confirmed to us that two of those killed, Malcolm Rennie and Brian Peters, were &quot;British born&quot;. The telegram recorded what the Foreign Office knew of their deaths. That included the fact that they had been with Fretilin forces when the house in which they were sheltering was hit and set on fire, that press pictures of the house had been published, and that we understood that they had been</p>
	<p pid="a.101.0/4" class="indent">&quot;killed, almost certainly inadvertently, in the course of an attack by Indonesian/UDT forces&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.101.0/5">It was believed then and in the immediately following years that the journalists had been killed in crossfire between opposing groups fighting in East Timor. None of our records shows that the Foreign Office was aware at the time of the presence in Balibo of the journalists, nor is there any record that it was aware that they were in East Timor&mdash;a country in which we had no resident representation&mdash;at all. Consular assistance was given by the Foreign Office at the time to the family members of the two British journalists.</p>
	<p pid="a.101.0/6">Following a subsequent period of seven years during which no further action was taken or requested, the consular files were destroyed in accordance with our usual procedures. However, in 1994, a television documentary about East Timor, &quot;Death of a Nation&quot;, reawakened interest in the deaths. The documentary reported claims that the journalists had been tortured and killed by Indonesian soldiers. Brian Peters' sister then contacted the Foreign Office and, in April 1995, in order to reassure her of the Foreign Office's transparency about this case, she was given a collection of unclassified documents detailing what we knew about her brother's death. In July 1996, it was agreed that she should be invited to the Foreign Office to read some further highly classified documents that she had asked for.</p>
	<p pid="a.101.0/7">In May 2002, the Foreign Office agreed to the early release from its 1975 and 1976 files of all the documents relating to the events at Balibo on <phrase class="date" code="1975-10-16">16 October 1975</phrase>. These have been available at the national archive since <phrase class="date" code="2002-10-17">17 October 2002</phrase>. I am aware of the publication of a book recording an apparent admission by Indonesian special forces that they killed the five newsmen. That report suggests that they were not murdered, but were casualties of an attack on Balibo. I am also aware that there is an analysis of Foreign Office documents on the national security archive. I believe that it would be inappropriate for me to comment on that analysis and consider that the documents should be accepted at face value.</p>
	<p pid="a.101.0/8">I do not accept that the relatives of the deceased have been misled, and certainly not deliberately. It is worth pointing out that it was exceptionally agreed to release many documents early to the family members and to the national archive precisely to make it clear that we have nothing to hide. It does seem that the reply to the parliamentary question in 1994 should have made it clear that the representations to the Indonesian authorities were made by the Australians on our behalf. The Foreign and Commonwealth Office had remained in close contact with the Australians, who were seeking information from the Indonesians about the five newsmen on behalf of themselves and the UK. All five newsmen were residents of Australia, working for two Australian networks. With hindsight, it might have been better if the Foreign Office had pursued its own inquiries, but in 1975 it was judged reasonable, and it made sense, to allow the Australians to make those representations on their own and our behalf.</p>
	<p pid="a.101.0/9">In June 2005, the Foreign Office wrote to the family members in the United Kingdom. The letter included the information that we obtained about the future security of information collected by the UN police in East Timor prior to 2001, and then held by the serious crimes unit in East Timor. Our inquiries and our letter made it clear that the information would remain confidential and that only the prosecutor-general in East Timor, and prosecutors handling a legal case, are expected to have full access.</p>
	<p pid="a.101.0/10">We also made clear to the UN in East Timor and to the Government of East Timor the importance that we attach to the security and confidentiality of that information. If the families are still concerned about that, I shall be happy to ensure that those points are restated to those responsible in East Timor, and to seek an assurance that the security and confidentiality of the documents will be assured.</p>
	<p pid="a.101.0/11">I understand that the New South Wales coroner has set aside three weeks in July for an inquest into the death of Brian Peters. We have not been asked to provide any assistance, but we will be happy to consider any request to do so. I believe, however, that the limited light that FCO documents can shed on events is contained in documents already released to the national archive.</p>
	<p pid="a.101.0/12">The report of the commission for reception, truth and reconciliation has not yet been made public, although copies have been given to Kofi Annan, the Secretary-General of the United Nations, and to Parliament in East Timor. When we have seen the report, we will of course consider carefully what it says. Indonesia continues to maintain that the journalists were killed in crossfire during an attack on Balibo. In light of that, we consider it unlikely that high-level discussions along <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1391" name="Don Foster">the lines suggested by the hon. Member for Bath (Mr. Foster)</phrase> will achieve anything.</p>
	<p pid="a.101.0/13">The reports of two Australian investigations&mdash;the Sherman reports in 1996 and 1999&mdash;provided comprehensive information on what was then known about the events at Balibo in 1975. The second report concluded that the journalists were killed by an attacking force of Indonesian troops and anti-Fretilin East Timorese, but under the control of Indonesian officers, and in circumstances of continuing fighting between attackers and defenders, or at least before the attackers had secured their objective.</p>
	<p pid="a.101.0/14">In his conclusion to the second report, Mr. Sherman says that he has</p>
	<p pid="a.101.0/15" class="indent">&quot;never reached the stage of concluding that the Balibo 5 were murdered&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.101.0/16">I very much hope that the coroner's inquest in New South Wales will be able to reach a clear conclusion about what happened on <phrase class="date" code="1975-10-16">16 October 1975</phrase>, and bring some certainty for the grieving family members.</p>
	<p pid="a.101.0/17">Finally, I understand that a thorough search has been made for all the documents requested by the hon. Gentleman in his letter of <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-15">15 November 2005</phrase> to the Secretary of State, and that the hon. Gentleman will receive copies of them very soon.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.103.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="103"  time="011:23:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h02.htm#60201h02_head1">
	Sitting suspended until half-past Two o'clock.
	 &mdash; 
	Urbanisation (Developing Countries)
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.104.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1741" speakername="Sally Keeble" colnum="104"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.104.0/1">I am pleased to have secured the debate. It is not often that Westminster Hall makes parliamentary history, but we are now about to have the first debate on the subject in Parliament, so I am especially pleased that the Secretary of State is replying to it. It is an appropriate time to hold the debate, too, because it is estimated that by next year more than half the people in the world will live in towns and cities.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.0/2">I shall explain the origins of the debate. Last year, the executive director of UN-Habitat gave an inspiring address on urbanisation to the all-party group on Africa, which is chaired by <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1953" name="Hugh Bayley">my hon. Friend the Member for City of York (Hugh Bayley)</phrase>. From that, it became clear that urbanisation had slipped down the political agenda, so this debate partly redresses the balance and presses the needs of the world's 1 billion slum dwellers. Previously, 75 per cent. of the world's dollar-a-day poor lived in rural areas, which is perhaps why so much development assistance has focused on rural communities.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.0/3">The picture is now changing. We are seeing urbanisation not only of people, but of poverty. If we are to understand better, overcome and stop the enormous sprawl of slums in the megacities of the future, we need to understand better the nature and dynamics of urban poverty in developing countries. There is a lot to celebrate in cities. Throughout history, they have been a source of inspiration, dynamism and creativity. They have been the cradles of great civilisations and the engines of economic growth. They have also been the scene of abysmal squalor and human suffering.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.0/4">I am sure that the majority of hon. Members in the Chamber will have walked around such slums and seen the open sewers, the so-called flying toilets, the putrid drinking water, hovels stacked together and so many desperately ill, semi-starved people&mdash;yet among them incredibly resourceful and resilient people using every trick, crime and act of ingenuity that they can find to fight their way out of poverty.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.104.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" speakername="David Taylor" colnum="104"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.104.1/1">There is something of a &quot;Groundhog Day&quot; about the debate in that, only days ago, a similar complement of people were discussing international development. I congratulate my hon. Friend on securing the debate. Is she aware of the publication yesterday of the United Nations international strategy for disaster reduction? It observes that the bad news for urbanisation in developing countries is that people often crowd around the environmentally unsatisfactory areas close to big cities, and that will worsen the risk and the impact of future natural disasters. Is that something to which she hopes to refer?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.104.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1741" speakername="Sally Keeble" colnum="104"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.104.2/1">I am grateful to my hon. Friend for raising that. I was not aware of the report nor was I about to deal with that point. However, since it is on the record, I am sure that others will refer to it. I hope that my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State will deal with it in his response.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.2/2">Many people in those slums are the product of exactly the same economic forces that shaped our cities, our rural to urban migration and our economic growth. However, there are some profound differences between urbanisation today and the processes that shaped our country. First, the scale of the population shifts that are taking place today outstrip anything that we have seen in the past. Secondly, urbanisation is fastest in the developing countries in the south. Thirdly&mdash;this is perhaps linked to the previous two facts&mdash;the process of urbanisation is greatest in countries that are the least equipped to deal with it by virtue of the weakness of their economies and the fragility of the systems of governance. The result is that, of the massive growth of the world's cities, the biggest growth will be in the number of slum dwellers&mdash;people who live in urban settlements without water, sanitation, security of tenure and permanent shelter, and with chronic overcrowding.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.2/3">I shall give a few figures. By next year, more than half the world's population will live in urban areas. By 2030, about 60 per cent. of the world's population will live in towns and cities. That means that the urban population will have increased from 2.9 billion to 4.9 billion and that the majority will live in the megacities, most of which will be in the developing world. The proportion of people living in slums has increased disproportionately. Already one in six of the world's people live in slums, which is a third of all urban dwellers. On current trends, that figure will have gone up to 41 per cent. by 2030. Almost half the people in the world who live in towns and cities will be living in slums unless things change.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.2/4">Some of the figures on urban growth in Asia are astonishing. In China, by the end of the period 2000&ndash;10, 160 million extra people will be living in cities&mdash;the equivalent of nearly three times the population of this country. However, Africa will be the scene of the biggest changes and challenges. It is the fastest urbanising continent in the world. Cities there are growing at twice the rate of those in Latin America and Asia.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.2/5">Cities such as Nairobi and Kenya are doubling in size every 10 to 15 years. Lagos will be the third largest city in the world by 2010, with 20.2 million people. The equivalent of about a third of the population of this country will be cramped into one city with inadequate services. Sub-Saharan Africa also has the world's largest proportion of urban residents living in slums. Almost three quarters of all urban residents in Africa&mdash;about 187 million people&mdash;live in slums. To put it another way, one in five of the world's urban slum dwellers is an African.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.2/6">To try to stop the process of urbanisation would be futile. In some countries, its pace may be slow because of particular cultural, political or economic features, but efforts to prevent urbanisation in the past have been doomed to failure. With the urbanisation of the population comes the urbanisation of poverty. Some of the indicators are startling. The slums are the most dangerous places in the world to live, especially for children. For example, in Nairobi mortality among the under-fives is 0.78 per cent. in non-slum areas and 11.3 per cent. in the slums. HIV prevalence in Kenya's urban areas is more than double that of its rural areas. Our poverty-focused aid has to take account of that seismic shift.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.2/7">Already the developing world, especially African Governments, is acting on the challenge. The Cities Alliance brings together cities in the developing world with their international partners, the World Bank and UN-Habitat, to improve the lives of slum dwellers. The African Ministers conference on housing and urban development&mdash;an initiative by the New Partnership for Africa's Development, the African Union and UN-Habitat&mdash;has its second meeting this April.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.2/8">The international community has made its commitments, too. The millennium development goals include a target to improve the lives of 100 million slum dwellers by 2020. The Commission for Africa recognises the scale of the problem and made particular recommendations on finance for slum upgrading, clean water and infrastructure.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.106.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1661" speakername="Philip Hollobone" colnum="106"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.106.0/1">I congratulate the hon. Lady on securing the debate and on her excellent contribution. When the Houses of Parliament were built, London was the biggest city in the world. Now, in 2006, many cities around the world are far bigger.</p>
	<p pid="a.106.0/2">May I make a plea about utilities? This country has particular expertise in the delivery of water, electricity and gas systems. Would it be possible for the Government to make further efforts to encourage British utility companies to be involved in the provision of infrastructure in some of the poorest cities around the world?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.106.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1741" speakername="Sally Keeble" colnum="106"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.106.1/1">The hon. Gentleman, my neighbour from Kettering, is right that the provision of utilities in slum areas is a major challenge. Access to clean drinking water, one of the targets for the millennium development goals, is essential, particularly for child health. I am sure that my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State will refer to that when he winds up.</p>
	<p pid="a.106.1/2">The hon. Gentleman is absolutely right that one of the problems that has to be tackled now and in future, as we try to prevent the sprawl of slum areas, is the provision of infrastructure services for people as they move into the cities. He is right to highlight that as a major issue for urbanisation.</p>
	<p pid="a.106.1/3">In addition to the Cities Alliance is the African Ministers conference on housing and urban development. That initiative was introduced by NEPAD and UN-Habitat and is due to hold its second meeting in April. The international community has also made commitments, and the MDGs include the goal of improving the lives of 100 million slum dwellers by 2020. The Commission for Africa also recognised the scale of the problem and made recommendations on finance for slum upgrading and on water and infrastructure. The significance of the problem was reinforced at last year's world summit, which underlined the fact that the future of slums would influence the achievement of all the MDGs.</p>
	<p pid="a.106.1/4">However, the international community's actions and commitments so far will not deliver on the goals that it has set. It is perhaps partly the size of the task that is daunting. There is the sheer number of people involved, and it is expected that there will be 1 billion extra slum dwellers. There is also the complexity of the services that are needed. As the hon. Gentleman said, there is the issue of utilities, water supplies and infrastructure. There is also the sheer cost of it all, particularly given the very statist view of housing in this country.</p>
	<p pid="a.106.1/5">I therefore have three requests to put to my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State as regards meeting the needs of the world's slum dwellers and achieving the MDGs. First, the UK Government must give priority to promoting slum dwellers' security of tenure and better urban governance. Without security of tenure, it will be impossible to achieve the rest of our goals. The residents' lack of security is a real barrier to upgrading slums, and slum dwellers can be swept away easily to satisfy a political elite's predilections, to make way for road building or as part of the ethnic cleansing of a capital city. UN-Habitat's excellent study of forced evictions lists a number of such removals, but I shall mention just two. First, there are the clearances in Khartoum, which my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State saw for himself. Southerners were moved to make way for, I think, for road building&mdash;at least, that was the excuse; in fact, the move was thought to be political because it involved southerners. Secondly, there are the forced removals in Zimbabwe, which I saw on my recent visit there. It caught not only some of the poorest and most vulnerable people, including HIV orphans, their carers and many more, but half of the Zimbabwean UN staff working in Harare, as well as some of the locally engaged staff from the British embassy in Harare.</p>
	<p pid="a.106.1/6">Secondly, I ask that my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State prioritise the development of financial instruments for slum upgrading. If <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1661" name="Philip Hollobone">the hon. Member for Kettering (Mr. Hollobone)</phrase> makes a contribution, I am sure that he will talk about infrastructure and utilities, but I specifically ask for priority to be given to the development of financial instruments for slum upgrading, because this country has particular expertise in financial modelling and services. Prioritising financial instruments in that way would also underline the fact that slum upgrading is an economic project. Slum dwellers pay quite high rents. However awful the housing, and however destitute the people in those shacks in Kibera, they all speak of how much rent they pay and how much they owe in rent arrears. Shacks are good investments in the conventional sense, and it is calculated that a landlord in Nairobi will recoup his investment in a shack within nine months, given the rent that he can charge on it.</p>
	<p pid="a.106.1/7">Thirdly, I urge my right hon. Friend to support the UN-Habitat proposal for a slum upgrade facility of $250 million a year for five years. Without it, there is little chance of meeting the MDG. The facility would provide a combination of short-term loans for housing schemes for poor people, loan mechanisms for grassroots schemes and funds for technical help in designing and setting up projects for slum upgrading.</p>
	<p pid="a.106.1/8">Above all, however, what is required, and what the debate is intended to achieve, is a high priority for urbanisation on the international development agenda. The world summit rightly recognised that we cannot achieve the MDG if we simply react to the terrible and growing poverty of the burgeoning number of slum dwellers. The international community also needs to run ahead of the problem and to prevent slum development, not by stopping urbanisation, but by planning for it and providing the governance, infrastructure and financial capacity to cater for the 1 billion more people who will be living in towns and cities. Last year's world summit specifically recognised that.</p>
	<p pid="a.106.1/9">I hope that my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State will set out his response to the three particular requests that I have made and, above all, that he will make clear the UK Government's commitment to meeting the challenge of the world's 1 billion slum dwellers.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.108.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1953" speakername="Hugh Bayley" colnum="108"  time="014:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.108.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1741" name="Sally Keeble">my hon. Friend the Member for Northampton, North (Ms Keeble)</phrase> on securing this debate on an important topic. I was not aware that it is the first time that Parliament has ever debated it. It is to her credit that she followed up the meeting of the all-party group on Africa, which the executive director of UN-Habitat, Anna Tibaijuka came to address, by ensuring that we had a debate in this House to discuss the important issues that she raised.</p>
	<p pid="a.108.0/2">Like my hon. Friend, I have seen, in squatter settlements, shanty towns and refugee camps in Africa, Asia and Latin America, poverty and squalor that is so intense that it takes one's breath away. There is poverty that robs people of their humanity. I am talking about children who do not have clothes because their parents have HIV/AIDS and have sold everything to buy food; people who do not have food or shelter; children without schools; sick people without health care; people without hope; and people who were driven from the countryside by violence, warfare or famine to the city because they hoped for a better life.</p>
	<p pid="a.108.0/3">Like my hon. Friend, I have also seen how, in appalling conditions in cities in developing countries, community self-help groups and donor-funded development assistance projects can raise one's spirits and make one realise that there are those with the human capacity to rise above incredible adversity and make a difference to their lives and those of others around them. I think of KENWA, a Kenyan women's organisation based in the slums of Nairobi. It has brought together women who are infected with HIV to give each other support and, if one of them dies, to give support to their orphaned children.</p>
	<p pid="a.108.0/4">Some 10 years ago, I met a Catholic priest in Khartoum who took me to see one of the displaced people's camps in the desert outside the city. It had housed people from the west&mdash;from Darfur&mdash;and people from the south of Sudan who were fleeing from the long-running civil war. At the settlement hundreds of homes had been bulldozed, as had churches, simply because the Khartoum state Government wanted to drive those people away, back into the countryside, but those people would not be driven back into the countryside&mdash;they had fled war and were looking for sanctuary, so they ended up sleeping rough in and around Khartoum until they found some other squatter settlement in which to build a rudimentary shelter. This man went out with sticks and polythene sheets to try to provide shelter for those people from the 130&deg; heat in the desert.</p>
	<p pid="a.108.0/5">I have seen Muslim women in villages in Uttar Pradesh, India, who went door to door to encourage other Muslim women to vaccinate their children against polio. Uttar Pradesh is one of the few parts of the world in which polio is still prevalent and claims lives. It is largely Muslim children who become infected, because a rumour has gone around that vaccination is a Hindu plot to make them infertile. That is utter nonsense. The most powerful message was carried by a Muslim woman who took her immunised child with her. If she is successful in that endeavour, which is funded by our Department for International Development, polio might be eradicated from India before long.</p>
	<p pid="a.108.0/6">I have seen teachers of girls in displaced people's camps for Afghan refugees&mdash;people who fled from the violence of the Taliban. They found in the camps both refuge and education for their girl children, which was not available in Afghanistan under the Taliban regime. There are enormous problems, but also thousands of people capable of overcoming them. The onus is on us in the rich world to provide help, support and funding to enable those people to do their work.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.109.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" speakername="David Taylor" colnum="109"  time="014:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.109.0/1">In a debate last week, I pointed out that although it is important that relief, aid and advice come from international governmental organisations, companies and charities, smaller contributions from the country concerned or from other countries have a role as well. That was pointed out to me by the Building and Social Housing Foundation, which is based in Coalville in my constituency. The foundation researches such issues and is particularly worried about the plight of people who are in informal housing and facing eviction in Africa. We can help. It does not take a grand-scale organisation to contribute to the alleviation of suffering.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.109.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1953" speakername="Hugh Bayley" colnum="109"  time="014:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.109.1/1">I could not agree more. Such problems in urban areas need to be solved from the bottom up. Of course, they need help, support and funding from the top down; small organisations will not fund themselves. With support from DFID and from multilateral agencies, local grass-roots initiatives and small-scale projects&mdash;including twinning projects between organisations in the UK and those in developing countries, about which I shall say more later&mdash;can make a real and much-needed difference.</p>
	<p pid="a.109.1/2">My hon. Friend the Member for Northampton, North spoke about the 2003 UN-Habitat report, &quot;The Challenge of Slums,&quot; which reported that, of people living in urban areas, 72 per cent. in Africa, 58 per cent. on the Indian subcontinent and 32 per cent. in Latin America and the Caribbean live in slum conditions. If we go back through our own country's social history, we see that there were similar conditions here not so long ago. In 1901, Seebohm Rowntree wrote a book called &quot;Poverty: A Study of Town Life,&quot; which was the first ever door-to-door survey or census of poverty in one city&mdash;the city of York, my constituency. The survey revealed that at the turn of the last century, a quarter of people in the city of York were living in poverty. Charles Booth did similar studies in London, of course.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.109.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" speakername="David Taylor" colnum="109"  time="014:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew8">
	<p pid="a.109.2/1">My hon. Friend mentions Charles Booth and his seminal work on poverty in London. It is no surprise that Charles Booth was a north-west Leicestershire person, who was equally generous with his time, ideas and resources to the people of Thringstone, in my constituency, where his memory and successes are venerated to the present day.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.110.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1953" speakername="Hugh Bayley" colnum="110"  time="014:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew9">
	<p pid="a.110.0/1">We have a lot to learn from the history of this and other European countries. Those lessons must and can be applied by leaders of urban communities in the developing world.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/2">The scale of the problem is enormous. Some 924 million people, roughly a third of the global urban population, live in slums. The number of people migrating from the countryside to towns, or being born in towns, means that the world's urban population is growing by 180,000 people each day. Roughly speaking that is the same as the population of the city of York and its surrounding suburbs and villages. That is the scale of the problem with which the world must grapple: can we build cities, homes, infrastructures, schools and health clinics around the world at the rate of a York a day? I believe that we can. We managed to overcome urban squalor in this country in a century, and I think that it is possible to do the same globally. That is the challenge that we face.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/3">It is important for us not to fall into the trap, as do some people who write about the problem of urbanisation, of setting towns against the countryside in a competition for scarce resources. In the countryside and in towns it is the same phenomenon that leads to human desperation: poverty. Poverty in the countryside is what drives people to the towns to seek a better life, and poverty in urban slums holds people back from finding that better life. For instance, the poor rickshaw puller in Dhaka in Bangladesh has probably come from the countryside and a poor existence as an agricultural day labourer. So it is not possible to solve the problems of the countryside at the expense of the towns, or vice versa.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/4">As my hon. Friend the Member for Northampton, North, said, the process of urbanisation is irreversible. Bulldozing settlements&mdash;as the Sudanese Government have done around Khartoum, the Mugabe regime in Zimbabwe and the Kenyan Government in Nairobi, and as has happened in Lagos&mdash;does not relieve the pressure on scarce resources in urban areas. Those people remain, and they still need education, health care and shelter.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/5">If we look back at the history of our own country it can be seen that local government has played an enormously important part in overcoming the problems of urban squalor. There is a growing recognition of the importance of local government in overcoming those problems in developing countries. After the Gleneagles G8 summit, the Prime Minister said that for the G8 deal</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/6" class="indent">&quot;to translate into poverty reduction across the continent it is important that Africa builds effective, accountable central and local governments&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/7">The Prime Minister has also emphasised the importance of local government in achieving the millennium development goals, some of which are particularly the responsibilities of local government, such as goal 7, target 11, on slum upgrading. The report by the Commission for Africa, of which my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State was a member, stressed that devolving power and taking decisions locally brings politicians and decision makers closer to those who use their services. That can also enable excluded groups, such as the disabled, women and, more generally, the poor to participate in the process of government.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/8">The Commission for Africa report, however, also rightly stressed that municipalities in most developing countries are hampered by a lack of trained personnel and resources. All too often, therefore, the services that they provide are patchy and inadequate. Donor countries such as ours and the Governments of African countries need to invest in capacity building in local government, in training local government officers and in making policy development, revenue collection and revenue spending more transparent and accountable locally. The Ghanaian Government, for instance, receive budget support through Government-to-Government aid from the UK and have a common fund that devotes a fixed percentage of national revenue to local authorities.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/9">At a grass-roots level, my city has a twinning link with Fanteakwa district in Ghana. I once visited Begoro, the main town of Fanteakwa district, met the chief executive of the council and saw some of the services that it provides in the district. They are good, well run services. There are schools and a technical college; he showed me a library that they were building. When I returned I talked to York and North Yorkshire library services and to the university college of York St. John to see whether we could obtain some suitable books&mdash;sending any old books would not be useful&mdash;for their library and ship them out. We collected books from academic and public libraries in North Yorkshire and e-mailed a list of titles to Begoro. They chose those that they thought suitable and appropriate and we shipped <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" name="David Taylor">the books out to them. As my hon. Friend the Member for North-West Leicestershire (David Taylor)</phrase> pointed out, small-scale, local, town-to-town links can make a difference.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/10">The Commonwealth local government forum, which receives &pound;2 million of DFID funding and about twice that in support in kind from local authorities in the United Kingdom&mdash;usually in the form of staff seconded to work for short periods in developing countries&mdash;has built some effective partnerships under what its good practice scheme. Lisburn city council in Northern Ireland, for instance, has worked with Swellendam municipality in the western cape of South Africa to create an economic development strategy. Plymouth city council works with Shama Ahanta council in Ghana to devise and implement a sustainable tourism strategy. Newham council works with Thiruvananthapuram council in India&mdash;I apologise to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1714" name="Ashok Kumar">my hon. Friend the Member for Middlesbrough, South and East Cleveland (Dr. Kumar)</phrase> if my pronunciation is poor&mdash;to use geographic information systems mapping to target economic development projects more accurately on poor communities in the area.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/11">Local government, if it is properly resourced, works. South Africa, after the move to enfranchise all citizens of all races, held its first local government elections in 1995. Since then, the number of homes in urban areas with electricity has increased from one third to three quarters. The number with clean water has increased from 62 per cent. to 85 per cent. Achieving connections in South Africa is the responsibility of local government.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/12">In Uganda, the local government association has created a scheme called city community challenges, targeting resources on urban areas of need. In Jinja, where the Nile leaves Lake Victoria, a city community challenge built 700 low-cost homes, using local materials and local labour&mdash;unemployed people from the slum areas of the city who received training in the craft skills they needed to build homes. Those selected to move into the homes were people who were excluded generally from society, such as disabled people and households headed by women. They, too, were provided with training as well as a home so that they could build a secure economic future.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/13">When Anna Tibaijuka from UN-Habitat came to speak to the all-party group in November last year, she mentioned her organisation's new report on financing urban shelter. Like my hon. Friend the Member for Northampton, North, I was struck by the following statistic: most slum dwellers rent shacks from private owners&mdash;I had assumed the shacks were self-built when people arrived in the city although in the majority of cases they are not&mdash;and the shack owners can get the cost back within nine months. How do they get their cost back so quickly? By charging exploitative rents.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/14">Businesses generally want a higher rate of return in developing countries than in the developed world because they perceive that the business risks are higher, but no legitimate business or finance house expects a rate of return of more than 100 per cent. in a single year. That makes me think that it must be possible to invest in higher quality housing at lower rents and still be able to achieve a sensible rate of return of the kind that an investor might expect in a developing country&mdash;perhaps a 20 or 25 per cent. return. If the council became involved in partnership with the financier, it could contribute real value by granting title to the land to the people who lived in the housing, and because the rent would be lower more money would be available to pay the local authority, or a private provider, for services such as electricity and water. Therefore, I warmly support UN-Habitat's slum upgrading facility proposal, which my hon. Friend mentioned.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/15">The second policy issue that we need to address in relation to the problems of urban areas in developing countries is crime. Most people in slums are decent, honest people, and they are far more likely to be victims of crime than criminals. However, there is sometimes a political correctness that leads to crime being overlooked. One of the UN-Habitat documents that I read on its website before this debate is entitled &quot;Today's Slums: Myths versus Reality&quot;. It states:</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/16" class="indent">&quot;Slums are often associated with crime, but in some places this is more a fabrication of the media than a reality.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/17">It is not a media fabrication if someone is a victim of crime&mdash;if someone is forced to be a drug mule for a drug baron in order to pay their debts or unpaid rent, or if someone is intimidated by a criminal gang as part of a protection racket or to secure their vote in an election.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/18">In the United Kingdom, crime is worst on our most deprived estates, even though the vast majority of people who live in those areas are perfectly honest, and it should come as no surprise that things are much the same in developing countries. Crime is highest where living conditions are worst. The development community cannot shy away from crime because of a form of political correctness; we must accept that law and order are vital for providing human security and an environment that allows economic development.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/19">The Commonwealth Parliamentary Association UK branch visited Jamaica last September. I attended its report-back meeting, and learned that in poor, inner-city Kingston there are places called garrison constituencies; they are parliamentary constituencies that are affiliated year in and year out with one or other of the main political parties&mdash;both of them are involved in the same way. Poor people support the party in anticipation of benefits that might accrue to them: access to employment, getting their child into school, or other basic services. At one stage removed from the politicians are criminal gangs that use violence to maintain the status quo.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/20">I spoke this morning to Andrew Tuggey, the secretary of the CPA UK branch. Before he came to work for the CPA branch in Parliament, he served as an Army officer in Northern Ireland. He drew a parallel between the situation in Kingston now, and the situation in Belfast in the early 1970s. Two things are vital to overcome those problems of politically related crime and violence in slums in developing countries. The first is effective security. The United Kingdom has seconded two assistant chief constables to the Jamaica police, and we also provide some training for the Jamaica defence force. The second thing is political reform. A new younger generation of politicians in Jamaica, in both parties, is pressing for change. Kingston city council's urban renewal policy, for instance, has stressed the need to build social housing in both green and yellow garrison constituencies, irrespective of political allegiance, and to allocate housing centrally, not through the constituencies.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/21">There are policy lessons to be drawn. I have been helped in forming my thoughts by an article by Dr. Aldrie Henry-Lee of the university of the West Indies, which appeared in a journal called <i>Environment and Urbanisation</i> last October. First, politicians must be divested of the power to distribute scarce benefits, including, as happens in many developing countries, budgets for buying small projects and works in their constituency. If they are seen as people who dispense favours or services from funds that they personally control, a form of clientism is bound to develop.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/22">Secondly, politicians must have nothing to do with criminal or violent gangs, or the leaders of those gangs, even if the latter appear to be a leadership divorced from the gangs themselves. Thirdly, politicians must identify any members of their party who associate with criminals, and deprive them of office, if they hold it, in the party or publicly. Fourthly, they must make sure that their security forces and municipal authorities give no protection to gang members. Finally, and importantly, as in this country, the police must provide protection to those who supply them with information about wrongdoing and act as witnesses when cases come to court.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/23">Perhaps what is happening in Kingston sounds a little like Chicago or Sicily: it is. The solution to the problem is the same. There is a need to clear out the corrupt politicians and introduce a new, clean politics.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.0/24">The week before last DFID published its consultation document seeking input to the White Paper that it intends to publish in the summer. I hope that today's debate will be seen as part of that consultation process, and that the White Paper will closely examine the importance of good governance and political reform&mdash;the Department has already made it clear that it will tackle that issue&mdash;as well as developing the capacity of local government to deal with the severe urban problems. Without stronger local government in developing countries they will not rise to the challenge of creating decent conditions in which people can live and prosper in the growing cities of the developing world.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.114.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1982" speakername="John Barrett" colnum="114"  time="015:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew10">
	<p pid="a.114.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1741" name="Sally Keeble">the hon. Member for Northampton, North (Ms Keeble)</phrase> on securing <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1953" name="Hugh Bayley">the debate. As the hon. Member for City of York (Hugh Bayley)</phrase> mentioned, it is key that the issue be discussed and absorbed by the Department for International Development. One quality of urbanisation&mdash;and the hon. Member for City of York mentioned this&mdash;is that it is irreversible. That is important now, but will become even more so in the years ahead.</p>
	<p pid="a.114.0/2">Urbanisation and the urbanisation of poverty have been described as the second biggest challenge for the developed world, after the HIV/AIDS pandemic. Clearly, the process of urbanisation is one of the most significant changes taking place in developing nations. The world's urban population multiplied tenfold in the 20th century and now stands at about 3 billion. Properly managing that change is one of the key challenges facing the international community today.</p>
	<p pid="a.114.0/3">Despite its importance, urbanisation is often misunderstood in international politics and we have yet to adapt to some of the challenges it poses. Africa now has a larger urban population than either north America or western Europe&mdash;I found that hard to believe about western Europe&mdash;yet it is often perceived as being overwhelmingly rural. Our aid efforts often seem to focus on farmers and rural challenges when the biggest challenges are perhaps in the more urban cities and townships. All too often donor agencies prioritise investment in rural areas, and it does not reach the majority of the poor.</p>
	<p pid="a.114.0/4">It is clear that the locus of poverty has fundamentally shifted away from rural areas to cities and townships. There is no point in denying that that change has occurred. It has happened and is, as the hon. Member for City of York said, irreversible. How best to deal with the urbanisation of poverty is one of our biggest challenges.</p>
	<p pid="a.114.0/5">Although rapid urban growth is often seen as a problem, it is worth remembering that it is normally the nations with the best economic performances that urbanise most rapidly. Also, there is a proven link between rapid urban change and a marked increase in standards of living. It is an often overlooked fact that some of the world's fastest-growing cities of the past 50 years have among the best standards of living in their respective nations, but that is not the picture that we see in many developing countries. Our own cities grew as our rural population declined, and that is a classic example of the shift from rural to urban. Edinburgh, for example, has grown steadily over decades and centuries while the population in the countryside has reduced dramatically.</p>
	<p pid="a.114.0/6">Many commentators see the rapid growth of sub-Saharan cities over the past 50 years as a serious problem, if not a full-blown disaster, but that approach over-simplifies the situation. One reason for rapid urbanisation is the achievement of political independence and the end of discriminatory controls over people's lives. In Uganda, urban growth was slower than expected in the early post-independence period because violence and instability crippled the country's economy. However, once stability was restored, the economy expanded and urbanisation was more rapid. More obviously, in post-apartheid South Africa, it is because of the legacy of apartheid that that country remains relatively non-urbanised, although there is a move to urban centres. Much of the explanation for that is the strict control imposed on the African population's right to live in urban areas. Those examples should be a warning against viewing urbanisation as necessarily a bad thing. Often it is the result of positive changes in a society.</p>
	<p pid="a.114.0/7">Urbanisation brings with it a whole range of problems if it is not managed effectively. Cities and urban centres can and should be hubs of creativity and economic growth, but rapid urbanisation in the developed world has left 1 billion people living in slums and squatter settlements; estimates suggest that that number will double by 2030. Almost no large city has had its initial urban expansion guided by a rational plan, but it is unrealistic to expect that.</p>
	<p pid="a.114.0/8">In cities in this country and other high-income nations, it is taken for granted that systems of governance exist to facilitate and monitor urban expansion. Planning controls, building standards, sewerage, drainage, schools and hospitals are more or less taken for granted. We all accept that the staff of urban governments should be answerable to elected representatives, but it is important to remember that the well worn paths of local governance are a relatively recent occurrence that we cannot take for granted. They simply do not exist in many cities and urban centres around the world.</p>
	<p pid="a.114.0/9">In many poor and developing countries, city governments are corrupt and unrepresentative with the result that decisions are afforded little legitimacy by the local population. The accountability of local authorities to their citizens is a fundamental tenet of good governance, but the widespread prevalence of patron-client relationships has further undermined and corrupted democracy and accountability. Corruption takes resources from those least able to afford the loss, and they work their way through to the richer. It undermines credibility and deepens urban poverty. As a result, investment in the basic infrastructure lags far behind what is desperately needed.</p>
	<p pid="a.114.0/10">As I mentioned last Thursday in the debate on international development, the Select Committee on International Development visited a clinic in Nairobi where, for want of the local authority connecting the water and electricity supplies for eight years, the doctors and nurses in that clinic had to remain in an outdated building. It is vital that the local authorities in such cities play their part. It is common for half or more of the population of cities in the developing world to be without access to water taps in their homes or yards, and for more than three quarters to have inadequate provision for sanitation.</p>
	<p pid="a.114.0/11">When the hon. Member for Northampton, North mentioned flying toilets, I was reminded of my visit to Kibera, the slum on the outskirts of Nairobi. I come from a city &mdash;Edinburgh&mdash;with a history of such things; in days gone by, people emptied sewage out of the high storeys of buildings with a cry of &quot;gardez l'eau&quot;. It is a disgrace that in today's world the waste from toilets is still flying through the air. In that same slum, we also visited a shack, and were amazed by the quality of life. The children were immaculately turned out to go to school. With so few basic facilities&mdash;no water supply, no sewerage&mdash;families were able to pick themselves up and did the best that they could.</p>
	<p pid="a.114.0/12">Sadly, that was by no means an isolated example. Most cities in Africa have sewerage connections for less than 10 per cent. of their populations, and many have no sewerage system at all. The harsh reality is that hundreds of millions of urban dwellers in Africa, Asia and Latin America have to rely on water sources that are unsafe, unreliable and difficult or impossible to access. As a result, it is common for one in every four children in poorly managed cities to die before their fifth birthdays. Many of those deaths can be directly attributed to chronic lack of infrastructure and services. In this country, we do not question the fact that our bins are emptied and, in some cases, our material for recycling is collected; street lamps line our roads; and our water runs hot and is clean enough to drink. We have become so used to the web of institutions that provide these services that we sometimes forget their fundamental importance.</p>
	<p pid="a.114.0/13">We have all seen satellite images of the world at night, showing a stunning map of brilliantly lit cities. Only across Africa do many cities remain dark at night. In the absence of appropriate or effective governance structures, too few planning controls are in place. Those that exist are often bypassed as a result of corruption, or for other reasons. As a consequence of ineffective land use planning, cities expand chaotically, causing problems along the way. Many cities have no city-wide plan because the built-up area falls into different local jurisdictions and no governance structure exists to enable co-ordination.</p>
	<p pid="a.114.0/14">The hon. Member for City of York mentioned the high rate of return on shacks in city slums. In New Delhi, there are massive slums&mdash;some officially recognised and some not&mdash;and what struck me was the fact that the return on a fast-food restaurant in one of the wealthiest parts of London is only one third of the return that a slum landlord can achieve in such a city. That is an outrage, and unless it changes, people will, for economic reasons, drive on with the continuation of slum dwellings.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.116.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1741" speakername="Sally Keeble" colnum="116"  time="015:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew11">
	<p pid="a.116.0/1">Does the hon. Gentleman agree that the fact that slum properties can generate money makes it possible to look at the financial mechanisms that can be used for slum upgrading, and to provide improved housing and greater security of tenure for slum dwellers?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.116.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1982" speakername="John Barrett" colnum="116"  time="015:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew12">
	<p pid="a.116.1/1">That is a valid point; clearly there area money and businesses in the slums and there are dynamic entrepreneurs. If that money could circulate in the same area, there could be a vast improvement. Without a doubt, those who receive those high rents do not live in the slums. Money is pouring out of the pockets of slum dwellers into the pockets of those living Californian lifestyles just around the corner.</p>
	<p pid="a.116.1/2">As many of the people in the room have seen first hand, many walled residential developments that are protected by security firms are only two blocks down the road from squatter communities. Such communities are sometimes unrecognised by the Government and lack the most basic infrastructure and services. Indeed, it is now common in some parts of the world for between a quarter and a half of a city's population to live in a squatter settlement without official approval or recognition.</p>
	<p pid="a.116.1/3">Such stories paint a bleak picture, and other hon. Members have pointed to the immense problems that we face. The scale of the challenge is indeed daunting: cities have become places to fear, where crime and disease are rife. Nairobi was mentioned earlier and it is sometimes called &quot;Nairobbery&quot;. Even on the recent Select Committee visit, a colleague was unfortunate enough to be robbed and mugged.</p>
	<p pid="a.116.1/4">However, the situation might not be all doom and gloom. There is no automatic link between rapid urban growth and urban problems. In his impressive body of work on the issue, David Satterthwaite of the International Institute for Environment and Development says that cities provide many potential advantages when it comes to tackling the problems that hon. Members have mentioned. The goals of ensuring universal provision of infrastructure and services, keeping down waste levels and de-linking a high quality of life from high levels of resource consumption are all more achievable in an urban setting. Far from being a cause of the current problems, cities can provide part of the long-term solution if they are governed in the right way. It is often easier to provide water supplies, drains, schools and health facilities to a static population of reasonable size in an urban area than to a smaller, mobile, rural population.</p>
	<p pid="a.116.1/5">There are many examples of expanding cities in low-income countries that have managed to avoid many of the problems about which we have heard. Curbita and Porto Allegre in Brazil, for example, have grown rapidly in recent years, but they have a high quality of living and innovative environmental policies. One reason for that is the improvement in local government planning, which involves all groups in the city. Many cities in poorer countries have created local Agenda 21s in response to the guidelines in Agenda 21&mdash;the action plan on sustainable development that most world Governments endorsed at the UN Earth summit in 1992. Unlike conventional city plans developed by consultants or town planning officers, these local plans involve all groups in the city in an attempt to gain a consensus on the priorities that need to be addressed. They have helped many cities to develop viable long-term planning that involves all key stakeholders and responds better to local needs and problems. That is community politics at its best.</p>
	<p pid="a.116.1/6">The other most obvious development that is needed to address the problems facing many urban centres is sustained investment in infrastructure and services in the poorest areas. Poverty, corruption and other social problems often mean that a major backlog of investment must be met before any real improvements can be seen. That is already happening in many cities, where major upgrading programmes have been set up.</p>
	<p pid="a.116.1/7">Obviously, it is impossible to generalise about what is needed in different cities in different countries, but the importance of good governance is a constant thread running through these issues. Investment and the adoption of local agendas have often been effectively supported via stronger and more accountable local democracy. For example, the introduction of city mayors and councillors has helped many city governments to be more accountable and more responsible to their citizens. When cities and smaller local authorities have power devolved to them and are empowered with sufficient resources and autonomy, they are more likely to meet their responsibilities.</p>
	<p pid="a.116.1/8">I want to give the Secretary of State ample time to comment, so I shall keep my concluding remarks brief. Obviously, the spectre of global poverty will hang heavy over any such discussion; indeed, the sheer scale of the problem makes it hard to see a solution. However, far from being a cause of poverty, urbanisation is one potential vehicle out of it. Rather than fretting about the pace of urbanisation, it is far better that we try to ensure that cities have effective, democratic local governments to allow them to meet the challenges that urbanisation poses. The problem is not the reality of urbanisation, but the lack of many basics of life, including infrastructure. As has been mentioned, to deal with the ill effects there must be sustained investment in water supplies, sewerage services, hospitals and schools. That will require a vast increase in investment, better planning controls, more decentralisation of power and responsibility, and increased efforts to tackle corruption.</p>
	<p pid="a.116.1/9">The problem of poverty in developing countries will not be solved overnight. However, urbanisation, if properly managed, may give us one tool to provide real improvements in the medium and long term. I look forward to hearing the views of the Secretary of State and his Department on this issue.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.118.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1862" speakername="Andrew Mitchell" colnum="118"  time="015:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew13">
	<p pid="a.118.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1741" name="Sally Keeble">the hon. Member for Northampton, North (Ms Keeble)</phrase> on securing a debate that she described as historic; it has been enormously interesting and at times illuminating. At the beginning of her speech, she set out the issues that she wanted to cover today, and she has set the scene extremely well.</p>
	<p pid="a.118.0/2">In a speech that showed great expertise on this issue and a profound understanding of <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1953" name="Hugh Bayley">the history of his city, the hon. Member for City of York (Hugh Bayley)</phrase> made many interesting points to which the Secretary of State will no doubt want to respond. I want to echo three of the hon. Gentleman's points. First, we should never underestimate the effect of conflict in enshrining poverty in the areas affected by this issue. It goes without saying that if people are being forcibly dispossessed or shot at, no amount of aid or trade will lift them out of poverty. Last week I returned from a visit to Rwanda, and I am particularly conscious that in the past neither international institutions nor Governments recognised adequately the importance of conflict prevention, which must be at the centre of the work of DFID, as I know it is under this Secretary of State.</p>
	<p pid="a.118.0/3">The second point made by the hon. Member for City of York was about the consultation process on the White Paper published last week. I want to echo his comments on the importance of that process, which ranges widely across the many interesting aspects of this subject. I strongly agree with his third point, which was about good governance in areas of the world where Britain is focusing its aid efforts. He will acknowledge that many of the foundations of the Government's current policies on good governance were laid by Chris Patten when he occupied a ministerial position, and indeed by Lynda Chalker. The good governance provisions that inform our policies in this area are immensely important for achieving the outcomes that we so fervently desire.</p>
	<p pid="a.118.0/4">One thing that strikes me about this debate and indeed the whole subject&mdash;t<phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1982" name="John Barrett">his follows on from what the hon. Member for Edinburgh, West (John Barrett)</phrase> said&mdash;is the extent to which all the political parties have pretty much converged on the same territory. We all agree on the importance of different policy aspects. There is very little between the aspirations of the two major political parties of this country. There are certainly issues on which the Opposition think that the Government can do more and issues on the international agenda on which we are as restless as the Government about the speed of progress. However, on many international development issues, there is no longer a Labour, Conservative or Liberal Democrat agenda&mdash;there is a British one. The Government derive great strength from that in pursuing important tasks in international forums as well as in their bilateral involvement in poor countries around the world.</p>
	<p pid="a.118.0/5">The secret minutes of an internal Labour party meeting happened to land on my desk, and they say that the Secretary of State suggested that the Conservatives were hanging on the coat-tails of the Labour Government on some of these issues, although I am sure that the comment was not delivered in quite as churlish a way as I represent it. In a number of important international development areas, the unity between Front Benchers and unity of purpose across the House of Commons are a great strength.</p>
	<p pid="a.118.0/6">On the interesting comments made by the hon. Member for Northampton, North, the developing world is an increasingly urban world, as she said. In coming years, the rural population of developing countries is projected to remain stable at about 3 billion, but the urban populations are expected to expand from some 2 billion today to about 4 billion by 2025. How does that affect development? Urbanisation in itself is no bad thing. Indeed, it offers a number of advantages, as higher population densities make it possible to provide a range of services such as education, infrastructure and health services in an efficient and cost-effective manner.</p>
	<p pid="a.118.0/7">Cities are often vibrant centres of innovation, culture and politics, but in too many places across the developing world the opportunities afforded by urbanisation are not being realised. Many national and local governments fail to provide the essential services that poor people need, leading to urban squalor and decay, weak economic growth and high unemployment. That foments discontent and radicalism, particularly among urban youth. As the hon. Member for City of York set out, the most vivid manifestation of the downside of urbanisation is the massive slums in many cities in the developing world. Anyone who has travelled in a major city in the developing world will be familiar with the crowded and unsanitary conditions in which millions of people are forced to live. The worst thing about those slums is often the dramatic lack of basic services, such as in health and education. For me, the journey from the airport in Mumbai to the centre of that great city is a strong example.</p>
	<p pid="a.118.0/8">Any response to the challenge of urbanisation must have at its heart measures to tackle infectious diseases, particularly HIV/AIDS; in general, infectious diseases spread more rapidly in urban areas. Providing clean water and sanitation is one of the most efficient and cost-effective ways of saving lives and reducing mortality, particularly infant mortality.</p>
	<p pid="a.118.0/9">Around the world, 1.1 billion people lack access to clean water. Many of them live in towns and cities, and in many cases, the urban poor actually pay more per unit for water than the urban rich. What is to be done? The primary responsibility, as ever, lies with Governments in developing countries, but there are things that Britain can do: we can use our money and influence to support the extension of access to Government water services, and we can champion innovative approaches that harness the dynamism and capital of the private sector to expand access to water in urban areas.</p>
	<p pid="a.118.0/10">DFID has sometimes been criticised for failing to reflect the importance of clean water and sanitation in its spending priorities. Will the Secretary of State explain what plans he has to increase the proportion of aid that DFID spends on this vital sector? In an interesting speech in February 2004, he posed an important question:</p>
	<p pid="a.118.0/11" class="indent">&quot;If relatively few developing countries see water and sanitation as a priority for inclusion in their Poverty Reduction Strategy Papers, what then? Our commitment to the MDGs&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.118.0/12">the millennium development goals&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.118.0/13" class="indent">&quot;and to country ownership point in two different directions.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.118.0/14">It would be interesting to hear how he plans to handle that tension in future.</p>
	<p pid="a.118.0/15">We should consider carefully how the private sector can help in delivering essential services such as water. It may well be damaging to keep water supply as a monopoly of the state in countries where the state is manifestly failing to deliver adequate services to its citizens. If there is proper supervision, regulatory bodies and contract enforcement, well-managed privatisation has the potential to help expand access to clean water and to save lives. I should be grateful to hear the Secretary of State's assessment of the merits of greater private sector participation in service delivery in developing countries.</p>
	<p pid="a.118.0/16">An important way to empower the urban poor is to strengthen and formalise property rights. The poorest suffer most when property rights are weak. Weak legal systems combined with dysfunctional political arrangements offer the urban poor no protection from arbitrary state force.</p>
	<p pid="a.118.0/17">The worst example, to which the hon. Member for City of York alluded, comes from Zimbabwe, where Robert Mugabe's latest repression has destroyed the homes of between 200,000 and 1 million people under the pretext of slum clearance. The campaign is called &quot;Operation Clean Up Filth&quot; or &quot;Operation Drive Out Rubbish&quot;. Children have been killed as houses were demolished around them. Some people have been forced to burn down their own homes. Weak property rights are also damaging in less dramatic ways.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.121.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1953" speakername="Hugh Bayley" colnum="121"  time="015:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew14">
	<p pid="a.121.0/1">What the hon. Gentleman says about Zimbabwe is right, and he is right to speak out against it. May I invite him to speak out as loudly and passionately about the very similar slum clearances in Lagos, Nairobi and Khartoum? The danger of always focusing only on Zimbabwe is that we allow Mugabe the excuse that we speak out on Zimbabwe because we are angry about white property rights being taken away and that we do not speak out with the same passion when the Government of the Sudan, for instance, bulldozes camps around Khartoum.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.121.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1862" speakername="Andrew Mitchell" colnum="121"  time="015:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew15">
	<p pid="a.121.1/1">The hon. Gentleman is right that we must condemn the slum clearance schemes in other countries&mdash;I entirely endorse what he said. The reason why I have not done so is partly the time left for debate and partly that he did so very effectively in his speech. When I talk of Zimbabwe, I am talking not about the dispossessing of white farmers and about their property rights, but about the 200,000 to 1 million Zimbabweans who have been treated in this way.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.1/2">Weak property rights are also damaging in less dramatic ways. A lack of formal property rights means that poor people cannot use their assets to create wealth, to trade assets outside local circles where people know and trust one another, or to use their assets as collateral for a loan to start a new business and to invest for their future. Without formal property rights, the basic machinery of wealth creation comes grinding to a halt, and people stay trapped in poverty.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.1/3">I was interested that the Secretary of State recognised in his speech to launch the White Paper consultation the importance of property rights in generating a climate in which capitalism can flourish, foreign investors can have confidence and economic growth can take hold. I would be most grateful to hear what plans he has to strengthen the Department's work in this vital area and his thoughts on the specific role that property rights can play in improving the lives of poor people in urban areas.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.1/4">In conclusion, urbanisation in the developing world is a source of both opportunity and new challenges. It impacts on a wide and divergent range of policy areas and issues: provision of basic health and education services; water and sanitation; property rights; the response to infectious diseases, in particular HIV/AIDS; and migration policy, and how to deal with refugees in emergency situations.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.1/5">The Department for International Development is doing good work in addressing those challenges, but its efforts can be enhanced. I look forward to hearing how the Secretary of State plans to improve our response to these important issues.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.121.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1669" speakername="Hilary Benn" speakeroffice="The Secretary of State for International Development"  colnum="121"  time="015:43:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.121.2/1">I join hon. Members in congratulating <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1741" name="Sally Keeble">my hon. Friend the Member for Northampton, North (Ms Keeble)</phrase> on having done us all a great service by securing this debate. She has a keen interest in urban matters, which dates back many years. It was evident during her time as a Minister in DFID and I am glad that it continues today. Her interest is shown not least in her having secured what we now learn, having come through those doors, is an historic debate on poverty and urban development.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/2">May I say to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1862" name="Andrew Mitchell">the hon. Member for Sutton Coldfield (Mr. Mitchell)</phrase> that I welcome the fact that there is apparently now quite a large degree of consensus? Had the Conservative party any coat-tails that the rest of us could have hung on to as far as development policy was concerned, we would perhaps have been pleased to do so. Since he provokes me just mildly, I must say that I enormously welcome the fact that the party that managed to cut our development spending as a percentage of our national wealth in half in 18 years has come to recognise that that was a fundamental mistake.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/3">I unreservedly welcome the fact that we are now able to debate the challenge of development in the spirit that we do. It demonstrates how development politics has moved from the margins, where it was in some people's minds, to bang in the centre of the big political questions of our age, because it is about the future of our planet. If we do not sort these problems out, we are all in big trouble, as the hon. Gentleman said.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/4">The movement of people to cities is as old as humankind. We have all agreed, during the debate, that that is an irreversible process and it is no good wishing that it could be different, because human beings will do as they will. The debate has brought out clearly the variety of reasons that lead people to move, including to find employment and flee conflict, as the hon. Gentleman said.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/5">Cities such as Kathmandu, Addis Ababa and Luanda have grown for many reasons. People have moved there because they might be marginally safer when the countries were going through conflict. Women have fled domestic violence. People have tried to escape the stigma and poverty of their caste. People have always come to cities to acquire a new identity. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1953" name="Hugh Bayley">My hon. Friend the Member for City of York (Hugh Bayley)</phrase> talked about people not having enough food to eat.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/6">In the past 20 years, the number of people living in Mumbai has grown by 100 per cent., but the number of squatters has increased by more than 1,000 per cent. That illustrates the scale of the problem.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/7">In our country during the 1970s, we thought that there was a bias towards urban areas and that we needed to concentrate on reducing poverty in rural areas, but we now recognise that we need to consider the problem in a much more rounded way. Indeed, there is a lively debate to be had about where urban areas stop and rural areas begin, particularly as technology makes it possible, in some countries, for people to live and work in ways that were not possible in the past.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/8">I want briefly to deal with four issues: how to understand better what is happening and what we are grappling with, economic growth, governance, especially local government, and finance. We have heard some of the statistics mentioned forcefully. The truth is that most&mdash;almost all&mdash;of the population growth in developing countries in the next generation will be in towns and cities. The total urban population in Africa, Asia and Latin America will double to 4 billion by 2035. Africa is the fastest-urbanising continent in the world. Nearly 40 per cent. of Africans currently live in cities.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/9">It is particularly striking that in 1960 Johannesburg was the only city in sub-Saharan Africa with a population of more than 1 million, but by 2010 there will be 33 cities in Africa with populations of over 1 million. That tells us all we need to know about the pace of change. One of our tasks is to understand better what is happening and to monitor the trends, because good information is vital if the Governments of developing countries are to make decent decisions about that fundamental change.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/10">Target 11 of the MDGs requires us to make a significant improvement in the lives of at least 100 million slum dwellers by 2020. Some countries are making progress and others are off-track and we need to understand why. Having reliable data on slums&mdash;the face of urban poverty&mdash;is vital. That is why we are working in partnership with UN-Habitat. I take this opportunity to pay tribute to Anna Tibaijuka and UN-Habitat for the work that they are doing and for flying the flag of this debate. UN-Habitat is responsible, as well as the World Bank, for global monitoring to ensure that we get decent data that will assist us.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/11">A number of hon. Members have said that cities are the powerhouses of economies. Urbanisation has been central to the sustained economic growth in Asia that has enabled a number of countries in that part of the world to lift many of their citizens out of poverty.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/12">Shanghai has just over 1 per cent. of China's population and contributes 12.5 per cent. of its GDP. I went for the first time last year and spent most of the time with my jaw on the floor. It is an astonishing place. To see the pace of change that is occurring there tells us just how important that city's contribution is to China's economy.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/13">That is happening not only in Asia. Nairobi comprises 12 per cent. of the population of Kenya. It contributes 30 per cent. of the GDP. That tells us in part about the great wave of migration within countries. We talk much about migration between countries, but that is dwarfed by the movement within countries as people leave the places where they have lived for towns to seek work and a better life. As the debate has demonstrated clearly, such growth comes at a price. Very poor people crowd into spaces that no one else will take. They are around open sewers, perched on the side of embankments along railway lines and live in the intense squalor to which my hon. Friend the Member for City of York referred.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/14">Land is the central issue. The poor rarely have tenure on the land that they occupy. It is not always clear who owns the land. We have heard about landlords who make a healthy return on renting their land, but what if there is no clarity about who holds the land? If people are unsure about their future on the land, there is less incentive to invest in improvements. Slum dwellers often have no right to services. In Dhaka in Bangladesh, it is formal policy not to provide them with services. Slum dwelling brings stresses and strains. Mental ill health is a problem. Crime is another problem. Sub-Saharan Africa has the highest proportion of urban population living in slums.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/15">There is spectacular wealth living alongside intense poverty, and that can bring violence. Indeed, the Commission for Africa said:</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/16" class="indent">&quot;Africa's cities are becoming the powder-keg of political instability and discontent&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/17">We ignore that at our peril. I could not agree more with my hon. Friend the Member for City of York when he talked about crime and ensuring that people are not abandoned because they are poor. Security is indeed the precondition for progress while communities try to deal with the enormous problems that such areas face.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/18">As <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1982" name="John Barrett">my hon. Friend the Member for Northampton, North and the hon. Member for Edinburgh, West (John Barrett)</phrase> said, slum dwellings are also places of inspiring resourcefulness. People make a living. They manage to turn their children out in the way that has been described, despite the shacks in which they live. It is possible to make changes. On my recent visit to Bangladesh, I saw a project that we had helped to fund. For about 25 years, a group of people had been living on the embankment going down to the river and by which the sewage was flowing not very fast. That project has provided clean water and sanitation facilities for members of the community, which played an important part in making that happen. According to their ability to pay, people contribute towards the cost. They keep a list and the community decides who can afford to pay what. The project was a striking example of what can be done. I asked the women, because it was they who led the work, about the impact on diarrhoeal diseases. Drinking dirty water gives children diarrhoeal diseases, which is why 6,000 children die in the developing world each day. They do not have clean water to drink. The women said that they had noticed a reduction.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/19">That is an illustration of what can be done to change people's lives for the better. However, above all, jobs are needed. Barriers that prevent people from migrating to towns to work must be removed. People must have the opportunity to set up their own businesses, which goes back to the title to land and property rights, a topic to which I shall return. It is necessary for people to be able to move around the town. Much of the economic life of cities depends on the contribution that is made by the people who live in the slums. They might be working in domestic service or contributing to the manufacture of goods that are exported.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/20">As several hon. Members have said, the process reminds us of what we have been through. It is exactly what happened to us at the start of the 19th century. The conditions were just as appalling. Let us draw on some of those lessons and the social reformers who reported on the condition of human kind, and motivated change through the political process in the 19th century, such as the great pioneer of health, John Snow, who finally proved that cholera was associated with dirty water by taking off the handle from the famous pump in Broad street. There were pioneers in local government who got together to decide what to do about the conditions&mdash;the problem included, of course, the great stink outside, which encouraged Parliament to take a greater interest. Joseph Bazalgette was responsible for building the sewers and the water supply system that probably did more than anything else in this country to increase life expectancy.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/21">That brings me to my next point, which is about Governments. Many countries are thinking more about how to devolve power to local level. We should welcome that unreservedly. The truth is that people know best what they need locally. What is striking about the issue of water&mdash;and I want directly to deal with the point that the hon. Member for Sutton Coldfield made&mdash;is how often, in many conversations that I have had in towns, villages and urban areas in developing countries, clean water has emerged as people's priority for improving their lives. Yet that priority does not seem, in many developing countries, to be reflected when national priorities are set.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/22">That is why, in my speech on world water day, to which the hon. Gentleman referred, I committed us to double our spending on water in Africa. I shall be reflecting on how things have gone&mdash;we have been working in slightly different ways in the past year in implementing that commitment&mdash;in a speech that I shall give later this month.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/23">The private sector has a contribution to make. My view on that score is fairly simple. I am profoundly uninterested in an ideological debate about whether the approach should be this or that. I am interested&mdash;and so I think are all hon. Members&mdash;in what will work to bring more clean water to the largest number of people. When developing countries and their communities have worked out how to do that, let us have more of it, and faster. That is the task that we face.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/24">Property rights are extremely important, but acquiring rights is the first stage. People have to be able to exercise them. I recollect from my first visit to Bangladesh that the landless poor there had rights&mdash;but when they tried to exercise them, the police used to come and beat them over the head. It was only through wonderful civil society organisations and their work to help them, which we funded, that those poor people were able to exercise the rights that the law accorded to them. However, the hon. Gentleman makes an important point.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/25">Power without money at local level will not do any good. There is a lack of capacity, and building capacity is fundamental to progress. I pay tribute to all the people in local government in the United Kingdom, and in particular the UK Local Government Alliance for International Development, who are working to build links. My hon. Friend the Member for Northampton, North referred to some of those. I recollect that in one case&mdash;that of Daventry and Iganga town&mdash;the link came about through environmental health officers. There was a rubbish problem, and progress was made in dealing with that.</p>
	<p pid="a.121.2/26">Those two towns learned from each other. We make a big mistake if we think that we have all the answers. We do not. In Dhaka in Bangladesh plastic bags have been banned, and the cacophony of two-stroke noise that assaulted me the first time I went was missing on my return in November because all the three-wheelers have been converted to using liquefied natural gas.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.126.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1741" speakername="Sally Keeble" colnum="126"  time="015:43:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew16">
	<p pid="a.126.0/1">Clearly the debate must continue. I wonder whether my right hon. Friend will take the matter up in the White Paper. Will he ensure that the urbanisation agenda is given a higher priority?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.126.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1669" speakername="Hilary Benn" colnum="126"  time="015:43:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h03.htm#60201h03_spnew17">
	<p pid="a.126.1/1">I certainly will, because that is one of the issues that we must deal with. I want to come directly to my hon. Friend's question about slum upgrading. We are funding work on that, and I saw an example&mdash;the concreting of alleyways&mdash;on my visit to India last year. We are supporting the slum upgrading facility to which she referred. We currently give it just under $11 million. It is a pilot run by UN-Habitat. There are pilot projects in Ghana, Tanzania and Sri Lanka. We need to see how that goes to support others.</p>
	<p pid="a.126.1/2">It is possible to make progress. Thailand, Mongolia and Uruguay have taken real steps in reducing the number of people living in slums. The biggest challenge, if good governance and local government are secured, is the cash to make things happen. The way in which we finance the work, and developing countries raise the necessary resources to finance the improvements in their towns and cities that the people who live in them, above all, want, is our big challenge for the coming months and years.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.127.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="127"  time="015:43:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h04.htm#60201h04_head0">
	RAF Stafford
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.127.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1833" speakername="David Kidney" colnum="127"  time="016:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h04.htm#60201h04_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.127.1/1">It is a pleasure to start this debate and to see my right hon. Friend the Minister of State, Ministry of Defence in his place to answer it. He and I have discussed RAF Stafford quite a lot in recent years, so I doubt whether anything that I say today will come as a surprise to him.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.1/2">Let me start with the background. At RAF Stafford, uniformed personnel and civilians provide&mdash;very effectively&mdash;a range of support services, all of which are time critical and some of which are dangerous. I am thinking of the tactical supply wing, which supplies fuel to front-line helicopters in times of conflict.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.127.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="127"  time="016:01:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h04.htm#60201h04_head1">
	Sitting suspended for a Division in the House.
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.127.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="127"  time="016:01:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h04.htm#60201h04_head1">
	<p pid="a.127.3/1">On resuming&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.127.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1833" speakername="David Kidney" colnum="127"  time="016:15:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h04.htm#60201h04_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.127.4/1">Uses of RAF Stafford have until now included a number of the air combat service support units&mdash;everything from motorised transport to catering&mdash;defence storage and distribution, tactical supply wing, engineering wing, mountain rescue, Ministry of Defence police and fire contingents, and cadet training, including Army cadet training since the Territorial Army centre in Stafford was sold under the strategic defence review. Recently, another Government Department, the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs, has announced that it will locate a new decontamination service serving the whole of the UK at RAF Stafford.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/2">RAF Stafford enjoys the full support of its local community. The base has existed for 60 years. In 2004, the community celebrated the 50th anniversary of having granted RAF Stafford the freedom of the borough. If RAF Stafford was unpopular locally, my constituents would not be so worried about losing some or all of the base's activities. In fact, it is very popular. In 2004, I started a petition to allow residents to express their support for RAF Stafford, and 5,000 people signed in three weeks. I presented that petition to Parliament. In time for this debate, I have another petition that I hope to give to the Minister. It was collected by local trade unionists. They simply stood in the market square in Stafford on three Saturdays in January, and they tell me that more than 2,000 local residents signed their petition in support of keeping the storage and distribution centre at RAF Stafford open.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/3">RAF Stafford also takes a full part in civic occasions. That includes Remembrance day parades and battle of Britain civic services, which are always well supported by civil society as well as the military community. As many of the jobs at RAF Stafford are civilian, many local people work there. Many of the uniformed personnel also own houses locally, and when they retire from RAF Stafford, many of them settle locally.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/4">The MOD continually reviews the way that services are configured, rightly seeking to ensure that we retain the best operational capability and value for money. However, I say to my right hon. Friend the Minister that the complete closure of the Stafford base would cause disastrous damage to our local economy. In round figures, about 900 civil servants work at RAF Stafford, along with 500 uniformed personnel engaged in logistic support&mdash;although they soon leave us&mdash;and 250 more uniformed personnel in tactical supply wing. It is not, of course, a main operating base; it does not have a runway.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/5">I do not want to dwell for long on the decision to move the air combat service support unit's logistics military personnel&mdash;there are about 450 of them&mdash;from Stafford to Wittering. That decision will be put into effect in March. As the Minister knows, he took that decision against my wishes, but I can at least say that there is a strategic rationale for moving the support units closer to the front-line forces that they would be expected to deploy with in the event of future rapid deployments. It also assists in training for operations between deployments if they are located near to each other. However, when the decision to move them was taken, there were forecasts of large financial savings, but I think that he could now confirm that those savings have not materialised. Perhaps that provides a salutary lesson for the Minister, as he has similarly been told that the Army's plans now for the Defence Storage and Distribution Agency will save money.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/6">The tri-service working is now very apparent at RAF Stafford in respect of storage and distribution. Whenever I visit, I see air, Army and naval stores and equipment there. It was very different before 1997, when there were separate stores and distribution arrangements for each service. As the RAF rationalised its storage and distribution arrangements, RAF Stafford eventually became the only remaining RAF base for those activities. You know very well about that, Mr. Martlew, because when the RAF had got down to the last two possible bases, one was Stafford and one was in your constituency at Carlisle. Stafford became the last one. Then along came tri-service working, and rationalisation has now started again. Today, the storage and distribution services at RAF Stafford form part of the Defence Storage and Distribution Agency, which in turn is part of the Defence Logistics Organisation. Stafford is run jointly with similar activities at the Army base MOD Donnington. All the storage and distribution workers at Stafford are civil servants.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/7">On <phrase class="date" code="2005-07-21">21 July 2005</phrase>, the Ministry of Defence announced its decision to close the operations at Stafford by December 2007, so ending the last RAF-specific contribution to the agency. The centre for such operations in future will be the Army base at Bicester. My local churches forum described this as an unfortunate decision. I found it curious, given that Stafford carries out 80 per cent. of the current operations of the agency, has achieved the best efficiency performance in the agency and has the only high-activity storage and distribution centre in the whole of the agency. Indeed, the business plan for taking most of the work to Bicester involves building a brand-new high-activity centre to replace the existing efficient one at Stafford, which presumably will stand empty after the transfer has taken place. There are echoes of the duff advice that the Minister was given over the savings to be had by a move of the air combat services support units to Wittering.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/8">I am pleased that the review of DSDA as a whole resulted in a decision to keep the storage and distribution operations in-house and to grant enhanced agency status. However, as a consequence of the decision on job losses at Stafford and, in reality, because of several other decisions involving civilian MOD job losses around the country in recent months, the trade unions are campaigning for a change of direction. In the case of RAF Stafford specifically, they are asking for a review of the decision to end storage and distribution operations at Stafford, and are presenting a case for continuing to make productive use of the high-activity storage and distribution centre, which is supported by an engineering enclave.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/9">On the proposal to retain the high-activity centre, I simply point out that the midlands is an acknowledged leader in logistics in the United Kingdom&mdash;understandably, given its location in the centre of the country. As the Minister saw when he visited RAF Stafford&mdash;it really was as long ago as September 2004, although it seems like yesterday&mdash;equipment comes into Stafford from all over the country all the time, and goes out to other MOD locations all over the UK on a daily basis. When I visit the Argos and Exel logistics operation at Acton Gate in my constituency, which is a comparable operation in the private sector, I am reassured that the midlands offers the same high standards in logistics in both the public and the private sectors.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/10">On the future for some 300 engineering workers at RAF Stafford, the Minister may know that twice in two years announcements have been made that have left them completely in the dark about their future. It would be a positive end to a worrying roller-coaster ride if they could be reassured about their future and, more generally, about the situation at RAF Stafford. One employee asked me to remind the powers that be, as he calls them, how loyal and supportive employees at Stafford have been to their colleagues in the MOD and Her Majesty's Government. He stated:</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/11" class="indent">&quot;Operation TELIC saw us not only meet all our operational requirements but also take on board several efficiency initiatives which were undertaken willingly and with great success&mdash;we proved ourselves to be the best and still are and we are very proud to be so.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/12">That reminder about Operation Telic caused me to review the National Audit Office report for Operation Telic. I am sure that the Minister will confirm the finding that the well-publicised supplies shortages that arose at that time related only to in-theatre operations. In fact, the NAO report on page 17 states:</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/13" class="indent">&quot;Operation TELIC required a massive logistic effort to be made by personnel and organisations from across the Department and the three Services.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/14">On page 3 it states:</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/15" class="indent">&quot;The logistic effort for the Operation was huge and key to success.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/16">The result was that twice the material was delivered to the theatre of operations in half the time, as compared with the previous 1990&ndash;91 Gulf war. When I visited during the period of maximum effort, I met workers who were turning in to work seven days a week to make the operation a success.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/17">Local people have responded as constructively as they can to the announcements by the Ministry of Defence, especially the one about ending storage and distribution operations at Stafford. I recently joined other concerned interests in Stafford such as the local councils and the regional development agency, Advantage West Midlands, to form a taskforce to co-ordinate the local response. It is not a matter of my asking the Minister what he can do to help us. We are doing what we can to help ourselves locally.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/18">The Minister knows about that because he kindly met a delegation from the taskforce that I brought to see him on <phrase class="date" code="2005-09-08">8 September 2005</phrase> and I was grateful for his co-operative responses. One of his decisions as a result of that meeting was to allow access to the civilian work force of Stafford by Jobcentre Plus and that has been helpful. It is proving extremely useful in building up support for those who will lose their jobs by way of training, advice and help with searching for jobs. The Minister also agreed that a representative of Defence Estates could support the taskforce and we have since met representatives of the Ministry of Defence as a result of that decision.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/19">The Minister knows that we have a loyal and long-serving work force at RAF Stafford. Many of those who will lose their jobs have worked there for a long time and are over 50. They are learning that they will be disadvantaged in the redundancy package allowed to them because they are over 50.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/20">I note from my correspondence with the Minister that the rules of the scheme are clear, but is there no help that could be given to workers aged over 50 who are facing sizeable financial losses? There is also a rule that help with retraining is not available more than three months ahead of redundancy. It would be helpful if the Minister could override that rule and say that workers at RAF Stafford who are threatened with the loss of their jobs next year could have help with retraining this year.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/21">The other uniformed personnel remaining at RAF Stafford are the tactical supply wing, which is a vital part of every dangerous mission, as I have explained. They are virtually first to the front line and supply the fuel that keeps helicopters flying. They have had a base in Northern Ireland for more than 30 years. The head of that service is Joint Helicopter Command. They will stay at RAF Stafford for the foreseeable future, but it would be helpful if the Minister could tell me something about their presence in the longer term.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/22">The question obviously arises as to whether there is a future for a military base at Stafford after these announcements. To be clear, Stafford people support our armed forces and want a presence in the county town. They support me strongly in seeking to persuade the Minister to agree to build up RAF Stafford with alternative military uses if current uses have to change. They also want continued opportunities for civilian jobs at the base.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/23">Opportunities are coming up to enable Stafford to be used for alternative military purposes. The Defence Medical Education and Training Service has been successfully built up again after the terrible hollowing out that occurred before 1997. There is a new hospital development at Birmingham, Selly Oak. I know that the service has been looking outside Birmingham but within its proximity for less costly accommodation for its headquarters and non-hospital activities. Stafford has been considered as one of a number of locations that might be suitable and I have been told that as many as 1,000 jobs are involved. I have provided the Ministry of Defence and the Defence Medical Education and Training Agency with a portfolio of evidence of the excellent clinical networks that are available at Stafford. There is a university on the doorstep with a school of health providing nursing training. There is an acute hospital trust that is willing to share training and laboratory work with the agency's headquarters. There is a mental hospital trust that is willing to form joint protocols on post-traumatic stress disorder investigations. There is a technology park next door to RAF Stafford with medical technology businesses that are at the forefront of development of medical technologies such as Sterilox Technologies International Ltd. Our ambulance service trust in Staffordshire is willing to do joint training with military personnel to assist them when they become civilians and need civilian qualifications later. Truthfully, I believe that the Defence Medical Education and Training Agency would benefit enormously from being plugged into those networks in Stafford.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/24">A new 22 Signal Regiment is being formed and the Army would be very welcome at Stafford. I understand that around 700 military personnel will be involved in that regiment. Given the highly technological nature of today's communications systems, there is, again, a glorious fit at Stafford with the neighbouring technology park, where several graduate IT and communications businesses were started. The university has an international reputation for computing sciences and a growing department for media technology studies. In the longer term beyond those opportunities, there is talk of the Army developing garrison town settlements and Stafford might fit well with that development. Its edge-of-town location, good communications with the rest of the country and supportive civilian population make it a good choice, in my book. Local media reported positively on the Gurkhas visit to Stafford. I do not know if the Minister knows anything about that.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/25">Such emphatically military uses will not provide anywhere near the number of civilian jobs that RAF Stafford supports in its defence, storage and distribution operations. That is why I ask the Minister to look at the trade unions' case for saving some of the storage and distribution, and engineering jobs at Stafford.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/26">The taskforce that I helped to set up makes a great case for buying from the Ministry of Defence a portion of the camp's land that immediately adjoins the successful technology park. We believe that we can quickly raise the money to pay the full asking price for that land, and we know that businesses are interested in having premises there for light industrial and further technological uses. Can we therefore not go through a tortuous MOD process that leaves off taking a decision about sales until every other decision has been taken? Businesses are taking their business decisions now, and we need to know whether we can offer them land at that valuable location. It even makes sense that the MOD should have the capital receipt from the sale and plough it back into making the remainder of the site more amenable for the other users who are under consideration so that everyone wins.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/27">I do not usually quote my local daily newspaper, the <i>Express and Star</i>, because it is not usually that supportive, but last week in an editorial it said:</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/28" class="indent">&quot;We must hope that the Government will listen and respond positively to the case being put for the threat to Stafford jobs to be lifted. If the Government is not prepared to give a stay of execution to the civilian jobs it is imperative that alternative military use is found for the base.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/29">That is a fair summary of the situation.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/30">The military activities carried out at RAF Stafford are all vital to the efficient and effective operation of the UK's armed forces, and the public of Stafford support the military presence in the county town and want it to continue. The announced losses of military and civilian personnel at RAF Stafford will harm our local economy unless we act decisively in response to the changing situation. We are doing all that we can for ourselves, but we need the MOD's co-operation. Retaining storage distribution and engineering capabilities at Stafford would help Stafford and be in the MOD's best interests. We would welcome the Defence Medical Education and Training Agency to Stafford and the clinical networks there would create two-way benefits for military and NHS clinical staff.</p>
	<p pid="a.127.4/31">We would welcome the establishment of a new 22 Signal Regiment at Stafford, and it would fit with our existing specialism in computing, IT and media technologies. An Army base at Stafford would be well received by local people and existing facilities at RAF Stafford could be adapted to meet the Army's needs. Our enterprising taskforce asks the MOD to allow us to buy a portion of land to enable us to provide alternative civilian jobs for those civilians who are due to lose their jobs at RAF Stafford next year. Clearly there is an agenda that we could all sign up to which would mean some success for everybody, but a lot depends on the response from the MOD. Perhaps that can start with the Minister's response to this debate.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.132.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1976" speakername="Adam Ingram" speakeroffice="The Minister of State, Ministry of Defence"  colnum="132"  time="016:33:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h04.htm#60201h04_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.132.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1833" name="David Kidney">my hon. Friend the Member for Stafford (Mr. Kidney)</phrase> on securing the debate and thank him for providing me with the opportunity to speak on this important issue. I pay tribute to his tireless efforts in support of his constituents' interests at RAF Stafford. Once again, he has set out his case cogently and well.</p>
	<p pid="a.132.0/2">The changes that have taken place at Stafford and in the wider region are part of a much broader process of change in the MOD. We are determined to modernise and improve the delivery of support services and to make the best use of available resources to ensure that every penny counts for the front line. As part of our response to the Gershon review, the MOD is committed to making 2.5 per cent. efficiencies annually between the financial years 2005&ndash;06 and 2007&ndash;08. That equates to &pound;2.83 billion of efficiencies by April 2008. The savings from those efficiencies will all be reinvested in providing better delivery at the front line of defence.</p>
	<p pid="a.132.0/3">As part of the defence change programme, the Department has also committed to reducing the number of civilian posts by more than 11,000 and the number of military posts in administration and support by more than 5,000. Again, the savings will all be reinvested in the front line. If we do not make those savings, the front line will go without.</p>
	<p pid="a.132.0/4">I am aware of the impact on MOD staff employed in the west midlands of the various recent announcements related to the defence change programme, which covered areas such as training, logistics, repair and maintenance and the supply chain. I am also conscious of the continuing uncertainty about the long-term usage not only of the MOD estate at Stafford but of other sites in the region, and I understand the impact of that uncertainty on the local community. I regret that I am not in a position to remove it today.</p>
	<p pid="a.132.0/5">As my hon. Friend is aware, a number of separate strands of work are being undertaken in the Department that bear on future employment opportunities in the region. He alluded to them, and I shall comment on them later. Hon. Members may rest assured that when I am in a position to make announcements to the House, I shall do so at the first possible instance.</p>
	<p pid="a.132.0/6">Today, the Stafford site has two principal defence users, the RAF and the Defence Storage and Distribution Agency, which is part of the Defence Logistics Organisation. RAF functions at Stafford comprise the 85 expeditionary logistics wing, which provides logistics support to deployed operations, and the tactical supply wing, which supports the joint helicopter fleet and is under the command of the Joint Helicopter Command headquarters. Also, an engineering services function recently transferred from the RAF to DSDA, and the RAF museum reserve collection is situated on one of the outlying sites under lease from the MOD.</p>
	<p pid="a.132.0/7">Two current initiatives will affect future employment at Stafford. The first stems from our announcement in July 2004 concerning the creation of the air combat service support unit logistics hub at Wittering. I appreciate my hon. Friend's recognition of the rationale behind that decision, and I recognise his unhappiness that it went against Stafford.</p>
	<p pid="a.132.0/8">The build-up of the logistics hub at RAF Wittering is proceeding as planned, and includes the relocation of the 85 expeditionary logistics wing from Stafford. That move will result in a reduction of 59 civilian posts and the transfer of about 440 RAF posts. With the transfer of the 85 EL wing, direct RAF interest in the Stafford site will cease. The technical supply wing, which employs 210 RAF personnel, will remain, pending a decision on the future basing requirements of the support helicopter force.</p>
	<p pid="a.132.0/9">My hon. Friend referred to another part of the process of change, and spoke about the &quot;duff&quot; information that I was given. What happened was this: we were looking at RAF Scampton as a preferred base for the communications hub. When we revisited Scampton for site analysis, we discovered that such a move would have considerable cost implications. We then looked around the rest of the estate, and considered Stafford while doing so. However, because of insufficient domestic accommodation, that move would have been costly to the MOD. As a result, we have announced that RAF Leeming will become the centre. I do not accept that the information was duff. It was the best information at the time, and it was carefully analysed and revisited. If RAF Stafford had come out favourably, of course we would have made that decision accordingly.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.133.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1833" speakername="David Kidney" colnum="133"  time="016:33:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h04.htm#60201h04_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.133.0/1">I do not want to go over old wounds, but it is important to consider when looking forward that my right hon. Friend was assured that accommodation at Wittering would be fine for the personnel transferring. Once the decision was taken, it was decided that it was not fine. The Ministry of Defence has paid premium prices for the construction of new accommodation for the people moving from Stafford to Wittering, and that was not taken into account in the original calculations. That is the kind of thing that I am asking him to beware of the second time around.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.134.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1976" speakername="Adam Ingram" colnum="134"  time="016:33:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h04.htm#60201h04_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.134.0/1">I am not sure that I agree with that analysis, but I shall write to my hon. Friend on the matter. We are always wary of the analyses, and we always ensure that they are properly scrutinised using a range of methods. That is why some of the things that we do change direction. As we do the site analysis, we discover infrastructure issues. For example, the water and sewerage might be very old. Any old site will have old infrastructure, and as we explore it we discover other elements. If the information is not accurate, it must be revisited and examined and hopefully the correct decision will be taken.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.0/2">The second stream of work that has an impact on employment at the site is the future of the defence supply chain initiative. It was launched in 2002 with the aim of improving the management of the defence supply chain. In July of last year, my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Defence announced to the House the selection of an in-house option known as &quot;Do Different,&quot; on the basis that it would provide the best balance between improved logistic support to operations and better value for money for taxpayers. Under the FDSCI three defence storage and distribution centres are due to close by 2009. The first of those will be at Stafford in 2007.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.0/3">An important aspect is that we are talking about an in-house preferred bid against private-sector competitors. We have been criticised in the past&mdash;wholly wrongly, as far as I am concerned&mdash;for believing that private is good and public bad. The present case is a good example of where the reverse is clearly the case.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.0/4">The closures to which I refer are in no way a reflection of the invaluable contribution that employees at the DSDCs have made&mdash;some over decades of employment at the MOD, as my hon. Friend said. Given the consequences for staff, the decision under the FDSCI was difficult. However, our experience on operations has shown that it is imperative for us to improve support to the front line. That is not a criticism of the work done at the sites, as my hon. Friend pointed out in reference to the National Audit Office report, but we must improve the means by which we deliver, right through from the factory at the beginning of the supply chain to the front line.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.0/5">Such a change will produce a modern and effective defence supply chain, focused on meeting the demands of today's armed forces. Our calculation suggests that full implementation of the change will make savings of more than &pound;50 million a year by 2010, and of more than &pound;400 million over the next 10 years. Those are very sizeable savings.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.0/6">The new supply chain organisation will require some 2,000 fewer posts. Of those reductions, almost all will be civilian jobs and approximately 530 will be at the Stafford DSDC. Natural wastage will account for some of the total reduction and there may be opportunities for some staff to transfer elsewhere within the MOD, but we expect about 280 redundancies. The future of engineering services, which employs slightly more than 230 civilian personnel and 33 servicemen, falls outwith the scope of the FDSCI and is the subject of a separate study.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.0/7">We are committed to providing appropriate support to the staff at RAF Stafford and elsewhere who are affected by these decisions, and we have engaged fully with the trade unions. Arrangements for MOD welfare and outplacement services will be extended to provide staff, their spouses and dependants at all affected sites with access to professional advice and assistance where possible. The service is designed to help with financial advice, preparation for employment in the private sector, and relocation. I have taken note of my hon. Friend's points about pensions and possible training in advance of some of the dates in question. Again, I will write to him on that point. If we can help, we will do so, but clearly we are sometimes inhibited by existing regulations.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.0/8">There may be some opportunity for staff working at Stafford to transfer to Donnington, or to other Government Departments, and so a staff preference exercise will be undertaken. As my hon. Friend knows, my officials are already working closely with Jobcentre Plus to manage the draw-down of numbers and, where possible, to identify alternative employment opportunities for staff affected.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.0/9">I commend my hon. Friend's positive engagement with Stafford borough council in establishing the taskforce that aims to secure the Stafford site as a long-term future source of local employment. I emphasise, however, that there are no plans to dispose of the Stafford estate. Defence Estates remains engaged with the taskforce and continues to explore possible alternative uses for the site. I know that the process seems long and drawn-out, but if we have valuable estate, we would be wrong to dispose of such assets until we know precisely what the future requirements of the site will be. Although it looks as if a planning blight is being put on the site, we are trying to do what is right for defence.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.0/10">The total number of staff who will remain on the Stafford site post-2007, not including those at the RAF museum facility or contractors, will be approximately 210 service personnel and two civil servants, all of whom are part of the tactical supply wing. Those figures do not, of course, take into account any number associated with future basing options that are the subject of ongoing studies, such as that considering the future of engineering services&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.135.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1484" speakername="Eric Martlew" colnum="135"  time="016:33:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h04.htm#60201h04_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.135.0/1">Order.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.136.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="136"  time="016:33:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h05.htm#60201h05_head0">
	Public Administration Review (Northern Ireland)
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.136.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1400" speakername="Peter Robinson" colnum="136"  time="016:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h05.htm#60201h05_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.136.1/1">I am delighted to have the opportunity to raise the review of public administration in Northern Ireland. Whatever anybody might think about the proposals brought forward by the Government before Christmas, there can be no denying the impact that the RPA will have on the administration of Northern Ireland, not only over the next few years but in the foreseeable future. It is therefore vital that we get it right, and I hope that this brief debate will be an opportunity to raise a few of the many vital issues presented by the RPA.</p>
	<p pid="a.136.1/2">In the absence of devolution, there are few occasions when we can get time to debate such matters at Westminster. Given the huge impact that the RPA will have on Northern Ireland, it is welcome that some time has been given to debate the matter in advance of the various pieces of legislation that the Government will no doubt bring forward. I have to say, however, that the Government ought to have set time aside, either in the House or in the Grand Committee, rather than an individual having to use this useful yet limited mechanism to have such important matters discussed.</p>
	<p pid="a.136.1/3">The process has seemed at times to be never-ending, and so it may seem a little strange for me to ask the Government to take a little more time over the decision. However, given the long-term impact that the review will have, it is important that the Government get it right. The process was first announced by the Ulster Unionist party Department of the Environment Minister in the Executive and at an Ulster Unionist party conference. It was later adopted by the Assembly Executive. I say that not to associate the UUP with the details of the outcome but simply to record where the process commenced and was shaped. The Government must take ownership of the details of the outcome. In defence of the Ulster Unionist party, because nobody is here to defend it, I will point out that the Government have sometimes employed the argument that because the Assembly began the process it is responsible for the outcome. That, I think, is difficult to reconcile with logic.</p>
	<p pid="a.136.1/4">We all hope, I believe, that devolution can return to Northern Ireland as soon as circumstances allow. It would be a pity if, because the Government did not take time to listen to the views of those who have been democratically elected in Northern Ireland, substantial time and effort were wasted in proposals that might be scrapped by an incoming Assembly. Making plans without any certainty about whether there will be a return to devolution has not been easy. We all recognise that. However, the review will clearly have an impact on the nature of local government in the Province. What is needed in the absence of an Assembly is clearly more extensive and meaningful than what would be required were devolution in place.</p>
	<p pid="a.136.1/5">One has to accept that when proposals are brought forward that are likely to effect a huge section of the public sector in Northern Ireland, vested interests will inevitably be at stake. Difficult decisions have to be taken and the Government undoubtedly have to take them. People understand that such a fundamental exercise cannot take place without an element of pain. Having said that, I believe that the Secretary of State is making some massive mistakes with some of the proposals that he announced before Christmas. In some areas, the Government are moving in the right direction and the proposed measures seem to be sensible. However, the decisions that they have reached in others are mistaken.</p>
	<p pid="a.136.1/6">The number of new local councils has been the most controversial of all the proposals in the RPA. I do not believe that many people would argue that we need 26 councils to perform the functions of local government in Northern Ireland, but the reduction to seven is, for almost all of us, a step too far. For a range of reasons, it does not make sense, the underlying one being that that would lack political support in Northern Ireland. Plans with far-reaching consequences which might take years to implement, and will shape the future of local government for a generation, need to command broad political support in Northern Ireland. It is clear that the proposal for seven councils has limited support from those who sought a mandate from the electorate last May. In fact, four&mdash;perhaps four and a half&mdash;of the five largest political parties in Northern Ireland are opposed to it.</p>
	<p pid="a.136.1/7">If the Government are keen to see devolution return, why do they want to proceed in a manner that they know to be in direct conflict with what the Assembly would do if it were making that decision itself today, and with what it might do in future? That does not make sense.</p>
	<p pid="a.136.1/8">This is not simply a DUP concern, but one that is shared by the Alliance party and the Ulster Unionist party and has been voiced by the Social Democratic and Labour party. Indeed, when a leading member of Sinn Fein takes his life in his hands and speaks out against the official republican line, it is clear just how strong feelings are on the matter. The Government used to welcome political consensus in Northern Ireland; now they seem to want to work against it. One of their rather lame explanations for proceeding in defiance of the political views in Northern Ireland was that they were doing so because of the results of the consultation process. That is a novel approach. The Minister will know what the consultation process said about the Government's post-primary education recommendations that relate to her Department, but I have heard no talk from her about that dictating what her policy should be.</p>
	<p pid="a.136.1/9">More importantly, the consultees who form the majority of those who made submissions represent a small fraction of the community, while those whom the Government regard as forming the lesser part of the consultation have a mandate from the overwhelming majority of the community in Northern Ireland. Moreover, it would be wrong for the Government, as they have done from time to time, to characterise the views of parties in Northern Ireland as being based simply on self-interest.</p>
	<p pid="a.136.1/10">One of the Government's central justifications for reducing the number of councils to seven is that it will create efficiency. How many dire crimes have been committed for that purpose? That was not an aspiration that the Government had when they designed the Belfast agreement, nor is it consistent with other elements of the RPA. When the RPA was being set up during devolution, my colleagues and I argued that its scope was too narrow, and that it needed to encompass the Northern Ireland Government Departments as well as local government and other public bodies.</p>
	<p pid="a.136.1/11">Why is local government being singled out while the Government close their eyes to the huge political bureaucracy that has surrounded the Belfast agreement: 108 Assembly members, 11 Government Departments, a host of north-south bodies and an equality agenda that bleeds millions of pounds out of public and private sector hands every year? Despite what is being suggested now, I doubt that, by the time the whole process is over, any meaningful savings will have been achieved by moving to seven councils rather than 15 or even 11. Indeed, some council chiefs have already been advised to set money aside to pay for the RPA. Why? We were told that it was going to save money, so why do we need to store up funds to pay for it? The reality is that seven councils will lead effectively to the balkanisation of Northern Ireland and to two large blocks. The approach is not sensible and it will lead to impossible decisions having to be taken about how those councils will be governed and how they will function.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.138.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1846" speakername="Iris Robinson" colnum="138"  time="016:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h05.htm#60201h05_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.138.0/1">Is my hon. Friend aware that despite the proposal in the RPA to cluster Ards with North Down, Castlereagh and Down district council, the latter is currently proposing to go ahead with a multi-million pound new civic centre? The unnecessary spending spree will cost all ratepayers money. Will he join me in appealing to Down district council to ditch the proposal, because there is no way, on the periphery of this new envisaged council area, that it would be central to where we should be meeting when the proposal kicks in?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.138.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1400" speakername="Peter Robinson" colnum="138"  time="016:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h05.htm#60201h05_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.138.1/1">I agree with my hon. Friend, and I will discuss that matter separately from that of balkanisation, which is an important issue that she has raised. The Minister and the Government will have to deal with the fallout that will undoubtedly occur because of things being done not only by Down district council but by others.</p>
	<p pid="a.138.1/2">On balkanisation, as a result of the division into seven that has been suggested, we will end up with a situation where Unionists will be dominant in the north and east while republicans will dominate in the south and west. Alternatively, we will have governance arrangements that will make the simplest decisions virtually impossible to take. Having seven mini-assemblies across Northern Ireland is not likely to prove the most sensible way to take decisions.</p>
	<p pid="a.138.1/3">Proposals for seven councils will also destroy any meaningful sense of local identity and will inevitably make local representation more remote from those whom the representatives serve. In effect, we will have not local but sub-regional government. Many of the areas being lumped together to establish the new councils will have virtually nothing in common.</p>
	<p pid="a.138.1/4">There could be no better illustration of that than the head scratching that is currently going on in an attempt to come up with names for the seven super-councils. For instance, what do Lurgan and Portadown have in common with the far side of Newry? I would suggest that the answer is not a lot. The geographical area envisaged for the most westerly new council is huge. Will councillors be expected to travel from the centre of the Province to the furthest tip of Fermanagh on council business or from the outskirts of Belfast to the north coast?</p>
	<p pid="a.138.1/5">A move to 15 or even 11 councils would make it possible to achieve many of the same efficiencies as a move to seven, while retaining a local connection. The Government claim to have reached their position in favour of seven in part, at least, on the basis of independent research and analysis, but I do not believe that these factors, when they are examined closely, outweigh other considerations in making the decision.</p>
	<p pid="a.138.1/6">I will touch on the issue that my hon. Friend raised, which is not about the nature of the proposals themselves but relates to their consequences, no matter whether we are talking about seven, 11 or 15 councils. The Government must step in with firm regulations about capital spending between now and the transfer to the new super-councils. There is already evidence of major spending by a number of councils in an attempt to dictate where future facilities will be placed by committing expenditure now, knowing full well that it will not be them alone who will have to pay for it, but their neighbours who will be clustered along with them.</p>
	<p pid="a.138.1/7">My hon. Friend raises the issue of Down district council. Its offices may well need to be improved, but the multi-million-pound development proposed is clearly the kind of development that one would expect for whichever council was to enjoy hosting the new super-council. Down is on the periphery of the area cluster, but perhaps the councillors of Down know the Government's thinking, and know that they are going to change their mind about the seven councils that they have already proposed. The Minister can be certain that if the Government do not stop that practice it will grow, and significant sums will be spent in the coming years in an attempt to spend now and get someone else to pay for it later.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.139.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1376" speakername="William McCrea" colnum="139"  time="016:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h05.htm#60201h05_spnew3">
	<p pid="a.139.0/1">Does my hon. Friend agree that it is about time that we told the Administration that any decision they make now will not tie any future Assembly that comes into existence? If an Assembly looks into the matter and believes that the decision is undemocratic and not right, that decision should be changed.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.139.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1400" speakername="Peter Robinson" colnum="139"  time="016:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h05.htm#60201h05_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.139.1/1">I hope that my hon. Friend and I have got that message across to the Minister. Given the amount of upset that such a reorganisation causes, it is sufficient if it happens once in a generation; that is better than twice. That is why it is essential that the Government carry the political parties of Northern Ireland along with them, rather than going head-on in defiance of the advice offered.</p>
	<p pid="a.139.1/2">In the context of overall public finance, local government spends a very small percentage of public money in Northern Ireland, yet it has come in for particular attention. So far, the Government have had very little to say about quangos. It will be interesting to hear whether the Government's proposals on them are as radical as their proposals on local government. Over the past 30 years, the lack of democratic accountability of those bodies has been disgraceful. It is absurd that those hand-picked by the Government to sit on one of those bodies should have more power than democratically elected politicians.</p>
	<p pid="a.139.1/3">In Northern Ireland, over the past three or four decades the route to power and to effecting change has not been to get involved in democratic politics and to run for office; it has been to join a paramilitary organisation or sign up for a quango. One need only look at the list of those who have been on more than one quango to see what an industry it has become. Whatever else the Government do, the issue of democratising quangos must be addressed. Where there continues to be a need for quango-type arrangements, it is important that democratically elected politicians make up a majority of those on the bodies.</p>
	<p pid="a.139.1/4">Much has been said about the potential for savings; little, however, has been said about the costs of setting up and operating the new structures. For instance, the five education and library boards will be reduced to one, but a raft of new bodies will be created. Furthermore, the bodies representing the Province's multitude of education providers are to remain, but with little discernible role. Health boards and trusts are coalescing, but a new tier of local commissioning is to be created. What will be the total for the setting-up and running of those seven primary care organisations?</p>
	<p pid="a.139.1/5">In light of the Government's eagerness to create efficiencies and save money, one of the most absurd decisions coming from the RPA is that relating to the roads function. I come to this issue as a former Minister for Regional Development, with, I hope, some of the knowledge that that brings. As a Minister, I had the opportunity to meet, and on occasion visit, key individuals on road and transport matters in countries across the world&mdash;from Europe, from the USA and from as far afield as Australia and New Zealand.</p>
	<p pid="a.139.1/6">The unanimous view expressed to me&mdash;and I heard it from every individual that I talked to about the problems that they faced in relation to roads&mdash;was that we should be counting our blessings that we had a unified road service. Many of the difficulties that others faced arose from the fact that responsibility for roads in their jurisdiction had been splintered. The proposal in the RPA has all the hallmarks of doing something for the sake of doing it. In this debate, there is not the opportunity to discuss those matters at length, but I ask the Government to look into the issue again. I believe that the Government are giving the responsibility to local government just to be seen to be giving it more powers. It is not a sensible basis on which to proceed. Those in local government will not thank the Government for it when, if I can use the pun, they are further down the road. The proposal to give roads functions to local government will not create efficiencies, nor will it deliver a better service. The decision flies in the face of virtually every other recommendation in the RPA.</p>
	<p pid="a.139.1/7">One matter that the Government have not yet decided in relation to the process is planning appeals in Northern Ireland. One of the proposals during the consultation process was that, with planning matters being returned to local government, the Department would take over the appellate function from the Planning Appeals Commission in a manner that is broadly in line with England. I need not tell the Minister the difficulties that are faced in relation to planning and some of the decisions that are taken, but the one element of the process that attracts the highest level of respect is the Planning Appeals Commission. There is a suspicion that, because it has been too independent and done its job too well over the years, the Government are taking this opportunity to get appeals back to the Department. That is a mistake. Will the Minister take account of the views that were expressed during the consultation by those who have knowledge of that facet of planning?</p>
	<p pid="a.139.1/8">Despite the initial announcement on the RPA, I believe that there is still time for the Government to think again about a number of the recommendations coming out of it. It must be clear to the Minister that by working with, rather than against, the political parties in Northern Ireland, it is much more likely that the Government will create arrangements that last another generation, rather than simply until devolution returns. I urge the Government to think again before embarking on a path that will ultimately be reversed, if it is ever fully implemented.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.141.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1388" speakername="Angela Smith" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Northern Ireland"  colnum="141"  time="017:06:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h05.htm#60201h05_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.141.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1400" name="Peter Robinson">the hon. Member for Belfast, East (Mr. Robinson)</phrase> on securing the debate. I know of his concerns and his interest in the review of public administration. I understand what he said about this being a brief debate&mdash;I am afraid that the reply will be even briefer, given the time available, but I will do my best to do justice to the issues that he has raised.</p>
	<p pid="a.141.0/2">Initially, I will make some general comments. The decisions on the outcome of the RPA were announced by the Secretary of State in November. As the hon. Gentleman recognises, the programme of reform is challenging in health, education and, particularly, local government. He is quite right to say that local government is an area of particular controversy. It is worth reminding ourselves why we embark on these changes in the first place. As he quite rightly pointed out, the process was started in June 2002, during devolution, just prior to the Assembly being suspended. It was initiated by the Northern Ireland Executive and it had overwhelming support from the Assembly and its Committees.</p>
	<p pid="a.141.0/3">All of us regret that, following that, devolution was suspended. It has fallen to direct rule Ministers to take the process forward and I do not think that any of us anticipated that we would be taking it forward to this stage. However, at every stage, the Northern Ireland political parties have been involved in the process, and until the Assembly is up and running that will be continue to be the case. Most of the hon. Members here today have met me on issues relating to education. I recall meetings on the RPA with all political parties, in which views were taken forward and comments on education were listened to and taken into account before final announcements were made.</p>
	<p pid="a.141.0/4">The devolved Administration, like the current Administration, recognised that Northern Ireland is hugely over-administered. There is unanimous agreement that government needs to be smaller in order to be effective. The review is also intended to ensure that taxpayers' money is not spent on bureaucracy and administration, but is redirected to front-line services for the public in order to get maximum value for money. Our view&mdash;I think that it was the view of the Assembly, as well&mdash;is that public services have to be responsive and accountable to the public, who pay for them.</p>
	<p pid="a.141.0/5">During the debate in the Assembly in June 2002, when the terms of reference for the RPA were secured, a colleague of the hon. Gentleman, Councillor Edwin Poots, MLA, made some comments that bear repetition. He said that</p>
	<p pid="a.141.0/6" class="indent">&quot;as public representatives we serve the public. It is our duty to ensure that the administration exists to serve the public, rather than us . . . The review provides a unique opportunity to do that, and we must ensure that its outcome is a better, more efficient system that saves money on administration and delivers better core services.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.141.0/7">We would all sign up to that and we are firmly of the view that the decisions announced in November will deliver it.</p>
	<p pid="a.141.0/8">The decisions announced by my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State and other Ministers who have been involved with this are a huge step in improving the development and delivery of public services. To that end, we have been true to the views expressed by the Assembly in 2002.</p>
	<p pid="a.141.0/9">The decisions radically streamline the whole Administration, whether we are talking about health, education, local government or public services. Those savings are not savings made just for the sake of it; they are made in administration to ensure that we have resources for front-line services. The hon. Gentleman said that it is important that we get it right, and I entirely endorse those comments.</p>
	<p pid="a.141.0/10">The review process has been highly transparent throughout, with very participative consultation involving key stakeholders, organisations, elected representatives and the wider public. There were two consultation periods, the latest of which was a six-month period. The review team had more than 80 different consultation engagements and meetings, which covered 300 different groups and approximately 1,000 individuals. There was also an extensive research programme, including academic papers and independent research on a wide range of relevant issues, surveys, focus groups and study visits. All that information is published on the review website.</p>
	<p pid="a.141.0/11">Ministers did not take decisions in a vacuum; they considered all the evidence presented, including that from all political parties. I challenge the hon. Gentleman: he said &quot;whether&quot; there would be a return to devolution. There will be a return to devolution and those issues will be taken up by local Ministers.</p>
	<p pid="a.141.0/12">The decisions were strongly evidence-based, particularly in relation to the seven-council model. I understand the concerns raised about that, but I am a little concerned sometimes that the debate is about the number of councils. During the meetings I had with the Northern Ireland Local Government Association when I was the Minister responsible for the environment, the question concerned the efficient, effective and economical delivery of local services. We have to consider the functions that we expect local government to deliver, prior to considering the number of councils.</p>
	<p pid="a.141.0/13">What are the functions, how can we best deliver those in the interests of public services and what number of councils can best deliver this model? All evidence pointed to the optimum number of councils being seven. No hard evidence presented counteracted that notion when Ministers made the decision. It is clear that councils need to operate on a much larger scale to maximise the benefits. The hon. Gentleman recognised that; I do not think that he was trying to defend a 26-council model. If we are to maximise the benefits by transferring functions to local government, we need to ensure that there are large enough councils to do that. It is not just a question of efficiencies, it is about increasing the role of local councils and councillors and extending their functions.</p>
	<p pid="a.141.0/14">There was broad support from across Northern Ireland for the seven-council model. Of the 113 responses to the further consultation document that indicated a preference for the number of councils, 62 per cent. supported seven and 18 per cent.&mdash;almost exclusively made up of those in the political establishment&mdash;supported 15.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.143.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1589" speakername="Mark Durkan" colnum="143"  time="017:06:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h05.htm#60201h05_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.143.0/1">The Minister referred to the responses. Some of us met some of the organisations mentioned, not least those in the community and voluntary sector quoted by the Government as supporting the seven-council model. Those organisations openly admit that they did not consult any local bodies on whether there should be seven councils in principle, or on any of the proposed councils. The hard evidence against the seven-council model will come when boundary hearings are held on the proposed, incongruous, local councils.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.143.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1388" speakername="Angela Smith" colnum="143"  time="017:06:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h05.htm#60201h05_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.143.1/1">If someone responds to a Government consultation and gives a point of view, we do not tend to go back them and ask them how they reached that point of view. If an organisation responds to Government consultation, we accept the response at face value. We would be criticised if we did not do so.</p>
	<p pid="a.143.1/2">The evidence that was considered dealt with research into the distribution of the property wealth base; population, social and economic issues and local identity figured very strongly as well. Consideration was given to equality, social need, the population spread and where people live and work. We took account of the views expressed to us by individuals and groups. We felt that the challenge was to ensure that local councils and local councillors engaged meaningfully with the public, so that the public felt engaged.</p>
	<p pid="a.143.1/3">One of the criticisms made has been of the roles and responsibilities of local government. I am disappointed that no hon. Members here today have said what a good idea it is, or how important it is, that local democracy has been enhanced by strengthening the functions of local government.</p>
	<p pid="a.143.1/4">The process will require meaningful engagement between councillors and local communities to ensure that local voices are listened to. I understand the points of the hon. Members for Strangford (Mrs. Robinson) and for Belfast, East about balkanisation, and how they feel that the proposals will repartition Northern Ireland. I do not accept the argument. People in Northern Ireland live where they live; council boundaries are not going to affect where people live. At present, the majority of people who live in council areas in the west of Northern Ireland tend to vote for nationalist parties and in the east they tend to vote Unionist. Whatever the configuration of local councils, those divisions will remain. That position remains. If there were to be 11 or 15 councils, I do not see how that will make any difference at all to the issue raised by the hon. Member for Strangford.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-02-01a.144.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1484" speakername="Eric Martlew" colnum="144"  time="017:06:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060201/halltext/60201h05.htm#60201h05_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.144.0/1">Order.</p>
	<p pid="a.144.0/2" class="indent">It being fifteen minutes past Five o'clock, the motion for the Adjournment of the sitting lapsed, without Question put.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

