<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.65.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.65.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.65.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.65.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.65.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.65.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.65.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.65.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.65.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1039" speakername="Edward Leigh" colnum="65"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h01.htm#50126h01_spnew0">
	<p pid=".65.3/1">In 2000, in the wake of the resignation of the Santer Commission over allegations of fraud, corruption, incompetence and nepotism, we debated fraud in the European Union in this Chamber. At the time, my predecessor as Chairman of the Public Accounts Committee, my right hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/847" name="David Davis">the Member for Haltemprice and Howden (David Davis)</phrase>, and I welcomed the appointment of Vice-President Kinnock, who was appointed to oversee the fight against fraud and to reform the Commission. We had high hopes that he would bring about fundamental change, but, even then, we were concerned about the speed of the proposed reforms. One development that we welcomed particularly was the new anti-fraud body, OLAF, because its predecessor had been completely ineffective.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/2">Five years on, we now have a new and enlarged set of commissioners under the leadership of Jos&eacute; Manuel Barroso and Vice-President Kallas, who is responsible for fighting fraud. With the United Kingdom presidency of the EU fast approaching, it is a good time to take stock of what has been achieved and what remains to be done. The signs of improvement are evident, but painfully slow.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/3">The Commission seems to be attempting to get a grip on fraud within its ranks, but about 80 per cent. of EU money is spent in member states where controls are even more lax and sloppy than in the Commission. My sense overall is that the European Union is still not taking fraud seriously. We urgently need a strong lead from the centre to drive member states forward into a new culture of zero tolerance of fraud and corruption, and that zero tolerance needs to start in the Commission itself. We must start putting warm words and plans&mdash;believe me, there are plenty of them&mdash;into action. We need a more rigorous approach to safeguarding taxpayers' money.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/4">How much have things changed? Well, we can measure the financial competence of any organisation by its independent auditors' report. In November 2004, the European Court of Auditors published its audit report on the Community's annual accounts and, for the 10th year in succession, the court was unable to give those accounts a clean bill of health. According to MEP colleagues in Brussels, there are worrying signs that the Commission is now pressuring the Court of Auditors to fine-tune the rules, so that the accounts can be signed off in future years.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/5">The Court of Auditors was also concerned about the lack of reliability of aspects of the Community's accounts. That was due partly to the Commission's accounting system, which could not record assets and    liabilities correctly&mdash;surely a straightforward accounting procedure that we would expect in a reputable organisation. Even more worrying, the number of errors that was found was so high that it could not vouch for spending streams that covered 93 per cent. of expenditure. That does not mean, of course, that all the spending was wrong, but it is astonishing that we cannot be confident that as much as 93 per cent. of expenditure was properly spent. For example, the court reported that payments under the common agriculture policy and for structural funds totalling about &euro;70 billion were affected in some way by errors. That conclusion was not new. It was a familiar story and we have been hearing it for a decade.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/6">When will that familiarity breed sufficient contempt to spark some action? The accounts and accounting systems tell us that the Commission falls far short of full financial competence. That is one thing, but what about fraud? The value of reported fraud in the EU was 49 per cent. higher in 2003 than it was in 1999. Fraudulent cases worth an incredible &euro;900 million were dealt with by OLAF in 2003 alone. Those statistics are one year old, so who knows what the situation is now? More worrying, the real levels of fraud are almost impossible to quantify at present.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/7">It is impossible to separate suspected fraud from irregularity. On the one hand, the Commission defines fraud as a deliberate, criminal act with intent to achieve financial advantage. Fair enough, but, on the other hand, irregularities are failures to comply with Commission regulations. So, until a case has passed through the criminal courts in the relevant country, which may go on for years, it cannot technically even be labelled as fraud.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/8">Member states report fraud differently. How can we track something down if we cannot agree on what it is? Some member states will not recognise fraud until a conviction has been obtained through their national legal system. Germany and Greece seldom report cases within a two-month deadline after detection. Some countries wait until recovery is underway before reporting cases of fraud. Greece often does not even report the date of the discovery. For the Commission to allow member states to pursue such varied practices is sloppy and suggests to me that it is not taking fraud seriously.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/9">The figures that we hear about are only those that have been reported. The actual value is probably much higher. I have estimates of fraud at anything between 7 per cent. and 10 per cent. of the total EU budget. It could have been as high as almost &euro;10 billion for 2003 alone. The Commission, of course, puts the figure much lower at about 2 per cent., but even that is almost &euro;2 billion. Whatever the exact figure, the problem of fraud is immense. The situation has surely gone on long enough.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/10">I turn now to the blame game. The Commission is too quick to shrug off responsibility for the astonishing levels of fraud and irregularity by blaming member states. They may well be culpable, but the Commission is too. It is not a moral responsibility, but a statutory responsibility set out in the founding treaty of the EU. It is time that the Commission seized the initiative with member states. We need common recognition that fraud is a problem and renewed determination to tackle it.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/11">Some frauds are so ludicrous that they should be blindingly obvious. For example, certain Balkan countries have preferential trade agreements with the EU for exporting sugar. The anti-fraud authorities eventually came across some suspect activities with the importation of sugar into Greece from Croatia, where it has been produced. What was the problem? It was not a complicated, underground system nor a corrupt and complex fiddling of the books. No, the fraud was   even more blatant than that and yet went unrecognised&mdash;Croatia does not produce sugar cane at all.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/12">Individual embezzlement also threatens public money spent by the EU, even when that money is aimed at vital infrastructure for people living in difficult conditions. In April 2002, OLAF investigated a case from the United Nations mission in Kosovo relating to alleged misappropriation of funds intended for the electricity sector in Kosovo. It turned out that the money had been stolen and spirited into personal bank accounts in Gibraltar. A further attempt by the principal suspect to send the funds from Gibraltar to Belize was thwarted. OLAF managed to secure the return of &euro;2.7 million. The suspect, a former United Nations official in Kosovo, is now serving a three-and-a-half-year prison sentence.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/13">Such activities happen in the United Kingdom, too. We cannot sit in a warm bath of our own prejudices and say that it is all down to Johnny Foreigner. It is not. My Committee has reported on several cases when abysmally lax control by public bodies allowed serious frauds to be perpetrated on EU funds, and further control improvements are still needed.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/14">I shall cite two examples. In 2002, my Committee published a scathing report on a notorious fraudster, a farmer called Joseph Bowden, who claimed against the common agricultural policy for different crops on the same piece of land and went on to give fictitious co-ordinates for some of the fields for which he was claiming. If those claims had been examined by experts, or anyone with a map, it would have been discovered that the fields were apparently in Greenland, the North sea and the Norwegian sea. He received a 30-month jail sentence as a result and new controls were imposed, but at the time he got away with it because controls were obviously lax in the then Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/15">My second concern is perhaps even more worrying. It could be said that that was just one fraudster and one case of lax controls in one Department, but the Committee also looked at the sheep annual premium scheme in Northern Ireland, an EU strategy designed to support sheep producers through payments for eligible sheep. When we investigated the administration of that scheme, we were shocked to find a catalogue of errors and control failures, all of which pointed to what we described as a &quot;particularly slack regime&quot; in place under the Department concerned, and I believe that there was almost certainly collusion. We found, for example, that some payments were made for dead sheep&mdash;surely something that is not unknown in Irish history, but there we are&mdash;even though there was often no evidence that they had ever existed. These dead sheep were never alive. When visiting farms, the Department's inspectors detected more than four times as many irregularities when accompanied by staff from the National Audit Office as when they were not accompanied by them, which suggests that they were on occasions turning a blind eye to the rules.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/16">I acknowledge that in response to our findings the Department agreed to take strong steps to address the Committee's concerns. Indeed, following wider changes in the EU, the sheep annual premium scheme itself has recently ceased to exist. However, the failure to address the European Court of Auditors' recommendations over 10 years was, in the Committee's view, a serious error of judgment. Failure to manage the scheme properly led the Commission to refuse to pay some of the UK's claim, &pound;1.5 million of which was attributed to   Northern Ireland. Perhaps controls are much more   lax in other European countries, particularly Mediterranean ones, but we, too, are not without blame.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/17">Such cases undermine the integrity of EU funding. If Departments and agencies are as soft on fraud as we found, fraudsters will regard it as a risk worth taking. All bodies involved in the administration of EU schemes must make fraud a decidedly unattractive proposition; they must have effective inspection processes, a rigorous prosecutions policy and penalties that far outweigh the potential gains from fraud.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/18">Our Committee has repeatedly emphasised that &pound;1 of EU subsidy is as much taxpayers' money as any other form of voted money. We make no distinction between the rigorous safeguards that we expect to see operated for EU subsidies and any other form of grant payment.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/19">Improving financial management in the EU has, of course, long been an important issue for the Public Accounts Committee, and in recent years it has increasingly become a priority for European institutions and member states too. Recently there seems to be a new spirit of co-operation between the Court of Auditors, the Commission and the European Parliament, to work towards the achievement of an unqualified opinion on the Commission's accounts.</p>
	<p pid=".65.3/20">The PAC's counterpart in the European Parliament, the Committee on Budgetary Control, has taken a robust approach to the discharge of the budget this year. It has closely questioned members of the Commission and, for the first time, officials from the European Court of Auditors, on how a positive statement of assurance can be achieved. That focused approach and pressure to address difficult issues has been welcomed by Vice-President Kallas, the new commissioner charged with the job of rooting out fraud. However, he is the subject of alleged fraud in his own country.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.68.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.68.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.68.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.68.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.68.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1039" speakername="Edward Leigh" colnum="68"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h01.htm#50126h01_spnew2">
	<p pid=".68.1/1">One would have thought so. Parliamentarians in the Westminster model find that extraordinary. I talked yesterday to my colleague, Mr. Chris Heaton-Harris, Member of the European Parliament for the East Midlands. It is colleagues such as him who are trying to change attitudes in the European Parliament, and although it is an uphill struggle they are doing their best. However, it is extraordinary that the budgetary control committee has found its teeth only this year.</p>
	<p pid=".68.1/2">There have been some moves towards a more accountable system that helps prevent fraud. One step was the introduction on <phrase class="date" code="2005-01-01">1 January</phrase> of an accruals-based Commission accounting system, which is an excellent start, as the Commission is fond of telling us, but even a first-class accounting system cannot guarantee good financial management. A certain company, now a household name for its high-profile failures in corporate governance, used accruals accounting. I am talking about Enron, and we all know what happened there.</p>
	<p pid=".68.1/3">There have also been some useful wider developments in the Commission. There is now a strategic planning function to assist commissioners, a deputy secretary-general to cut through red tape and an internal audit   service starting in May to look at control of management. We are told that there is now a human resources policy in the Commission&mdash;whatever that is&mdash;that will help manage whistleblowers better, and an audit progress board to ensure that recommendations are followed up. However, the impression I get from talking to Members of the European Parliament is that the only people who have suffered so far in the European Commission in rooting out fraud are the whistleblowers themselves. Even in the EUROSTAT scandal, it was Dorte Schmidt-Brown, an official who revealed what was going on, who lost her job, suffered a nervous breakdown and effectively had her career ended.</p>
	<p pid=".68.1/4">Hans-Martin Tillack, a German journalist, was arrested on <phrase class="date" code="2005-03-19">19 March</phrase> on the orders of the EU's anti-fraud office, OLAF, and taken into custody. His personal papers, computer and archives were confiscated in an effort to identity sources of revelations about EU corruption. That was his crime. He was arrested because he was not prepared to reveal his sources who had told him about EU corruption. OLAF says that it is implementing a policy of zero-tolerance towards corruption and fraud in the European institutions and is working to produce a robust estimate of the level of fraud and error. We are told that at least we will understand the full scale of the problem. We await results.</p>
	<p pid=".68.1/5">I am pleased that my right hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/951" name="David Heathcoat-Amory">the Member for Wells (Mr. Heathcoat-Amory)</phrase> is present in the Chamber. He fought almost a lone fight in the Commission to try to give extra powers to the European Court of Auditors. Indeed, extra powers were given to virtually every other institution in the EU, but not the Court of Auditors. My hon. Friend's warnings fell on deaf ears. However, I am delighted that he is here today. He is clearly an expert on these matters in the House of Commons.</p>
	<p pid=".68.1/6">In conclusion, there are signs of improvement in the way that the EU manages its finances and I am encouraged to see a glimmer of light, but it is, as yet, a light of expectation, rather than action. We need dedication and prompt action from the Commission and all member states, including the UK, to stamp out fraud. The UK's presidency of the EU in the second half of 2005 provides an excellent opportunity for us to drive forward further progress.</p>
	<p pid=".68.1/7">In dealing with fraud and corruption in an institution it is not enough to say that the rules are being carried out correctly. Moral corruption on a petty scale, and on a large scale, must be dealt with too. It is not good enough for any institution to say &quot;We are carrying out the   rules,&quot; if the rules are corrupt. Let us take one example of petty corruption. Members of the European Parliament are paid travel expenses on the basis of what is known as kilometrage, which involves fixed payments per unit of distance travelled. The sums paid are the equivalent to club class air travel. If Members choose a cheaper form a travel, and, of course, most of them do, they save considerable amounts, which they are allowed to keep because there is no mechanism by which it can   be returned. That is an example of petty moral corruption. It can be argued that there are examples of much larger moral corruption on a grand scale, and one such example would involve the European fisheries policy. However, that is a debate for another time and place.</p>
	<p pid=".68.1/8">I said in my opening remarks that now was a good time to take stock. Taxpayers across Europe are rightly concerned at the apparent endemic inability of the EU to manage its finances well. We have every reason to believe that money is still pouring down the drain. We may not be able to say how fast the flow is, or whether it is quicker or slower than before, but it is time to plug the hole. We need a radical policy where we press for our own National Audit Office, which has a reputation second to none, to be allowed to pursue the trail of the money that we give to the Commission into the Commission.</p>
	<p pid=".68.1/9">Currently, the NAO has no rights of access in the European Commission. The Public Accounts Committee will go to Brussels in March to discuss what further progress is planned, within its rights of access. It will have no ability to cross-question officials, but some points are evident from the outset. We need the Commission's new accounting system to work and the Commission to drive forward consistency in member states' approaches to reporting fraud. We also need all public institutions across the EU to treat each euro of EU subsidy as they would every euro funded by their own national Treasury or finance ministry. That is a very clear agenda for the UK Government as they take on the presidency and I commend it to the Minister.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.70.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.70.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.70.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/816" speakername="Frank Cook" colnum="70"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h01.htm#50126h01_spnew3">
	<p pid=".70.0/1">Order. This is a 90-minute debate and it is advisable to remind right hon. and hon. Members that the usual convention is to start the first of the three winding-up speeches 30 minutes before its conclusion. While I am interested in the subject and am learning a lot, I appeal to all right hon. and hon. Members to bear in mind the time limitations. We need to start the concluding winding-up speeches at 10.30 am.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.70.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.70.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.70.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/951" speakername="David Heathcoat-Amory" colnum="70"  time="009:52:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h01.htm#50126h01_spnew4">
	<p pid=".70.1/1">When I heard my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1039" name="Edward Leigh">the Member for Gainsborough (Mr. Leigh)</phrase> making his excellent speech, I experienced a strong sense of d&eacute;j&agrave; vu, because the issues are of considerable antiquity. I grappled with some of the problems when I was a Minister with responsibility for Europe 10 years ago, and also when I was at the Treasury as the Minister responsible for our contribution to the European budget. At the time, I failed to push through the necessary reforms. I received the brush-offs from the European institutions, and the warm assurances that everything would be different, that reforms were in place and that I had to wait only another year and everything would be fine. Of course, the reform never happened.</p>
	<p pid=".70.1/2">In the background, there was a strong sense of not in front of the children. The issue was seen as an internal matter where exposure would damage the European project, so there was a strong reluctance to bring many of the deep-seated problems into the open.</p>
	<p pid=".70.1/3">We are now well past that point. The public know perfectly well what is going on and are aware of the scale of the waste, mismanagement and fraud, which was so well described by my hon. Friend. That is now an open sore on the face of the European Union and contributes in large part to the widespread disillusionment and disenchantment that the public feel towards it.</p>
	<p pid=".70.1/4">The problem has got much worse during the intervening 10 years. The European budget is now more than &euro;100 billion a year and growing, and, as we have heard, the accounts have not been signed off by the auditors for 10 years. If the EU was a commercial institution operating in the private sector, all of the directors would now be in prison. If it were a public institution operating in a member state, those responsible would have been kicked out long ago. Instead, the whole project simply rolls forward, despite the fact that it destroyed the last but one European Commission; the Santer Commission resigned en masse in 1999 because of fraud and mismanagement in its budget.</p>
	<p pid=".70.1/5">Things are still going on. EUROSTAT has been discovered to be riddled with fraud, with money siphoned off into secret accounts. The Government's contribution to that subject is the Treasury Command Paper 6134, which was published last April and goes into some detail. It is truly awesome that one of the agencies of the Commission had secret bank accounts and there was no audit trail. When that was discovered, no one lost their jobs.</p>
	<p pid=".70.1/6">My hon. Friend is right to remind hon. Members that the only people who ever lose their jobs are the whistleblowers&mdash;the people who draw attention to scandals. OLAF, the anti-fraud office, was rather dismissively referred to by the Government last year as part of the Commission, which is a telling observation. It is not an independent body as we would understand such things, but part of the European Union institution that causes most of the problem. It is a branch of the    Commission and reports to it. It is not truly independent.</p>
	<p pid=".70.1/7">I had a rather sad conversation with one of the whistleblowers, Marta Andreasen, when she came to this country to give a lecture before Christmas last year. She was the first qualified accountant to be appointed chief accountant in the European Union. She pointed out that the system has no proper double-entry bookkeeping. I am a chartered accountant; I declare that interest. Every first-year student of accountancy learns about double-entry bookkeeping. In fact, it was a European invention. It was discovered by the Venetians in the 15th century. It has been around for quite a long time in Europe, but it has not yet reached Brussels.</p>
	<p pid=".70.1/8">Ms Andreasen reported the failings to her superiors and, of course, nothing was done. Her objections and complaints were ignored and, even more scandalously, she never received a proper hearing from the people who should be the guardians of our interest&mdash;the European Parliament. When Mr. Prodi retired as President of the European Commission he was congratulated in the European Parliament on the way in which he got rid of    Marta Andreasen by the leader of the Liberal Democrat group. That speaks eloquently about the lack of assistance&mdash;to put it at its mildest&mdash;that we get from the European Parliament in guarding not only British taxpayers, but the European taxpayers.</p>
	<p pid=".70.1/9">I want to discuss opportunities for reform and to be positive. There was a giant opportunity in the form of the Convention on the Future of Europe, on which I sat. It was given a wide remit, in particular to reconnect with the citizens of Europe. Knowing that an important part of that reconnection was to assure the public that something would be done in future about the European budget and about the scandals, I submitted a six-page paper on <phrase class="date" code="2003-07-07">7 July 2003</phrase>, which was referred to in kind terms by my hon. Friend in his remarks.</p>
	<p pid=".70.1/10">I set out the problem in detail. I referred to whistleblowers and their evidence, and I suggested some   reforms, for example, how budgetary control committees in national Parliaments&mdash;in our case the Public Accounts Committee and the National Audit Office&mdash;should be given some way of following national money through into the European system to ensure, and to help, the value for money procedures in Brussels.</p>
	<p pid=".70.1/11">I suggested reforms to the audit process, and I suggested that where the European Court of Auditors had severe misgivings about a budget line, it should be able to block expenditure until it could sign it off as being regular and legal. I also suggested making reforms to the European Court of Auditors, to strengthen its authority and independence. I suggested that OLAF be given proper independence and be subjected to democratic scrutiny.</p>
	<p pid=".70.1/12">I advanced a case for greater transparency and openness. In that connection, it is interesting that, this afternoon, we are debating that issue in the European Scrutiny Committee, which, amazingly, still sits in secret, and there is a move by some Government Members to entrench that secrecy in our proceedings. I also suggested giving additional rights to whistleblowers in the European Union, to match the statutory protection that we give them in our country.</p>
	<p pid=".70.1/13">All that was completely ignored. It was never referred to in debate in the Convention, except by myself and a few of my allies. I submitted specific amendments to the evolving European constitution to reflect the need for some of the reforms that I have just outlined. Again, all of them were ignored and, sadly, they were not supported by the British Government representative on the Convention.</p>
	<p pid=".70.1/14">The only plan advanced by the European institution itself was to set up another European institution called the European public prosecutor. That body would consolidate new, awesome powers to prosecute and investigate at European level, right across the European Union, from Brussels. It is not the setting up of new institutions that we want; we have seen that too often in the past. We need to reform the existing institution before we give it more powers. That is one reason why the European constitution deserves to fail, and will fail. But my hon. Friend deserves to succeed in his noble crusade to do something about the matter at national level, and I very much hope that he does.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.73.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.73.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.75.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.75.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.76.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.76.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.76.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.76.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.76.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.76.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.77.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.77.0" matchtype="multiplecover"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.77.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.78.0" matchtype="multiplecover"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.77.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/707" speakername="Richard Bacon" colnum="77"  time="010:16:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h01.htm#50126h01_spnew10">
	<p pid=".77.0/1">Does my hon. Friend recall that when the European Union financial perspective 2007&ndash;13 was discussed at a seminar sponsored by the Commission in Helsinki 18 months ago, two items dominated the agenda&mdash;first, the British rebate and, secondly, common European taxation?</p>
	<p pid=".77.0/2">Mr. Cash: Absolutely, and the lies that have been generated from outside the House with respect to the matters that my hon. Friend raises are simply incredible. There is a determination to move to a common tax policy; that is connected with the budget and therefore with the question of fraud. The scale of the fraud speaks for itself.</p>
	<p pid=".77.0/3">The problem can be resolved, but there is a lack of willingness to resolve it. In fact, there is a determination not to. If one asks some of the other 26 member states what are the rules for the equivalent of our Public Accounts Committee, do we find that in the other member states they properly examine matters, with the scrutiny available through the National Audit Office and the Comptroller and Auditor General? Is there a determination in each of those member states to deal properly with the accounting system? The Marta Andreasen case and the complete failure of the then Vice-President, now Lord Kinnock, to deal with the matter is a good example of the massive problem of the accounting system and fraud in the European Union, which affects us and our voters. The way in which the whole of the European Union finances operate and the increase in the amount of fraud is a disgrace to the   European Union and to those who have been responsible for trying to correct it.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.78.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.78.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.78.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/707" speakername="Richard Bacon" colnum="78"  time="010:16:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h01.htm#50126h01_spnew11">
	<p pid=".78.0/1">In the last year or so&mdash;certainly in the last 18 months&mdash;the Committee has visited the Cours des Comptes in Paris, the Bundesrechnungshof in Berlin and, last October, the Tribunal de Cuentas in Madrid. The European Court of Auditors in Luxembourg is modelled on that continental, juridical, legalistic model&mdash;not on the financial audit, taxpayer, value for money model, such as the one we have here. Does my hon. Friend not appreciate that the reform he is looking for will not happen because it is utterly inimical to the system?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.78.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.78.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.78.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.78.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.78.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/752" speakername="Colin Breed" colnum="78"  time="010:27:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h01.htm#50126h01_spnew13">
	<p pid=".78.2/1">Whether people are avowedly in favour of the European Union or totally against it, no one could suggest that anyone would countenance fraud and the misuse of taxpayers' money. Therefore it is absolutely right that we have these debates and, while there is a certain amount of d&eacute;j&agrave; vu, they should continue, because these are extremely important matters.</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/2">The annual reports by the European Court of Auditors and the European anti-fraud office&mdash;and, indeed, the National Audit Office&mdash;are scrutinised at a number of national and European levels. In the UK, of course, they are considered by the European Scrutiny Committee and European Standing Committee B. As a member of the Scrutiny Committee for quite a little while, I concur with all who have spoken on the subject today that our scrutiny process, in general, needs to be significantly enhanced. It needs to be open, not held in secret as it is, and it ought to have many more powers to ensure that it can get to the bottom of things, not least the budget and the control of funding. All other areas of scrutiny could be significantly enhanced as well.</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/3">Part of the problem is that we have a majority Government, and therefore a Government majority on the Committee, whereas most other European scrutiny committees are comprised of coalitions. While they may not get to the bottom of all their finances, I suspect they hold their Ministers to account more. Far too often when I was on the Scrutiny Committee we were advised that the Minister had ignored the scrutiny reserve and had gone ahead and decided on a particular view at the Council of Ministers, of which he informed us later. Our European scrutiny process is in need of great reform and overhaul, and it needs to be held in public.</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/4">Fewer matters should be referred to the European Standing Committee and more should to be taken on the Floor of the House. That was often recommended by the Committee, but was never taken up. There is ample evidence that parliamentary time is available on the Floor of the House, particularly on Thursday afternoons, when we could properly debate the issues that we are discussing today.</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/5">The European Court of Auditors produces an annual report, as has been said, and I have had a good look at the most recent one. It is required to do so by the treaty that established the European Community to provide the European Parliament and the Council of Ministers with a statement of assurance&mdash;I am not quite certain what it assures at the moment&mdash;</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/6" class="indent">&quot;concerning both the reliability of the accounts drawn up by the Commission and the legality and regularity of the underlying transactions.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/7">I understand that to be the payments actually made.</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/8">The court's assessment usually goes beyond what we would see as a pure accounting exercise; it also assesses the financial management and control structures of the EU Executive. As we have heard, for the 10th successive year it has failed to give the all clear to the accounts. It refused to give a positive assurance on the legality and regularity of 93 per cent. of the EU budget, which is an extraordinary figure. Most auditors would say that in the time available and in normal circumstances they are unable to get 100 per cent. of everything right, but for the court to say that it could not vouch for 93 per cent. is extraordinary.</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/9">The notes on the reliability of the accounts are quite instructive. I want to quote a couple of paragraphs from what was said. Paragraph III states:</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/10" class="indent">&quot;In the absence of effective internal control procedures for miscellaneous revenue and advances, the Court cannot be certain that the transactions relating to the sundry debtors item have been correctly and completely recorded.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/11">Almost any auditor going into almost any public or multinational company would be unable to provide absolute assurance in the way in which it is expressed there. Paragraph VI (b) states that</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/12" class="indent">&quot;in the case of the structural measures, owing to persistent weaknesses at Member State level in the systems for supervising and controlling the implementation of the EU budget, payments were still subject to the same errors occurring with the same frequency as in previous years.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/13">That gets to the heart of the matter. The fact that, for 10 years in a row, the court has qualified or failed to sign off the accounts seems to have had no effect whatever. There has been no real improvement. Auditors will often make suggestions and indicate areas where there needs to be more effective control, and they would expect, a year later, to see at least some improvement. That is one of the most damning paragraphs; despite 10 years of not being able to sign off the accounts, the payments are</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/14" class="indent">&quot;still subject to the same errors occurring with the same frequency&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/15">I should like to make one further observation on the report. It relates to paragraph VII, which states</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/16" class="indent">&quot;The Court notes the progress made by the Commission as regards the reform of its internal control system and the positive impact of this reform on the legality and regularity of operations subject to direct management by the Commission. However, progress is still required in terms of actual implementation.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/17">Progress has been made in one area, but there is a problem with implementation. That seems to indicate that although new regulations are introduced and new instructions given, implementation is not followed through. That is another part of the damning evidence.</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/18">I turn now to OLAF, which also produces a report. Its report indicates that the irregularities that it finds are not necessarily fraud but are the result of simple, non-criminal errors. In that context, I want to give an example of one of my constituents, a farmer who&mdash;I   believe quite properly&mdash;indicated that after the re-measurement of his fields some of his subsidy claims needed to be revisited. He reported that his fields were slightly different, and had carried different crops over the past four years, and in doing so he was made to feel an absolute criminal. He was then asked to return all the subsidy that he had received and told that he would be subject to a penalty, notwithstanding the fact that some of the changes would have resulted in credits and others in debits: in some cases he would have received too much, but in others too little. He thought that, having reported the matter, he would receive fair treatment&mdash;that a balance of the credits and debits over the four-year period would be calculated, and that if a payment was due he would pay it, and if not, a payment would be made to him. But he was told absolutely categorically that that could not be the case; he would have to pay back all the subsidy that he had received and a penalty would be imposed. He felt pretty bruised by the whole exercise.</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/19">That case would probably go down as fraud, but it was not a fraud. My constituent reported the matter and the difficulties were explained. He was extremely harshly treated. I do not know whether that was the result of an attempt to crack down on fraud, but obtaining money in such a way is not always fraudulent.</p>
	<p pid=".78.2/20">The main source of fraud undoubtedly seems to be farmers making fraudulent claims. Spot checks found that 25 per cent. of farm payments in Italy were in error or fraudulent, 23 per cent. in Greece, 21 per cent. in Spain, and 14 per cent. in France. Our error rate was said to be 6 per cent. That may be better than everybody else's, but it is still a problem. How many of those cases were actually fraud rather than honest mistakes I am not certain.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.81.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.81.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.81.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.81.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.81.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.81.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.81.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1246" speakername="Richard Spring" colnum="81"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h01.htm#50126h01_spnew16">
	<p pid=".81.2/1">First, I warmly congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1039" name="Edward Leigh">the Member for Gainsborough (Mr. Leigh)</phrase>, the distinguished Chairman of the Select Committee on Public Accounts, on securing this debate and on his contribution, based on his considerable knowledge and expertise. What he said about the principle of zero tolerance is absolutely right. Nothing alienates people from the European Union more than the thought that taxpayers' money is being squandered in a irresponsible and unmeasured way. I thank him for what he has done this morning.</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/2">I absolutely accept that the European Commission is not inherently corrupt. However, it is bureaucratic, inefficient and vulnerable to fraud, and that vulnerability has been exploited. My hon. Friends the Members for   Stone (Mr. Cash) and for South Norfolk (Mr. Bacon) and <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/843" name="Ian Davidson">the hon. Member for Glasgow, Pollok (Mr. Davidson)</phrase> made this point tellingly this morning. The Government are to assume the presidency of the European Union. We have the NAO and other close mechanisms for inspecting any type of financial irregularity in this country. If the Government have, as they say, influence in the EU, it is fundamental that they seek to address the problem in the next year, because the situation has not improved to the satisfaction of people who consider these matters and feel depressed by them, as I do.</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/3">I pay particular tribute to my right hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/951" name="David Heathcoat-Amory">the Member for Wells (Mr. Heathcoat-Amory)</phrase>. I have looked again at his contribution on systems of management during the proceedings of the Convention on the Future of Europe. It is a telling document and a telling analysis of what could and should be done in that context. I pay tribute to him for often being a lone voice on these matters. He has been right in so many instances, and we are seeing that again this morning on immigration and asylum.</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/4">The first step must be to acknowledge the extent of    the problem. The European Commissioner for Institutional Relations and Communication Strategy, Mrs. Wallstr&ouml;m, has said that the Commission has the problem of being afraid of too much openness and has a way of thinking that is &quot;in the walls here&quot;. That must change, because it certainly has not changed in any adequate sense of the word. As we have heard, there have been so many instances of fraud, including the   EUROSTAT affair and the disgraceful situation involving Croatia and sugar cane. That cost the EU &pound;700,000.</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/5">In its annual report in November, the EU's own OLAF said that the incidents of fraud in the aid budget increased by 9 per cent. to 637 over 12 months. The report stated that the international aid budget was dogged by &quot;complex and well-organized&quot; financial fraud. For instance, the EU funded a project to improve water supplies to 50 local authorities in Paraguay. An external audit found that 90 per cent. of the funds had   disappeared into a foundation that had nothing whatever to do with the project. The report stated:</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/6" class="indent">&quot;Such fraud takes  . . . advantage of the lack of coordination in the monitoring and auditing activities between the various international donors&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/7">OLAF's director-general has said:</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/8" class="indent">&quot;Of the problems we detect, more and more are in the aid sector, where things have to be looked into more closely.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/9">He also says:</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/10" class="indent">&quot;All donors have systems of control, but we have to improve them&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/11">I totally agree. After the terrible tsunami disaster and the terrible problems in Zimbabwe and other parts of Africa, international aid is very much at the forefront of people's minds.</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/12">We have heard about Mrs. Andreasen, the European Commission's chief accountant, who was suspended by   the Commission after exposing publicly how its accounts were wide open to fraud and abuse. I say with some pride that Conservative Members of the European Parliament helped Mrs. Andreasen to make those shocking accounting practices public, thus fulfilling their public role. The European Court of Auditors has repeatedly confirmed many of her most serious allegations. I add in passing that a British accountant, Brian Gray, is seeking to carry on the work that she was originally put in place to do. We all wish him well in his role and in introducing some of the high standards that we have in this country. In any event, Mrs. Andreasen got her reward in October by being sacked from her post.</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/13">Regrettably, in November, we yet again faced a farcical situation in which, for the 10th year running, the European Court of Auditors could not give a positive statement of assurance in respect of the overall EU accounts. It is simply unacceptable that the Court found that 93.4 per cent. of spending was either unsafe or riddled with errors, up from 91 per cent. the year before. Indeed, the Court said that once again there is</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/14" class="indent">&quot;no reasonable assurance that the supervisory systems and controls of significant areas of the budget are effectively implemented so as to manage the risks concerning the legality and regularity of the underlying operations&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/15">That speaks volumes for the Court's view of the accounts, and is what qualifying the accounts really means. Spot checks by the Court found fraud or error leading to demands for repayment in 25 per cent. of farm aid to Italy, 23 per cent. for Greece, 21 per cent. for Spain and 14 per cent. for France. Given the huge burden of the common agricultural policy, the fact that fraud continues under the umbrella of agriculture is an absolute disgrace.</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/16">I understand that the usual defence is that the blame lies with the member states. A senior EU auditor said that the Brussels budget is high risk because most of it is doled out to member states, making it hard to track, but&mdash;this is the important point&mdash;he went on to say that Commission officials set a dreadful tone, behaving like:</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/17" class="indent">&quot;rats in a bag seeking to evade responsibility.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/18">It is absolutely wrong that hard-working, tax-paying families have their taxes so blatantly misused in this way.</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/19">We welcome the fact that the Commission has a reform plan, but I doubt that will be enough. The full resource accounting system that we are implementing in Britain has not been replicated in the European Commission&mdash;aspects of it have, but not the full system. We need to deal with this problem seriously, and to encourage the European Parliament in its role as watchdog, because it should take itself even more seriously in that role.</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/20">I accept that the Commission has made limited progress in this direction. I am pleased that it has taken up our proposal to have a Commissioner with sole responsibility for budgetary control. Frankly, reform must go further. As the treaties say, the buck stops with the Commission. That is a simple fact.</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/21">All Commissioners should have a Cabinet member with specific responsibility for all management control issues. They must take full political responsibility for   failings within their department. This is hugely important if public credibility is to be reasserted. Quite frankly, it is absolutely wrong that these reports have been signed off, given the circumstances.</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/22">OLAF should be fully independent, with its own staff, budget and organisational priorities, subject to a new   management board. Member states must account adequately for all expenditure on EU programmes. The Court of Auditors should undertake programme audits for all member states, rather than just a sample of them, publishing a detailed assessment of each. That should be followed up so that progress can be measured in subsequent years.</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/23">Until voters can have confidence in EU accounting, Conservative MEPS will refuse to sign off the Commission's accounts, and so would a Conservative Government. The British people contribute to the EU, and they deserve value for money. They do not expect to have their money stolen. Openness, accountability and honesty from the EU should not be too much to ask. After almost eight years in power, the Government have not gripped the issue significantly.</p>
	<p pid=".81.2/24">There have been some practical suggestions this morning on how to take the matter forward. I look forward to the Minister's explanation of what the Government will do about such a serious state of affairs, which must be part of the reason that the credibility of the European Union has never been so low, not only in this country, but in many other parts of the European Union.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.84.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.84.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.85.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.85.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.86.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.86.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.86.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.86.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.86.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.86.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.86.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.86.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.86.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.86.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.86.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.86.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.86.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.86.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.87.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.87.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.88.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.88.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.88.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.88.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.88.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/822" speakername="Brian Cotter" colnum="88"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h02.htm#50126h02_spnew0">
	<p pid=".88.1/1">I am delighted to have the opportunity to debate education funding in North Somerset, and I am grateful that the Minister is attending.</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/2">Funding for education is a priority for us all. I am deeply concerned about the lack of such funding for   North Somerset. The local education authority covers the constituencies of Weston-super-Mare and Woodspring. Funding for education in the area has consistently been below the national average, and education services there are beginning to suffer.</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/3">Concerned about current education funding levels in North Somerset, I asked the Secretary of State for Education and Skills about the average funding per pupil in England and in North Somerset. I was extremely concerned about the figures given in the ministerial response that I received. They showed that average funding for pupils in North Somerset had been consistently lower than the national average for a great number of years, and that the trend was set to continue. In 2004&ndash;05, pupils in North Somerset will receive &pound;340 less on average than other pupils across England. That adds up to an &pound;11 million shortfall this year in education for the region.</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/4">North Somerset has consistently ranked among the lowest-funded LEAs in England, and the provisional figure for 2004&ndash;05 shows that the trend is continuing. North Somerset is currently ranked 121st of the 150   LEAs in England and Wales for secondary school funding and 134th for primary school funding. The model that is used to calculate the funding needs of each LEA is fundamentally flawed. The relative affluence of the Woodspring constituency has been overvalued, and the significant social and financial deprivation in areas of Weston-super-Mare has been grossly undervalued. The funding model appears to bear little recognition of the difficulty and costs associated with addressing the needs of small groups in isolated areas. Rural poverty is not a consideration in the model. Those factors added together ensure that schools in Weston-super-Mare are not receiving a fair level of funding and are struggling to maintain standards.</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/5">Those levels of underfunding are certain to have an effect on local schools and education services. Teachers in Weston-super-Mare have worked extremely hard to produce excellent exam results, but cracks are beginning to appear in other areas. Presented with the figures for underfunding, I decided to conduct a survey among local head teachers to learn more about how poor funding levels were directly affecting local schools and education services. I questioned 37 head teachers about how underfunding had affected their schools and asked them to provide specific details of those effects. I   circulated the survey to 37 LEA schools in my constituency, comprising five secondary schools, six infant schools, four junior schools and 22 primary schools.</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/6">Twenty-five head teachers responded to the survey, and the results were deeply concerning. Almost two thirds of those surveyed said that underfunding had affected their school. More than half said that it had affected resources and equipment, and a third said that it had affected the appointment of teaching staff. Almost a quarter of those surveyed said that large class sizes were a problem in their schools. The general comments made by head teachers were also alarming. One wrote:</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/7" class="indent">&quot;If I had known the extent of under-funding, I would not have applied for a headship in North Somerset.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/8">Another wrote:</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/9" class="indent">&quot;Years of under-funding in North Somerset is now taking its toll on the quality of education on offer.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/10">Those are just a few of the outcomes of the survey, but   head teachers also identified many other significant    problems caused by Government underfunding. They included the impossibility of implementing Government-set targets in certain areas. One example is teachers' planning, preparation and assessment time. As I am sure the Minister is aware, from September 2005, all schools must guarantee their teaching staff a minimum of 10 per cent. of their timetabled teaching time as PPA time. In order to guarantee that that time can be spent away from the classroom, head teachers must have support staff available to provide cover. However, the lack of funding means that local heads are unable to hire the staff that they need.</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/11">For example, Mr. Bruce Dale, head teacher of Mendip Green first school in my constituency, said:</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/12" class="indent">&quot;By the time you've paid the wages, there's little left with which to appoint auxiliary staff.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/13">The cost to local schools of employing additional staff for PPA time will be &pound;65,000 to &pound;70,000&mdash;money that these schools simply do not have. It will therefore be impossible for most schools in North Somerset to meet this Government-set target, for which they could again be penalised with reduced funding. That is clearly unfair.</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/14">The environment in which pupils are taught has also been affected by underfunding, according to local head teachers. Indeed, 41 per cent. of head teachers surveyed said that underfunding had affected their school buildings and maintenance. Many such buildings have seen very little refurbishment since they were built, which for some schools goes back to the 1950s.</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/15">To put the problem into context, I shall use an example involving Mr. Ron Richards, the head teacher at Priory community school in my constituency. He had to organise a meeting with the school's business manager to check whether it was okay to replace a 27-year-old faulty central heating boiler. He said:</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/16" class="indent">&quot;I didn't have a choice about paying for it to be fixed, but it has already put our maintenance budget into the red. In this day and age, it's incredible we have to worry about minor, but necessary expenses such as this.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/17">In such a situation, there should have been no question about the cost of the repair. It should simply have been done automatically. To put it quite simply, schools in Weston-super-Mare and the constituency as a whole should be better funded so that necessary expenses such as those incurred by that basic maintenance requirement can be dealt with immediately and do not create such a significant problem for the school's budget.</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/18">I must take a moment to credit the teachers in my constituency who have worked extremely hard to ensure that pupils in Weston receive the best possible education. However, in order to fund projects in schools and ensure a high level of education, head teachers are forced to look for increased funding wherever they can find it. Many are forced to apply for grants simply to top up their funding to national levels. Grants are all very well, but gaining them requires a lot of time and preparation, and there is not always certainty. Applying for grants is time consuming, but without them, the schools in my area would be unable to provide much-needed education services. Head teachers are therefore forced to spend their precious time completing grant applications one after the other, rather like beggars.</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/19">The education problems in Weston have previously been recognised by the Government. As I am sure the Minister is aware, in 1998, Weston became one of the first 25 education action zones to be established by the    Government. That meant additional funding of &pound;750,000 a year for three years, subsequently extended to five years. Following on from that, Weston was transformed into an excellence cluster on <phrase class="date" code="2003-09-01">1 September 2003</phrase>. That means &pound;650,000 of additional funding for schools across the zone and ensures that all the secondary schools receive leadership incentive grants.</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/20">I admit that those grants and that additional funding have enabled Weston schools to provide services that otherwise would have been impossible with the basic funding levels. For example, Worle community school has been able to run a learning support learning to provide extra support for pupils with special education needs. Since the establishment of that unit, no permanent exclusions have been made at the school. The head teacher, Trevor Bailey, believes that that is largely attributable to the unit.</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/21">Excellent work has been done as a result of the grants that have been received, but those grants and additional funding from the excellence cluster scheme will end in April 2006, and there are currently no Government plans to renew the funding. If basic funding levels remain as they are, several services in local schools will have to be scrapped. Local schools should not have to rely on those Government grants to provide much-needed services. The basic funding level should be sufficient to carry the provision of necessary services.</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/22">Head teachers in my constituency have expressed grave concern about the short termism of the Government's attitude. Special grants are a help in schools, but part of what they do is simply cover up for a short time the fundamental problems caused by the lack of basic funding. The only way to ensure the long-term future of education services and projects in local schools is to provide improved basic funding year on year.</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/23">Teachers in my constituency work extremely hard to try to ensure that the shortfall in education funding is not translated into a shortfall in local pupils' education and opportunities. They have taken on a great deal of additional responsibility and given up their own time for that purpose. Several teachers have brought to their schools resources and equipment such as paper and pens from their own homes to use in lessons as they know that funding is simply not available to provide enough of those resources in their schools. Bruce Dale of Mendip Green school, whom I have already mentioned, said:</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/24" class="indent">&quot;The lack of funding is ridiculous. It has meant buying everyday school items is fast becoming very difficult.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/25">The increased pressure on teachers to maintain high standards in local schools is unacceptable and inevitably means problems with retaining local staff. Why work in a school in North Somerset with low funding and increased stress when one can move to a different LEA for increased funding and decreased stress, work the same job and receive the same rate of pay?</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/26">I ask the Minister to take note of what I am saying today. We have a genuine problem. The consistently low levels of Government funding for North Somerset have caused cracks to appear in the education system in my constituency. Despite the continued hard work of local head teachers and their staff, it is inevitable that, without the necessary funds, they will not be able to prevent the growing problems. Head teachers are battling to climb a descending escalator, and as they have admitted in the survey, in some areas they are beginning to lose the service that they have provided until to now.</p>
	<p pid=".88.1/27">Pupils across the country deserve the same standard of education and the same opportunities, but the current funding levels are beginning to put pupils in my constituency at a distinct disadvantage. Many of these pupils already come from deprived areas and simply deserve a better deal. In the light of the increasing problems and the growing concerns of local head teachers, I ask the Minister to look again at the funding model and the levels of funding for North Somerset. I should also like him to meet me and head teachers so that we can discuss the way forward.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.91.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.91.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.91.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1295" speakername="Derek Twigg" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Education and Skills"  colnum="91"  time="011:15:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h02.htm#50126h02_spmin0">
	<p pid=".91.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/822" name="Brian Cotter">the hon. Member for Weston-super-Mare (Brian Cotter)</phrase> on securing this debate, and I note his concerns about education funding in North Somerset.</p>
	<p pid=".91.0/2">I would like to start by talking about the performance of schools in North Somerset. When we speak about education in the House, it is important to recognise the outstanding work that is carried out in our schools. I am pleased that figures published in April 2004 show that there are now 3,900 more teachers in schools in the south-west than in 1997 and 500 more teachers in the region than in 2003. The &quot;School Workforce in England&quot; statistical release shows that in the south-west full-time equivalent teacher numbers have increased from 36,300 in 1997 to 40,200 in 2004. The number of   support staff has increased from 13,100 in 1997 to 23,200 in 2004. In North Somerset, regular teacher numbers have increased from 1,360 in January 1999 to 1,500 in January 2004&mdash;a 10 per cent. increase. Over the same period, the number of school support staff working in the county has risen by almost 50 per cent., from 490 to 730. The teacher vacancy rate in January 2004 was 0.4 per cent.; there were five vacancies.</p>
	<p pid=".91.0/3">I want to put on the record my gratitude for the work of the teachers and pupils in North Somerset who have been responsible for significant improvements in the quality of education in the county. For example, the percentage of pupils leaving primary schools in North Somerset who are doing well in English has risen from 70 per cent in 1998 to 79 per cent in 2004. In maths, the figure has risen from 64 per cent to 77 per cent, and in science it has risen from 78 per cent to 89 per cent. I am sure that hon. Members will agree that that represents outstanding work in primary schools.</p>
	<p pid=".91.0/4">Looking at the transition into secondary education, there is equally impressive evidence of what is happening in North Somerset at key stage 3. Some 75 per cent. of pupils achieved level 5 and above in 2004, compared with 72 per cent. in 1998; in mathematics 78 per cent. achieved that level, compared with 65 per cent. previously; and in science 73 per cent. did so compared with 61 per cent. I am pleased that the number of pupils achieving the important five A to C grades in their GCSEs has continued to increase steadily, moving from 50.9 per cent in 1998, compared with the national average of 46.3 per cent., to 54.9 per cent. in 2004, compared with 53.7 per cent. nationally.</p>
	<p pid=".91.0/5">On funding, it is worth reflecting on the increases in funding that North Somerset has received since this Government came to power. We estimate that, between 1997&ndash;98 and 2004&ndash;05, North Somerset's total funding per pupil has increased in real terms from &pound;2,690 to &pound;3,520&mdash;an increase of &pound;830. Capital investment has also greatly increased. In 1997&ndash;98, capital funding in North Somerset was &pound;4.3 million. Its 2004&ndash;05 allocation is &pound;27.1 million, while for 2005&ndash;06, the allocation so far is &pound;17.9 million.</p>
	<p pid=".91.0/6">Looking ahead to the national picture, recurrent funding for schools will increase by about &pound;2 billion in 2005&ndash;06. As the hon. Gentleman will know, last July, my hon. Friend the Minister for the Cabinet Office announced school funding arrangements for 2005&ndash;06. Further details were announced as part of the provisional local government finance settlement early in December. The settlement builds on the package of funding measures introduced in 2004&ndash;05 in response to the funding difficulties of the previous year.</p>
	<p pid=".91.0/7">The settlement for 2005&ndash;06 promotes continued stability and certainty in school funding. For 2005&ndash;06, all secondary and special schools will have an increase in their budgets of at least 4 per cent. per pupil where pupil    numbers stay the same. The guarantee for primary and nursery schools is higher, at 5 per cent. per pupil, which recognises that those schools need extra support to implement the final phase of the work force reforms from September 2005, as the hon. Gentleman mentioned.</p>
	<p pid=".91.0/8">We have also ensured that every LEA has the resources, headroom and flexibility to deliver the guarantee and provide support to help schools facing additional pressures. Next year, all LEAs will receive an increase in their school formula spending share of at least 5.5 per cent. per pupil. North Somerset's increase is significantly higher, at 7.2 per cent. per pupil, and follows its above average increase of 6.5 per cent. per pupil in 2004&ndash;05. Also, standards fund support, school standards grant and LSC funding for sixth forms will all increase by 4 per cent. for 2005&ndash;06. Of course, we expect LEAs to play their part in ensuring that funding reaches schools. We expect them to assess and support the needs of every school and to ensure that resources, on top of the minimum guarantee, are targeted effectively to deliver the highest possible standards.</p>
	<p pid=".91.0/9">The point has been made that North Somerset receives lower funding than many other authorities. Although North Somerset has, like other authorities, benefited from the significant increases in funding that   the Government have committed to education, the funding on a per pupil basis is below the national average. Indeed, I understand that the hon. Gentleman tabled a parliamentary question last September about the level of funding per pupil.</p>
	<p pid=".91.0/10">I have checked with my officials, and we have not received any representations in the past year from the    LEA about any serious concerns regarding underfunding in schools. I take the point about seeking a meeting, and I shall certainly see whether we can arrange a date and time. I shall come back to the hon. Gentleman on that, but I stress that we have so far received no representations from his LEA saying that there are specific problems in schools in his constituency.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.93.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.93.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.93.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.93.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.94.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.94.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.94.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.94.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.95.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.95.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.96.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.96.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.96.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.96.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.96.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/717" speakername="Kevin Barron" colnum="96"  time="014:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h03.htm#50126h03_spnew0">
	<p pid=".96.1/1">Through you, Mr. Deputy Speaker, I thank the Speaker for selecting this topic for debate this afternoon. Although there are not many Members present in the Chamber, the issue is one that concerns Members of both Houses. I shall put the debate in context by discussing what brought about the referral to the National Institute for Clinical Excellence and its guidelines as well as the work of the all-party group on infertility, of which I am chairman and of which some Opposition members are present.</p>
	<p pid=".96.1/2">I am sure that it is clear to many people in this House and outside that one in seven couples in the United Kingdom will experience problems conceiving at some point in their reproductive life. For about two thirds of them, the only way in which they will successfully conceive is through treatment consisting of either the use of ovulatory stimulatory drugs or techniques such as in vitro fertilisation&mdash;commonly known as IVF.</p>
	<p pid=".96.1/3">Unfortunately, although the World Health Organisation recognises infertility as a public health problem, the condition has not received public funding to allow those with fertility problems to receive treatment on the national health service as patients with other health problems do. As a result, about 80 per cent. of couples have to resort to paying for their own treatment, the cost of which can run to tens of thousands of pounds. Even in areas where funding is available, couples can be on a waiting list for years and might exceed the age limit before they receive treatment. I suspect from the evidence that I have received from my local primary care trust that in years to come there will be a increase in the age of people on the NHS waiting list, who cannot afford the option of turning to the private sector for treatment. Many people are forced into the private sector for treatment because of non-availability of the treatment on the NHS, although I accept that the Government are trying to make the system fairer than it was 12 months ago; I shall come on to the detail of that later.</p>
	<p pid=".96.1/4">The all-party group on infertility works closely with the National Infertility Awareness Campaign, which is an umbrella body formed in 1993 as a development of national fertility week. It was established with the support, which it continues to enjoy, of all the major infertility charities, patient support groups, most members of the medical profession dealing with the subject, and the pharmaceutical industry. I am not sure whether I should declare the fact that I also chair the all-party pharmaceutical industry group, although I have no pecuniary interest in that respect.</p>
	<p pid=".96.1/5">Most of us are generally dissatisfied with the level of infertility treatment that our constituents receive. I have been an MP for more than 20 years, and I have encountered about six cases in which I have sat with a couple who could not afford to go to the private sector as others can. I have shared both their disappointment with what was not happening in the national health service, and their disappointment as a result of wanting a family but, unlike many of us, being unable to have one without difficulty.</p>
	<p pid=".96.1/6">In November 2000, following pressure from NIAC, other stakeholders and, I suspect, from MPs, the Government asked NICE to produce a clinical guideline on the treatment and management of infertility. The Secretary of State for Health at that time, my right hon. Friend for Darlington (Mr. Milburn), made it plain in a Department of Health press release at that time that his aim was to ensure that</p>
	<p pid=".96.1/7" class="indent">&quot;infertile couples get fairer, faster access to clinically, cost-effective and appropriate treatments.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".96.1/8">In May 2003, NIAC approached supportive parliamentarians for their assistance in setting up an all-party group on infertility, both to raise awareness in Parliament of infertility issues and to maintain pressure on the Government to drive forward implementation of the guideline. As I recall, the guideline was at that time   in draft form but had been leaked to the press. Some extraordinary claims were made in the press&mdash;for   example, that the guideline would cost up to &pound;400 million&mdash;and some cancer charities were dragged into the debate, saying a choice would have to be made between infertility treatment or dealing with cancer. I thought that was a misguided debate and do not know how it reached the press, but as a consequence of that initial debate, the all-party group was formed.</p>
	<p pid=".96.1/9">At first, we put together a report with a group of experts working in the field of infertility in both the public and the private sector. The report outlined the structures needed to meet the NICE recommendations in full and was timed to coincide with the guideline's publication. Exactly what NICE was likely to recommend in its final report was no secret after the first leak of the draft, and we and the specialist group concentrated on that. In particular, the report recommended ways to achieve cost savings in the investigation and treatment of infertility by streamlining procedures, avoiding the duplication of tests and treatment and reducing the numbers of embryos transferred.</p>
	<p pid=".96.1/10">The report also discussed concerns surrounding the commissioning of infertility services and the problems associated with that following the move towards specialised commissioning by PCT consortiums. The aim was to demonstrate to PCTs how the guideline recommendations could be met in the most cost-effective way&mdash;that refers to what the then Secretary of State said back in 2000. Copies were sent to all PCTs as well as to the Department of Health&mdash;my hon. Friend the Minister for Public Health will have received one&mdash;and since then the group has continued to raise awareness in Parliament of the plight of infertile couples and the need for speedy and full implementation of the guideline.</p>
	<p pid=".96.1/11">It might be useful to say what the key recommendations in the guideline were. They were, first, that all women should be screened for chlamydia before they undergo procedures to check whether their fallopian tubes are blocked; secondly, that women who have no history of problems with their fallopian tubes should be offered an X-ray to see if their tubes are blocked, rather than an invasive procedure; thirdly, that couples with unexplained infertility problems, slightly abnormal sperm count or mild endometriosis should be offered six cycles of intra-uterine insemination; and fourthly that couples where the woman is aged between 29 and 39 who have an identified cause of their fertility problems or unexplained fertility of at least three years' standing should be offered three cycles of stimulated IVF. Our report certainly looked at far more than just IVF, but I suppose that IVF took the lion's share of the debate because of its costs and the pressures on the health service to supply it. We might have been remiss in not looking at the guideline as a whole, because the focus is on IVF treatment issues and the deadline of April this year. However, there is a lot more in the guideline that I would have liked the NHS to address, but up to now, according to my information, it has not done so.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.98.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.98.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.98.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.98.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.98.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.98.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.99.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.99.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.99.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/717" speakername="Kevin Barron" colnum="99"  time="014:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h03.htm#50126h03_spnew4">
	<p pid=".99.0/1">That is correct. The Secretary of State is not with us, and the Minister for Public Health probably will not know the answer to this question, but it would interesting to ask why that criterion was put in the Department of Health press release at that time. There were many others that could have been in there that would operate locally as well.</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/2">Although NIAC and the all-party group welcomed the Secretary of State's announcement as a starting point for full implementation, there was a degree of disappointment about the lack of any clear time frame for the remaining two IVF cycles to be put into place. As is now well-known, one cycle offers approximately a 25 per cent. chance of conceiving, compared to 70 per cent. chance of success over the recommended three cycles. Waiting lists tend to consist of women who are getting near to the age cut-off, and my local PCT is saying that they will treat women who were under 40 when they started treatment until they are 42 years old, and then the cycles will be over. That is very important.</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/3">On <phrase class="date" code="2005-02-25">25 February</phrase>, the same day that the announcement was made, I actually rose at Prime Minister's Question Time and asked him directly when he expected full implementation of the guideline. He responded to me, saying that he hoped that</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/4" class="indent">&quot;over the next couple of years we shall see at least very substantial progress towards implementation of the full NICE guidelines&quot;.&mdash;[<phrase class="offrep" id="debates/2004-02-25.278"><i>Official Report</i>, 25 February 2004; Vol. 418, c. 278</phrase>.]</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/5">Of course, &quot;the next couple of years&quot; is substantial progress from the Secretary of State's less forthcoming</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/6" class="indent">&quot;In the longer term I would expect the NHS to make progress towards full implementation&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/7">That was also in the Secretary of State's press release of <phrase class="date" code="2005-02-25">25 February</phrase>. That phrase, &quot;in the longer term&quot;, was reiterated last year by my hon. Friend the Minister for Public Health when she addressed the June 2004 national infertility day conference.</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/8">It has been nearly a year since the NICE guidelines were published, and the PCTs should have the necessary structures in place by now to meet the April deadline for providing at least one full cycle of IVF to all eligible couples. I alluded earlier to the fact that I have kept in touch with what is happening in my locality, primarily through the good offices of Dr. John Radford at the Rotherham primary care trust, whom I have known for many years and who is leading on commissioning for a group of PCTs. Last week I received a draft paper that sets out the criteria for access to NHS-funded specialist fertility services for patients who are the responsibility of 13 primary care trusts. I am sure that this time last year I would have been very happy that people were looking at commissioning infertility services in that way, particularly in areas where there was no cover for issues such as IVF, as <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1034" name="Andrew Lansley">the hon. Member for South Cambridgeshire (Mr. Lansley)</phrase> said earlier.</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/9">The 13 PCTs in question cover the North Derbyshire, South Yorkshire and Bassetlaw commissioning consortium&mdash;Bassetlaw being north Nottinghamshire from a geographical perspective. The consortium is known as NORCOM. Two of the PCTs covering my constituents in Rotherham. The paper sets out the draft   minimum entitlement across the consortium to NHS in vitro fertilisation, intracytoplasmic sperm injection and   intra-uterine insemination. There are currently significant differences between the NORCOM PCTs in respect of existing specialist fertility treatment policies, and phased introduction will be required to bring them all to one common policy. It is envisaged that each PCT will adopt at least the minimum eligibility criteria, and it is not intended that any of them will adopt a more restrictive policy than their current one. The present policy in Rotherham is to offer two cycles, so I am glad the consortium has addressed that issue. I have had anecdotal evidence, which I will not use in this debate, that there has been a reduction in the IVF treatment on offer. I would be interested to know if my hon. Friend the Minister has any evidence of that.</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/10">The NORCOM document continues,</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/11" class="indent">&quot;Initial investigation of patients is usually carried out by a network of specialist gynaecologists at District General Hospitals throughout the NORCOM area&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/12">The report published by the all-party group on the day that the guidelines were published considered whether specialist centres were needed. I understand they operate in Scotland. I would be interested, if my hon. Friend has time today, to hear whether she thinks we should consider that option. The document continues:</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/13" class="indent">&quot;In any healthcare system there are limits set on what is available and on what people can expect. Primary Care Trusts are required to achieve financial balance; they have a complex task in balancing this with individuals' rights to health care. It is the purpose of the criteria set out here to make the limits on fertility treatment fair, clear and explicit. Nationally this is undertaken through the work of the National Institute for Clinical Excellence and this paper reflects this. The paper should be read in conjunction with the NICE Fertility Guidance.</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/14" class="indent">&quot;The NICE Guidance places NHS assisted fertility services firmly in the mainstream of NHS provision&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/15">I think everyone, no matter where we are at this stage, should be pleased about that. I certainly am. The paper then states:</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/16" class="indent">&quot;Patients as a result will expect the NHS to provide this. This document includes recommendations for the first part of the phased introduction of the Guidance. Further phases of the implementation will be defined in the light of future Department of Health requirements and the prioritisation and availability of resources&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/17">It goes on to list a series of criteria the that will be used in that commissioning area. What is interesting about the &quot;mainstream&quot; comment is that from now on, I assume, the PCTs in my area will be looking to central Government for direct guidance about what they should do next, and when they should do it. One issue has been dealt with, because it was centrally driven, so PCTs will expect direction from the centre on what should happen next and when.</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/18">In her speech to the national infertility day conference last year, the Minister said that the April deadline was &quot;a starting point&quot; to support PCTs in meeting the first stage of implementation and the subsequent implementation of the guidelines in full. The Department of Health agreed a broad programme of action last June, and last year the Minister answered parliamentary questions that I and other hon. Members tabled on this issue. Part of the programme was that the Government would</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/19" class="indent">&quot;look to strategic health authorities (SHAs) to work with PCTs to ensure that they have effective arrangements in place for the provision of services, to investigate the barriers to implementation of NICE guidelines and to help ensure that the barriers can be    overcome.&quot;&mdash;[<phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2004-10-04.1978"><i>Official Report, </i>4 October 2004; Vol. 424, c. 1978W</phrase>.]</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/20">The programme also included advice from NICE on the development of resource templates to enable PCTs to estimate the resources needed.</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/21">The Minister will realise that a number of key questions remain about PCTs' progress toward meeting the April deadline. In part, that is what this debate is about. Are PCTs being monitored, are strategic health authorities playing their part and are they and NICE providing assistance? Does NICE have a further role to play? NIAC and the all-party group are keen to learn what support the Government are providing to PCTs, given that no additional funding has been provided either to meet the April deadline or to assist with the implementation of the guideline in full. What will be the repercussions for PCTs that fail to meet the guidelines? That question is relevant at this stage in the countdown to April.</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/22">The next issue is the old chestnut of NHS waiting lists. Will there be action by the NHS centrally to measure and, we hope, reduce waiting lists for couples needing infertility treatment? Now that the Government have gone so far as to ask for the delivery of one IVF treatment cycle by this April as part of the start of implementation of the guidelines, we could not accept people having to be on waiting lists for months, if not years, to get that first IVF intervention. I would be grateful if the Minister had any comments on that.</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/23">It must not be forgotten that even if PCTs meet the deadline to provide at least one full cycle of IVF, there will still be postcode provision of infertility services in the United Kingdom. People in Scotland can access up to three cycles: I am led to believe that in the constituency of the Secretary of State for Health, for example, couples have been entitled to three cycles for a number of years. That is unlike the position in my area, although the position there is a vast improvement on that in some areas of England and Wales, in which there has been no offer of IVF treatment under any criteria for many years past.</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/24">Access to infertility treatment on the NHS is well known to be patchy&mdash;indeed, treatment by postcode remains an intolerable feature of the NHS. We called for the debate to stress to the Government the need for full implementation of the guideline to ensure that couples have access to the most effective treatment, regardless of where they live. Fair and equal access for all those with an established need is the only way to tackle the unacceptable postcode lottery of treatment.</p>
	<p pid=".99.0/25">It is crucial that the NICE recommendations are implemented as fully and as quickly as possible throughout the country to ensure fair and equal access for all. As the Secretary of State said last year, we cannot expect all areas, particularly those that have never offered any IVF treatment, to be achieve that overnight. I think that we all accept that. However, 12 months have elapsed since publication of the NICE guideline. I hope that, by now, we are in a position to have an idea whether the <phrase class="date" code="2005-04-05">5 April</phrase> deadline for the single IVF treatment cycle will be met and&mdash;given that we are now looking at implementing the second phase&mdash;an idea of the timetable for the second and third IVF intervention if other fertility services have failed the couples involved.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.102.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.102.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.102.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/769" speakername="Paul Burstow" colnum="102"  time="014:25:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h03.htm#50126h03_spnew5">
	<p pid=".102.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/717" name="Kevin Barron">the right hon. Member for Rother Valley (Mr. Barron)</phrase> on securing the debate. I share his disappointment that others cannot be present to take part in it, but I pay tribute to him for his work as chair of the all-party group on infertility and for giving us the opportunity to explore how far the Secretary of State's undertakings in respect of the NICE guidance have been implemented.</p>
	<p pid=".102.0/2">I would like clarification of the two phrases that were used by the Secretary of State and the Prime Minister: what is the difference between long term and substantial progress in the next couple of years? The debate should be about getting some idea of the timelines involved. The right hon. Gentleman posed some important questions that I want to take up; I also have a few questions of my own for the Minister.</p>
	<p pid=".102.0/3">The issue is charged with emotion; it is about the fundamental desire that very many of us have to have children. Infertility frustrates that desire, which is further frustrated if a person does not have the financial means necessary for private sector provision and as a result has to go on an NHS waiting list. Prior to the NICE guidelines, about 70 to 80 per cent. of couples paid for private treatment. It is not long since the NICE guidelines were published and the Secretary of State expressed the desire that at least one cycle of IVF be available to couples in each PCT area. Can the Minister say how much she expects that to change? Will there be a reduction in the number of couples who will need to pay privately to have the treatment as a result of the guidance being implemented?</p>
	<p pid=".102.0/4">The right hon. Gentleman has already given some of the figures but it is worth repeating one or two of them: approximately one in seven couples in the UK need help in conceiving a child and rely on treatment, either ovarian stimulatory drugs or IVF. Figures available up to 2001, supplied to my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1348" name="Paul Marsden">the Member for Shrewsbury and Atcham (Mr. Marsden)</phrase> in June last year, suggested that 28,076 patients had received IVF in that year, which was an improvement on 1997, and that 2,718 had received donor insemination in the UK, which was down from 1997. It puzzles me that more up-to-date figures than those for 2001 are not available. I hope that the Minister can shed further light on the matter and update the figures, so that we can see what progress has been made.</p>
	<p pid=".102.0/5">The NICE recommendations have been described in detail by the right hon. Gentleman, who is absolutely right to draw attention to the fact that most press reporting of those guidelines and the Secretary of State's response to them tended to dwell more on the number of cycles of IVF than on other aspects of the guidance. It is right to reflect that the guidelines referred to a host of other issues, not least that of screening, which is an important safeguard. At the time, the chief executive of NICE said:</p>
	<p pid=".102.0/6" class="indent">&quot;Implementation of our guidance will take time. We have therefore suggested to the Department of Health and Welsh Assembly Government that they consider giving advice to NHS organisations on how they should approach putting our recommendations into practise.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".102.0/7">The debate is about the Secretary of State's advice and to what extent it should be just that; should it be   about social considerations and how they affect the   criteria formulated by the PCTs in framing their approach to implementing the NICE guidance? The Secretary of State said on <phrase class="date" code="2005-02-25">25 February</phrase>:</p>
	<p pid=".102.0/8" class="indent">&quot;As a first step, by April next year I want all PCTs, including those who at present provide no IVF treatment, to offer at least one full cycle of treatment to all those eligible.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".102.0/9">The Minister later emphasised that that is the starting point. However, it is not clear from anything that has been published or said to date what the subsequent steps will be. What is the timeline for getting us from where we are now, which is patchy provision of IVF and of NHS fertility services generally, to the ideal that the NICE guidelines set out? What progress has been made in achieving that first step?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.103.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.103.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.103.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.103.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.103.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/769" speakername="Paul Burstow" colnum="103"  time="014:25:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h03.htm#50126h03_spnew7">
	<p pid=".103.1/1">I agree entirely. It would be wrong of PCTs to interpret the Secretary of State's comments in last year's press release as relieving them of their obligation to set out their plans for implementing the    NICE guidelines. I hope that the Healthcare Commission will look carefully and critically at the extent to which PCTs have done that. It should also evaluate whether the April deadline in the arbitrary timetable set out by the Secretary of State is a sufficient response to the NICE guidelines.</p>
	<p pid=".103.1/2">I will go one step further and say that it would be useful if the Minister confirmed the status of the Secretary of State's statement. Does it have any formal force in terms of what PCTs should be doing? In particular, what is the status of his comment about giving</p>
	<p pid=".103.1/3" class="indent">&quot;local priority to couples who do not have any children living with them&quot;?</p>
	<p pid=".103.1/4">Surely in an NHS where the balance of power is shifted to local providers to make decisions of that sort, the Secretary of State should not give that sort of instruction, or implied instruction, to the NHS.</p>
	<p pid=".103.1/5">There are a number of concerns about the Secretary of State's recommendations, some of which the right hon. Member for Rother Valley itemised. First, the NICE guidelines come with a price tag attached, but exactly how much will they cost to implement? No additional resources were provided to allow the services to be developed; it is therefore incumbent on the Government to set out how they will assist PCTs and how they expect PCTs to plan for the implementation&mdash;not what they should do, but the mechanisms that they might wish to follow.</p>
	<p pid=".103.1/6">As the right hon. Gentleman said, the anecdotal evidence seems to point to a timeline that runs at least six years into the future. It would be useful if the Minister said whether that is a realistic assessment of how long it will take to implement the NICE guidelines fully. In answer to the right hon. Gentleman's question, the Prime Minister said that it would be a couple of years before we saw substantial progress. Yet when one looks at the NHS figures between 1997 and 2001, one sees that although the number of women having access to a cycle of IVF increased, the average number of cycles per woman decreased, and some people are concerned that access to more than one cycle will decrease further. The PCTs that already offered access to more than one cycle will take the opportunity of following the Secretary of State's advice from last year to level down, rather than to maintain their service at its current level. It is therefore important to monitor the situation at local level to ensure that that does not happen. As the right hon. Gentleman said, there is a 25 per cent. success rate from one cycle, but that rises to 70 per cent. with three.</p>
	<p pid=".103.1/7">I believe that Lord Winston expressed some concerns about the policy of offering one cycle, describing it as &quot;half-baked&quot; due to the financial and emotional costs of investigating whether a couple is suitable for treatment. There is a huge emotional commitment to going down that road, yet after making that commitment couples could be told, &quot;You've had your one chance&quot;, even if they are reaching the age where they will no longer be able to gain access to the treatment. Infertility treatment is a huge investment for a couple, which is more than just financial.</p>
	<p pid=".103.1/8">There is also concern about specialised commissioning&mdash;tertiary commissioning and tertiary fertility services&mdash;and to what extent the roll-out of such commissioning is occurring. There is concern that the still patchy nature across the country of PCTs engaging with specialised commissioning will again slow the process of implementing the NICE guidelines. I would welcome the Minister's comments on that matter.</p>
	<p pid=".103.1/9">Can the Minister say whether the Department has   assessed of the cost of implementing the NICE guidelines in full? I should be surprised and stunned if the Department had not made some assessment. Does the hon. Lady plan to share the Department's figures with us? I hope that she does. Is the figure of about &pound;50 million, which was the assessment made by the all-party group, a realistic assessment of the true cost of full    implementation throughout the country? What discussions have taken place with Scottish Ministers, who are already supporting a three-cycle policy in Scotland?</p>
	<p pid=".103.1/10">There are financial pressures in the NHS; we need only read the <i>Health Service Journal</i> from one week to the next to learn about those pressures and their consequences. At present, there is a &pound;500 million deficit in the NHS, which I am sure will disappear magically by <phrase class="date" code="2005-03-31">31 March</phrase> until <phrase class="date" code="2005-04-01">1 April</phrase> of the following financial year. However, there is a real financial problem that the PCTs must grapple with. They have to find the resources to achieve the targets that are set by Whitehall, and everything else for which there is no target becomes a lesser priority. The NICE infertility treatment guidelines might fall into the second category, and we doubt whether the necessary resources will be delivered.</p>
	<p pid=".103.1/11">As we have heard, the anecdotal evidence suggests that progress is patchy. There are concerns that having one IVF cycle as a first step will give a green light to some PCTs to reduce the number of cycles that they provide. I hope that the Minister can tell us today what the plan is beyond the first step, whether that plan is on course, and when it will deliver. Will it be in six years, or in a couple of years? There are thousands of people outside the House who want the answers to those questions because they matter to them and their lives.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.105.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.105.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.105.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1034" speakername="Andrew Lansley" colnum="105"  time="014:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h03.htm#50126h03_spnew8">
	<p pid=".105.0/1">I    join <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/769" name="Paul Burstow">the hon. Member for Sutton and Cheam (Mr. Burstow)</phrase> in congratulating <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/717" name="Kevin Barron">the right hon. Member for Rother Valley (Mr. Barron)</phrase> on securing this debate. I also thank the right hon. Gentleman for the work that he has done as chair of the all-party group on infertility; as vice-chairman of that group, I have seen that work at close quarters and I know what a close and dedicated interest he has taken in the work of the group. He has also secured influence over the subject, which I hope is reflected in the context of the debate. I do not disagree with anything that has been said. However, I shall elaborate a little on some points and try to capture some of the questions that I am sure that the Minister is expecting to answer. I hope that there will be ample time for her to do that.</p>
	<p pid=".105.0/2">This debate is not the first occasion on which we have discussed infertility&mdash;indeed, the history of debates on the subject goes back further than the right hon. Gentleman took it. On <phrase class="date" code="1998-05-06">6 May 1998</phrase>, the Minister's predecessor, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1007" name="Tessa Jowell">the right hon. Member for Dulwich and West Norwood (Tessa Jowell)</phrase>, responded to an Adjournment debate in which I participated. Agreeing with the comments of my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1243" name="Caroline Spelman">the Member for Meriden (Mrs. Spelman)</phrase>, I said</p>
	<p pid=".105.0/3" class="indent">&quot;there is a case for national guidelines&quot;&mdash;[<phrase class="offrep" id="debates/1998-05-06.662"><i>Official Report,</i> 6 May 1998, Vol. 311, c. 662</phrase>.]</p>
	<p pid=".105.0/4">The then Minister said that the Government's policy objective was to ensure national consistency. At that point, it was intended to achieve that through national service frameworks and the National Institute for Clinical Excellence; subsequently, it has been done through NICE guidelines. We are therefore more than six and a half years past the point when the Government signalled their intention of getting rid of the postcode lottery for infertility treatment.</p>
	<p pid=".105.0/5">As the right hon. Gentleman said, the then Secretary of State for Health asked NICE to undertake the preparation of guidelines in November 2000. What happened then is a classic illustration of one of the key policy issues. While NICE was preparing the guidelines, there should have been a sense of what the developing consensus was likely to be, because work did not start from a blank sheet of paper: eminent bodies had already been examining the issue. Between November 2000 and February 2004, primary care trusts and others working in the field should have made themselves aware of what capacity would be needed to supply the infertility treatments that were likely to be recommended as both clinically effective and cost effective. That is what should happen when NICE does its work in future, but there is little evidence that it happened in the present case until the NICE guidelines were published in February 2004. NICE activity was a reason for there to be, in effect, planning blight in the system: services were not being developed. Therefore, in November 2000 the policy of some PCTs, including in my area was to provide assisted conception only in exceptional cases.</p>
	<p pid=".105.0/6">That illustrates something that has always depressed me since back in 1998, which is that the NHS is investing time, quality effort and resources into the investigation of infertility, but only those patients who are able to afford assisted conception are able to have treatment. That was certainly the case in my constituency, and my constituents justifiably regarded it as deeply unfair that they were unable to access assisted conception when in other parts of the country they would have been able to do so. We are trying to get rid of that. We want to establish a degree of consistency and a good standard of    service. There is a special irony in relation to my   constituency: the Bourn Hall clinic is in South Cambridgeshire. It is where the IVF treatment was conducted that led to the birth of the first test-tube baby, Louise Brown, in 1978. Bourn Hall was at the forefront of the provision of those services. It was deeply frustrating that people who lived in the same area as Bourn Hall could not access its services unless they were able to pay for them.</p>
	<p pid=".105.0/7">I am keen to achieve consistent delivery of infertility services. From time to time there are debates about the relative priority of IVF and infertility services. I have had them with constituents and colleagues in the House, and PCTs and health authorities have debated where the priority lies. Should resources go to infertility as distinct from other pressing health needs? Such judgments are always invidious.</p>
	<p pid=".105.0/8">We are now reaching the point where it can be seen that the job of the NHS is not simply to deal with the problems of physical ill health, but to achieve, wherever possible, a sense of well-being in the community and to   promote positive public health. We should not underestimate the psychological and social harm that can result for couples who desperately want to have children but who are unable to do so. Equally, we should not underestimate the social benefit and enormous good that can result from enabling such people to have the opportunity of parenthood; the children would be loved and wanted. As it would depress us to discuss them, I   will not go into the circumstances of unwanted children, children who are unloved by parents and not looked after by them, and the number of pregnancy terminations.</p>
	<p pid=".105.0/9">If the NHS should, for the reasons I mentioned, provide infertility services, what does it make sense to do? The question of providing one cycle of IVF was touched on by the hon. Member for Sutton and Cheam. The point of the debate is that NICE examined what was not only clinically effective, but cost effective for the NHS to provide. The evidence, which I do not think is disputed, shows that to provide three cycles of IVF broadly speaking gives one, in each of those first three   cycles, a good chance of conception; The figures vary but let us say it is a 20 to 25 per cent. chance. That number falls off dramatically after three cycles. Subsequent cycles are much less likely to have a positive result. The same is true of age. Beyond a certain age&mdash;35&mdash;the chances of conception diminish; the balance that the NICE guidelines struck was 39. The same would also be true for body mass index. There are clinical criteria, so we can avoid the NHS pushing resources into the provision of treatments that have much less chance of success.</p>
	<p pid=".105.0/10">Having said that, the object of NICE was to produce a sound evidence basis on which treatment could be provided across the NHS. I hope that NICE will have the opportunity to do much more such work. Its work should establish a standard that patients, their clinicians and GPs should be able to access and that the NHS knows it should be gearing up to provide.</p>
	<p pid=".105.0/11">The hon. Member for Sutton and Cheam was kind enough to allow me to intervene during his remarks to highlight something that happened in February 2004. There ought to have been a straightforward process: even if PCTs had not prepared for the NICE guidelines, at least in the subsequent local delivery plans they should have set out a process, which, according to the NICE guidelines in paragraph 3.1 would have been straightforward. PCTs would look at the template and set up the kind of implementation process that is required; in a local delivery plan, they would show their timetable for delivery of the service. Such a process does not require them to do it tomorrow, nor does it set a rigid timetable, but it would have enabled every PCT to be accountable for how and when it will deliver the standard. I cannot see what purpose was served by the Secretary of State intervening to say, &quot;Oh, by April 2005 you should have delivered one cycle of IVF,&quot; but not giving any indication of what would happen thereafter or to what timetable it should happen. Would it not have been better simply to have said, &quot;We know what standard we are aiming for&quot;?</p>
	<p pid=".105.0/12">I hope that it is not true that some PCTs are reducing the service that they provide simply in order to meet the aim of providing one cycle of IVF. That is not true in my area because we are, in a sense, gaining services from a very low base. I also hope that the situation does not mean that there will be primary care trusts that make no provision and establish no plans to go beyond April 2005 and meet the NICE standard. The object is to meet that standard and to know when that will happen.</p>
	<p pid=".105.0/13">It would be instructive if the Minister could tell us precisely what steps the Department, or the SHAs on behalf of the Department, will take to ensure that PCTs show how they will meet the standard. It is not clear, for   example, how the Healthcare Commission will do that, it is to inspect against core standards only. The performance rating that the Healthcare Commission will construct for primary care trusts will reflect those core standards, but we do not know whether it will embrace developmental standards in 2005&ndash;06, and to what extent this particular aspect of NICE guidelines will be included in that. None of that is set out yet, and it is not in the Healthcare Commission's consultation, which is too vague to enable us to establish whether there is any requirement on PCTs to show how they will meet the guideline. Clearly, that is an area that needs to be considered.</p>
	<p pid=".105.0/14">What we seek is an explanation of what the Secretary of State intended by his intervention in February 2004. We also want to know how the Department will achieve the delivery of services to the standard set out in the NICE guidelines, on which I hope we all agree. As I see it, there are two possible explanations why the Secretary of State referred to one cycle of IVF. The implication at the time was that it had to do with available capacity, not cost. Members of the all-party group had a number of discussions with those involved in the provision of infertility services; it seemed perfectly clear to me that although there are some capacity constraints, they are not such that they would require service provision to be restricted to one cycle of IVF. In many parts of the country, it would be perfectly possible to provide access to three cycles of IVF, and generally across the country we can scale up services to that level quite quickly. There is a passing difficulty associated with some of the smaller units, which might have been affected by the introduction of new European Union directives, which had implications them, but they would reduce capacity only temporarily.</p>
	<p pid=".105.0/15">If the ability to access services is the problem, the Department can publish the evidence on which it based its judgment. If, however, the issue is not capacity, it must be cost. The hon. Member for Sutton and Cheam asked about that. The all-party group looked into the costs and benefits associated with changes in infertility services, and we reached a conclusion that seemed balanced and reasonable to us. If the Department reached the same conclusion, it raises the question why one cycle of IVF was the constraint placed upon such services. In terms of expenditure and the reduction of cost to PCTs, that is much more drastic a constraint than would have resulted from dividing &pound;50 million among 300 PCTs across the country. The sort of costs implied to PCTs were not so great.</p>
	<p pid=".105.0/16">The third point relating to the Secretary of State's intervention is where the additional social criterion came from. As the right hon. Member for Rother Valley said, it raises serious questions about the impact on couples if, for example, the children in the home are those of either partner's previous marriages or partnerships. It can therefore place mothers and fathers in a difficult situation in which their access to infertility services and their chance to be a father or mother is deprived by the application of a rather arbitrary criterion. Where did it come from and why was it necessary?</p>
	<p pid=".105.0/17">As everyone who has spoken in the debate has stressed, can the Minister say precisely how the Government envisage the timetable from now to the full implementation of the NICE guidelines? The review of the guidelines is probably due in about 2008. I hope that well before we reach that point, we will have had the chance to see how the standards are being met throughout the NHS and the benefits that are flowing from them, so that another review does not happen a few years down the line. We do not want to be here again debating why people are subject to a postcode lottery and, in particular, why expensive resources in the NHS are being used to support investigations and why only those who can afford it subsequently receive treatment.</p>
	<p pid=".105.0/18">I cannot tell hon. Members the number of times that I have been castigated by the Government, whose inaccurate view is that my party is somehow not concerned about access to services being based on need, rather than ability to pay. We believe in NHS services that are based on need. We are discussing an NHS service that is intended to be provided but which, at the moment for many people, is available only if they have the ability to pay. We know what service the NHS ought to provide. I hope that that will be achieved and that the Minister will tell us how and when.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.109.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.109.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.110.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.110.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.110.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.110.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.110.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.110.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.110.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.110.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.110.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1000" speakername="Melanie Johnson" colnum="110"  time="014:57:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h03.htm#50126h03_spnew12">
	<p pid=".110.3/1">Although there are no formal means of instruction, there are informal means of conveying messages. Strong messages would have been sent.</p>
	<p pid=".110.3/2">There are questions about the implementation of the guideline. I will come on to monitoring, the structured arrangements surrounding that and the amount of contact that there has been.</p>
	<p pid=".110.3/3">First, the guideline covers an enormously sensitive subject. Infertility causes huge distress. Because of that and the historical postcode lottery, the Government felt   that this was a worthy area on which NICE could produce a guideline, one with a commitment on implementation. The definition of infertility is given as a failure to conceive after regular unprotected sexual intercourse over two years, in the absence of a known problem. Implementation has priorities, such as screening for chlamydia and assessing tubal damage. Nobody mentioned chlamydia in the debate, but it is enormously important in this context, because it is increasingly causing infertility, and we are storing up a problem in the longer term. We must put the questions together&mdash;hence the huge investment in the whole area of sexual health and sexually transmitted infections.</p>
	<p pid=".110.3/4">There are six cycles of intra-uterine insemination for    couples with mild male infertility problems, unexplained fertility or minimal to mild endometriosis. Contributions to the debate have mainly concentrated on the couples qualifying for up to three cycles of IVF. The guideline provides a consistency of approach across the health service. In welcoming that, we looked to PCTs to meet, by April this year, a national minimum provision of at least one cycle of IVF for those who meet the clinical criteria in the guideline. Our purpose was to put down a landmark to show that progress had begun to be made.</p>
	<p pid=".110.3/5">My right hon. Friend the Member for Rother Valley recently wrote to me on behalf of the all-party group, suggesting that the group's estimate of the costs involved was about &pound;36 million. We believe, on the basis of the work done by NICE, that the cost of full implementation will be about &pound;80 million. A number of Members have asked about the figures. They are already in the public domain; certainly, I wrote to my right hon. Friend about them.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.111.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.111.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.111.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.111.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.111.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.111.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.111.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.111.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.112.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.112.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.112.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.112.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.112.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.112.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.112.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.112.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.112.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1000" speakername="Melanie Johnson" colnum="112"  time="014:57:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h03.htm#50126h03_spnew20">
	<p pid=".112.3/1">Advice on those matters would certainly have come to Ministers, but I am not sure that there is any formal report or study of the kind that the hon. Gentleman is looking for, or anything that would be published.</p>
	<p pid=".112.3/2">We expected PCTs to give priority to those in greatest need. Hon. Members have referred to couples with no children living with them and those who have children, or a child of one or other of the couple, living with them. It was felt that if PCTs had to prioritise, some help should be given to them on how to do that, and it was fairest to prioritise those who had no children living with them. Hon. Members can disagree with that if they want to, but we had to look at a difficult situation and make some difficult choices rather than leave PCTs without any advice from the centre about how they prioritised those choices. That is not to say that couples with children living with them are not to be considered at all. I am talking simply about a ranking of priorities and a reflection of advice to PCTs.</p>
	<p pid=".112.3/3">We rely on the NHS locally, through the PCTs, taking account of the needs of the local population and discussing proposals with patients and the public. That debate is happening in the context of the resources that are allocated to the health service rising to record levels, from &pound;69 billion in 2004&ndash;05&mdash;the financial year just ending&mdash;to &pound;92 billion in 2007&ndash;08. The sums that we have been discussing should therefore be seen in the context of a lot of extra money that is going to the health service. Overall, the national average increase over that time is nearly 31 per cent. in cash. There is a real-terms increase for Rotherham PCT of 6.5 per cent. in 2003&ndash;04, 7 per cent. in 2004&ndash;05 and 6.6 per cent. in 2005&ndash;06. That is only a sample, but it is typical and representative of the increases across the wider NHS.</p>
	<p pid=".112.3/4">My noble friend Lord Warner, who speaks on health matters in another place, wrote to the NHS on <phrase class="date" code="2004-06-14">14 June 2004</phrase> to set out a programme of action to support the implementation of the NICE guidance and set that in context with the Government's overall policy for national standards in the NHS. He made it clear that broad partnership in local health economies is needed to ensure that patients get access to the quality of care that is recommended by NICE. However, that entails strategic health authorities working with PCTs to ensure that they have effective arrangements in place, are investigating barriers to implementation and are making sure that those barriers can be overcome. Lord   Warner's letter referred to the Department's consultation on national health care standards for the NHS in England, which is now published as &quot;Standards for Better Health&quot; and includes a standard for patients to receive effective treatment and care that conforms to nationally agreed best practice, particularly as defined in NICE guidance. There is a direct link between the NICE guidance, the standards for better health care and the work of the strategic health authorities.</p>
	<p pid=".112.3/5">In relation to the NORCOM consortium arrangements, I am delighted that there is a wide consortium of 13   PCTs in my right hon. Friend's area that has developed a local commissioning policy based on the NICE guidelines. We are pleased to see that sort of local co-operation and partnership. To some degree, such arrangements answer the point raised by <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/769" name="Paul Burstow">the hon. Member for Sutton and Cheam (Mr. Burstow)</phrase> about specialist commissioning and people working together across PCTs. There are a lot of specialist commissioning arrangements for different services, including infertility services: they are growing in sophistication and effectiveness and we welcome and encourage them.</p>
	<p pid=".112.3/6">What progress are PCTs making towards implementing the NICE fertility guideline? The NHS has needed time to take account of the guideline and draw up its plans, but we know that PCTs are working together. The evidence that we have says that they are   working hard to implement the guideline and are focusing on moving in the right direction, for example, by offering one cycle of IVF where previously they offered none and maintaining services at least at the current level where they offer more than the minimum. If any hon. Member has anecdotal evidence to the contrary, we shall be happy to consider it, but we have no such evidence other than that which I mentioned earlier, which we investigated.</p>
	<p pid=".112.3/7">I agree that monitoring implementation is important. Overall, SHAs are responsible for overseeing PCTs' performance. If a PCT fails to implement the guideline, SHAs will explore the reasons and work with that trust to overcome the barriers. The independent Healthcare Commission, which reports directly to Parliament on the state of health care in England and Wales, will use the standards in assessing health care provision. The chief executive of the Healthcare Commission has confirmed that assessing the implementation of NICE guidance is one of the commission's priorities. It is currently consulting on the assessment process that it will apply.</p>
	<p pid=".112.3/8">I note that the NIAC is conducting a survey of PCTs, in partnership with the all-party group, I believe. We shall be interested to see the results of that survey. If barriers to implementation are identified, we shall bring them to the attention of the relevant SHAs. The basic principle is that PCTs, in liaison with local health bodies and patients' groups, take resources and priorities into account when deciding how best to implement the guideline.</p>
	<p pid=".112.3/9">On devolution versus standards and targets, I have to argue a little with the hon. Member for Sutton and Cheam. I am sure that his comments on the subject were entirely well meaning, but they were somewhat muddled. There cannot be complaints about instructions and, at the same time, complaints that we are not tackling the issues. We must balance the need to give guidance and advice, to steer and to provide frameworks that drive progress with local commissioning and local production of services. One could argue that giving instructions works against local commissioning, but local commissioning might lead to ongoing postcode lotteries if developments do not take place within the right framework. We must achieve the right balance between putting a framework in place and local decision making on priorities and how to achieve them. That is what we have sought to achieve.</p>
	<p pid=".112.3/10">I have already mentioned that we put the costs of full implementation at about &pound;81 million. We know the standard that we are aiming for: to achieve full implementation of the NICE guidance. We recognise that PCTs are starting from different places, which means that we are not in a position to give a formal plan beyond this year, but I am sure that we shall consider that after this year's implementation phase. We shall be look to see what the future holds, but I am sure that there will still be some PCTs on two IVF cycles and others that have only just achieved one. We need to work on that and allow what are felt to be the most appropriate choices to be made in local health economies.</p>
	<p pid=".112.3/11">My right hon. Friend the Member for Rother Valley asked about waiting lists and other hon. Members raised questions about sanctions. Before I address those points, however, I should like to say that our estimate of the effectiveness of cycles is slightly different my right hon. Friend's. Our estimates are that the pregnancy rate is about 25 per cent. for one cycle of IVF, about 33 per cent. for two cycles and about 50 per cent. for three cycles, which is slightly lower than the figures he quoted. I am sure that the figures vary according to the population on which they are based. However, those figures are the best that we have and are the ones to which we are working.</p>
	<p pid=".112.3/12">The hon. Member for South Cambridgeshire is right to say that there comes a point at which there is a fast-diminishing return. That is something that NICE considered. Hard as it might be for many couples to accept, we must recognise the problem and the advice that NICE gave us.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.114.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.114.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.115.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.115.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.115.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.115.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.116.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.116.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.116.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1000" speakername="Melanie Johnson" colnum="116"  time="014:57:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h03.htm#50126h03_spnew24">
	<p pid=".116.0/1">I understand my right hon. Friend's point. When we came into government, waiting times in some cases were 18 months&mdash;and that was only for in-patient admissions, including the out-patient wait. Now, the process will last a maximum of 18 weeks from start to finish, and given that that is the maximum waiting period, some people will be coming in earlier. To hit our target, we shall probably need to hit about 10 to 12 weeks for most patients&mdash;we shall need to bulk them in the middle of the period to achieve the maximum wait target&mdash;so we shall be able to offer a substantial improvement across the board. In so far as it can, the strategy will encompass patients who are experiencing infertility problems and a number of other patients who have complicated diagnostic and treatment schedules.</p>
	<p pid=".116.0/2">The hon. Member for Sutton and Cheam asked about the need for private treatment. I find it difficult to answer his question, however, because we do not know how many people on NHS lists are already going for private treatment or will go for it at some point. It is very to know how great the double-counting element is, and we do not necessarily have access to all the figures from the private sector.</p>
	<p pid=".116.0/3">On the number of people receiving treatment, the HFEA will fairly soon be updating the figures that the hon. Gentleman mentioned, which were from 2001. That follows work on its database of treatment services. It generates the figures, because it collates them nationally.</p>
	<p pid=".116.0/4">I think that that deals with all the points that have been raised. The debate has been useful and has raised useful issues. We are committed to an improvement in the services offered to infertile couples and particularly to progress towards full implementation of the NICE guideline as soon as NHS services can achieve that. We are committed to ensuring that the implementation due in April 2005 takes place. We welcome feedback on issues or difficulties, which we shall take seriously, and we look forward to the channelling of some of our huge investment in the NHS into improvements to fertility services.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.117.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.117.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.117.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.117.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.117.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1282" speakername="Paddy Tipping" colnum="117"  time="015:26:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h04.htm#50126h04_spnew0">
	<p pid=".117.1/1">I am delighted to have the opportunity to introduce this short debate and equally delighted that the Minister for the Arts is here to respond.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/2">The Minister will recall that we had a similar debate about children's play 15 months ago, on <phrase class="date" code="2003-11-03">3 November 2003</phrase>. There have been several developments since then.   The report &quot;Getting Serious About Play&quot;, which my right hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/856" name="Frank Dobson">the Member for Holborn and St. Pancras (Mr. Dobson)</phrase> produced, was published on <phrase class="date" code="2004-01-21">21 January 2004</phrase> after a fairly long period of gestation. Indeed, when we last debated this matter, we talked about how long it had taken for the report to be published.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/3">Just last week, on <phrase class="date" code="2005-01-16">16 January</phrase>, my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Culture, Media and Sport responded to what I shall characterise as the Dobson review. I am pleased to say that that ended a long period of uncertainty. The process has been fairly lengthy, and people from the play sector, and particularly the voluntary sector, have been involved in the discussions. The lack of decisions has caused uncertainty. There has been a positive outcome, but on the more negative side, people from the play sector were concerned about what the outcome would be.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/4">It might be helpful for me briefly to recount the history of the review of children's play. Just before the previous general election the then Secretary of State</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/5" class="indent">&quot;outlined the Government's intention to kick off Britain's biggest ever children's play area building programme in a second term.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/6">He went on to say that &pound;200 million from round 4 of the   New Opportunities Fund would be earmarked to   create 2,000 new children's safe play areas. That announcement was received with great applause from people connected with children's play, because they saw it as a real opportunity. Almost four years on, and as we approach another general election, whenever it will be, we have an opportunity to take stock of what has been achieved since that time.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/7">Last week, the Secretary of State said that the Government</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/8" class="indent">&quot;reaffirmed its commitment to revitalising children's play areas up and down the country with a huge investment from across lottery distributors.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/9">She added that she</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/10" class="indent">&quot;expected &pound;200 million of lottery money to be spent on new and improved play opportunities.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/11">I welcome that clarification; the news is to be welcomed and I do not disparage it. However, I know that the Minister will not mind my saying, as this is a fact, that that does not quite match up to the original commitment made four years ago.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/12">That is the case because, first, that spending is an expectation, to use the Secretary of State's words, and not a firm guarantee. Put another way, it is an aspiration rather than a pledge. Secondly, the spending of &pound;200   million would be across all lottery distributors, while the original pledge was that &pound;200 million would come from the New Opportunities Fund. It is therefore no surprise that the play sector was promised and hoped for more. Thirdly, the planned spending period in which the money will be available runs from 2006 to 2012&mdash;a slightly longer period than was originally envisaged. Fourthly, and most importantly, the announcement makes it perfectly clear that, although the aspiration is to provide &pound;200 million, that money is not earmarked or ring-fenced. It is not there specifically for children's play.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/13">There is no point trying to disguise the disappointment, concern and perhaps anger in the play sector about the disparity between the two pledges. There was a delay in coming to a decision and there is a strong view that the pledge has been watered down. I shall quote one or two people from the play arena. Angela Neil, a participation worker for Torbay children's fund, said:</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/14" class="indent">&quot;On behalf of local projects within the Torbay area, I would like to voice our serious concern over the fact that it seems the promised extra lottery money will not now be made available. Many groups have worked long and hard to be in a position to apply for some of this 'promised' money. Dear Secretary of State for Culture, Media and Sport, please keep your promise to give the extra &pound;200 million lottery money to play.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/15">Perry Else, who works on children's play in Sheffield, said, in effect, &quot;We have done a lot of work&quot;. I quote:</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/16" class="indent">&quot;We've set up a coordinated partnership approach to provide for the city's 110,000 kids aged 5&ndash;14, but where's the money?&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/17">Returning to my own area, my old colleague Rachel Adams said of Nottingham that she was</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/18" class="indent">&quot;very concerned about the lack of information on the 'Play Review Money'&mdash;&pound;200 million. Discussions have already taken place locally about how this money could be spent in the area&mdash;trying to gain a consensus on the most pressing needs and on how finance can contribute to sustainable development.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/19">All those people are effectively saying, &quot;We worked hard alongside the Dobson review. We were promised &pound;200 million and the money that is available is not quite what we anticipated.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/20">I acknowledge that point, but in this debate I want to be positive. I say clearly that &pound;200 million is still a significant amount. I know that the Minister will make that point. Whatever has happened in the past, we need to try to move forward, as they say, and to work in a positive and constructive way. I have been impressed by the approach of the new distributor, the Big Lottery Fund. I have been particularly impressed with its chief executive, Steve Dunmore. Mr. Dunmore has been around the sector. He has talked to it and seems willing to listen, engage and consult. Everybody welcomes that step forward.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/21">While ring-fencing the &pound;200 million has been ruled out, the consultation on future spending plans for the Big Lottery Fund provides a possibility for it to consider different workstreams, frameworks and programmes. I hope that there will be continued discussion on that. We have between &pound;100 million and &pound;200 million between 2006 and 2012. How can it best be spent? What kind of framework can we put in place to ensure that that money is wisely spent? The play sector is keen to be involved in those discussions.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/22">In her announcement last week, the Secretary of State expressed her desire to meet the authors of the report, &quot;Getting Serious About Play&mdash;A Review of Children's Play&quot;, together with the lottery distributors. Although such a meeting would be helpful, a lot of value would be added if not only the authors of the report and chairmen of the lottery distributors were invited, but key figures from the world of children's play. They would not be hard to identify. My only direct request to the Minister today is that they be invited.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/23">The announcement has been made and there is disappointment, but it is important to move forward and build a consensus on the direction of children's play. I hope that the Minister will seriously consider my request, because I want a number of things to come out of any such meeting and discussions. I am clear that we ought to use the principles of the Dobson review about the future funding of children's play. A lot of work has gone into that; people have devoted a lot of time, and there is, by and large, consensus on the way forward. It would be sad if the underlying principle of the review were thrown away.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/24">The worst thing that could happen would be that a blank canvas with &pound;200 million was made available and groups were told, &quot;You come and bid, and we'll allocate on a piecemeal basis.&quot; That &pound;200 million is a lot of money; it is a shot in the arm for children's play. I hope that we can develop some programmes and a framework to enable us to spend that money wisely, so that it is not only strong bidders who get money, and there is a more thoughtful approach to building benefits across the sector.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/25">One theme of the Dobson report is focusing money on   areas of disadvantage. I hope that we will pick up that theme. If we look at where lottery funds have traditionally been spent, we see that affluent areas have   generally tended to do better than areas of disadvantage, unless help and support is given to people, and capacity is built in neighbourhoods to bid for those funds. I hope that we will focus on such disadvantage.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/26">From my experience of looking around the sector, I   know that there is an awful lot of good practice in children's play, although there is also poor practice. We ought to identify the best practice and promote good practice, and try to roll it out across the sector. The sector agrees with that approach and would strongly support it.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/27">I am keen that we should continue the process of involving children and their parents in planning the kind of play provision that they want in their areas. It is interesting to listen to children talk about play. They have strong ideas about local needs and solutions. When one asks parents about their priorities for their neighbourhood, one thing comes high on the list: safe and exciting things for children to do. I hope that we will also pick up on that theme.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/28">I also hope that the work being done by good local authorities working in partnership with the voluntary sector and the play sector to build plans for areas&mdash;not only plans that run from now, but approach plans over a period of years&mdash;will continue. If the play sector were invited to a meeting of the kind envisaged by the Secretary of State, it would not be long before there was agreement that such principles should underlie the funding of children's play and the distribution of the &pound;200 million.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/29">I want to focus on two points that were raised in our last debate. The Minister will remember that slightly lively discussion, in which I was anxious that lottery funding was additional and was not a substitute for mainstream local authority funding. I am keen to see such an approach, as I see signs across the sector of local authorities delaying in bringing forward play projects while the decision on the &pound;200 million was made. In a sense, I want that &pound;200 million to be cornerstone money that is used to build new development. I do not want local authorities and other funding bodies to be let off   the hook; I want lottery funding to stimulate development across the piece. We can do that, and there is good will for us to achieve it.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/30">As we now know, commitments on lottery funding for children's play are not for ever. It is quite clear that the money envisaged from the Big Lottery Fund runs from 2006 to 2012. It is important that we use that six-year period to develop an approach to children's play that we can learn lessons from, because when lottery funding falls out, as it inevitably will, those lessons will ensure that we can keep the programme going. Again, there is wide support across the sector for that approach.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/31">Before I conclude, I want to return to another theme that formed part of our last discussion. I have now followed children's play for 25 years or so; I have long ceased to be a practitioner; I call myself a philosopher on the subject instead. One thing that has struck me throughout those 25 years is the fragmentation of funding bodies for children's play. In terms of what happens in Whitehall, the Department for Culture, Media and Sport is rightly the lead Department, but the Department for Education and Skills has a stake. The Home Office also has an interest in the matter, and the Office of the Deputy Prime Minister is also a clear player, because of a range of activities connected with local authorities. I hope that one thing to come out of the review and the discussion of the &pound;200 million&mdash;this aspect is acknowledged by the Secretary of State&mdash;will be greater emphasis on co-ordinating the approach.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/32">We can add value to children's play simply by making sure that we work better together. We ought to be able to use the planning and regeneration process, for example, to create marvellous examples of children's play. I am not confident that we are doing that at present, and neither am I confident that it is happening at a local authority level. Again, at district and county council level, the approach to play is fragmented. I note that very few performance demands are made on local authorities around children's play.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/33">I had a look at &quot;Every Child Matters: Change for Children&quot;, and I saw an elaborate graph at the back of the report showing who is responsible for what, yet children's play features only slightly in it. I am keen to raise its profile across the board in our approach to children. It would not be impossible for us to look at the notion of public service agreements with local authorities in respect of play, and it would not be hard to identify some clear targets that the Government could set.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/34">As I said at the outset, a lot has happened over the past couple of years&mdash;or since the last manifesto was prepared and the commitment of &pound;200 million for children's play. As all the parties now look towards their manifestos, I am keen that we see children's play as a way of preparing children and their families, as well as their local neighbourhoods, for the future. Investment in children is investment in the future, and investment in children's play is investment in all our futures. I hope that this short debate has contributed to the manifesto process.</p>
	<p pid=".117.1/35">The Minister has a longstanding commitment to children's play: &pound;200 million is a significant amount. We can get a great deal of action and a lot of change if the   Government, the lottery, the local authorities and the voluntary sector in particular work together in neighbourhoods to bring about change that will benefit not just children but the whole community.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.121.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.121.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.121.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1123" speakername="Estelle Morris" speakeroffice="The Minister for the Arts"  colnum="121"  time="015:46:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h04.htm#50126h04_spmin0">
	<p pid=".121.0/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1282" name="Paddy Tipping">the Member for Sherwood (Paddy Tipping)</phrase> on securing another debate on the subject of children's play. It does not seem a year since our last debate on the subject, but it has been. I    acknowledge my hon. Friend's contribution to keeping children's play high on the parliamentary agenda and his commitment to the issue throughout his working life; the two are very much intertwined. As I    said in the previous debate, it is essential that Parliament has the expertise of people who have delivered a service as well as being able to talk about it, and my hon. Friend has done both.</p>
	<p pid=".121.0/2">I apologise for the delay in responding to the report. There are several reasons for that, none of which is related to the Government's, or the Department's, attitude to play or their obstinacy in getting round to replying to my right hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/856" name="Frank Dobson">the Member for Holborn and St. Pancras (Mr. Dobson)</phrase>. It is not the job of those who work in the sector to understand the intricacy and bureaucracy involved in Government decisions, and it must have seemed an inordinate amount of time to them. I am grateful to my hon. Friend the Member for Sherwood for not exploiting the delay in the meantime and damaging the trust between the Government and the sector even further.</p>
	<p pid=".121.0/3">The crux of the matter, as my hon. Friend said, is that   things have moved on and the commitment to &pound;200 million ring-fenced from the lottery fund has got into the same policy area as reform of the lottery. Had that not happened, there would not have been a delay and I would not be in the slightly difficult position of justifying what I accept is different from what was pledged originally. The intentions are clear, and I think we can reach a similar end, albeit by taking a slightly different route.</p>
	<p pid=".121.0/4">The irony in the reform of the lottery is that we are responding to the voluntary sector. On the whole, people do not want ring-fencing; they do not want the Government to intervene, or the top-slicing of grants for   something that the Government want. All hon. Members know, from their time in politics, that everyone hates those pots of money unless they get one. I suspect that one part of the voluntary sector has had its money taken away at the very point when it was going to get a ring-fenced amount. If I were part of the voluntary sector and that happened, I would feel very cross.</p>
	<p pid=".121.0/5">However, in the wider sense, it is right that Governments should be less hands-on in terms of the NOF part of the funding. It also goes to show that the   voluntary sector, which will include the play community, will have access to the millions of pounds that were formerly spent through the New Opportunities Fund, to which they had no access. They were rarely the chosen partners of delivery. The top-line message is that the announcement may not be as bad as the play sector thinks. It gives it slightly less certainty, because the &pound;200 million ring-fenced pot was a belts-and-braces measure.</p>
	<p pid=".121.0/6">I will respond to one point in particular, which I hope will be helpful, and then answer questions and put on the record how we wish to proceed. As my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State made clear, and as my hon. Friend said, we anticipate, or whatever word we chose to use, that because our approach to the lottery is hands-off, it is far more difficult for us to give an absolute pledge, but it is more than an aspiration. I aspire to a great deal&mdash;in terms of layers, there are some things that I will aspire to all my life and will never achieve, but this proposal is not in that arena. As much as Ministers can with the new arrangements for the lottery, this may be more of a determination to do all that we can to ensure that it is delivered. However, the decisions will be for the Big Lottery Fund to make.</p>
	<p pid=".121.0/7">I was pleased with, grateful for, and appreciative of, the comments that my hon. Friend made about Stephen Dunmore and the meetings that they have had so far. I want to say one thing that he did not mention, which I think will bring some assurance to the set down. One of the essential matters will be to ensure that the amount of money spent on play is monitored. I do not want a Minister in 2012&mdash;they will still be a Labour Minister&mdash;to have to come back to an Adjournment debate and suddenly be faced with the question of whether &pound;200 million was spent over six years. The sector needs to know what progress it is making towards the &pound;200 million during those six years.</p>
	<p pid=".121.0/8">I confirm that my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State is prepared to meet not only the lottery funders but the Children's Play Council, Tim Gill and my right hon. Friend the Member for Holborn and St. Pancras. I suggest that the Children's Play Council may want to put on the agenda the question of how the lottery distributors will monitor how much money is spent on play. That is important because I know that we are building trust where the terribly long delay has damaged it. If I can help in that, I will.</p>
	<p pid=".121.0/9">My hon. Friend raised a point about the need for cross-departmental work. We will have to see how that progresses, but I wanted to raise the importance of the issue. I am here on two counts: play is part of the remit of culture, media and sport, but in this case play is also about the lottery fund. However, so many Ministers could have answered a debate on play&mdash;those from the Department for Education and Skills, the Office of the Deputy Prime Minister, the Department of Health or the Home Office. Such is the contribution that play can make to children's lives in so many areas that those Departments all have a responsibility. If we turn that around, every one of them can contribute to play through their policies.</p>
	<p pid=".121.0/10">My hon. Friend is right to say that, try as we might, cross-departmental working does not come easily to Ministers, for no other reason than the pressure of time.   We have made an essential first step: now, my Department regularly meets each of the Departments that I have mentioned and is beginning to draw up a Government agenda for play by drawing together existing strands. The advantage of doing that in such a way is that one does not start again. Seeing where various Departments are on the issue of play and how to bring the existing work streams together works better   than announcing&mdash;heaven forbid&mdash;one of those Cabinet cross-departmental committees that can be the bane of our lives, to start again with a different group of civil servants. Although we are late in starting and we are taking a different journey from the one that we might have imagined, I think that it can still lead us to a situation where &pound;200 million has been spent on play by 2012.</p>
	<p pid=".121.0/11">There are one or two more points to reply to. It is absolutely essential that areas of deprivation are targeted. Historically, more affluent concerns tended to get a larger share of the lottery. My hon. Friend will know as a constituency MP the effort that the NOF and the Community Fund have made to get more money to the coalfield communities and areas of greatest deprivation. The instructions that we will give to the Big Lottery Fund will be about looking after such areas and having regard to the fact that areas of deprivation should benefit most, especially in such matters.</p>
	<p pid=".121.0/12">We must learn from best practice. To some extent, the worst way to spend &pound;200 million would be to give it out to 200, 400 or 1,000 projects, each of which did its own thing, and then, in 2012, to say, &quot;Where do we go from here?&quot; It is essential that there is some planning&mdash;some strategy, to use the word that my hon. Friend did. I hope that some of the work that people have been doing in anticipation of the money can be put to good effect. It needs to be about learning what works, getting an evidence base and bolstering the case for play when the lottery money runs out in 2012. I hope that when they talk to the lottery funders, that will be one of the approaches they can take.</p>
	<p pid=".121.0/13">Lastly&mdash;I believe this to be the case because I have heard it from more than one party&mdash;some local authorities assume that the lottery will pick up the play tab from now on, and they will be able to spend their money on other things. That is a dire warning because, as my hon. Friend said, lottery money runs out, by definition. It was never meant to be long-term funding. Lottery money should serve to yank more money into play. It should lever more money from local authorities and the community, private and voluntary sector. Otherwise, it does not do its purpose. It is an injection, a shot in the arm, for play: getting that evidence base, getting good practice, building capacity and making the argument. By 2012, however, the rest of society must have been sufficiently persuaded that the question &quot;Shall we now stop funding play?&quot; would be a very silly one to ask, because communities could not imagine a time without it.</p>
	<p pid=".121.0/14">Some of the things that my hon. Friend and I have talked about in this worthwhile adjournment debate could form the agenda that must be the basis of a dialogue between the lottery distributors and the play sector in the years to come. I know that is asking more of the voluntary sector and the play sector. I hope that, step by step, we can persuade the doubters&mdash;through our decision to fund aspects of the sector, and some posts there&mdash;that we are serious about that, even if, because of another event, we are approaching it in a different way.</p>
	<p pid=".121.0/15">I am not sure how carefully plotted the timing of this debate was. I cannot recall whether the debate was requested before we responded, or whether the debate forced us to respond a week or two earlier than we might otherwise have done. I would like to think that this fairly long, convoluted Adjournment debate&mdash;upon which I again congratulate my hon. Friend&mdash;is the end of one phase, and has set out the map, dialogue and plan for the beginning of the second. I apologise that the first stage of the journey has been as long as it has, but I am confident that the second can get the trust and partnership back. At the end of the day, I have never heard of any difference of opinion between the Government and the sector about the importance of play.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.124.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.124.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.125.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.125.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.125.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.125.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.128.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.128.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.128.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/703" speakername="Charlotte Atkins" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport"  colnum="128"  time="016:16:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050126/halltext/50126h05.htm#50126h05_spmin0">
	<p pid=".128.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/750" name="Tom Brake">the hon. Member for Carshalton and Wallington (Tom Brake)</phrase> on securing this important debate on the safety of vulnerable passengers on public transport. We take the issue very seriously, and I share his deep concern about the case of his constituent, Janice Norman. I should like to take this opportunity to offer my deepest sympathy to Ms Norman and her family for this terrible loss. I can fully appreciate her desire and determination, backed by her Member of Parliament, to raise awareness of the need to show consideration towards fellow passengers on public transport.</p>
	<p pid=".128.0/2">It is difficult to know exactly how one could collate information about such incidents, as they will be extremely varied. Many years ago, for instance, I was on a tube train with a youngster in a buggy, and I was worried that there was such a crush that people would fall over on top of the buggy. That situation was not life threatening, as in Janice Norman's case, but it was deeply worrying. I agree that the safety and comfort of vulnerable passengers must be ensured as far as possible, and the Government and the train operating companies already do a lot of work in this area.</p>
	<p pid=".128.0/3">As the hon. Gentleman said, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1280" name="John Thurso">the hon. Member for Caithness, Sutherland and Easter Ross (John Thurso)</phrase> tabled a new clause to the Railways Bill seeking to require the Secretary of State to launch a campaign to   encourage passengers to be more considerate to vulnerable passengers and raise awareness of priority seating. My hon. Friend the Minister of State, Department for Transport, acknowledged that this was   a serious subject on which he had been in correspondence with the hon. Member for Caithness, Sutherland and Easter Ross, as well as and with the Association of Train Operating Companies and the Rail Passengers Council. My hon. Friend said:</p>
	<p pid=".128.0/4" class="indent">&quot;In the strict technical sense we cannot pursue the new clause because it would not achieve anything. The Secretary of State has no power to instruct the RPC or ATOC to do anything. ATOC is the umbrella group of a private industry. We could instruct it all we like, but we have no power to tell it to do anything. We have set up the RPC, of old and of new, as an independent body outside Government. It is rather inappropriate for us, having set up an independent body, to then instruct it what to do.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".128.0/5">He went on to say:</p>
	<p pid=".128.0/6" class="indent">&quot;The new clause asks the Secretary of State to instruct two organisations that we have no locus to instruct. However, it goes further than that and would legislate for behaviour. That is the crux of the matter.&quot;&mdash;[<i>Official Report, Standing Committee A</i>, 18 January 2005, c. 294]</p>
	<p pid=".128.0/7">Clearly my hon. Friend could not accept the amendment, but he was sympathetic to the view expressed by the hon. Member for Caithness, Sutherland and Easter Ross. He said that he had written to ATOC and the RPC asking them to consider the matter in more detail and asking whether they would be happy to lend their weight to a broader campaign. He added, and I would also like to add, that we would be more than happy to be party to such a campaign. He also referred to London Underground's &quot;Love is . . . &quot; campaign, which he said had had a modicum of success in focusing on what should be second nature&mdash;consideration of fellow passengers generally, and a high degree of consideration for people such as pregnant women, who are clearly vulnerable.</p>
	<p pid=".128.0/8">The hon. Member for Caithness, Sutherland and Easter Ross stated in the Committee that some train operators, such as South West Trains, Thameslink and South Eastern Trains, also offer complimentary first class upgrades to pregnant women holding season tickets when there are no seats available in standard carriages. My hon. Friend the Minister of State undertook to ensure that train operating companies that use that practice continue to do so, and that those that do not use it consider implementing it. That also raises an issue about ladies who have not got season tickets. Often, a pregnant lady will be more vulnerable if she is not aware of the situation and the trains. If one is a season ticket holder and regularly uses the train, one is more likely to be aware of the situation.</p>
	<p pid=".128.0/9">The Rail Safety and Standards Board, the industry's own safety body, is due to publish a report at the end of the month on the first phase of research into the health and safety effects on rail passengers of crowding on trains. That will include consideration of the different groups of people at risk, such as the very young, the elderly, pregnant women and disabled people. The Rail Vehicle Accessibility Regulations 1998 prescribed a minimum number of seats for the use of disabled passengers. In addition, as the hon. Member for Carshalton and Wallington said, most train operators also designate priority seats for those who have difficulty standing, such as pregnant women and the elderly.</p>
	<p pid=".128.0/10">Our aim is a transport system that works for everyone. We have done much to achieve that aim by improving the accessibility, punctuality, reliability and safety of public transport. However, it is clear that not all groups have benefited equally from our increasingly mobile society. Understanding and recognising the different perceptions and needs of all passengers is fundamental to our transport policy. The Department sponsors a wide-ranging programme of research and consultation on issues such as people's mobility needs and personal security. We have issued good practice guidance to assist planners and providers to deliver services that meet people's needs, including many of the most vulnerable. I am not sure whether that includes guidance on the number or location of priority seats, but I will write to the hon. Gentleman about that. I imagine that some sort of guidance is probably given, but it is clearly guidance and not prescription.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.130.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.130.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.130.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.130.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.131.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.131.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26.131.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-26a.131.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

