<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">

<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >

<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >

<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY micro "&#181;" >

<!ENTITY euro "&#8364;" >
<!ENTITY sup2 "&#178;" >
]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.71.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.71.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.71.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.71.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.71.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.71.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.71.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.71.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.74.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.74.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.74.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.74.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.78.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.78.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.78.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.78.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.78.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.78.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.79.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.79.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.79.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1775" speakername="Vera Baird" colnum="79"  time="10:01:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm051026/halltext/51026h01.htm#51026h01_spnew6">
	<p pid="a.79.0/1">I hope that I do not appear greedy by intervening on the hon. Gentleman straight away.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.0/2">I am worried about the poor representation of the younger Bar by the more senior Bar because of the &quot;strike&quot;, which was, frankly, encouraged by the Criminal Bar Association. Members have been asked to decline to take any brief that comes in after a particular date in October.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.0/3">When I was a silk&mdash;it will be the same for the hon. Gentleman, who is a senior member now&mdash;my case diary was full for months, perhaps even a year ahead. Not taking a case after <phrase class="date" code="2005-10-01">1 October</phrase> would have been no skin off my nose, if I may use a colloquialism. Long before the strike ended, I would have had plenty more cases coming in, and I already had a year's work. The youngsters who get a brief today and have to go to the magistrates court with it tomorrow are the ones who will suffer. That situation was encouraged by the leadership, and I do not like it.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.79.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.79.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.79.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1710" speakername="Elfyn Llwyd" colnum="79"  time="10:01:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm051026/halltext/51026h01.htm#51026h01_spnew7">
	<p pid="a.79.1/1">The hon. and learned Lady is absolutely correct. Several people in my own chambers in Chester are agonising over the problem. I suppose that, by nature, barristers are not likely to strike, but many junior members of my chambers are very concerned. They do not want to stand out and take work that might have gone to others who have declined to accept it. At the same time, exactly as she said, they are at the lower end and have bills to pay.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.1/2">Also, everyone in chambers has received a letter from the Crown Prosecution Service. The letter sent to those on the Wales and Chester circuit and the letter sent to those on other circuits have common paragraphs, one of which is rather threatening. I forget the wording now, but in effect it says, &quot;We are watching you. If you decline briefs now, we will see how we get on when this is all over.&quot; That is very worrying for a junior member of the Bar.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.1/3">There is also the issue of preferment. Many in the judiciary privately believe that the action is right, but that it will inevitably create some difficulty in the courts&mdash;not at the higher end, where the diary is full for I will truncate what I have to say, because the hon. and learned Lady put the case extremely well, but I shall give a bit of background. The graduated fee scheme was introduced in 1997. It was meant for one to 10-day cases and provided weightings to reflect different elements in cases. The original rates for 1997 were based on 1995 fee levels. They have not been increased since then, and that in itself is a real-terms cut of 24 per cent. In 2001&ndash;02, there were more than 17,000 one to 10-day cases, and the average cost was &pound;1,587. In 2003&ndash;04, there were 19,000 such cases, but the average cost was lower, at &pound;1,541. There is already pretty firm control in that area, and I believe that that is right&mdash;there has to be a control on public spending; that is obvious.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.1/4">In 2002, the graduated fee scheme was extended to cases of up to 25 days, with a gradient introduced for longer cases. That in itself provided an important weighting to reflect the gravity and complexity of the longer cases, but there was no increase in rates. In fact, the figure delivered proved to be much lower. So there had been another significant cut to what had been paid before.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.1/5">Finally, in the summer of 2004, the Department for Constitutional Affairs accepted that it had got it wrong. It increased other weightings to make good the shortfall for future 11 to 25-day cases, and extended the fee scheme to 40-day cases. More than two years had passed and the payment was written off, but the DCA promised a vital review of the whole system, to start in May 2005. In the meantime, the total spending on criminal defence rose by little more than half the rate of inflation between 2001&ndash;02 and 2003&ndash;04.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.1/6">Everybody here, and, I am sure, those outside, will be concerned about very high-cost cases. As the hon. and learned Lady said, up to 50 per cent. of the budget goes on a very small number of cases&mdash;perhaps as small a proportion as 1 per cent. Clearly, that needs to be addressed. However, to put a fair case forward, that probably would not detrimentally affect the junior Bar.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.1/7">With regard to cracked trials, the Criminal Defence Service (Funding) (Amendment) Order 2005 cut the amounts to be paid when cases &quot;go guilty&quot;&mdash;in other words, for cracked trials. Guilty pleas are often entered on the day when the trial is meant to commence. That order took &pound;15 million out of barristers' Crown court fees. The saving has not been redistributed to the underpaid one to 10-day cases. On <phrase class="date" code="2005-07-05">5 July</phrase> the DCA announced the removal of the gradient for cases of over 10 days. That reduced the fees payable in those cases to hard-pressed members of the junior Bar by an average of 15 per cent.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.80.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.80.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.81.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.81.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.83.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.83.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.83.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.83.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.85.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.85.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.85.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1791" speakername="Jeremy Wright" colnum="85"  time="10:28:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm051026/halltext/51026h01.htm#51026h01_spnew12">
	<p pid="a.85.0/1">I should also declare an interest: I am a non-practising member of the criminal Bar.</p>
	<p pid="a.85.0/2">As <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1775" name="Vera Baird">the hon. and learned Member for Redcar (Vera Baird)</phrase> said, the difficulty with what the Government have in mind in relation to criminal legal aid is that although the junior Bar would probably have no objection to the redistribution of money from the top ranks of the Bar to the lower ranks, that is not what is going to happen. The Government have indicated that cuts will be made at the lower ranks of the Bar to the criminal legal aid budget, but there will be no corresponding transfer to those ranks. That will create a number of significant difficulties.</p>
	<p pid="a.85.0/3">There is no doubt that there is room for reform in the system of payments to the Bar. I accept that the current system is ridiculous. Based on the amount of preparation I do on a Monday night for a Tuesday morning case as a member of the Bar, I could be paid &pound;46.50 or &pound;1,500</p>
	<p pid="a.85.0/4">a review in May, but it did not materialise. The criminal Bar has been waiting a long time for them to explain their long-term vision.</p>
	<p pid="a.85.0/5">The hon. and learned Lady summed up the issue well. It is not whether we pay high-ranking barristers &pound;200,000 or &pound;300,000 a year; it is whether we can attract the best quality applicants to the junior criminal Bar, not because we compare&mdash;this is where I disagree with her&mdash;the earnings of the junior Bar with average earnings throughout the country. We need to attract the best quality advocates to do the vital job of defending and prosecuting in our criminal courts because they could instead go into other strands of the legal profession, such as the commercial Bar. They could become commercial solicitors or go into other professions with far higher rates of pay. Barristers spend a lot of time and, now, money to train for the criminal Bar. We need to attract them and to retain them. It is not automatic that those who join the criminal Bar become silks and make the sort of money that has been mentioned. It is the junior Bar that needs the Government's attention. I hope that they will give it that attention and they recognise the problems.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.86.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.86.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.89.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.89.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.90.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.90.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.91.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.91.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.91.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.91.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.94.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.94.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.94.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.94.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.94.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.94.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.94.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.94.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.94.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1716" speakername="Phyllis Starkey" colnum="94"  time="11:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm051026/halltext/51026h02.htm#51026h02_spnew2">
	<p pid="a.94.3/1">I shall not give way. I have little time. It is not usual in these debates to give way and I do not intend to do so.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/2">That vision was set out clearly by the Israelis. In 1993, the then Prime Minister Rabin said:</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/3" class="indent">&quot;I prefer the Palestinians to cope with the problem of enforcing order in the Gaza Strip. The Palestinians will be better at it than we&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/4">the Israelis&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/5" class="indent">&quot;because they will allow no appeals to the Supreme Court . . . They will rule by their own methods, freeing . . . the Israeli army soldiers from having to do what they will do&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/6">It seems that Prime Minister Sharon is carrying forward the vision that was set out originally by Prime Minister Rabin.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/7">I am warning against the apartheid state solution because not only is it unjust for the Palestinians, but it is ultimately unsustainable and therefore not in the long-term interests of the Israelis. I wish to make it clear that I accept that Israel has the same right as every other state to protect the security of its citizens, even those who are illegally occupying land in the west bank. However, Israel's right, as with every other state, must be exercised within international law and not, as is too often the case, in complete disregard of the rights of others, notably the Palestinians.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/8">During my stay in Israel, I found that many Israelis, even liberal Israelis, seemed unaware of either the reality in the occupied territories&mdash;the huge depth of poverty and the dangerous well of resentment that is building up there&mdash;or the international community's view of the situation.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/9">In Israel, I was given the national parks authority map, which shows Israel including&mdash;without any internal borders whatsoever&mdash;all the Palestinian territory and the Golan heights, which are occupied Syrian territory. Most Israelis appear to think that those are Israel's accepted borders, but they are not accepted by anyone else. Israelis need to understand that.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/10">I shall start by describing the situation as I saw it in Gaza. The Israeli authorities helpfully demonstrated on my arrival at the crossing point at Erez who really controls Gaza; they kept me waiting there from 8 am until past 4 pm, even though I had an invitation from President Abbas, before suddenly deciding to let me through.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/11">When I arrived in Gaza, I found the atmosphere extremely mixed. On the one hand, there was a huge sense of elation and liberation because all the settlers and Israel Defence Force soldiers had gone. To give people here a feel for what that feels like for ordinary people there, I should say that I visited the rehabilitation hospital, which has a lovely, wheelchair-accessible garden. For the first time, patients and visitors were enjoying that garden completely free from the fear that they would be shot at by IDF snipers; on a previous occasion, two nurses at the hospital had been killed by the IDF.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/12">There were huge rallies all over the place. As we were driving through Gaza, we happened upon an enormous rally organised by Hamas in one of the settlements. Thousands of women and children were pouring in, as tourists in their own territory, to see what the abandoned Israeli settlements were like.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/13">A huge crowd was preparing a rally for the next day down at the Rafah border close to Egypt, in the wasteland that the Israelis, having demolished more than 2,000 homes, had created. After that, my hosts drove me back along the length of Gaza, up the Salah al-Din Road from Rafah to Erez. That was the first time in 16 years that my hosts, who were Gazans, had been able to drive up that road from one end to the other without risking being shot at by the IDF. So there was a huge feeling of liberation.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/14">There is also an optimism in the degree of political consensus, notwithstanding the continued internal security problems and the continued conflict between the armed factions. Even Hamas is hinting that it may accept the two-state solution and recognise Israel, as did the Palestinian Authority in the Oslo agreement. There is a consensus between all factions, including Hamas and Islamic Jihad, on how the settlement land is to be used for the benefit of the whole population to provide for homes and employment. When I met members of the legislative council, they were absolutely insistent that all factions must be able to participate in the elections due in January so that they can build a pluralist and civil society. However, they also stressed that a true democracy needs economic stability.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/15">That brings me to the other, pessimistic side of Gaza. There was widespread despair at the desperate situation of most people there and the lack of solutions. Seventy per cent. of the people are under the poverty line and there is huge unemployment. Living costs are extremely high and are effectively set by Israel. For example, the gas that people use for cooking costs 10 times more than in Egypt because it has an Israeli price, yet people in Gaza are on poverty wages, if they have any at all.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/16">There was a feeling that the settlements had been left like dead bodies, as they were described, for the Palestinians to clean up. The occupation has left an army of the handicapped and disabled; education and health services are overstretched; and schools have 60 to 70 children in a class and often run two sessions. The refugee camps are unimaginably poor and discharge raw sewage directly into the sea. I do not know how the people in the refugee camps survive, as they seem to have no income at all, but are totally dependent on charity and the United Nations Relief and Works Agency.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/17">The Israelis continue to control Gaza. They control the register of all births, and whom can be given Palestinian citizenship. That means that refugees who returned from Jordan after the Oslo agreement and husbands and wives applying under family reunion rules are left in limbo with no citizenship whatsoever.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/18">The UN Office for the Co-ordination of Humanitarian Affairs and the World Bank both agree that although the Palestinian economy is soaking up huge levels of aid from the international community, that aid is simply mitigating the effects of the Israeli blockade. Not only is the international community effectively subsidising the costs of the occupation and relieving Israel, as the occupying power, of the need to provide for the Palestinians; the Israeli economy actually benefits from those donor funds because 45 per cent. of every dollar of aid for the Palestinians is spent in Israel. From 2000 to 2004, the aid doubled to almost $1 billion a year, but because of the curfews and closures actual personal incomes in Palestine fell by 40 per cent. The economy can recover only if external borders are opened, internal borders between Gaza and the west bank are relaxed and Palestinian labour is allowed into Israel. However, Israel continues to control completely all the borders of Gaza, including that with Egypt and the sea and the air borders, which are still not open more than a month after the disengagement.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/19">Even the Quartet's middle east envoy, James Wolfensohn, who is hardly a dangerous liberal, was particularly scathing about Israel's delaying tactics and failure even to allow free movement at Rafah between Gaza and Egypt. He said that the occupation continues, despite the disengagement, because the Israelis are still controlling all the borders.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/20">If I found a mix of optimism and pessimism in Gaza, among Palestinians in the west bank and Jerusalem I found unremitting pessimism. The Israeli Government continue to build the so-called security wall on Palestinian territory. It is twice the length of the green line border and has appropriated an additional 10 per cent. of the west bank and imprisoned nearly 50,000 Palestinians between the wall and the green line. These people have to have permits from the Israelis to live in their own homes.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/21">On <phrase class="date" code="2005-10-18">18 October</phrase>, <i>The Guardian</i> set out the scale of the Israeli land grab: 23 square miles of land has been appropriated on the west bank since July, which more than offsets the land evacuated in Gaza, with 14,000 additional settlers in the illegal settlements on the west bank, which is 65 per cent. more than the number that left Gaza. The Israeli Government are pursuing a deliberate policy of squeezing Palestinians out of Jerusalem. The city is being encircled by expanded illegal settlements and cut off from its natural hinterland in the west bank. I was really shocked by the depth of despair of the Jerusalemites I met. They are Palestinians who in the past have been the most liberal and open to engagement with Israel. I found them more depressed than the Palestinians who I met in Gaza. They are depressed by the expansion of the settlements, which are killing Arab east Jerusalem economically and excluding many people with Jerusalem identity cards from their own city.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/22">The wall has arbitrarily cut through neighbourhoods, including the Ar Ram neighbourhood, and removed people from Jerusalem. Without moving, they are no longer living in Jerusalem. The UN estimates that a quarter of the 230,000 Palestinians who currently have Jerusalem ID cards have been excluded from Jerusalem by the wall and risk having their ID cards confiscated. Many people are caught in the situation where if they do not live in Jerusalem their ID card is confiscated and if they do not have a Jerusalem ID card, even the land they own in Jerusalem is confiscated.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/23">The Israelis continue to demolish houses. One person took me to his huge family house, which he had built with all his savings and which has now been shut up by Israeli order because a demolition order is going through the courts. He and his family of seven are squashed into a two-room flat because they cannot live in their own house. Fourteen of his neighbours' houses have already demolished and the excuse is that planning permission has been refused because the planning framework has not been finalised, but the framework process was started by the Israelis in 1992. It is clear that they have no intention of ever drawing up a planning framework so that they can always say that buildings are being built without permission.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/24">Palestinian institutions in Jerusalem are being threatened. The al-Quds medical school has had students marooned in Gaza for the past four years with patients unable to reach clinics and medical students unable to access the other main hospitals. I was told of rumours suggesting that the Israelis will introduce a new law to outlaw Jerusalem institutions from employing people with west bank permits. If that were carried through, it would mean that the al-Makassed hospital would lose 50 per cent. of its staff and the Industrial secondary school, which I visited, would lose 41 of its 54 employees, many of whom have worked there for decades. The Israelis are currently trying to bribe that institution out of Jerusalem. They have offered to pay for its relocation to the west bank.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/25">There was an unmistakable feeling among all the people I met in Jerusalem that things were getting so bad&mdash;with no hope of improvement and no attention, they felt, from the international community&mdash;that violence was the only way out. That is a dangerous feeling to be growing within Jerusalem's Palestinian population.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/26">On the west bank, the expansion of settlements and the continuation of checkpoints and road blocks are making people's lives a misery. They interfere with the free movement of Palestinians to school, university, hospitals and work. Even when the checkpoints are open, people do not feel confident that they will not be closed arbitrarily, leaving them trapped on the wrong side. People's movements are heavily controlled as a result. I could go on to describe all the other instances that I came across in the various towns of the west bank. I want to get over to people the dangerous atmosphere that is building up within the Palestinian population because they feel that there is no hope of improvement and that they are being left with only one outlet: violence.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/27">That situation is hugely dangerous, both for the Palestinians and the Israelis. Ordinary Palestinians can see with their own eyes that the current Israeli Government are creating facts on the ground that will completely rule out a viable and contiguous Palestinian state. They can see that they are going to be offered only a series of disconnected Bantustans, totally under the control of Israel and totally dependent on it. They fear, in particular, that the whole of Jerusalem, including the al-Aqsa and the Dome of the Rock, will be lost to them.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/28">Even in Gaza, the Israelis are failing to offer any semblance of real autonomy or sovereignty. People can see no chance of the poverty of people in Gaza being reduced. The current Israeli strategy is leaving ordinary Palestinians with no hope for any improvement for their future and is undercutting moderates in the Palestinian community who want to find a negotiated solution. People such as President Abbas have almost nothing to show to Palestinians as an example of what has been delivered through the negotiation route. Instead, negotiation seems to have delivered a worse and worse lifestyle for Palestinians. As I say, the temptation is for more and more Palestinians to conclude that violence is the only answer.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/29">The British Government, the European Union and the rest of the Quartet are committed to a two-state solution based on the road map and the relevant UN resolutions. The Minister has recently reiterated in a series of written parliamentary answers the UK position on the illegality of all the settlements and our opposition to any further land grab by the Israelis. The international community and significant parts of Israeli society believe that disengagement from Gaza should be the first step towards that two-state solution, but if that is to have any chance of success, the international community needs to put effective pressure on the Israeli Government now to stop them taking action that makes the two-state solution impossible. It is not credible for the international community to continue to ignore the annexation of Palestinian land, and it is even less credible to suggest that the wall and the settlements will be dismantled at some point in the future.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/30">Israel constantly claims to be the only democracy in the middle east, but if the current Israeli Government are permitted to continue to expropriate Palestinian land, encircle east Jerusalem and deprive Palestinians of their right to live in and have access to the holy city&mdash;which is the holy city not only of Jews, but of Muslims and Christians&mdash;they will destroy Israel's right to make that claim. An apartheid state where Palestinians are in enclaves that are nominally autonomous but actually under the control of Israel, and where Palestinians are excluded from participation in Israel's democracy, will not be a democracy in any recognisable sense. Furthermore, such a solution will not ensure Israel's security; it will be a recipe for continued violence.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/31">For that reason, if the Government are to continue to be a friend to both Israel and Palestine, they must take action now to ensure that Israel complies with its obligations under the road map. Britain and the European Union must use every bit of leverage that they have, including financial leverage, to pressure the Israelis to stop expropriating Palestinian land; for example, they could suspend the EU-Israel trade association.</p>
	<p pid="a.94.3/32">There must be a speedy agreement by the Israelis&mdash;in line with the obligations that they are asked to fulfil by Mr. Wolfensohn&mdash;to the opening of access to and from Gaza, and there must be freedom of movement across the west bank and into and out of Jerusalem. Palestinians must be readmitted to the road network in the west bank; it is currently reserved for Israel's illegal settlers. In addition, the UK and the EU need to undertake public diplomacy, and explain directly to the Israeli people the cul-de-sac down which the Israeli Government's policies are leading them.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.99.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.99.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.102.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.102.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.102.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.102.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.105.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.105.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.106.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.106.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.106.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.106.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.108.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.108.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.111.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.111.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.111.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1546" speakername="Annette Brooke" colnum="111"  time="15:09:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm051026/halltext/51026h03.htm#51026h03_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.111.0/1">I, too, congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1787" name="Sandra Gidley">my hon. Friend the Member for Romsey (Sandra Gidley)</phrase> on securing a debate on an issue that is of importance to every MP. I also have an enormous postbag on the subject and agree that the CSA is a shambolic institution. I have spoken at length on the subject and want to concentrate on one case: my constituent versus the CSA computer. I concur with all the other points that have been raised and have letters on those in my mailbag.</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/2">This particular case and some of the written communications to which it has given rise&mdash;I have some of them here&mdash;create the impression of a body that is completely out of touch with people and the state in which our constituents find themselves once they are in conflict with the CSA.</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/3">My constituent's relationship with the CSA dates back to 1997, but I will not start from then because it would involve a long catalogue of events. For the sake of brevity, I begin in March 2005, when my constituent, out of total frustration&mdash;I note how many times that word has been used in this short debate&mdash;with the system, asked for her case to be closed. She just could not cope with the stress arising from the catalogue of errors. Her frustration arose from the uncertainty of whether she would receive any payments, which affected her housing benefit and made her situation worse.</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/4">At that stage, she was owed &pound;600, and I understand that enforcement action is being taken. Hon. Members should note the language used in a letter to my constituent which arrived in May. It states:</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/5" class="indent">&quot;I have investigated the issues raised within your correspondence and would like to take this opportunity to apologise for the poor level of customer service you have received from the Agency.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/6">So far, so good. It concludes:</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/7" class="indent">&quot;While the new IT system is working well for most clients, there are some, more complex circumstances where we still have difficulties . . . I can confirm your case has been closed as requested with effect from <phrase class="date" code="2005-03-01">1 March 2005</phrase> but due to a technical fault the system is unable to fully progress your case to closure. All written notifications have been inhibited on your case although this is no guarantee you will not receive any notifications in the future owing to the technical fault. Your case has been referred to the Incident Team to resolve the fault.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/8">I ask hon. Members to consider what it would be like to receive such a letter.</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/9">That is not the end of the story because, for really good reasons, my constituent decided to ask for her case to be reopened and initiated a new claim in June 2005. The CSA did not respond. She kept telephoning. She was told that her application had not been received and was not on the system. Eventually, she got a one-to-one meeting&mdash;that was quite good really&mdash;and she was promised money within a week.</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/10">The money did not come within a week. That took us to the end of August. I heard from my constituent on <phrase class="date" code="2005-08-30">30 August</phrase>. Apparently, her ex-partner had paid &pound;50 to the CSA in June, July and August 2005, but the CSA claimed that it was not possible to pass the money on to her given that her case with them was closed. That is quite a problem, involving a closed case and a newly opened case.</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/11">It is often said that the fault does not lie with the CSA, but with people not paying money to it. However, in this case, the CSA has the money. It is appalling that it is trapped in the system. The CSA has confirmed to me that it is owed to my constituent, but has said that there is a problem with the computer system. The case was passed to the live service support unit of the CSA and it has been given MP priority.</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/12">It is interesting to note that between the closure of the case and now, there have been no changes in the circumstances of my constituent's former partner. Therefore, all the necessary information was on the computer system. One would have thought that there was no need to use a manual system, but the enforcement action for the &pound;600 meant that the newly opened case had to be dealt with manually. However, in my experience, there is no simple way of manually processing applications with the CSA, even though there is with most other organisations.</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/13">The MP priority system brought me a letter on <phrase class="date" code="2005-10-20">20 October</phrase>&mdash;a high-speed response. It stated that there was a</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/14" class="indent">&quot;a problem of a technical nature&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/15">that was preventing my constituent's case from being progressed. It continued:</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/16" class="indent">&quot;Our technical people are currently working on this and we are awaiting authorisation from them for the case to be progressed clerically. Once authorisation has been received the case will be prepared for submission to a specialist clerical team. The average time being taken for a case to be completed is 18 weeks.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/17">So that is my priority case as an MP. It started in June and it is now the end of October, but my constituent has not gotten a penny and the CSA has her money.</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/18">What is the impact on our constituents? Mine has to work really long hours to make up the money due to her, and the stress affects her physical and mental well-being. I am angry that the Government are party to a system that shows no understanding of how people on relatively low incomes live. For a mother bringing up two children, and working for a relatively low rate of pay, &pound;150 is a great deal of money. It is the difference between the children having the right shoes for school and them wearing trainers, which are not acceptable to the school.</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/19">People on relatively low incomes budget week to week. It is unacceptable that they receive letters saying that a clerical team will deal with their problem in three months' time. Like <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1959" name="Michael Weir">the hon. Member for Angus (Mr. Weir)</phrase>, I feel sorry for the front-line staff who have to work under this dreadful system. Someone must be responsible for the chaos. Is it the people who were involved in drawing up the specifications for the computer system? Or is the problem down to some of the more general principles behind the Child Support Agency? We need something that relates to people, because we are all here to help them, but the system actually makes life worse for people who are already in difficult circumstances.</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/20">My constituent concludes:</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/21" class="indent">&quot;God help my deprived children and others who rely on the CSA&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.111.0/22">The CSA in its current form is past praying for, and I look forward to the Minister offering us some hope for the future.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.113.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.113.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.118.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.118.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.120.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.120.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.120.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1909" speakername="James Plaskitt" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Work and Pensions"  colnum="120"  time="15:43:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm051026/halltext/51026h03.htm#51026h03_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.120.0/1">Everyone who contributed to the debate had the same motivation to do so: as constituency MPs&mdash;I include myself in this&mdash;we have all wrestled with difficult constituency cases over the years. Constituents have become embroiled in the CSA, and the agency has let them down in one way or another. Hon. Members have spoken of distress, tears and anguish, and we have probably all seen those things in our surgeries. That is why many of us have long-held concerns about the state of the agency and want to see the problems addressed.</p>
	<p pid="a.120.0/2">I felt that we were having a constructive discussion. Hon. Members have brought their genuine experiences to the table and, quite rightly, they want me to answer questions about the agency. They are concerned about the parents who are enmeshed in these matters. More essentially, they are concerned about the children.</p>
	<p pid="a.120.0/3">We were having a debate of that type until we reached the previous contribution, which unfortunately indulged in raising other issues. That suggests that <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1948" name="Paul Goodman">the hon. Member for Wycombe (Mr. Goodman)</phrase> is perhaps not as interested in the agency as he is in other matters.</p>
	<p pid="a.120.0/4">Turning to the meat of the debate, I begin by congratulating <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1787" name="Sandra Gidley">the hon. Member for Romsey (Sandra Gidley)</phrase> on securing this opportunity as well as on is clear that I am not talking about a success story, and there is no point pretending that I am doing anything other.</p>
	<p pid="a.120.0/5">However, it is important to keep a certain perspective on what is going on at the agency. In our surgeries, we all&mdash;me included&mdash;come across the cases that have gone wrong in one way or another. Almost by definition, we do not come across the cases that are working. Before rushing to judgment, therefore, we need to be a little careful to determine whether the thing has completely failed and whether we have the whole picture in front of us.</p>
	<p pid="a.120.0/6">We must bear it in mind that since the agency was established, it has collected &pound;4.5 billion of child maintenance payments and that 527,000 children are being supported by maintenance payments because of the CSA. We do not hear about the cases that get processed and set up in six weeks, although I assure hon. Members that there are some.</p>
	<p pid="a.120.0/7">Nor are we paying attention to the quite sharp recent increase in action by the agency to chase non-compliant non-resident parents. Let me share with hon. Members the figures on the issuing of liability orders, which is the necessary preliminary step to taking action to recover debts and non-payments. In 2002&ndash;03, the agency issued 2,383 such orders; in 2003&ndash;04, it issued 3,885; and in just the first six months of the current financial year, it issued 4,539. The impression that is sometimes created is that the agency is falling down on the job and doing nothing to chase non-compliant non-resident parents, but that does not quite match the entirety of the picture.</p>
	<p pid="a.120.0/8">We all know, however, that alongside those elements of the agency that work&mdash;I am pleading for perspective here&mdash;there are far too many elements that do not. I shall not pretend for one moment that the agency's performance is in any way acceptable; it has let far too many people down and the issues need to be addressed. The hon. Member for Wycombe is perfectly right to quote back at me things that I said in the House of Commons as a constituency MP. I said that these issues had to be tackled and I consider myself quite fortunate because I am now in a position, perhaps, to ensure that we do something about them. Indeed, we are doing something about them.</p>
	<p pid="a.120.0/9">The new chief executive went in nearly six months ago, and he and his team are doing a root-and-branch analysis of the agency, with nothing being left unexamined. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1951" name="David Laws">The hon. Member for Yeovil (Mr. Laws)</phrase> wants to know whether my ministerial colleagues and I are asking all the tough questions to get to the bottom of the agency's problems. I am happy to reassure him that that is exactly what we are doing. The questions are very tough, and the task that the chief executive has been given is extremely challenging.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.121.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.121.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.121.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.121.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.125.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.125.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.125.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.125.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.126.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.126.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.126.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.126.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.129.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.129.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.129.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.129.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.130.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.130.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.132.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.132.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.132.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.132.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.133.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.133.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.133.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.133.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.133.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.133.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.133.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.133.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.134.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.134.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.134.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.134.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.137.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.137.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.139.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.139.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26a.139.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-10-26b.139.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

