<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.345.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.345.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.345.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.345.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.345.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.345.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.345.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.345.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.345.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.345.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.345.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1515" speakername="Geoffrey Clifton-Brown" colnum="345"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm050628/halltext/50628h01.htm#50628h01_spnew1">
	<p pid="a.345.4/1">May I thank you, Mr. Olner, and through you Mr. Speaker, for giving me the opportunity to secure this debate on planning regulations for mobile telecommunications masts, which are generating huge interest up and down the country and among colleagues. I also thank the Under-Secretary of State, Office of the Deputy Prime Minister, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1765" name="Jim Fitzpatrick">the hon. Member for Poplar and Canning Town (Jim Fitzpatrick)</phrase> for being in the Chamber to respond to this important debate.</p>
	<p pid="a.345.4/2">There is a desperate need to address the many serious concerns about the Government's policies on planning regulations for mobile telecommunications masts. It is ironic that mobile phones, which were created to allow connection and conversation between people separated by distance, have proved how distant the Government are and how incapable they are of listening, even to the most persistent interlocutors.</p>
	<p pid="a.345.4/3">Each time the Government have gone through the motions of listening to people's concerns, it quickly becomes apparent that no real action has been taken. When the Government claim to accept:</p>
	<p pid="a.345.4/4" class="indent">&quot;the importance of ensuring that effective public consultation&quot;&mdash;[<phrase class="offrep" id="debates/2004-10-18.743"><i>Official Report</i>, 18 October 2004; Vol. 425, c. 743</phrase>.]</p>
	<p pid="a.345.4/5">takes place, as the then planning Minister&mdash;the current Under-Secretary of State for Education and Skills, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1512" name="Phil Hope">the hon. Member for Corby (Phil Hope)</phrase>&mdash;said on <phrase class="date" code="2004-10-18">18 October 2004</phrase>, they also quietly admit that that really means that arrangements are necessary to ensure that development is not delayed.</p>
	<p pid="a.345.4/6">The Office of the Deputy Prime Minister press release on <phrase class="date" code="2004-12-09">9 December 2004</phrase> said:</p>
	<p pid="a.345.4/7" class="indent">&quot;People have a right to know where masts are located.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.345.4/8">At the same time, however, the Government go to great lengths to prevent obtrusive new masts from being subject to planning permission.</p>
	<p pid="a.345.4/9">The then planning Minister continued:</p>
	<p pid="a.345.4/10" class="indent">&quot;these planning cases would be more likely to end up as planning appeals . . . because an application had been refused.&quot;&mdash;[<phrase class="offrep" id="debates/2004-10-18.744"><i>Official Report</i>, 18 October 2004; Vol. 425, c. 744</phrase>.]</p>
	<p pid="a.345.4/11">The Government are speaking with forked tongue; they claim to be listening to people's concerns about the effect on health of telecommunications masts, while a planning Minister sends out explicit instructions to councils that they should not impose a ban on mobile phones on health grounds.</p>
	<p pid="a.345.4/12">The Government are simply not listening. Following the Stewart report, they promised to hold several consultation exercises, but they have clearly not taken enough exercise and must now be shown how to get planning permission for mobile telecommunications masts back into shape.</p>
	<p pid="a.345.4/13">The Government must not be seen to accept the &pound;22.5 billion third-generation mobile phone licence fees and then ignore the concerns of many worried constituents, yet that is exactly what appears to have happened when an august and unbiased body such as the Library says in its debate pack of <phrase class="date" code="2005-06-20">20 June 2005</phrase> that Government policy is</p>
	<p pid="a.345.4/14" class="indent">&quot;most notable for not giving ground to objectors against masts&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.345.4/15">I would be very interested to hear from the Minister about the outcome of yesterday's meeting between the Minister of State, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1744" name="Ian Gibson">the hon. Member for Norwich, North (Dr. Gibson)</phrase>, and Alan Meyer of Mast Action UK. What flaws in Government policy on planning permission for telecommunications masts did Mr. Meyer highlight in that meeting?</p>
	<p pid="a.345.4/16">As things stand, the <i>New Scientist</i> of <phrase class="date" code="2001-02-10">10 February 2001</phrase> predicted that 3G operators will need at least 100,000 new masts to facilitate their service. That figure, however, is based on an assumption that the current system will prevail for some time. That is not the best way forward.</p>
	<p pid="a.345.4/17">We are much more likely to enjoy innovative solutions if we can give local communities more influence over how the increasing demand for supply is satisfied, and innovative solutions must involve things such as mast sharing and roaming, which operate very successfully on the continent.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.346.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.346.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.346.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.346.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.347.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.347.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.347.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.347.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.347.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1515" speakername="Geoffrey Clifton-Brown" colnum="347"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm050628/halltext/50628h01.htm#50628h01_spnew5">
	<p pid="a.347.1/1">I congratulate the hon. Gentleman on having managed to give advance notice of his meeting. I have no doubt that many hon. Members present will wish to attend. He raises the important matter of Tetra masts, which have all sorts of issues associated with them, and which worry many local communities that have such big masts near them. Peter Jones from Actix, which developed new wireless technology for mobile companies, has warned that the number of masts could increase by three or four times. That means that we are slipping into a situation in which people can choose whether to have a mobile phone, but not whether to live by a mobile phone mast.</p>
	<p pid="a.347.1/2">Many cases that have arisen around the country suggest that that state of affairs needs to be corrected. I draw the Minister's attention to one in particular. It is a sad case. The Merseyside Society for Deaf People in West Derby has found it impossible to overcome the problem of a mast that interferes with hearing aids, because the mast has been given an ICNIRP certificate&mdash;that stands for the international commission on non-ionising radiation protection. However, local campaigners are convinced that when such problems occur, such certificates are not worth the paper that they are written on. People feel that they have no control or influence over the masts that affect their environment; communities clearly do not have a large enough role in the consultation process.</p>
	<p pid="a.347.1/3">I would be grateful to the Minister if he would tell me how he proposes to remedy the situation. Will the Government establish a national database of masts, as recommended in the Stewart report? When will they make a commitment to publish in full the reports by Reading university and Arup, and by Micro Consultants Limited, so that communities have access to the relevant information? Will they publish the report by the Defence Science and Technology Laboratory on epileptiform activity and cognitive performance, so that people's fears about health issues can be addressed?</p>
	<p pid="a.347.1/4">Health concerns relating to telecommunications masts are not limited to Merseyside. I do not intend to dwell on health issues&mdash;that is not the purpose of the debate&mdash;but they are important, and must be mentioned. Many of my constituents in the Cotswolds are not only concerned about protecting the beautiful countryside that surrounds them, important as that is, but worried about the risks to schools lying in the radiation of the beam of greatest intensity from masts. They have limited confidence in the precautionary principle laid down in planning regulations and are aware that, as I said, the Government have not published all the reports that they have received on the potential health risks.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.348.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.348.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.348.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.348.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.349.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.349.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.349.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.349.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.349.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1515" speakername="Geoffrey Clifton-Brown" colnum="349"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm050628/halltext/50628h01.htm#50628h01_spnew9">
	<p pid="a.349.1/1">My hon. Friend and neighbour has raised a very good point. The mobile phone industry must be much less defensive and must have more constructive dialogue with the Government. Equally, the Government must listen to local people's concerns. That should be taken into account when the Government come to decide whether they should return power to local communities to shape their own environment, or whether they should continue to give almost unchecked power to mobile phone operators to put masts where they please.</p>
	<p pid="a.349.1/2">I must make it clear, because no doubt the Mobile Operators Association will be on to me this afternoon, that I do not blame the operators for their actions. They are working in an incredibly competitive field and contribute a great deal to our economy, employing tens of thousands of people. Indeed, when the industry was first created the Conservative Government encouraged it, as we saw the great benefits of such a technologically advanced sector and the huge employment gains, and other benefits, that it would bring. However, there must be more openness and consultation.</p>
	<p pid="a.349.1/3">The Government have boasted that the present system offers</p>
	<p pid="a.349.1/4" class="indent">&quot;a major advantage for mobile phone operators.&quot;&mdash;[<phrase class="offrep" id="debates/2000-12-06.118"><i>Official Report</i>, 6 December 2000; Vol. 359, c. 118</phrase>.]</p>
	<p pid="a.349.1/5">That was according to the present Minister for Children and Families, who was Under-Secretary of State for the Environment, Transport and the Regions at the time. While seeming to ignore rural and urban communities, the Government have created a system that gives operators an automatic right of installation if local authorities delay decision making to take account of all the facts. They have awarded operators statutory undertaker status, allowing them to exercise compulsory purchase powers in collusion with the Secretary of State.</p>
	<p pid="a.349.1/6">Instead, the Government should deliver on their promise&mdash;and I quote&mdash;to</p>
	<p pid="a.349.1/7" class="indent">&quot;give local planning authorities and local people an idea of potential design solutions for particular sites&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.349.1/8">According to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1602" name="Nick Raynsford">the right hon. Member for Greenwich and Woolwich (Mr. Raynsford)</phrase>, when he was a Minister, that would</p>
	<p pid="a.349.1/9" class="indent">&quot;help to promote better dialogue and a collaborative approach&quot;&mdash;[<phrase class="offrep" id="debates/2001-01-24.1039"><i>Official Report</i>, 24 January 2001; Vol. 361, c. 1039</phrase>.]</p>
	<p pid="a.349.1/10">That seems a very constructive way forward, and in its report of <phrase class="date" code="2004-07-03">3 July 2004</phrase>, the all-party group on mobile communications said that approach could be best achieved by subjecting all masts to full planning permission because that would result in</p>
	<p pid="a.349.1/11" class="indent">&quot;a higher level of engagement and subsequent ownership of the process by local communities&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.349.1/12">It went on to say that that would also benefit the operators by</p>
	<p pid="a.349.1/13" class="indent">&quot;resulting in less objections, less likelihood of rejection of the proposals, and less confrontation between operators and objectors&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.349.1/14">From an all-party group, that is a very constructive approach.</p>
	<p pid="a.349.1/15">I am proud of my party's approach to this difficult issue, which contrasts with the Government's record on telecommunications masts. When we were in government, and before it was realised what the future rate of growth in the mobile network would be, we gave succour to a nascent industry that would employ tens of thousands of people. However, we also introduced a framework of regulations that has laid the basis for what needs to be done today. The Town and Country Planning (General Permitted Development) Order 1995 was introduced by a Conservative Administration, and it is now the only significant measure on which the Government can call.</p>
	<p pid="a.349.1/16">Since 1997, we have tirelessly tried further to improve the regulation system for telecommunications masts. Colleagues have tabled a host of early-day motions and parliamentary questions, and we have offered the Government every encouragement to listen to local communities. We have a set of widely supported proposals for regulations for full planning permission, which my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1449" name="Eric Pickles">the Member for Brentwood and Ongar (Mr. Pickles)</phrase> will no doubt elucidate from the Front Bench. We propose a single decision-making process for all masts, regardless of type or location, a commitment to increase local government's control over planning permission, and demands on the industry to demonstrate that proposed masts will not damage the local environment and that options for mast sharing have been extensively explored.</p>
	<p pid="a.349.1/17">My party's work on the issue continues today. Beyond this Chamber, Conservative candidates such as Stephen Day in Cheadle are standing up for their local communities. On behalf of Cheadle Hulme residents, he is leading a local campaign against a planning application for a phone mast on Anfield road. He has highlighted the environmental&mdash;</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.350.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.350.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.351.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.351.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.351.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.351.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.352.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.352.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.352.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.352.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.352.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.352.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.352.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.352.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.352.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.352.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.352.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.352.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.352.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.352.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.352.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.352.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.353.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.353.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.353.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.353.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.353.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.353.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.353.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.353.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.353.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.353.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.353.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1971" speakername="Jo Swinson" colnum="353"  time="010:01:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm050628/halltext/50628h01.htm#50628h01_spnew25">
	<p pid="a.353.4/1">Let me first congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1515" name="Geoffrey Clifton-Brown">the hon. Member for Cotswold (Mr. Clifton-Brown)</phrase> on securing this debate on an important issue. I want to touch on three points: local consultation, permitted development rights and the inclusion of health implications in the planning process.</p>
	<p pid="a.353.4/2">I know&mdash;not just from my mailbag, from my email inbox and from knocking on doors&mdash;that this is an issue in my constituency. Using the new pledgebank.com website, I recently set up an online pledge to organise a public meeting in my constituency about mobile phone mast applications if at least 20 people showed an interest in attending. The speed at which the required 20 people signed up to the pledge shows the level of interest in the issue ,at a time when there is apparently little appetite for old-fashioned political engagement at public meetings and suchlike. That meeting will take place later in the summer, and I hope that representatives from mobile phone operators will attend.</p>
	<p pid="a.353.4/3">That meeting will be useful, because there has been a lack of consultation. One mobile phone operator who wants to site a mast in Bearsden recently agreed to meet local residents for consultation, but only if there would be no more than 10 residents at the meeting. That is not my idea of adequate consultation.</p>
	<p pid="a.353.4/4">We all recognise the need for mobile phone masts. Most of us, and most of our constituents, use mobile phones and enjoy the benefits of convenient communication. The key is to ensure that the masts are sensitively sited, and that requires meaningful consultation at the start in local areas.</p>
	<p pid="a.353.4/5">Hon. Members will be aware that Scotland is often a pioneer leading the way, and so it is with the planning process for mobile phone mast applications. South of the border, phone masts of a certain height can be erected without reference to local communities and planning authorities, and that is a recipe for disaster. No wonder people feel powerless and without a voice. I urge the Minister to look at the Scottish example, where planning permission is required for mobile phone masts of all heights, to see whether lessons can be learned.</p>
	<p pid="a.353.4/6">However, ensuring that the erection of masts has to go through the planning process is not enough. My constituents feel frustrated that there is inadequate scope for their views to be heard, and local authorities still do not have adequate decision-making powers on applications. One example, on which <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1664" name="George Howarth">the hon. Member for Knowsley, North and Sefton, East (Mr. Howarth)</phrase> touched, is that the impact on health cannot be used as a ground for refusal. Yet many people's concerns about phone masts relate directly to the impact on health, especially the health of their children.</p>
	<p pid="a.353.4/7">The 2004 Stewart report recognised that whatever the health implications, children are more at risk. Government advice is that children under eight should not use mobile phones. Parents are understandably concerned by the mixed messages. The daily radiation produced by a mast is often compared with the number of minutes spent talking on a mobile phone&mdash;yet although parents are told not to allow their children to spend many minutes talking on their mobile phones, they are expected not to be concerned about the health implications of nearby masts.</p>
	<p pid="a.353.4/8">Further research is clearly required&mdash;for example, to ascertain the radiation effect of clusters of phone masts in a local area. That will become more important, as 3G technology requires more masts, so people will live close to several. Land contours should also be taken into account when measuring radiation levels. It is not much good citing the radiation at ground level when the top of the mast beams into upstairs bedrooms where children sleep.</p>
	<p pid="a.353.4/9">Perhaps most importantly, the precautionary principle should be applied in these cases. East Dunbartonshire council, like many local authorities, recently had a policy of not siting masts near schools, but that policy was overturned on appeal. However, the Government's own documents state that the precautionary principle should be used. I refer to the sustainable strategy document entitled &quot;Securing the Future&quot;, which was written in March and, I think, launched today. It says that policies should respect five principles, one of which is &quot;Using Sound Science Responsibly&quot;, which is defined as</p>
	<p pid="a.353.4/10" class="indent">&quot;ensuring policy is developed and implemented on the basis of strong scientific evidence, whilst taking into account scientific uncertainty (through the Precautionary Principle)&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.353.4/11">I welcome the Minister's comments on how he sees that idea fitting into the planning process for mobile phone applications.</p>
	<p pid="a.353.4/12">In considering future action on the issue, I would urge the Minister to be bold and not bind the hands of those making planning decisions. Removing permitted development rights would be a good start, but it is not enough on its own. Local planning authorities must have the tools to examine all the issues relating to mobile phone masts.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.355.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.355.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.356.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.356.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.356.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.356.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.356.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.356.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.356.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.356.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.357.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.357.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.357.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.357.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.357.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.357.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.357.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.357.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.357.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.357.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.357.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.357.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.358.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.358.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.358.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.358.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.358.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.358.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.359.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.359.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.359.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.359.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.361.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.361.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.361.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.361.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.361.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.361.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.361.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.361.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.361.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.361.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.362.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.362.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.362.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.362.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.362.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.362.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.363.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.363.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.363.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.363.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.363.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.363.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.363.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.363.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.364.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.364.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.364.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.364.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.364.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.364.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.365.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.365.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.365.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.365.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.366.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.366.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.368.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.368.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.368.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.368.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.368.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.368.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.368.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.368.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.369.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.369.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.370.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.370.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.370.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.370.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.370.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.370.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.371.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.371.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.371.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.371.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.371.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1520" speakername="Gwyneth Dunwoody" colnum="371"  time="010:59:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm050628/halltext/50628h02.htm#50628h02_spnew0">
	<p pid="a.371.1/1">It is always a delight to see you in the Chair, Mr. Olner, and may I begin by saying that it is a great honour to have the opportunity to appear in Westminster Hall before you? I would also like to pay tribute to my hon. Friend the Minister. It is very exciting to see lots of women Ministers, but seeing nice, talented and charming Ministers is an added bonus.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/2">No society anywhere in the world can operate on the exploitation of labour that is poorer and less free and able to defend its interests than labour from the host nation. As a thriving commercial country that is full of the stimulation of exciting new jobs and frequently needs the support of people who want to do the jobs that are perhaps more routine and boring, we are an ideal country to welcome overseas workers. Of course, that is the case as long as we apply our own standards and make it clear to those who come to work in this country that they are protected and will not be part of an almost invisible, exploited group of workers.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/3">Such people have the right to expect fairness of treatment, and certainly the protection of their interests. As a nation that has evolved a sense of fair treatment and equality for so long, it would be appalling if we were found to be treating those who come to our shores legitimately to seek work in an unacceptable and reprehensible manner.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/4">I have become aware of a situation that I think is probably not unique. In fact, the more work I have done, the more it has occurred to me that the same situation is arising throughout the United Kingdom, whereby British employers&mdash;I emphasise the word &quot;British&quot;&mdash;are seeking to employ mostly immigrant workers in conditions that are sometimes frankly reprehensible. I am indebted to the Library, which has supplied me with detail about the conduct of employment agencies and the laws under which they operate. On reading the information, some of which has also been supplied to me by trade unions, it is extraordinary to see how many laws and protections are apparently in place to ensure that we cannot exploit workers.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/5">It is extraordinary in the 21st century that people can still be cheated of the minimum wage. There are still people operating in the agriculture and transport sectors who are apparently not protected by the rights that are genuinely enjoyed by British workers and which we would expect to be the norm. In some instances, we would expect those rights to be the absolute ground base. However, that lack of protection is happening in spite of the fact that we have not only excellent controls on paper over the work of employment agencies, but in some instances, codes of conduct that are meant to control the employment of workers in industries such as agriculture.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/6">When we read those codes of conduct and see the large firms that have signed up to them and the work that was done by the National Farmers Union and the Transport and General Workers Union to reach a workable code of conduct that can be defended&mdash;an example of what we ought to be doing in many instances&mdash;we can only possible wonder at the gap between the structure that we think is in place and the reality for those who come to this country to work.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/7">Why is this a matter of concern to me? It should be a matter of concern to all trade unionists, and I have been in a trade union since I was 16. Moreover, it ought to be of concern to every member of the United Kingdom. I am horrified to learn that there have been developments during the past few years that to me are wholly indefensible. Some British employment agencies, faced with the restrictions of existing British law, seem to have found ways of sailing astonishingly close to the wind. Members will recognise that as a technique not unknown to those who wish to consider only their own commercial interests, but it becomes horrifying when large numbers of people are involved.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/8">For example, many employment agencies advertise in nations that have newly joined the European Union. That is perfectly legitimate, and as long as those agencies stick to the employment laws, no one can possibly criticise them. What appears to have happened is rather different. Workers are being encouraged to come to the UK, where they are told there will be constant work. Perhaps the word &quot;constant&quot; is an overstatement; they are told there will be steady amounts of employment. They are encouraged in some instances to pay large sums towards their transport.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/9">Such workers then come here and sign contracts, sometimes in languages that they do not understand. They are told that their accommodation, transport and employment will all be taken care of. In some instances, they are put into accommodation that is grossly overcrowded and that does not offer the level of care that would be expected as a very minimum. They are offered work. They do not speak the language of the country. They do not know their rights and they are unable to access that information.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/10">Those people go to work in various different types of jobs. Unfortunately, this issue is not restricted to one type of industry. As far as I can see, people are being exploited across large numbers of different types of jobs: distribution, agriculture and even, to my horror, long-distance driving. If there is one idea that frightens me, it is not a lorry driver who does not know how to handle the machine that he is asked to drive, but one who does not understand the rules of road safety that apply to the United Kingdom and cannot read the road signs. That matter should give the Department for Transport some thought. Polish long-distance lorry drivers are taking out vehicles on our roads in large numbers and although they may be perfectly adept at driving, the fact that they are not aware of the conditions in this country and not, in many instances, even capable of reading warning signs or the information on the gantries of motorways must constitute a hazard and the Department should consider that very closely.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/11">The situation is far worse, however. Many of those workers, who have paid to come here, paid for accommodation and been informed that they will have jobs, discover that whatever the job&mdash;in many instances, it is extraordinarily lowly paid&mdash;there are large numbers of deductions from the amounts that are paid to them on a number of grounds. Their passports are confiscated. In many instances, they are kept apart from the people of the area so that they are unable to seek support. There is also the issue of what happens if for any reason their employment ceases. For example, in the case of agricultural workers, people have frequently been driven to an agricultural job and told when they arrive that it is not available. They have then been driven back again and charged for the transport even though they have not received any payment. Let us remember that these people are not operating with large cheque books and nice comfortable buffer zones in a working current account; in many instances, they are penniless, do not speak the language or understand the conditions, and are being exploited.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/12">The worrying thing is that there is evidence of a consistent policy of deliberate isolation. I do not know whether the Department for Trade and Industry is aware of that or capable of getting beyond it. If there is such a policy, it explains a great many things. I discovered during the course of my research that the Department puts out useful leaflets on the website in Portuguese and Polish, which I have printed off and am endeavouring to get to the people concerned. However, for someone coming to this country for the first time who does not have access to a computer and does not know how to access Government services, putting those leaflets on the website is a limited facility, although it is important.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/13">So what happens then? Any suggestion by any of the workers concerned that they dispute the terms and conditions of the work, the terms and conditions under which they are living or, even worse, the circumstances in which they find themselves if for any reason they cannot maintain constant employment, is met with this suggestion: &quot;Well, you can go out on the street.&quot; In fact, that is happening in increasing numbers. The local authority then finds itself in an extraordinary situation. These are workers who should not have any claim on the support system that operates in the United Kingdom. They are not entitled to any kind of benefit, housing or social care. Yet, what is the alternative?</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/14">In my constituency, we are beginning to see that hidden group of people contributing to very real problems. If people are thrown out on to the street hungry, with no money, no likelihood of employment and no command of the English language, they will inevitably resort to methods that most of us would find reprehensible. There has been a little crime wave due not only to some petty difficulties where people are stealing food, but to some greater instances involving a number of quite serious cases, some of which cannot be discussed because they are still going through the courts. The homelessness problem is becoming real.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/15">As far as one can see, none of the workers is ever screened. There is a mechanism for applying to the home country for information about them, but it is difficult to access, and many of the employment agencies are not concerned about carrying out detailed checks. They should be, but they are not. The respectable agencies may do so, but they can find it difficult. I have read in the information that has been provided to me about the machinery through which one accesses somebody else's criminal record system, and it makes the British version look almost uncomplicated.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/16">The reality is that people come into this country, and no one checks their ability to work or their criminal past, and no one asks them about their background. These people are being employed in the food industry, including in catering, and in long-distance lorry driving. In some cases, it has been the individual action of employers in seeking to solve their workers' practical difficulties that has led to a clear statement of such extraordinary arrangements.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/17">The confiscation of passports is clearly forbidden. In all the rules that one reads about employment agencies, it is clear that they have a responsibility to check, to record and to assure themselves that information is precise, but that they have no right to take people's passports and hold them. If there is a dispute between the workers whose passports have been taken by the agency and the employer, that group of people can no longer get work; they will have no papers, no way of proving their status and no way of asking for assistance. Even if other employers are prepared to employ them, they cannot do so.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/18">The trade unions have increasingly sought to assist such workers. After all, it is in no one's interest for a great pool of unemployed workers to be moved from place to place clandestinely and without any support. The unions have been rebuffed, however, and in many instances they have been physically refused access to the groups of workers concerned. The unions have found it extraordinarily difficult to get over the information about minimum wages, deductions and the rights of the workers concerned.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/19">Even worse, many of these workers are becoming not only homeless but a real, practical difficulty, because of the way in which British employment agencies and British employers treat them. The Salvation Army offers these people food parcels when they are starving, and I understand that it has found it increasingly difficult to do so because of various unacceptable responses from many people connected with employment agencies. The local council is faced with a number of people whom it cannot assist. It has no right to repatriate people, even if that is what they want, and neither does it have access to money or any way of checking the circumstances of the people who present themselves. Workers are being brought here in large numbers by recruitment agencies, supposedly on the basis of local employment needs. The agencies are recruiting energetically in Poland, Latvia and the former Czechoslovakia. They are exploiting these people, both as landlords and as employment agencies. There has been a rise in shoplifting and in the number of assaults. Increasingly, as I said, there is a problem with some of the driving rules.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/20">The really frightening thing, however, is the conscious policy of isolation that some of the employment agencies are adopting. If one is recruiting, employing, housing and controlling a group of workers, one must be extraordinarily careful that it is clear where the lines of demarcation lie. I have with me wage slips that make it clear that people were offered &pound;300 for two weeks' work, but that they received &pound;40 at the end of that period. That is not acceptable in this country. No one would go along with it. To be fair, the employers concerned are not automatically acquiescent. Many of them need workers and are not aware of the savagery with which many people are being treated.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/21">The local authority has noted an increase in begging on the streets. It knows that no local emergency accommodation is available. We have one YMCA centre, which does a fantastic job for those in the age range of 16 to 25, but it is always over-subscribed. There are no resources to help any of the migrant workers. Not only is no assistance offered to them individually, but there is no way of getting translation and interpretation services to them. There is a growth of resentment in the host population, both in the workplace and in the areas in which these people are dumped, sometimes 50 to a house. The issue is already creating real problems with overcrowding.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/22">We need to consider not just the legislation regarding the acceptance of migrant workers, but the behaviour of the employment agencies. We need to discipline those agencies. We need to enforce the laws. It is all very well sitting back comfortably and saying, &quot;We have not only suitable laws, but codes of conduct&quot;, but there is a problem if we are not enforcing those laws. That is indeed what is happening. We need legislation to identify the role and responsibility of the recruitment agencies that bring in workers. We need to integrate the workers into our communities, and we need to be certain that the group in question, which consists not of asylum seekers or refugees, but of people who want to return to their country of origin when they have sufficient money, is not exploited in conditions that amount almost to slavery.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/23">I ask the Government a number of questions. We cannot have employment agencies deliberately exploiting workers. It must be possible to split the role of those who recruit, supply and house such workers. I have made rough calculations and I think that some of the employment agencies walk away with &pound;600 or &pound;700 a week in cash from the workers. We are not talking about small amounts. Some of the agencies that are simultaneously providing housing are in charge of hundreds of houses in Cheshire and Staffordshire. We need to consider how we deal with the individual problems. I am not suggesting that we should have a fund to repatriate people to their own countries. That is not the right approach. Those who deliberately exploit existing legislation, and gaps in it, should be forced to pay.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/24">We need multilingual social workers. In my area alone, workers speaking at least three or four eastern European languages need assistance. We also need to insist that the agencies must have access to those people. If people are not only not given much money but are escorted forwards and backwards to the local shops so that they cannot talk to local people or get in touch with anyone who might assist them, it could lead to an enormously dangerous situation. I believe that that is happening in my constituency and elsewhere.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/25">I have a great deal more detail, but I will not bother the Minister with it today. She has got the burden of my argument, which is that no civilised country can operate by exploiting large numbers of workers. The Romans could not do so, and the French revolution grew out of precisely such a savage exploitation of one group of workers by another, and they had nationality in common. We have the beginning of an enormous social problem. The benefit of employing workers from overseas should be not only that we offer support, money and opportunities, but that we are able to demonstrate that we are a civilised society and that people are not expected to work as they might have done in the early 19th century.</p>
	<p pid="a.371.1/26">Unless our laws are enforced, they are not a great deal of help. The best bit of paper is not a defence against someone who refuses to give a person information or protection, or to ensure that that person is being treated in any way other than very harshly. The United Kingdom does not want to develop that reputation. That is not a United Kingdom that a Labour Government want to present to the world, and it is not a situation that I would ever find acceptable.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.376.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.376.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.377.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.377.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.379.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.379.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.379.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.379.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.379.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1830" speakername="John Pugh" colnum="379"  time="011:28:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm050628/halltext/50628h02.htm#50628h02_spnew4">
	<p pid="a.379.1/1">That is precisely the case. Most of the right noises have been made and the right codes of conduct published, but not all of us are satisfied that people apply them. There is almost a culture of not asking too many questions.</p>
	<p pid="a.379.1/2">The agency model takes a lot of pressure off many people. The issue came at me from a different direction when I spoke to someone from the building trade, who told me that most people who work on building sites are not working for big builders such as the McAlpines, but are agency staff. I asked why, and he pointed out that there is an escalating number of accidents in the building industry and that, as far as the main builders are concerned, if workers work for agencies rather than for them, health and safety legislation sits more loosely on them. I encountered one case in which, in order to get agency employment on a building site, workers were encouraged to take shares in the agency. That peculiar device created special difficulties when the workers took umbrage against the agency because of some accident, or some site that had not been properly supervised, and found themselves suing the company in which they had shares.</p>
	<p pid="a.379.1/3">There is a culture of complicity. The Government cannot ignore this issue. There is a lot of exploitation in which people who come here to work and who expect a good day's work for a good day's pay find that a lot of the good day's pay is missing when they examine their finances at the end of the week and find out how much rent they have to pay. Outsourcing, as we call it, it is increasingly popular. Indeed, Departments are driven to do it right, left and centre. That makes it easier to fall into a culture in which the more dubious agencies find ways into the economic system to their great profit.</p>
	<p pid="a.379.1/4">I have one more example to give the Chamber. Liverpool John Lennon airport has all sorts of security requirements. Naturally, it wants to get security for the best price, so it outsources. A few months ago, it outsourced to a perfectly reputable security company, which works for various blue-chip firms, but the people who were employed turned out to be illegal immigrants who nobody could put clear names to. That can happen when outsourcing and agency working become more common and when the Government take their eye off this particular ball. As I said at the start, the hon. Lady has drawn attention to a major problem that is going to get bigger.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.380.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.380.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.382.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.382.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.382.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.382.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.383.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.383.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.383.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.383.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.383.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.383.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.384.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.384.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.384.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.384.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.385.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.385.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.387.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.387.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.387.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.387.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.388.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.388.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.388.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.388.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.388.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.388.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.388.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.388.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.389.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.389.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.389.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.389.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.389.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.389.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.390.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.390.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.390.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.390.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.394.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.394.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.394.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1657" speakername="Don Touhig" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence"  colnum="394"  time="012:48:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm050628/halltext/50628h03.htm#50628h03_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.394.0/1">May I, at the outset, apologise on behalf of my right hon. Friend the Minister of State, who, as <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1509" name="Ann Winterton">the hon. Member for Congleton (Ann Winterton)</phrase> said, is in Portsmouth for the fleet review. He would otherwise have been here to answer this debate.</p>
	<p pid="a.394.0/2">In addition, I congratulate the hon. Lady on having obtained time for this debate on a key programme for defence and for the Army. I am grateful to her for giving me the opportunity to explain, on behalf of the Department, the thinking behind the future rapid effects system programme. Having asked a number of questions, taken part in debates and raised issues concerning FRES, the hon. Lady has built up quite a knowledge of the programme and the idea behind it. Her contribution has been helpful and appropriate in the context of the wide-ranging debate that we need to have.</p>
	<p pid="a.394.0/3">It might be helpful if I clarify what FRES is. I shall outline the drivers for the requirement, and give details of the progress that we have made in an immensely complex and demanding programme. The underlying requirement for FRES stems from two strategic requirements. First, we need to replace some of our current armoured vehicles, such as the Saxon, the FV 430 and the CVR(T), and, secondly, we need to develop a medium-weight capability so that we have a balanced force of heavy, medium and light brigades.</p>
	<p pid="a.394.0/4">FRES will also be rapidly deployable by air at battle group level&mdash;in other words, a battalion or regiment-sized force. The strategic defence review and its new chapter identified the need to enhance our expeditionary capability, but since then our thinking has developed further. The 2003 and 2004 defence White Papers clearly explain our vision to develop a highly effective medium-weight capability. As a result of the review, the Army will be rebalanced, reducing the emphasis on heavy armoured forces and increasing the emphasis on light and medium forces.</p>
	<p pid="a.394.0/5">By ensuring that each deployable brigade is fully manned and has its own integral enablers and logistics, the Army will be better equipped and structured to conduct all types of operations. FRES is at the heart of the Army's equipment programme and it will have wide uses, not only in the medium forces, but also as a key support role for our heavy forces.</p>
	<p pid="a.394.0/6">Whether for short intervention operations or enduring peace support, we often need forces with greater firepower, protection and mobility than that of light forces, but with deployability and agility that cannot be achieved by heavy forces. By providing this capability, FRES will underpin the rebalancing of the Army and the development of a truly effective medium-weight force.</p>
	<p pid="a.394.0/7">In a nutshell, FRES will be a family of medium-weight armoured vehicles of around 20 tonnes, enabled by communications, information and surveillance systems, with the growth potential to develop over time. It will be the central pillar of the Army's capable and deployable balanced force, which will have a wide operational role, from warfighting to peacekeeping.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.395.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.395.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.395.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.395.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.398.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.398.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.398.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.398.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.399.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.399.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.399.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2008" speakername="Douglas Alexander" speakeroffice="The Minister for Europe"  colnum="399"  time="013:07:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm050628/halltext/50628h04.htm#50628h04_spmin0">
	<p pid="a.399.0/1">I begin my contribution to this debate by paying tribute to my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1658" name="Stephen Hepburn">the Member for Jarrow (Mr. Hepburn)</phrase> for securing this debate and commend him for the concern and interest that he has shown in this matter on behalf of his constituents. The death of two young boys is tragic, wherever it occurs, but when it happens so far from home it is all the harder for the family to come to terms with their grief. They have our sincerest condolences.</p>
	<p pid="a.399.0/2">It may aid understanding of the role of the Governor and of the Foreign and Commonwealth Office in a case such as this if I briefly outline the constitutional status of the British Virgin Islands and thereafter discuss its traditional system. The British Virgin Islands is a British overseas territory with a large measure of internal self-government. The Governor, who is appointed by Her Majesty the Queen, is both her representative in the territory and the constitutional head of the British Virgin Islands Government. He or she has direct responsibility for external affairs, defence and internal security, including the police, the public service and the administration of the courts.</p>
	<p pid="a.399.0/3">The constitution provides for a ministerial system of government headed by a Chief Minister, an Executive Council chaired by the Governor, and a Legislative Council. The Government of the British Virgin Islands have front-line responsibility for all aspects of life in the territory that do not fall within the Governor's responsibilities. The present constitution came into force in 1977 and has been amended periodically, with the last amendment being effected in 2000. A constitutional review is under way: the constitutional review committee appointed by the British Virgin Islands Government submitted its finding to that Government in April.</p>
	<p pid="a.399.0/4">The Governor has responsibility for the administration of the courts, but, to guard against possible or perceived claims of interference, the judiciary itself is entirely independent. The British Virgin Islands, like all British overseas territories, has its own separate legal jurisdiction and its own body of civil and criminal law. The judicial system in the British Virgin Islands consists of a local magistrates courts with a single stipendiary magistrate and, above that, the Eastern Caribbean Supreme Court, which consists of a High Court and Court of Appeal. Two High Court judges, who are appointed by the Eastern Caribbean Supreme Court, reside in the territory, while the Court of Appeal is a circuit court.</p>
	<p pid="a.399.0/5">The Eastern Caribbean Supreme Court covers nine countries and territories of the Eastern Caribbean. Three British overseas territories--Anguilla, Montserrat and the BVI--fall within its jurisdiction. Based in St Lucia, it was established in 1967 by the West Indies Associated States Supreme Court Order, when all its members were still UK-dependent territories. Above the Eastern Caribbean Supreme Court is the Privy Council, which is the final court of appeal in both civil and criminal matters for all overseas territories.</p>
	<p pid="a.399.0/6">One of the issues that my hon. Friend raised was the appointment of judges in the overseas territories and I will say a word or two in response. In most territories other than those covered by the Eastern Caribbean Supreme Court, about which I have just spoken, the Governor appoints judges. As I explained, the Eastern Caribbean territories and states have been within the court's jurisdiction since 1967. The court is widely respected as a judicial body of long standing and has served the relevant independent states of the Caribbean and the three overseas territories well. However, my hon. Friend asked whether it would be possible to register a complaint about the conduct of an individual judge. The Eastern Caribbean Supreme Court has no formal complaints procedure although there is a disciplinary process if allegations are made against a judge. That would not apply if it was decided that a judge was simply exercising judicial discretion.</p>
	<p pid="a.399.0/7">As my hon. Friend said, the sad events that we are discussing took place on <phrase class="date" code="2004-08-05">5 August 2004</phrase> and the following morning. At 11 pm a collision occurred between a dinghy holding Luke Noble, Denis Campbell Harty, a United States national, Ian Murray and Stephen Noble and a boat&mdash;a Boston whaler&mdash;operated by Dutch national, Arjaan Hendriksen. At midnight, the Virgin Islands search and rescue service was alerted and joined the search for the boys. Ian Murray and Stephen Noble were found and taken to hospital. A US coastguard helicopter joined the search at first light the following morning with the Royal Virgin Islands police plane. At 8 am, the bodies of Luke Noble and Denis Campbell Harty were recovered. The Governor's office informed the Foreign and Commonwealth Office and the United States consul in Barbados of the incident.</p>
	<p pid="a.399.0/8">The case was heard in the High Court of the Eastern Caribbean Supreme Court and started on <phrase class="date" code="2005-05-31">31 May</phrase> this year. The accused was charged with two counts of manslaughter under section 153 of the British Virgin Islands criminal code of 1997. On <phrase class="date" code="2005-06-15">15 June 2005</phrase>, he was found guilty on both counts and on <phrase class="date" code="2005-06-20">20 June</phrase> was sentenced to a fine of US$30,000 on each count. The right of appeal against both verdict and sentence is subject to British Virgin Islands legislation. As the legislation stands, there is no provision for the prosecution to appeal against the sentence. We understand that following the case a review of the situation, which is already under way, will be speeded up. That is the substantive answer that I offer to my hon. Friend's query about the capacity for cases to be reviewed. As I said, in the light of this case, a review is taking place in the British Virgin Islands.</p>
	<p pid="a.399.0/9">The Governor's office provided practical assistance following the accident and took a close interest in the case throughout. Staff maintain contact with the family through Luke's uncle, Tony Noble, who is resident in the British Virgin Islands and seconded to the Royal Virgin Islands police force. The Governor wrote a letter of condolence to Mr. and Mrs. Noble shortly after the accident.</p>
	<p pid="a.399.0/10">The Governor's office kept the overseas territories department of the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, which is responsible for the British Virgin Islands, fully informed of developments. The officer responsible for the British Virgin Islands in the Department was in contact with a member of Luke's family and wrote a letter of condolence to Mr. and Mrs. Noble. After initial contact with the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, the family did not request further assistance.</p>
	<p pid="a.399.0/11">As an overseas territory under British sovereignty, there is no legal framework for the provision of consular services that are normally provided by a state to its nationals in the territory of another state. However, we are well aware that to many UK tourists the overseas territories are as foreign as independent countries. The Foreign and Commonwealth Office and the staff in the Governors' offices are always ready and have appropriate training to provide assistance informally to visiting British citizens who may require help in an emergency while in an overseas territory.</p>
	<p pid="a.399.0/12">In conclusion, I repeat my thanks to my hon. Friend for raising this issue. We all feel sympathy with the Noble family, who have suffered a heart-wrenching loss. The loss of a loved one of such a young age is a tragedy. However, I hope that during this debate I have at least been able to clarify for my hon. Friend exactly how the judicial system in the British Virgin Islands works and where responsibility for decision-taking lies. As I tried to explain, no scope exists for appeal by the prosecution against sentence. Given its responsibility for the criminal justice system within the territory, it is the responsibility of the British Virgin Islands Government to review any change to the system. We understand that they are now doing do.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.402.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.402.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.403.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.403.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.403.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.403.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.405.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.405.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.405.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.405.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.405.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.405.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.407.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.407.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28a.407.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-06-28b.407.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

