<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.1.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.1.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.1.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.1.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.1.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.1.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.2.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.2.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.2.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.2.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.3.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.3.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.3.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.3.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.3.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.3.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.4.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.4.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.5.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.5.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.5.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.5.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.5.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.5.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.5.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.5.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.6.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.6.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.6.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.6.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.6.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.6.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.6.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1850" speakername="David Drew" colnum="6"  time="009:48:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0001.htm#09032425000530">
	<p pid="a.6.2/1">The hon. Gentleman is leaving that to me. The report is a good starting point, and I do not deny many of the problems that rural Britain is facing, but I want to examine some other issues and where we should be going in dealing with current problems.</p>
	<p pid="a.6.2/2">Let us start with the Select Committee report. Certainly I have some pride in what we penned. It is a good analysis of the problems and comes up with a number of solutions. There were two key points of inquiry that we started from. The first was the degree to which the rural economy can mainstream policies. We see this with the recession at the moment. The recession has an impact, but policies can also impact on the rural economy in the same way as they do on the urban economy. I have never believed that we have a sacrosanct rural economy that sits in splendid isolation and is different from the rest of the country. I feel strongly that we caricature the rural economy in that way to our cost. We also too often fall into the trap of believing that there is one rural economy and that we can have policies that embrace that.</p>
	<p pid="a.6.2/3">That is one reason why some of us were never happy about having any form of Ministry of rural affairs. It tends to make people believe that they can pull levers, but as the Select Committee has found time after time with our inquiries, DEFRA is unable to pull those levers in the rural economy, because so many of them are with&mdash;dare I say it?&mdash;higher-order Departments such as the Department for Children, Schools and Families, the Department of Health and the Department for Transport. Nevertheless, DEFRA can have an influence, and one of the good things that it has introduced is the idea of rural-proofing to see how wider policies are playing a part in the rural economy. That has become part of our lexicon.</p>
	<p pid="a.6.2/4">The second point of inquiry was to consider the potential for economic growth. Again, I am a wee bit disappointed that although the hon. Member for North Wiltshire quoted Stuart Burgess on a number of occasions, he did not refer to what Stuart Burgess said on that issue. He came up with astounding figures when he said that the unlocked potential of the rural economy is worth between &pound;236 billion and &pound;347 billion. All parties need to consider that as their starting point. One problem is that we are not considering how development can be a keynote element in what we talk about and do.</p>
	<p pid="a.6.2/5">My area is suffering because, again, there is a misunderstanding of the Strouds of this world. My area has a higher percentage of people employed in manufacturing than the national average and it is higher than anywhere else in Gloucestershire. At the moment, a number of the bigger firms face difficulties, which has a knock-on effect on the smaller firms. That said, one of the strange elements for someone such as me, who calls continually for a local supply chain, is that not having as much of a local supply chain as we want has meant that there has not been as great an impact on some of those smaller firms as I had feared. However, we do need to find ways to forestall some of the worst impacts of the recession.</p>
	<p pid="a.6.2/6">Like other hon. Members, I am involved every week in negotiations to try to protect jobs&mdash;principally to secure training opportunities in two of the larger companies in my area, Renishaw and Delphi. I hope that my right hon. Friend the Minister will take this point away, although of course it is not her responsibility: we need to ensure that we get wage compensation into the automotive industry, so that we can give value to that training. I and a number of other hon. Members are calling for that.</p>
	<p pid="a.6.2/7">Interestingly, agriculture is having almost a counter-cyclical impact on the economy. I do not believe that farming is going through an unalloyed period of joy. Nevertheless, the figures from 2007-08&mdash;the latest year for which we have figures&mdash;showed growth of nearly 40 per cent. in total income from farming. That can only be a good thing at the moment, because that money is going into the rural economy. The Committee's current inquiry is on food security. Without wishing to prejudge it in any way, I think that the future must be in our growing more of our own food. That means more farmers and more land. Although I could argue with the Government about the set-aside rules at the moment, perhaps we need to move on and consider the opportunities to which I have just referred, because that will help our rural economy and it really concentrates our minds on what opportunities there are.</p>
	<p pid="a.6.2/8">There are other impacts on the rural economy. I think that the Government have a good record on protection of public services&mdash;bar the Post Office, which I shall deal with separately. In my area, we have blocked the closures of village schools, other than in one case, in which there was an amalgamation. In other parts of Gloucestershire there have been closures, but that is because there are, in effect, no young people living in those villages any more. All parties have to face up to the fact that there has been rural depopulation. There has not necessarily been a huge movement of people away, but there has been a change in terms of social class&mdash;we know about the cost of living and the cost of housing in those areas&mdash;and we have also seen the ageing of the countryside. That is having an enormous impact, and the more rural and peripheral the areas, the greater the impact has been. We must do something to overcome that.</p>
	<p pid="a.6.2/9">When Labour came to power in 1997, some of us set up the Back-Bench group of rural Labour MPs and we did a rural audit. I think that that document has stood the test of time. I pay tribute to Peter Bradley, who was the chair. He is sadly no longer with us. We found that the overwhelming issue in rural Britain at that time was access to good public transport. Lack of such access was the reason why people either could not or did not live there. When we examined the issue again, housing had clearly moved way up the agenda. I suspect that at the moment the issue of jobs would be paramount in most people's minds. Again, we have to turn that into an opportunity, rather than just seeing it as a threat.</p>
	<p pid="a.6.2/10">As the rural advocate, rural tsar or whatever we want to call Stuart Burgess has been saying, there is clearly untapped potential in the rural economy. That has as much to do with jobs as anything else. We must recognise that we have to create jobs in rural Britain, and that we can do so. If we do that, we have to have people who can live in rural Britain, and we have to have reasonable transport so that people can move about there.</p>
	<p pid="a.6.2/11">The Government, with their rural transport grants and some of the things that they have done on health and a rural policy domain, have done well. The issue of the Post Office, however, is a running sore. I believe that the closures were often unnecessary and hurried and could have been dealt with in other ways. I have to say that dealing with Post Office Ltd or Royal Mail is part of the problem because they seem to have a death wish in terms of the services. I am pleased that at long last&mdash;through ideas such as the post bank and offering postal services, rather than the complete panoply of things that one would expect in a post office&mdash;we are beginning to move on and see how a flexible approach can begin to lock those services in.</p>
	<p pid="a.6.2/12">Let us move on to the private sector. The situation is in a sense gloomier there, partly because of the current state of the economy, but more than anything because of the way in which many of our villages have changed in terms of social stratification. We have seen the closure of shops and pubs, and we have seen other services dependent on them suffer. We could argue all day about the causes of that. I am pleased to see the work being done by <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1672" name="Greg Mulholland">the hon. Member for Leeds, North-West (Greg Mulholland)</phrase>. With the help of some of us, he has just made a submission regarding the Select Committee on Business and Enterprise inquiry into the future of pubs. That looks at, very straightforwardly, the role of pubcos&mdash;pub companies&mdash;which I think has been largely negative, and the way in which they have encouraged the closure of many pubs. The impact on shops has a lot to do with the lack of a market threshold and people not buying in their local shop. That is causing immense problems.</p>
	<p pid="a.6.2/13">That brings me to where I see many of the answers. We need social enterprise because that is the way to keep services open. I have three voluntary shops in my constituency, and I am likely to get two more. The three existing shops are at North Nibley, Cowley and Whiteshill. Another is operating as a pseudo-social enterprise at Chalford, and I hope that a further shop will shortly open in Horsley. All of that has come about because of the will-power of the local population, with some help from outside. That is the way we need to go.</p>
	<p pid="a.6.2/14">I want to link that to another issue. I pay tribute to two academic colleagues from the university of Gloucestershire, Nigel Curry and Stephen Owen, and to Kate Braithwaite from the Carnegie Institute, who have taught me what really goes on in rural areas. I want to advertise their work and I encourage the Minister to look at it, because there are some very interesting ideas about how we can provide, protect and improve services in rural Britain.</p>
	<p pid="a.6.2/15">The other issue that I want to link to is asset-based rural community development, which uses the property base in rural communities. Like other hon. Members, I have argued strongly that some buildings are underused&mdash;the church is an obvious one, and there are also the village halls. We need to look at that asset base and do some interesting things with it. That is crucial at this time in the recession. That asset base gives us an opportunity, and that is where the state can help centrally. Innovative grants and support in the form of advice and encouragement are long overdue. That is where we need to go. We need to learn the lessons from what has gone wrong. Too often, the rural economy is seen as an anchor that pulls things back, but it can be a driver. There are opportunities, and I want us to act on them.</p>
	<p pid="a.6.2/16">The key areas of housing, transport and jobs keep coming back, and we need to act on those and act quickly.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.9.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.9.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.9.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.9.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.10.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.10.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.10.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.10.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.10.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.10.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.10.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1489" speakername="Mark Williams" colnum="10"  time="010:05:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0002.htm#09032425000535">
	<p pid="a.10.2/1">It is a pleasure to serve under your chairmanship, Mr. Atkinson. I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1926" name="James Gray">the hon. Member for North Wiltshire (Mr. Gray)</phrase> on securing this important debate.</p>
	<p pid="a.10.2/2">I should say at the start that there is rurality and rurality&mdash;the hon. Gentleman alluded to that&mdash;and there are differences in the communities that we represent. We have heard about the farms on the periphery of Upminster and we have heard from Wiltshire and Gloucestershire. However, I represent a very rural, sparsely populated constituency of 440,000 acres and 147 villages.</p>
	<p pid="a.10.2/3">The recession affects all parts of the country, of course, and national political and economic dimensions permeate every part of our constituencies. However, my point to the Minister&mdash;I am sure that she understands this&mdash;relates to the fragility of the rural community and particularly of its sparsely populated communities. I do not necessarily subscribe to the view that the recession is hitting rural areas harder than urban areas, but we none the less need to respond to that fragility. Rural communities find themselves on the brink and are struggling to ensure their future viability.</p>
	<p pid="a.10.2/4">Like all hon. Members, I have been having discussions with small businesses in my constituency. Such businesses play the most vital role in our rural communities. More than half the people employed in my constituency are employed in micro-businesses&mdash;businesses that employ fewer than nine people. About two thirds of the people employed in my constituency are employed by businesses with 49 or fewer employees.</p>
	<p pid="a.10.2/5">The chief concern of such small businesses is still the lack of credit from the banks. They are also concerned by the charges that the banks are levying. A Federation of Small Businesses survey found that 16 per cent. of small firms have seen an increase in their bank fees in recent months, while 33 per cent. said that the banks were imposing changes in their financial arrangements that would prove detrimental to their futures. The case has been well rehearsed, but there is a mismatch between what we hear from the Government in this place and what is being done on the ground.</p>
	<p pid="a.10.2/6">As my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1444" name="Roger Williams">the Member for Brecon and Radnorshire (Mr. Williams)</phrase> suggested, there is also concern about the forthcoming 5 per cent. rise in business rates in England and Wales. The RPI in September 2008 was the determining factor, but inflation was then at its peak. Although my hon. Friend did not use the word today, he described the situation as &quot;madness&quot; during the last week's Welsh questions, and indeed it is&mdash;it is difficult for any of us to disagree with him. It is bad enough to hit businesses with a massive rise in business rates at any time, but when we are in the grip of the worst recession for a generation, it is entirely counter-productive. If our intention is to kick-start the economy, we should encourage businesses far more proactively. I urge the Minister to take back to the Treasury the message that we need an averaged RPI when we look at business rates, rather than a figure at a particular point in time.</p>
	<p pid="a.10.2/7">My hon. Friend and the hon. Member for North Wiltshire alluded to empty property rates. The introduction of a &pound;15,000 threshold is helpful, but many businesses are still suffering from having to pay full rates. Again, I ask the Minister to take that concern back to her colleagues.</p>
	<p pid="a.10.2/8">The hon. Member for North Wiltshire is a member of the Environment, Food and Rural Affairs Committee, and <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1850" name="David Drew">the hon. Member for Stroud (Mr. Drew)</phrase> mentioned its excellent report, so I hope that they will not mind me, as an interloper from Wales, briefly touching on it. The report focused on the potential in the rural economy, rather than just on the concerns that many of us have. I find it odd, as, I think, the Select Committee did, that DEFRA has not quantified the potential in rural communities. I hope that the Minister will give her backing to that recommendation. The sum that has been mentioned of, I think, &pound;237 billion, represents huge potential for the rural community.</p>
	<p pid="a.10.2/9">The report rightly highlights the position of rural issues within the Government, and points out that instead of making a rural affairs target a departmental strategic objective, those matters should be part of a cross-Government public service agreement. Of course, while DEFRA must pay attention to rural needs, other Departments certainly do not rural-proof their policies. I can give two parochial examples of that from west Wales. The new motorcycle testing regime requires testing to be carried out at a multi-purpose test centre. There will be none of those centres in Ceredigion or Powys, so my constituents will have round trips of 150 miles. The other example is the closure of tax offices. The closure of the office of Her Majesty's Revenue and Customs in Aberystwyth, in my constituency, was justified on the grounds that it was the smallest tax office in the country. Neither of those decisions was rural-proofed.</p>
	<p pid="a.10.2/10">I have only one, very mild, criticism of the report, and that is its focus on the Commission for Rural Communities as the body that will have to consult on rural benchmarks and indicators. The CRC is an excellent body, with an excellent rural communities tsar, but it is an England-only body, and given that aspects of DEFRA policy are not devolved, I hope that Welsh bodies and Ministers will be consulted about non-devolved matters.</p>
	<p pid="a.10.2/11">It is not possible to overstate the importance of broadband in the future of the rural economy, which would be significantly boosted by a universal service obligation, as Lord Carter identified in his report &quot;Digital Britain&quot;. We await the final report for details about how that can be achieved. There are significant issues to overcome in some of our communities, not least of which is topography. We want a thorough report, but I hope that that will be swift. The new universal service obligation could certainly alter BT's current position as the supplier of internet infrastructure, and my concern is that with uncertainty about the future of the new USO, BT may be reluctant to carry out the work until the new system is in place. We need action on that now.</p>
	<p pid="a.10.2/12">Much of rural Wales is blighted by &quot;not-spots&quot;. It is not just a case of the speed at which broadband can be accessed; it is more that there are no broadband connections at all. Broadband is vital for rural communities, and they are mindful of its importance. The broadband think-tank Point Topic recently released a figure showing that 26.9 per cent. of people in Wales are unable to get 2 megabits per second connection. In that respect, Wales is second only to Northern Ireland, which has a figure of 32 per cent. BT claims that 99 per cent. of homes in Wales can access broadband, but that is not the experience in my constituency.</p>
	<p pid="a.10.2/13">Some parts of the farming community have pointed out that they can do well in the recession. The growing popularity of locally sourced and organic food has given farmers opportunities&mdash;there is potential. The increase in lamb and beef prices has been welcomed, although of course much of the benefit has been dulled by increased costs. There are, of course, other severe impediments to the farming sector. The chief concern among my constituents is the proposed introduction of compulsory electronic identification of sheep, even though that may seem like a peripheral issue. I was alarmed when, during a recent Prime Minister's questions, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1506" name="David Jones">the hon. Member for Clwyd, West (Mr. Jones)</phrase> raised the issue and he was roundly laughed at from the Labour Benches. The issue is a critical for hon. Members representing the farming community. The National Farmers Union revealed in a recent survey that 84 per cent. of sheep farmers in Wales said they would reduce their flock, and 32 per cent. said they would consider quitting altogether. The hon. Member for Stroud is of course right that we need to attract new people and young people into the farming sector, but that is not the way to do it in the less favoured areas of much of the country. The NFU has provided a vivid illustration of the concern in the industry about the plans in question.</p>
	<p pid="a.10.2/14">I secured a debate on the matter last year. The Minister&mdash;I think that she had just been appointed&mdash;was extremely sympathetic to our cause, and there was cross-party agreement. The nationalist party in Wales, the Liberal Democrats, the Conservative party, and Labour voices as well, all sympathised very much with the view opposed to the proposal. I believe that the Council of Ministers meets this week, and it is essential that we put the matter back on to Europe's agenda.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.13.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.13.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.13.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.13.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.13.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.13.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.13.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.13.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.13.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1489" speakername="Mark Williams" colnum="13"  time="010:05:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0003.htm#09032425000539">
	<p pid="a.13.3/1">The hon. Gentleman is right. There is a complete lack of coherence in the policy, and we need the Government to continue to make those points on our behalf and on behalf of the farming community, not least because it is strongly felt in that community that the measures that were already in place were robust enough to deal with the problems that the European Commission wanted to alleviate. I hope that we shall hear from the Minister whether progress has been made.</p>
	<p pid="a.13.3/2">I shall leave my script now to talk more directly about the social issues raised by the hon. Member for Stroud. My constituency is rural, and I have no doubt that the sun is shining on the coast of Ceredigion today and that it all looks very rosy. However, underneath that picture is something more sinister. It is a convergence funding area for good reason. Many of my rural and urban communities have the National Assembly for Wales designation of Communities First area, because they have some of the highest rates of deprivation in not just Britain, but the entire European Union. Perhaps my vision of the essential ingredients of village communities is old-fashioned, but it is one in which there is still a functioning post office&mdash;not the van that trundles in intermittently and disappears, and which, I suspect, will disappear altogether in three years' time&mdash;in which there are churches and, to add to what the hon. Member for North Wiltshire said, chapels as well, and one where if there is still a last village shop, it has a sustainable future. We have heard about young people moving into a community. I suggest that if those essential ingredients of community have gone, if the village hall or old church or chapel has been sold to development when people have moved from outside and is no longer there for community use, if the community facilities and post office have gone, if the last shop has gone, if there are pressures on rural garages&mdash;something that has not been mentioned in the debate&mdash;and if the pub is under threat, there is very little incentive for young families to move into a community. That is, of course, all compounded by the economic situation.</p>
	<p pid="a.13.3/3">In parts of rural Wales there is migration of young families away&mdash;goodness knows where to, given the enormity of the economic problems. The hon. Member for Stroud alluded to the fact that elderly people are moving in. That means elderly people living on the interest from their savings which, in the present climate, affects their purchasing power as well. That is the reality of rural life now. It is not in a box that is distinct from national pressures, but there is a sense of fragility about our communities, and we ignore that fragility at our peril.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.14.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.14.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.15.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.15.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.15.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.15.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.15.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.15.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.16.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.16.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.16.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1923" speakername="Tim Farron" colnum="16"  time="010:26:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0003.htm#09032425000544">
	<p pid="a.16.0/1">Thank you, Mr. Atkinson. I am not sure whether to be flattered, but at least <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1477" name="James Paice">the hon. Member for South-East Cambridgeshire (Mr. Paice)</phrase> has a few more minutes to prepare his speech. None the less, it is a pleasure to serve under your chairmanship.</p>
	<p pid="a.16.0/2">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1926" name="James Gray">the hon. Member for North Wiltshire (Mr. Gray)</phrase> on making a powerful opening speech. The debate is of immense importance to the House. Frankly, it ought to have been attended by more Members. However, as Members representing rural areas, we are not engaged in special pleading. We have many strengths, as well as facing many challenges. However, we feel that the rural economy presents a slightly different picture to the urban one.</p>
	<p pid="a.16.0/3">We are concerned that the Government, and the apparatus of government in general, lack an understanding of the workings of rural communities. For instance, a number of the excellent civil servants that I meet see the countryside as something that is to be visited on the odd weekend; they do not understand the vitality of the rural community. That is part of the malaise; it is part of the problem.</p>
	<p pid="a.16.0/4">As the Member of Parliament for a large chunk of the Lake district, part of the Yorkshire dales and a large swathe of south Cumbria that is just as beautiful but not in either, I have a body of evidence to draw on in my remarks. It is important to stress the strength of the rural economy. It is important to remind people that, much more than in urban areas, businesses and industries in the rural community are more likely to have a more positive balance sheet. We export more; we do more business outside our shores than the average business in an urban area. Our contribution to the bottom line of UK plc is therefore greater.</p>
	<p pid="a.16.0/5">Over the past 10 years, the growth in rural areas of knowledge-intensive services, often home-based, has been at twice the rate of that in urban areas. Contrary to public perception, the percentage of people employed in manufacturing in rural areas is roughly the same as in urban areas. There is an innate strength in the rural economy, and it is important to acknowledge that before considering the fact that the recession is hitting us, and hitting us hard&mdash;and in some ways hitting us differently from urban Britain.</p>
	<p pid="a.16.0/6">Unemployment is undoubtedly rising. I draw up experience in my constituency. Kendal serves the bulk of my constituency, and the local jobcentre has seen a tripling in the number of people claiming jobseeker's allowance for the first time. As we heard from other Members, we also struggle because the other jobcentre that serves my constituency closed a couple of years ago. It is at Ulverston, just outside my patch, in the constituency of Barrow and Furness, which is represented by the Secretary of State for Defence. That is having a critical effect on the ability of people living in the rural areas on the Furness and Cartmel peninsulas to find employment. The quality of Jobcentre Plus has undoubtedly increased, but it is not good if one cannot get to it. I think that that was incredibly short-sighted.</p>
	<p pid="a.16.0/7">As has been mentioned by a number of hon. Members, rural areas have a higher proportion of older residents, who are more likely than others to rely on the income from savings. Negative inflation and almost non-existent interest rates have a massive impact on the spending power of ordinary families in rural Britain, which, obviously, leads to a negative multiplier effect and people spending less money in their communities. We heard about the fragility of the rural economy from my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1489" name="Mark Williams">the Member for Ceredigion (Mark Williams)</phrase>, who made an impassioned plea on behalf of his communities.</p>
	<p pid="a.16.0/8">The drop in demand comes at a time when many of our rural services are already under threat. We have lost rural post offices owing to a deliberate closure programme and the removal of vital services that underpin post offices. As <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1850" name="David Drew">the hon. Member for Stroud (Mr. Drew)</phrase> said, we have also lost village pubs, which is down not only to a reduction in demand, but to unfair competition and ownership legislation. That needs to be addressed immediately. Furthermore, over the past 20 or 30 years, we have also lost community shops, in part, due to unfair advantages granted to out-of-town supermarkets.</p>
	<p pid="a.16.0/9">The recession has hit an infrastructure already weakened by bad Government policy over a number of years, but the ultimate strength of our rural communities centres on their creativity and resourcefulness. We should be proud of that and play to those strengths. I shall provide three quick examples from my constituency: the first is the Greyhound pub at Grizebeck, where I spent Friday night. It is a community-run pub that would have shut had it not been for the community volunteers running that enterprise. Secondly, I also went to the Storth post office, which is a community-owned, co-operative enterprise employing its own postmaster. Had it not been for those people, it would undoubtedly have shut. The third example is the Witherslack shop. The former post office closed down, and Post Office Ltd. would not allow it to reopen, so the local people&mdash;this is a small community of 400 houses&mdash;raised &pound;150,000 and worked with the local community land trust to reopen that outstanding local shop. All those wonderful examples, which demonstrate the vitality of rural communities, happened despite, and not because, of the Government. We need to play to the strengths of rural communities, not cause greater difficulties.</p>
	<p pid="a.16.0/10">One of the great problems faced by rural areas is that we appear more affluent than we are, a point to which the hon. Member for North Wiltshire referred. Unemployment in many rural areas is relatively low, but we must not forget that employment, certainly in places such as mine, is very much part-time, low-paid and, because it is often in the tourism sector, seasonal. Another important indicator of poverty and well-being that is rarely acknowledged is the differential between average incomes and average house prices. In rural Britain, the gap between those two figures is greatest. In my constituency, the average house price, even with the drop in house prices, is 12 times the average income, which leaves the average person completely unable to afford their own home. Some 12,500 houses in my constituency were once council houses, and a few more than 3,000 still are, but now, with the great tragedy of repossession, more people are moving on to the waiting list. It is a real pressure-cooker situation and a problem that we need to address.</p>
	<p pid="a.16.0/11">The development of more affordable housing would not only meet the needs of the hundreds of thousands of people in rural Britain who are desperate to escape the abysmal housing, or who have to move away from rural areas, which robs them of their vitality, but give a vital boost to the construction industry. That has to be done in a bottom-up and effective way. There is the will within rural communities&mdash;we are the opposite of nimbies&mdash;to build new more affordable homes, but the Government's one-size-fits-all regional spatial strategy is not the answer. It is counter-productive and a nonsense in a district such as mine, where more than half the land mass is in a national park so cannot be touched. That is why the regional spatial strategy should go.</p>
	<p pid="a.16.0/12">We need to support rural communities in coming up with their own solutions. For example, in my area, we have trailed a &quot;home on the farm&quot; initiative, which allows farmers to develop under-used or disused farm buildings and turn them into affordable homes for local families. In the past few weeks, the first was built at Selside just north of Kendal. We also need to maintain consumer demand in rural communities and acknowledge the damaging impact on some of them of excessive second-home ownership. We need to consider ways of managing that problem, putting covenants on new builds and perhaps giving local authorities some tax-varying powers.</p>
	<p pid="a.16.0/13">It is vital that farming, which is the backbone of the economy, be put at the top of the agenda. It tends to survive recessions&mdash;it tends not to do too well out of the booms either&mdash;because even in developed economies people still have to eat. They might change their demands and where they shop, but the bottom line is that they still need to eat. We are also blessed by the fact that British farmers are some of the most entrepreneurial in the world, producing the highest quality food and meeting by far the highest environmental and animal welfare standards in the world.</p>
	<p pid="a.16.0/14">It is important to note, however, that British farming is at a crossroads, because despite the industry's huge strength in quality and innovation, the unit of production&mdash;the family farm&mdash;is under enormous pressure from the overly powerful players higher up the chain, such as, most notably, the supermarkets. The impact on the farming economy of this unfair market is huge. Despite British farming's many strengths, we have still lost 900 million litres of dairy production in the past three years, and dairy farmers still leave the industry at a rate of two a day.</p>
	<p pid="a.16.0/15">Anecdotally, in my constituency, six out of every seven hill farmers have no line of succession. The hon. Member for North Wiltshire referred to livestock farmers' incomes, but it sounds like his livestock farmers are doing better than mine. Average hill farm incomes are significantly less than &pound;10,000 a year, so no wonder that many question whether they have a future in the industry and struggle to persuade their children to follow them. Furthermore, I endorse the comments of my hon. Friends the Members for Ceredigion and for Brecon and Radnorshire (Mr. Williams) about sheep tagging, and I hope that the Minister will refer to the situation in Europe.</p>
	<p pid="a.16.0/16">It is important that the Government accept the Liberal Democrat proposal for a supermarket regulator, rather than a toothless ombudsman, to provide control and power within the market and to ensure that farmers get a fair price for their produce. It is also important that we make good use of the public money invested in agriculture. It seems a nonsense that we are wasting &pound;7 million a year handing out tiny cheques to people at the bottom end of single farm payments&mdash;people who, bless them, are not farmers&mdash;when that money could be redistributed and spent on, for example, setting up a new hill farm apprenticeship scheme. We should certainly do that.</p>
	<p pid="a.16.0/17">I endorse the comments of <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1696" name="Philip Dunne">the hon. Member for Ludlow (Mr. Dunne)</phrase> about public sector jobs in rural areas. It is beyond me why the Government are pressing ahead with their tax office closure programme at a time like this. During British tourism week, it is important to ensure that we support British tourism and recognise that, in England, the funding for the marketing of tourism is dire compared with other parts of the United Kingdom. We should also recognise that, in the Lake district alone, we have a &pound;1 billion industry giving vast amounts of money to the Exchequer, but getting very little back for marketing support.</p>
	<p pid="a.16.0/18">There are real ways to boost our rural economy. We can make the food market fair through a supermarket regulator. We can ensure that taxpayers' money designed to support farmers does actually do so, and that it is not wasted on bureaucracy, but directed at helping a new generation of farmers to bring new vitality to the industry. At a time when we are wasting more than &pound;10 billion of food a year, we could help farmers by investing in new anaerobic digestion facilities on farms&mdash;where people want them&mdash;to create clean energy and to dispose of waste. We could back companies in rural areas that want to reduce energy usage while creating employment. I must mention the croppers who provide the paper for <i>Hansard</i> who want a biodigester for their site in Burneside, but need &pound;200,000 of public of money to buy one. That would be a massive service to the community, if only they could get it. We need a new deal for the countryside. Rural Britain should be seen as a living and vibrant set of communities that must be able to reach its potential and play to its strengths. We need a Government who understand rural communities and who are on the side of the many in those communities.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.19.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.19.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.22.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.22.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.22.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.22.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.22.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.22.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.22.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1690" speakername="Jane Kennedy" speakeroffice="The Minister of State, Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs"  colnum="22"  time="010:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0004.htm#09032425000548">
	<p pid="a.22.2/1">It is a pleasure to be here under your chairmanship, Mr. Atkinson. I know that the constituency that you represent gives you a keen interest in this debate. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1926" name="James Gray">The hon. Member for North Wiltshire (Mr. Gray)</phrase> is to be congratulated on securing the debate. Normally, the Under-Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs, my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1750" name="Huw Irranca-Davies">the Member for Ogmore (Huw Irranca-Davies)</phrase>, would have responded to this debate in detail, but he could not be here this morning as he is on Government business. However, I hope to be able to respond to the genuine concerns that have been expressed.</p>
	<p pid="a.22.2/2">It is true that the recession is making life hard for many communities and businesses. As we have heard this morning, that is just as true of rural communities as it is of our towns and cities. It is important that we do not treat the two separately. I heard the comment that the hon. Member for North Wiltshire made from a sedentary position about my urban constituency of Liverpool, Wavertree, and I thought that it was somewhat ungenerous.</p>
	<p pid="a.22.2/3">My hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1714" name="Ashok Kumar">the Member for Middlesbrough, South and East Cleveland (Dr. Kumar)</phrase> has been urging me to respond robustly to some of the more ridiculous suggestions that the Labour party is unaware of the concerns of rural and farming communities. After all, more than 120 Labour Members represent rural constituencies. However, I will not respond to those suggestions, because I should take time to respond to other, more serious points, not the least of which concerns what happened yesterday at the Agriculture Council in Brussels.</p>
	<p pid="a.22.2/4">In many ways, the economies of rural areas mirror those of urban areas, but rural areas boast businesses of all shapes and sizes, as hon. Members have said. They provide all sorts of goods and services, and change in rural communities continues apace. That can be seen particularly in the growth of high-tech and high-skill businesses. The Commission for Rural Communities tells us that in the past 10 years, the number of people working in businesses in rural areas has risen by nearly 300,000, which is more than twice the increase in urban areas. As <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1477" name="James Paice">the hon. Member for South-East Cambridgeshire (Mr. Paice)</phrase> said, rural areas are home to about 1 million businesses&mdash;a quarter of England's total&mdash;providing just over 5.5 million jobs. Together, they have a turnover of more than &pound;300 billion a year. In fact, there are more businesses for every 10,000 people in rural areas than in urban areas.</p>
	<p pid="a.22.2/5">The evidence to date suggests that the impact of the current economic situation on rural areas is similar to its impact in urban areas. Not a single Member who has spoken has failed to mention concerns about rising unemployment and job losses. Many have listed the impacts on their constituency. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1922" name="Andrew Murrison">The hon. Member for Westbury (Dr. Murrison)</phrase>, who is not in the Chamber just now, and other hon. Members drew attention to, and criticised, Government decisions to move Government work, as they described it, from rural communities into more urban settings. However, in my previous roles, I have spent many hours debating such issues, particularly how we collect taxes in this country. We need to modernise our tax collection systems, and that involves employing fewer people. In this economic climate, it would not be right for the public sector to be less efficient than it could and should be simply to provide employment. I know that hon. Members who have participated in this debate would not urge that of any Government.</p>
	<p pid="a.22.2/6">The employment rate in rural and urban areas is similar, but there are proportionately more retired people and fewer unemployed people in rural areas. The proportion of people claiming unemployment-related benefits is rising at a similar rate in rural and urban areas. The number of redundancies is lower in rural areas in both absolute and proportional terms, but not by a great deal.</p>
	<p pid="a.22.2/7">I am not complacent. As someone who represents a Liverpool constituency, I have particular reason to know the threat of serious unemployment, although I will not waste time drawing attention to the previous Government's attitude to dealing with unemployment. We need a better understanding of risk if we are to enable rural communities and businesses to survive the economic downturn. It may be that we should discuss those risks and how they should be managed on another occasion when we have more time.</p>
	<p pid="a.22.2/8">I have been asked a couple of specific questions, and I shall respond to the question about e-ID, as I know that there is a lot of interest in it. It was discussed yesterday at the Agriculture Council, and a large number of countries&mdash;13 or 14, I think&mdash;took part in the debate. I would not say that I was over-encouraged by other member states' responses, but it was encouraging, at least, that many countries spoke in favour of the Hungarian motion to introduce e-ID on a voluntary basis. The Commission also responded relatively positively to my suggestion that it should consider further our proposals that would reduce even further the burdens of that otherwise costly regulation. Although I accept that not all rural businesses involve farming, businesses such as upland farmers and sheep farmers are critical to some of the most beautiful areas of the British countryside, and I accept the points made about such farmers' income.</p>
	<p pid="a.22.2/9">We need to ensure that any regulation that we make is proportionate to the policy problem that we are trying to fix. There is unanimity not only among parties in the UK, but in the Welsh Assembly and Scottish Parliament, that the e-ID proposals, as they stand, are disproportionate and that the Commission's assessment of the impact is inadequate and should be revisited and renewed so that we can get a better understanding at Commission level of the proposals' potentially damaging impact. I am hopeful that we can make further progress with the Commission. The commissioner indicated that she was prepared to consider further details, including locating reading equipment at centres where sheep are brought in the normal course of business, whether in marketplaces or in abattoirs or processing plants.</p>
	<p pid="a.22.2/10">As always happens in such debates, time is running away. My hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1850" name="David Drew">the Member for Stroud (Mr. Drew)</phrase>, who made a good and thoughtful contribution, referred to ways in which we could help rural communities through the recession. He promoted the idea of social enterprise&mdash;I agree. If anything, other parties demonstrated their lack of understanding of the potential benefits of such ideas in their responses to his proposals. The social enterprise model has strengths and could be adopted in a rural setting.</p>
	<p pid="a.22.2/11">There are great pressures on the housing market at the moment, which is why the Government are taking steps to help home owners and first-time buyers in urban and rural areas, expanding the availability of shared equity, and working closely with lenders to keep people in their homes. For example, we are extending income support for mortgage interest payments to help people when they fall on hard times.</p>
	<p pid="a.22.2/12">Finally, as I have only a few moments left, let me say that I agree with the comments of the hon. Member for North Wiltshire about broadband. We are working hard to ensure that funding is available through the regional development agencies to encourage and help farmers and other rural businesses to adopt and adapt to broadband.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.25.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.25.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.25.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.25.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.25.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1717" speakername="Siobhain McDonagh" colnum="25"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0004.htm#09032425000549">
	<p pid="a.25.1/1">I am grateful for the chance to debate an important matter. What is happening at the moment in Sri Lanka is an international humanitarian crisis, and the International Red Cross says:</p>
	<p pid="a.25.1/2" class="indent">&quot;the humanitarian situation is deteriorating by the day.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.25.1/3">Sri Lanka is, in many ways, a forgotten crisis. More than 3,000 people have been killed in Tamil areas of Sri Lanka since the end of January, and that is many more than the number who died in Gaza last autumn. Every day, 150,000 people are being shelled in the Sri Lankan Government's designated no-fire zone, and tens of thousands more are trapped in a thin strip of land&mdash;just 13 square miles&mdash;where the battles are taking place.</p>
	<p pid="a.25.1/4">Despite those huge numbers, we must not forget that this is also a deeply personal tragedy. Every Friday, I hold an advice surgery for about five hours. As is the case for many MPs, barely a week goes by without me meeting constituents who have family members back home in the Tamil region of Sri Lanka. More than 70,000 people have been killed in the conflict; the numbers are so big that the crisis is almost impossible to comprehend. Each week, I meet constituents face to face who tell me their stories and fears for their families, which makes a complex international crisis very personal.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.25.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.25.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.25.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.25.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.25.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1717" speakername="Siobhain McDonagh" colnum="25"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0004.htm#09032425000551">
	<p pid="a.25.3/1">I agree with the hon. Gentleman, as would all hon. Members in the Chamber&mdash;their constituents have brought them here. The work of the Tamil community in Britain has tried to force this issue up the list of things that the Government are considering.</p>
	<p pid="a.25.3/2">I have been trying to trace a number of constituents' relatives who are caught up in the conflict. Last week, I was told by the International Committee of the Red Cross that it is</p>
	<p pid="a.25.3/3" class="indent">&quot;unfortunately, not able to carry out tracing in this area.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.25.3/4">Throughout the debate, I hope that hon. Members will put themselves in the position of my constituents who have been told by the organisation that is most likely to be able to locate their families, &quot;Sorry, we can't.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.25.3/5">Britain's Tamil community is large and vibrant. It adds enormously to the economy and well-being of our country. There are approximately 250,000 Tamils within the M25. In my constituency, as I am sure in those of all hon. Members, they are hard-working, small business people. They are doctors, or the people on whom we rely for the continuation and running of our cities.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.25.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.25.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.26.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.26.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.26.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1717" speakername="Siobhain McDonagh" colnum="26"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0005.htm#09032425000553">
	<p pid="a.26.0/1">I agree with the hon. Gentleman. The work of the Tamil community in highlighting a cause to which people tend to close their eyes has been admirable. The Tamil community in my constituency works hard. People send their kids to university in overwhelming numbers. At this time of year, they come to my surgery desperate for places in grammar schools within the London borough of Sutton&mdash;as a secondary modern girl, I often find that challenge difficult. One constituent came to me to say how outraged he was that the Government were discriminating against pupils from public schools getting places at Oxford and Cambridge. That was a Tamil sub-postmaster in my constituency who had managed to afford to send his daughter to Wimbledon High school. How many people of our community in similar circumstances would be in a position to do that? That shows the emphasis placed on education within the Tamil community.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.26.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.26.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.26.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.26.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.26.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.26.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.26.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.26.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.27.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.27.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.27.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.27.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.27.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.27.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.28.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.28.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.28.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.28.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.28.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.28.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.28.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.28.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.28.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1628" speakername="Andrew Dismore" colnum="28"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0005.htm#09032425000564">
	<p pid="a.28.3/1">I assure my hon. Friend that I do not have a drug problem, despite what the Sri Lankan Government say on their website. They have also suggested that I am embracing a terrorist regime, but I have been one of the main critics of the LTTE when I have stood up for Tamil people in the House. I have investigated whether it would be possible to sue the Sri Lankan Government for libel but, apparently, sovereign immunity means that I cannot. Bearing in mind that the law does not allow us to hold that Government to account in the courts, I urge my hon. Friend the Minister to bring pressure to bear on the Sri Lankan high commission to make sure that it stops these attacks on Members when we are simply doing our job.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.29.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.29.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.30.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.30.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.30.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.30.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.30.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.30.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.30.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1560" speakername="Stephen Pound" colnum="30"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0005.htm#09032425000568">
	<p pid="a.30.2/1">I am sorry to interrupt my hon. Friend's flow. She mentioned that the Government of Sri Lanka have run a successful PR campaign, but does she agree that if Members of Parliament receive one more photograph&mdash;we seem to be receiving such photographs hourly&mdash;of a Government of Sri Lankan soldier cradling a Tamil child, it will have completely the opposite affect of that intended? I am starting to doubt seriously the veracity of that propaganda&mdash;not that I had an enormous amount of belief in it in the first place&mdash;because it there is simply too much and it is too indiscriminate.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.31.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.31.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.31.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.31.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.31.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.31.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.31.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.31.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.31.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.31.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.32.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.32.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.32.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1651" speakername="Lee Scott" colnum="32"  time="011:23:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0006.htm#09032425000574">
	<p pid="a.32.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1717" name="Siobhain McDonagh">the hon. Member for Mitcham and Morden (Siobhain McDonagh)</phrase> on securing the debate. It is vital that we raise these issues, but I promise to be brief, Mr. Atkinson.</p>
	<p pid="a.32.0/2">My constituents are, like those of the hon. Lady, concerned about their families and what is happening. We are the only voices who can put forward those concerns because, as has been said, our media are not doing so. With every other conflict of recent times, people have turned on the news and it has been a No. 1 or No. 2 item. However, I cannot remember the last time I have seen anything on any news bulletin about this issue. A tragedy is unfolding and innocent people are losing their lives.</p>
	<p pid="a.32.0/3">Like <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1628" name="Andrew Dismore">the hon. Member for Hendon (Mr. Dismore)</phrase>, I have always spoken up against terrorism and will continue to do so. However, we are not talking about that; we are talking about innocent women, children and men being killed every day. The world seems to be saying nothing and is completely silent. I agree with the hon. Member for Mitcham and Morden: pressure must be brought to bear on the Sri Lankan Government. If that pressure has to take the form of a suspension from the Commonwealth, and that is what it will take to get the message through that a ceasefire must happen now, so be it.</p>
	<p pid="a.32.0/4">Particularly over the past few months, but also in the past few weeks, hon. Members from all parties have been calling for that ceasefire. We attended a meeting with the Foreign Secretary, and a number of us also met the Prime Minister to discuss the issue. Everyone is calling for a ceasefire, but it seems that the Sri Lankan Government are not taking a blind bit of notice of what anyone anywhere in the world is saying. That has to stop and it has to stop now. In four or six weeks' time we cannot still be saying exactly the same thing, because a lack of action will mean that more innocent people will have been dying.</p>
	<p pid="a.32.0/5">My constituents, like those of the hon. Member for Mitcham and Morden, come from all walks of life. However, a few weeks ago, they gathered to raise money and humanitarian aid to help the young people and those who are suffering so terribly. I sincerely hope that that aid is allowed through to the people who so desperately need it now. The world should hang its head in shame if it allows what is happening to continue.</p>
	<p pid="a.32.0/6">Like the hon. Lady, I have spoken to colleagues about the matter, some of whom gave me the same response that she received. The high commission's public relations machine has to be commended, because, like other hon. Members, I get e-mails from it perhaps two or three times a day. Some of the things that the Sri Lankan Government have said about anyone who dares to speak up about providing humanitarian aid for those who are suffering are deplorable. They should ashamed of what they have said about hon. Members who are purely doing their jobs and representing their constituents' concerns about humanitarian issues. I hope that that is taken on board when they read the report of the debate. If they stop saying such things, they might find that people have a different opinion.</p>
	<p pid="a.32.0/7">A wise man once said, &quot;With whom can I talk peace, but my enemies?&quot; He was right. I hope that the Sri Lankan Government will listen, talk peace and stop the carnage now. Perhaps there can then be a peaceful future for everyone in Sri Lanka and people will be able to live in harmony together. Perhaps they can be educated, have food on their tables, a roof over their head, hospital treatment when they need it, and motorways opened. If that can happen, we will have done some good in this House of Commons. I will end my contribution there, Mr. Atkinson, but I would like to apologise for the fact that at approximately quarter to 12, I have to go to a meeting that was prearranged weeks ago. I apologise for having to leave at that time, but I felt it important to be here and say those few words.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.33.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.33.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.33.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1572" speakername="Joan Ryan" colnum="33"  time="011:27:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0006.htm#09032425000575">
	<p pid="a.33.0/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1717" name="Siobhain McDonagh">the Member for Mitcham and Morden (Siobhain McDonagh)</phrase> on not only securing the debate, but putting the case for action so eloquently. That is what is crucial about this morning. It is not just about a debate or words; it is a call for action. My hon. Friend has called for Sri Lanka to be suspended from the Commonwealth. In recent weeks, there have been calls for our Government to seek a UN Security Council resolution. None of those things are happening. However, the Prime Minister is, I believe, the first world leader to call for a ceasefire. That call was very welcome and genuine. We were all pleased to hear that call, but it was some weeks ago, and we know that fine words and good intentions on the part of all of us here will not save a single life. The time for action is now.</p>
	<p pid="a.33.0/2">We have outlined all the arguments and we must continue to do so, because the matter is not high enough up the political or media agenda to get the attention it so clearly needs and deserves. It is worth repeating some of my hon. Friend's points. I refer particularly to the leaked report by the United Nations Office of the Resident/Humanitarian Coordinator that put the total minimum number of civilian casualties between <phrase class="date" code="2009-01-20">20 January</phrase> and <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-07">7 March 2009</phrase> at 9,924, including 2,683 deaths. It was later conceded that the figure was likely to be a gross underestimate. Those are numbers, but if 2,683 people were lined up to greet us in Westminster Hall, we would see exactly what the number means&mdash;and that is just since <phrase class="date" code="2009-01-20">20 January</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.33.0/3">This is a catastrophe, and we know that it is happening. We do see some images, but not enough. There is not enough of a sense of reality about the situation. If there were, I cannot believe that action would not be taken.</p>
	<p pid="a.33.0/4">The most important thing that has happened recently is the offer that was made at the weekend. In fact, it was more than an offer. As has been said, the political leader of the Tamil Tigers, Balasingham Nadesan, pleaded for a ceasefire, and I understand that less than three weeks ago a ceasefire offer was put on the table, again by the Tamil Tigers, but was rejected out of hand by Sri Lanka. The excuse is made by the Sri Lankan Government that they made offers a year or more ago that were not taken up. That does not make it okay not to listen to a ceasefire offer now. Given the number of people who are dying or being injured, a ceasefire is required immediately. If it was right for the Sri Lankan Government to suggest some time ago that there should be a ceasefire, surely it must be right for them to take up such offers now. It is completely contradictory to ignore the pleadings for a ceasefire, in the face of the situation and the suffering.</p>
	<p pid="a.33.0/5">An important point that is worth noting&mdash;it has been made by several Members&mdash;is the willingness to enter negotiations without preconditions. I do not understand how Sri Lanka can refuse that offer. It gives our Government every possible opening to put on as much pressure as they can, and to urge other Governments around the world&mdash;not least the Government of India, who should be playing a much more high-profile role in this matter&mdash;to put pressure on the Government of Sri Lanka.</p>
	<p pid="a.33.0/6">Undoubtedly, if the evidence could be collected, we would see that war crimes are being committed. The Government of Sri Lanka have unambiguously and wilfully failed to meet their obligations. The Geneva convention states:</p>
	<p pid="a.33.0/7" class="indent">&quot;In order to ensure respect for and protection of the civilian population and civilian objects, the Parties to the conflict shall at all times distinguish between the civilian population and combatants and between civilian objects and military objectives and accordingly shall direct their operations only against military objectives.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.33.0/8">On any reading of the situation, we could not say that the Government of Sri Lanka are meeting those obligations, given their indiscriminate attacks and use of cluster bombs, multi-barrel rocket launchers and white phosphorous. Indeed, the Sri Lankan Government have publicly abrogated their duty to protect civilians. On <phrase class="date" code="2009-02-02">2 February</phrase>, the Sri Lankan Ministry of Defence, Public Security, Law and Order stated:</p>
	<p pid="a.33.0/9" class="indent">&quot;While the Security Forces accept all responsibility to ensure the safety and protection of civilians in the Safety Zones, they are unable to give such an assurance to those who remain outside these zones. Therefore, the government, with full responsibility, urges all civilians to come to the Safety Zones&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.33.0/10">Of course, we have heard time and again in recent weeks of the bombing of safety zones and hospitals. Indeed, the last hospital has now been bombed and is no longer operating. We have had reports of casualties on the beaches, and feet blown off by land mines. Those aid agencies that are there and are able to operate have to choose between the most severely injured and the badly injured, and have to leave the badly injured lying on the beach. That cannot by any stretch of the imagination be considered humane treatment.</p>
	<p pid="a.33.0/11">This is a humanitarian crisis and a violation of human rights. It is beyond our imagining, but we must try to put ourselves in that place, because no one is speaking up for those people. They have no voice, but, surely, giving them a voice is one of our first responsibilities.</p>
	<p pid="a.33.0/12">Like my hon. Friend the Member for Mitcham and Morden, I have people coming to my surgeries about this issue. I do not have a large Tamil population, but those families who do come to my surgery are absolutely frantic. They do not know whether their family and friends are displaced, injured or, worse, dead. They have no contact whatsoever, but they know what we know and what the world chooses to ignore about severely injured people lying on beaches.</p>
	<p pid="a.33.0/13">Sometimes when we explain such things or speak about genocide, people say that we are using purple prose, or embellishing in some way. They say that we should not use the word &quot;genocide&quot; because it is a serious charge. Yes, it is the most serious of charges, but I believe that, unfortunately, we can use such terms in this situation. Our description of the horror, fear, injuries and deaths of innocent Tamil people and what they are suffering is not purple prose. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1662" name="Edward Davey">The hon. Member for Kingston and Surbiton (Mr. Davey)</phrase> outlined the horror and fear of people who have to survive day to day&mdash;if they manage to survive. That is a reality. We stand here in comfort and warmth and discuss the situation, but we do not see any action. We need action.</p>
	<p pid="a.33.0/14">I understand the argument that is being made in the Chamber&mdash;that it would be worse if we did not get a UN Security Council resolution than if we did. I believe that it was the Chairman of the Foreign Affairs Committee, my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1652" name="Mike Gapes">the Member for Ilford, South (Mike Gapes)</phrase>, who said at the last Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs questions that Russia would veto such a resolution, or was making it clear behind the scenes that it would do so. There is a discussion to be had as to whether we should be opening this up. We should be speaking to Russia through diplomatic channels. Perhaps my hon. Friend the Minister cannot comment on that&mdash;perhaps it is happening and he is not able to go into much detail. However, I want to put it on the record that many Members of Parliament and others&mdash;Professor Boyle, for instance, who recently circulated a paper&mdash;feel that it might be about time to put the matter on the agenda or at least to have a discussion about it, instead of allowing Russia, if Russia is the problem, to hide behind the fact that it is not on the agenda. I sincerely hope that my hon. Friend and his colleagues are having such discussions.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.35.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.35.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.35.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.35.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.36.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.36.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.36.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.36.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.36.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.36.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.36.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1831" speakername="Simon Hughes" colnum="36"  time="011:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0006.htm#09032425000580">
	<p pid="a.36.2/1">I shall keep to that, Mr. Atkinson, and I am very grateful to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1717" name="Siobhain McDonagh">the hon. Member for Mitcham and Morden (Siobhain McDonagh)</phrase> for initiating the debate.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/2">On <phrase class="date" code="2009-02-26">26 February</phrase>, I received, as others may have, a message from the Bishop of Mannar, passing on a message from a parish priest in northern Sri Lanka, who said that the bishop</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/3" class="indent">&quot;requested me to communicate this message to you all.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/4" class="indent">Sri Lanka's army is massacring Tamils. About 300 Tamils were mutilated and those people were thrown into camps. Heavy shelling takes place on the innocent civilians.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/5" class="indent">From Mullaithevu two elderly priests were allowed to come out on mercy grounds. These aged catholic priests witness the gruesome suffering of civilians.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/6" class="indent">These priests say that the army is pouring bombs on safer zones.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/7" class="indent">Kindly insist that International monitoring committee monitor the so called safer zones.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/8" class="indent">Both Sri Lanka and LTTE are recruiting small boys and girls. Parents are crying</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/9" class="indent">If the Indian government wishes it can stop the war. Kindly put more demands on the Indian government not to support the Sri Lankan Army.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/10" class="indent">Due to lack of medical personnel and medicine most of the innocent civilians are dying. If the war is continued the Tamil race will be destroyed completely&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/11">The message goes on in that vein.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/12">Just the other day, on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-13">13 March</phrase>, I had an update, as colleagues will have done, from the hugely respected United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees and its representatives. I shall be selective in quoting from its long and full report, but it says that</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/13" class="indent">&quot;some agencies are yet to be given access to the sites&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/14">the holding sites for people&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/15" class="indent">&quot;limiting the level of assistance that can be provided...tens of thousands remain trapped inside a 45 square kilometre area.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/16">The report says that the people leaving the area</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/17" class="indent">&quot;have described the dire conditions there, caused by severe overcrowding, serious food shortages, poor sanitation and no medical facilities.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/18">And the UNHCR says that the LTTE has prevented many people from leaving.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/19">We are all trying to confront a situation in which the Government of Sri Lanka appear to be absolutely impervious to the criticisms of their own people and of others. The Government look as if they are beyond rational response. When the Defence Secretary, who is the brother of the President, said, as he did on <phrase class="date" code="2009-02-02">2 February</phrase>, that all criticism of the Government was treason; when the army commander insisted, at the same time, that Sri Lanka is a Sinhalese Buddhist country, not a multi-ethnic, multi-religious nation; but when many people of many races and faiths have been there for centuries, no wonder the international community is having difficulty winning the argument with the Government. Our plea, from all parts of the House, to the British Government is that they seek to do more, without discrediting what they have done so far. The UK must continue bilateral representations with the Sri Lankan Government.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/20">I should like the Minister to tell us what has happened since the European Union Council of Ministers came to a view in February and came up with a unanimous recommendation. I should also like to know whether it is now time to follow the suggestion of <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1572" name="Joan Ryan">the right hon. Member for Enfield, North (Joan Ryan)</phrase>, which others support, including my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1662" name="Edward Davey">the Member for Kingston and Surbiton (Mr. Davey)</phrase>, that we put the issue on the agenda at the United Nations.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/21">As this is a debate about the Commonwealth, I should like to ask three simple questions about whether we cannot get the organisation to be much more proactive. Historically, it has been willing to take action against a member Government when they have broken the Commonwealth's principles, which are that member Governments allow democracy and human rights across their territories. First, why at the Commonwealth meeting on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-04">4 March</phrase> did the Minister present&mdash;I think&mdash;represent the UK, rather than the Secretary of State or a Minister of State? There was considerable criticism that we were not represented at a higher level during the meeting of the Heads of Government and Government representatives at Marlborough house.</p>
	<p pid="a.36.2/22">Secondly, what specific initiatives have the British Government taken to seek to get the Commonwealth to be much more proactive&mdash;to achieve the ceasefire, the access to humanitarian aid, free journalism and, because there has been an invitation, the assurance that any British or other Commonwealth MP who goes to Sri Lanka can go wherever they feel they need to go? Finally, is the Minister sympathetic to the view that I believe my hon. Friend the Member for Kingston and Surbiton will express, similar to those from all parts of the House, that there must be a specific initiative by the Commonwealth, showing that it is a serious organisation that takes membership seriously? It is not an organisation without principles or rules, and those of us who are keen supporters of it believe that it must show its colours and its principles. If it does not do so now, for the people of Sri Lanka, it will not be an organisation worth belonging to. They must be shown that the relationship between Sri Lanka and the Commonwealth means something, and the Commonwealth must stand up and take international responsibility.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.38.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.38.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.39.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.39.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.39.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.39.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.40.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.40.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.40.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1927" speakername="Stephen Hammond" colnum="40"  time="011:53:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0007.htm#09032425000584">
	<p pid="a.40.0/1">I am grateful for the opportunity to comment in this important debate. The message that will have gone out clearly from this debate is that no hon. Member in this Chamber supports the violence. There have been condemnations of the LTTE as well. However, the most important thing, as <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1717" name="Siobhain McDonagh">the hon. Member for Mitcham and Morden (Siobhain McDonagh)</phrase> said, is that we Members of Parliament must bear witness to oppressed minorities wherever they exist in the world. It is important to recognise that the Tamil minority in Sri Lanka is being oppressed by its Government.</p>
	<p pid="a.40.0/2">First, I want to press the Minister and ask about what action the Government are taking to impress on the Sri Lankan Government the need for capacity for evacuation for innocent women, children and men. He cannot have been deaf to the comment made by the representative of the International Committee of the Red Cross only last weekend:</p>
	<p pid="a.40.0/3" class="indent">&quot;The capacity for evacuation is far below the need...We have to decide to take the casualties who are more badlv injured and leave behind the ones who are less badly injured&quot;,</p>
	<p pid="a.40.0/4">or leave behind people who are not injured at all who are then unwittingly used as human shields. The Tamil community is being abused in that way. The Government need to take direct action in respect of the Sri Lankan high commission in London to impress on it the need to allow the evacuation of innocent Tamil citizens.</p>
	<p pid="a.40.0/5">Secondly&mdash;the Sri Lankan Government should hear this&mdash;mercy missions are on their way from the community and from international organisations. I cite the mercy mission ship that could land in Vanni if the Sri Lankan Government allowed it to do so. Surely, if that Government had any humanity towards their citizens they would allow that ship to dock, for it has on it representations from the international community. This is not a ship that could in any way be called a front for terrorism; it would deliver much-needed food and medical aid to that area. The UK Government must stand up and make a representation to the Sri Lankan high commission on that point, as so many hon. Members who have contributed to this debate have done today.</p>
	<p pid="a.40.0/6">Thirdly, the Sri Lankan Government may be cautious about what Balasingham Nadesan said at the weekend, but unless they take the brave step towards a ceasefire, accept that the offer might be genuine and does not contain preconditions, and come to the table, there will be no political solution. The political solution is the only way forward, because a military solution cannot ever win. Equally, with a ceasefire, it should be incumbent on the Sri Lankan Government to accept international validation on certain points.</p>
	<p pid="a.40.0/7"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1831" name="Simon Hughes">The hon. Member for North Southwark and Bermondsey (Simon Hughes)</phrase> made some telling remarks about the role of the Commonwealth, and all hon. Members in the Chamber will be listening to what happens.</p>
	<p pid="a.40.0/8">Fourthly, post-action and post-ceasefire, the UK Government must impress on the Sri Lankan Government that the ceasefire must include not only the LTTE, but all sections of the Tamil community. There is a role for the Tamil National Alliance, and other democratic people, in that process. Equally, the UK Government could suggest to the Government of Sri Lanka&mdash;tied in with their request for a ceasefire and the threat of suspension from the Commonwealth&mdash;that there could be a genuine international reconstruction fund. For if the Tamils are to be able to play a full part in the life of Sri Lanka, they will need not only the political solution but the economic solution. An international reconstruction fund would be a part of that process and the Commonwealth could lead it. If not, our Government should lead the process of putting that fund in place.</p>
	<p pid="a.40.0/9">I am aware of your strictures, Mr. Atkinson. Like so many other hon. Members I could speak for rather longer. I hope that the Minister will respond to those four points.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.41.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.41.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.41.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1662" speakername="Edward Davey" colnum="41"  time="011:57:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0007.htm#09032425000585">
	<p pid="a.41.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1717" name="Siobhain McDonagh">the hon. Member for Mitcham and Morden (Siobhain McDonagh)</phrase> on securing the debate and on her remarks. Both she and <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1572" name="Joan Ryan">the right hon. Member for Enfield, North (Joan Ryan)</phrase> have been tireless in their campaigning in recent weeks and months and it has been a pleasure to work with them to put forward the Tamil case, and the case for human rights and a ceasefire.</p>
	<p pid="a.41.0/2">The hon. Member for Mitcham and Morden shares my anger and the anger of my Tamil constituents and the whole Tamil diaspora, and she is frustrated that nothing seems to be happening. The killing seems to be going on and the humanitarian catastrophe seems to be getting worse, even in the safe areas, as she so graphically described. We have these debates and we ask questions, but I say to the Minister that the frustration is getting deeper every day. People keep hearing about the communities with which they have connections back through the generations being devastated and about family members disappearing and being killed. We have to speak out, and the Government have to speak out far more than they have done to date.</p>
	<p pid="a.41.0/3">I commend the Prime Minister and the Foreign Secretary on the comments that they made a few weeks ago and for calling for a ceasefire. However, that call has fallen on deaf ears, so we urgently need to take more action.</p>
	<p pid="a.41.0/4">No doubt colleagues have received many reports&mdash;not just PR from the Sri Lankan high commission&mdash;from Tamil constituents and campaign bodies, and from people who are in the Vanni. One of the most graphic reports that I have received is entitled &quot;Voice of the Voiceless and Helpless People of the Vanni&quot;. It talks about the horrific conditions in the so-called safe area. It seems that the Sri Lankan Government have set up not a safe area, but a concentration camp, which it is even prepared to shell. That cannot go without huge criticism from the British Government and the international community. It is a crime, and we must speak out loudly against it.</p>
	<p pid="a.41.0/5">I hope that the Government will take three concrete actions. First, they have not exerted enough pressure through the Commonwealth, which can often act behind the scenes and put moral pressure on Ministers of other Governments. My hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1831" name="Simon Hughes">the Member for North Southwark and Bermondsey (Simon Hughes)</phrase> said that at the recent meeting in London, the British Government were represented by only a Parliamentary Under-Secretary. The Government could have done more, given that Sri Lankan Government representatives were here in London.</p>
	<p pid="a.41.0/6">[Hywel Williams <i>in the Chair</i>]</p>
	<p pid="a.41.0/7">My hon. Friend and I have discussed whether we should join the calls for Sri Lanka's suspension from the Commonwealth, because that would be a major move and the Commonwealth traditionally uses behind-the-scenes moral pressure. We have come round to the point of view of the hon. Member for Mitcham and Morden. We must begin that process, and the leader of my party, my right hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1812" name="Nicholas Clegg">the Member for Sheffield, Hallam (Mr. Clegg)</phrase>, has agreed to write to the Secretary-General of the Commonwealth today asking for an immediate inquiry into the action of the Sri Lankan Government and whether it is compatible with Commonwealth membership, the Harare principles and so on. That inquiry needs to be set up as the start of the process for Sri Lanka's suspension, and I hope that the Minister will join my right hon. Friend in that call to Commonwealth leaders. There should be an investigation, and it should happen now.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.42.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.42.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.42.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.42.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.42.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.42.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.43.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.43.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.43.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.43.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.43.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.43.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.43.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.43.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.43.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.43.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.43.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1662" speakername="Edward Davey" colnum="43"  time="011:57:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0007.htm#09032425000593">
	<p pid="a.43.4/1">Not only do I pay tribute to the hon. Lady, I have paid tribute to the Prime Minister and the Foreign Secretary. However, it is no good them calling for a ceasefire, as they did a few weeks ago, with no action. We need action now, and I do not regret anything that I have said today.</p>
	<p pid="a.43.4/2">This matter should be one of the top foreign policy issues facing the Government, and it should involve the efforts of not just the Minister, but the Foreign Secretary and the Prime Minister. They should provide leadership in the Commonwealth, the United Nations and the European Union to put pressure on the Government in Colombo. I hope that the Minister will assure us that that has been happening without us being aware of it, or that it is about to happen.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.44.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.44.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.44.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1735" speakername="Keith Simpson" colnum="44"  time="012:09:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0008.htm#09032425000594">
	<p pid="a.44.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1717" name="Siobhain McDonagh">the hon. Member for Mitcham and Morden (Siobhain McDonagh)</phrase> on raising this debate, and on how she put forward her views. Only a few weeks ago, on <phrase class="date" code="2009-02-05">5 February</phrase>, we debated Sri Lanka in one of the aptly named topical debates.</p>
	<p pid="a.44.0/2">The immediate issue that has been brought forward by all hon. Members is how to ensure the safety of the tens of thousands of people caught up in what is effectively a fighting zone&mdash;the so-called no-fire zone/safe zone. Both sides have been guilty of the indiscriminate and discriminate use of violence. I say &quot;indiscriminate&quot; because if the Sri Lankan army is using area weapons such as assault from the air and artillery fire, it will kill large numbers of people in a very densely populated zone. I mean discriminate violence in the sense that so-called prisoners are shot by the Sri Lankan armed forces and, equally, the LTTE has ended up shooting people that it has tried to force into fighting units. This is a human tragedy on a vast scale and our immediate problem is how to bring pressure to bear not just on the Sri Lankan Government but on the LTTE to make certain that the civilians are evacuated and protected.</p>
	<p pid="a.44.0/3">As the hon. Member for Mitcham and Morden and <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1572" name="Joan Ryan">the right hon. Member for Enfield, North (Joan Ryan)</phrase> mentioned, the LTTE has come to the table suggesting that it wants a ceasefire, with no conditions attached to it. The sadness is that both sides have played that game over the years. Both sides have tended to propose a ceasefire when they have perhaps been at a point of weakness and want to bring the other side to the table. However, there are powerful arguments now for the Sri Lankan Government to recognise that they have the LTTE on the ropes and that, in terms of not only domestic public opinion but international public opinion, they should show a degree of magnanimity and produce a ceasefire that puts the LTTE on the back foot.</p>
	<p pid="a.44.0/4">It seems to me that, as other hon. Members said, the Sri Lankan Government are determined militarily to destroy the LTTE. There is no doubt that the reason for their refusal to allow in a UN force and most international media and for the constraints that have been placed on the non-governmental organisations is that they believe that if there is one final push, the LTTE will be militarily destroyed. However, as many hon. Members pointed out, that military victory will not produce the lasting settlement that they want. History is littered with examples of that. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1628" name="Andrew Dismore">The hon. Member for Hendon (Mr. Dismore)</phrase> pointed that out. My experience from teaching this to British armed forces over many years is that the tube of toothpaste is squeezed in a different direction. There will be a new generation of Tamil Tigers, who will end up fighting by unconventional warfare against the Sri Lankan Government and, more importantly, their people, not only in Sri Lanka but worldwide, and on a scale that we have not seen so far. They will escalate that on a scale that will be quite frightening.</p>
	<p pid="a.44.0/5">I urge the Sri Lankan Government to think very seriously about that. The irony is that in the next two or three weeks they will undoubtedly achieve that military victory, in that they will capture the final strongholds of the LTTE, but they will actually snatch defeat from the jaws of victory. We should be thinking of how we persuade the Sri Lankan Government that they are about to achieve a tactical victory that is in fact a strategic defeat.</p>
	<p pid="a.44.0/6">Let me explain where I disagree with hon. Members. At one level, I am impressed by the fact that the Sri Lankan Government have put out vast amounts of PR and publicity, just as the Tamil Tigers have, but I have not found it very sophisticated. If I were advising the Sri Lankan high commissioner, I would say, &quot;The one way you do not go about influencing the debate in the House of Commons is by defaming hon. Members. You try to produce arguments that will convince them that at the very least you have some arguments on your side.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.44.0/7">The Sri Lankan Government have damaged their case by refusing entry to the area of combat for journalists and they have an ambivalent attitude towards aid workers. At least the British can speak from experience on this matter. I suspect that if we had decided in the long conflict in Northern Ireland to do just that, we would have lost what in effect was a conflict 20 or 30 years' ago. We would have certainly lost any form of support from within Ireland, southern Ireland, or indeed in the United States of America. In their own interests, I urge the Sri Lankan Government to reconsider. However, we should bear it in mind that it is not exactly easy for a journalist or an aid worker to have operated in the zones controlled by the LTTE, either. Putting aside those moral issues, I have sympathy for any Government who are fighting unconventional warfare when they have to reach a moral bar that is often far higher than that of the unconventional side.</p>
	<p pid="a.44.0/8">I want to give the Minister as much time as possible to respond to the debate, so I shall briefly pull some thoughts together about what is to be done.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.45.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.45.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.45.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.45.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.46.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.46.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.46.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.46.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.46.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.46.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.46.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1616" speakername="Bill Rammell" speakeroffice="The Minister of State, Foreign and Commonwealth Office"  colnum="46"  time="012:18:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0008.htm#09032425000599">
	<p pid="a.46.2/1">May I start by genuinely congratulating my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1717" name="Siobhain McDonagh">the Member for Mitcham and Morden (Siobhain McDonagh)</phrase> on securing and leading the debate? She has been consistent in her advocacy on behalf of her Tamil constituents. I saw that at first hand when I addressed a meeting of a group of her constituents whom she brought to Westminster. I know that she will continue to make that case.</p>
	<p pid="a.46.2/2">I also congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1735" name="Keith Simpson">the hon. Member for Mid-Norfolk (Mr. Simpson)</phrase>, who leads for the Opposition, on striking absolutely the right tone in a constructive and thoughtful contribution, probing the Government in a difficult set of circumstances. One of the blunt realities is that we cannot just mandate actions on behalf of a Government in a different country.</p>
	<p pid="a.46.2/3">Let me place emphatically on the record the Government's clear view that Members of this House have an absolute, unequivocal right to speak up on behalf of their constituents. Spurious personal attacks on the character of individual Members by any high commission or embassy in this country are not only wrong and unacceptable, but completely counter-productive in advancing the cause of those involved, and I can assure hon. Members that we will send that message loudly and clearly to the Sri Lankan high commission.</p>
	<p pid="a.46.2/4">The ethnic conflict between the Government of Sri Lanka and the LTTE has reached a critical phase, and the UK Government are extraordinarily concerned about the grave humanitarian situation and particularly about the fate of the large numbers of civilians caught up in the fighting.</p>
	<p pid="a.46.2/5">As many hon. Members in the Chamber who are extremely knowledgeable about the situation know, the conflict in Sri Lanka has been raging for more than 25 years and has claimed the lives of more than 70,000 Sri Lankans. The dramatic advances by the Government forces since January have claimed the lives not only of Sri Lankan soldiers and LTTE cadres, but, most shockingly, of innocent civilians, including women and children.</p>
	<p pid="a.46.2/6">The lack of independent reporting from the conflict area makes it impossible to obtain definitive figures. However, the UN estimates that more than 2,600 civilians have been killed and more than 7,200 have been injured since <phrase class="date" code="2009-01-20">20 January</phrase> alone. Those figures are truly appalling. I very much agree with my hon. Friend the Member for Mitcham and Morden that nothing justifies what happened in Gaza, but the figures in this case are more significant. Given the conflict that is taking place, there has not been enough attention in the international media.</p>
	<p pid="a.46.2/7">The UN High Commissioner for Human Rights, Navi Pillay, recently said that</p>
	<p pid="a.46.2/8" class="indent">&quot;certain actions being undertaken by the Sri Lankan military and by the LTTE may constitute violations of international human rights and humanitarian law.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.46.2/9">There are more civilian casualties every day, including those who were killed or wounded when a hospital, which had been declared a no-fire zone, was repeatedly hit by shells over a number of days in February. As I made clear in the House when Sri Lanka was last debated on <phrase class="date" code="2009-02-05">5 February</phrase>, we expect and urge the Government of Sri Lanka fully to investigate any allegations of abuses by their forces. We would support a full and independent investigation into all concerns about war crimes, including the shelling of the hospital and other civilian deaths.</p>
	<p pid="a.46.2/10">Hon. Members have understandably voiced concerns about accusations that Government forces have used cluster bombs and resorted to indiscriminate bombing, and we have raised those allegations with the Sri Lankan Government. Although they have stated that they do not use cluster munitions, we have made very clear to them our strong opposition to the use of such munitions and to indiscriminate bombings. We condemn the killings of civilians unequivocally and in the strongest possible terms, however they happen, and we have urged all parties to the conflict to avoid action against civilians.</p>
	<p pid="a.46.2/11">We are now at a critical phase. The last remaining territory held by the LTTE measures less than 30 sq km, and large numbers of civilians&mdash;internally displaced persons&mdash;are trapped in that area. Since January, more than 40,000 IDPs have left the conflict area and moved into Government-controlled territory. Estimates of the numbers who remain vary from 70,000 according to the Sri Lankan Government to 200,000 according to the UN. These people have been repeatedly displaced over the past 18 months each time the front line has moved.</p>
	<p pid="a.46.2/12">We have rightly been critical of the actions of the Sri Lankan Government, and I have just made that clear again. However, it has become increasingly clear that the principal reason why more IDPs have not left the conflict area is that the LTTE is forcibly preventing them from doing so. A number of NGOs working in northern Sri Lanka have publicly stated that that is happening. The UN has also condemned the LTTE for forcibly recruiting civilians, including women and children. We must attack that on all fronts and we must express our concerns to the Sri Lankan Government. I urge anyone with influence and with access to the LTTE to put those concerns forward.</p>
	<p pid="a.46.2/13">Civilians have been under direct threat not only from the fighting, and there is enormous concern about the ability to get aid into the area. Much more needs to be done about that. It was because of our concerns about the humanitarian situation in the conflict area that the Prime Minister first called for a ceasefire on <phrase class="date" code="2009-01-14">14 January</phrase> and wrote to President Rajapakse. My right hon. Friend the Foreign Secretary followed that up by telephoning the President and urging him to declare a humanitarian ceasefire. We have been consistent in advancing that cause in all forums.</p>
	<p pid="a.46.2/14">We have also rightly been releasing resources. Given the urgency of the situation, we have allocated a further &pound;2.5 million&mdash;on top of the &pound;2.5 million that we committed in October 2008&mdash;to support the efforts of humanitarian agencies in Sri Lanka. We have also sent a Department for International Development humanitarian expert to bolster the capacity of our high commission in Colombo to deal with the unfolding humanitarian situation. The hon. Member for Wimbledon asked about the post-conflict situation. The international community will inevitably need to assist with reconstruction efforts in communities affected by the conflict, and we will certainly play our part in such efforts.</p>
	<p pid="a.46.2/15">We have not been working on this issue alone. One very helpful development in recent weeks was the joint statement by the Foreign Secretary and the Secretary of State in the United States Government, which called for a &quot;temporary no-fire period&quot;. The co-chairs group&mdash;the US, the EU, Japan and Norway&mdash;has also called for the delivery of humanitarian aid and for the LTTE to discuss ways of ending the current hostilities.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.48.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.48.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.48.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.48.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.50.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.50.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.50.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.50.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.50.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.50.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.50.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.50.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.50.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.50.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.50.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.50.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.51.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.51.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.51.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.51.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.52.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.52.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.52.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.52.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.54.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.54.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.56.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.56.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.56.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.56.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.58.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.58.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.58.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.58.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.59.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.59.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.59.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.59.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.59.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.59.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.59.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.59.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.59.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1452" speakername="Ian Cawsey" colnum="59"  time="013:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0010.htm#09032425000618">
	<p pid="a.59.3/1">I praise all the work that my hon. Friend has done on the steel industry since he has been in the House. He is part of the all-party steel group and, along with myself, a member of the Community group of Members of Parliament. I will refer to what is happening in Wales a little later in my speech. At this stage, I will say that I entirely endorse my hon. Friend's comments, and that such initiatives are something that we need to consider.</p>
	<p pid="a.59.3/2">I am indebted to the Community union, which has met with MPs and peers with an interest in the steel industry and has put a lot of time and effort into considering how such a support package should be constructed. I am also grateful to the management of Corus. On behalf of all of us who have steel plants in our constituencies, I should like to say that both locally, through the local management, and nationally, through the briefings that we have received, we have had excellent support from Corus, which has been very candid and frank with us. As Members of Parliament who represent steel interests, we are all extremely pleased with the way in which it has kept us in the loop.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.59.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.59.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.59.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.59.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.60.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.60.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.60.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.60.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.60.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.60.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.60.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.60.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.62.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.62.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.64.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.64.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.64.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1452" speakername="Ian Cawsey" colnum="64"  time="013:16:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0011.htm#09032425000626">
	<p pid="a.64.0/1">As I mentioned, during Prime Minister's Question Time, the Prime Minister has indicated that he was looking for ways to push a scheme such as ProAct out across the country. I accept that the Minister might not be in a position to answer that point today, but perhaps he could write to hon. Members to let us know what progress is being made.</p>
	<p pid="a.64.0/2">Although I agree with the general point about subsidy and the dangers of dead-weight, does the Minister not accept that in the TUC and Federation of Small Businesses proposal, dead-weight is specifically addressed? That can be avoided through careful control, as my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1814" name="Angela Smith">the Member for Sheffield, Hillsborough (Ms Smith)</phrase> alluded to. We can get the benefits without the disadvantages. It is about subsidy and links to training, which we need while people are in work rather than on jobseeker's allowance.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.64.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.64.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.65.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.65.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.65.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.65.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.65.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.65.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.65.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.65.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.66.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.66.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.66.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.66.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.66.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1661" speakername="Philip Hollobone" colnum="66"  time="013:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0011.htm#09032425000632">
	<p pid="a.66.1/1">It is a pleasure to serve under your chairmanship, Mr. Williams, and I thank Mr. Speaker for granting me this important debate. The issue is extremely important to my constituents in Kettering, as well as to those of my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1915" name="Peter Bone">the Member for Wellingborough (Mr. Bone)</phrase>, who is in the Chamber, and of the Minister of State, Department of Health, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1512" name="Phil Hope">the hon. Member for Corby (Phil Hope)</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/2">The Government launched their university challenge in March 2008. In response, a local partnership was formed in north Northamptonshire comprising all four borough and district councils, the county council, Tresham institute of further and higher education, the university of Northampton, Northamptonshire Enterprise Ltd, North Northants Development Corporation and the Learning and Skills Council. That partnership has pledged its commitment to preparing a business case for the university challenge proposals for a multi-site, dispersed higher education centre that will provide a full offer of higher education in response to student demand.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/3">Tresham institute currently offers a small number of higher education programmes in Kettering, Wellingborough, Corby and east Northants, but it would be able to deliver a wider range through its three existing campuses in Kettering, Corby and Wellingborough if the university challenge application were successful. A large local petition is supported by the local<i> Evening Telegraph</i> and has attracted thousands of signatures. The partnership submitted an expression of interest to the Higher Education Funding Council for England in October 2008, and I am delighted that the scheme has been shortlisted as one of the 27 that are being put forward for the 20 available places. Consultants acting for the partnership are preparing our business case, which the partnership intends to submit to HEFCE by June 2009.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/4">The university challenge project is one of the Government's better ideas. When it was announced, Ministers said that they believed that</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/5" class="indent">&quot;a local high quality higher education centre can open up the chance of higher education to more young people and adults who previously may never have thought about a degree while helping drive local economic and social regeneration. Economists estimate that every extra job a university creates is matched by another elsewhere in the economy.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/6">When launching university challenge, the Secretary of State for Innovation, Universities and Skills said:</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/7" class="indent">&quot;In these challenging economic times never have universities and colleges been more important to education, economic development, regeneration and the cultural life of our rural areas, towns and cities.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/8">I could not agree more. Indeed, a delegation from Kettering, Corby and the rest of north Northants went to see the Secretary of State in his office in June 2008. After that meeting, he said:</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/9" class="indent">&quot;I thought it was an impressive presentation. The team that came to see me have really understood the main points of the university challenge and how they can bring economic development to&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/10">their local areas.</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/11">Under the rules of the university challenge project, an expression of interest has to be made by a sponsoring university. The university of Northampton is heading the bid to HEFCE for a university in north Northamptonshire and it is strongly supported by the second sponsor, the university of Bedfordshire. The expression of interest, which was submitted in 2008, said:</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/12" class="indent">&quot;The Secretary of State's...&quot;New University Challenge&quot; was warmly welcomed by local authorities in the north Northamptonshire area, by Tresham Institute of Further and Higher Education (TI) and by The University of Northampton (UN)&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/13">and others, because it provides</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/14" class="indent">&quot;both a stimulus and an opportunity significantly to enhance, extend and deepen access and wider participation to higher education in the north of the county.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/15">It continued to say:</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/16" class="indent">&quot;UN has been developing its relationship with TI to this end, but the Secretary of State's paper has generated a multi agency commitment to and support for the establishment of (a) formally recognised Higher Education Centre(s) to serve the needs of both young and mature HE learners in the Corby, Kettering, Wellingborough and East Northamptonshire Boroughs&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/17">and districts. It went on to say:</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/18" class="indent">&quot;The initiative also has the full support of Northamptonshire County Council (NCC), the Northamptonshire Enterprise Limited (NEL), the Learning and Skills Council (LSC) and the North Northamptonshire Development Company (NNDC). NNDC has agreed to provide overall leadership and co-ordination of the preparation of a bid, via The University of Northampton, and the University of Bedfordshire has expressed its willingness to join the partnership.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.66.1/19">I want to point out early on that the bid is a unified and united one. Whatever the political differences between elected representatives in north Northamptonshire from time to time, they have all signed up to the bid. Everyone has put their signature on the same bit of paper, and there is no difference between any of us, because this issue is so important to the future of our local area, particularly for economic growth.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.67.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.67.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.67.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.67.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.69.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.69.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.69.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.69.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.69.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1661" speakername="Philip Hollobone" colnum="69"  time="013:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090324/halltext/90324h0011.htm#09032425000636">
	<p pid="a.69.1/1">My hon. Friend is right. One of the important things about the university challenge bid is that the locations for a further education offer are already in place in Corby, Kettering and Wellingborough. A university could be bolted on to such locations. The template exists locally in the three major towns in north Northamptonshire to provide doorstep access to higher education for many local people who currently do not aspire to it. If people do aspire to higher education, they currently have to go further afield to access the higher education that they seek.</p>
	<p pid="a.69.1/2">Tresham institute is already developing its higher education offer. However, if the university challenge bid was successful, it would provide some rocket fuel to those ambitions. Tresham institute's concept and approach to higher education in north Northamptonshire includes:</p>
	<p pid="a.69.1/3" class="indent">&quot;The validation of Higher Education and Higher Level Skills that relate to the economic and skill needs of the community of North Northamptonshire.</p>
	<p pid="a.69.1/4" class="indent">Significant opportunities to attract 'new learners' who might not have previously considered Higher Education and Higher Education Progression.</p>
	<p pid="a.69.1/5" class="indent">Diploma line developments and a linked line to Higher Education and Higher Education Progression Opportunities from the schools sector&quot;,</p>
	<p pid="a.69.1/6">and supporting</p>
	<p pid="a.69.1/7" class="indent">&quot;employer engagement and enabling part-time flexible upskilling.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.69.1/8">This year, Tresham is establishing higher education programmes in business and fine art, and level 5 in accounts. Next year and in 2011, there will be further higher education programmes in health and care, sport, public services and additional education programmes. A further seven higher education programmes are planned for 2011 to 2013.</p>
	<p pid="a.69.1/9">In the guidance that HEFCE has issued on what will make a successful bid, it lists among the criteria some of the following, all of which are met by the bid from the north Northamptonshire education partnership: increasing higher-level skills, particularly for those with no previous experience of HE; the creation of a highly skilled work force, with relevant skills for the local business community; supporting appropriate progression arrangements; supporting a sustainable demand for studying; stimulating a sustainable demand for studying; collaboration between higher education institutes, and between HEIs and further education colleges; strong, coherent support for local partners. In addition, it also states that a new higher education centre would contribute to meeting the needs of local, regional and national employers.</p>
	<p pid="a.69.1/10">The bid from north Northamptonshire is strong and has already impressed the Secretary of State for Innovation, Universities and Skills. Everyone in the local area is signed up to it, and considering all the house building that is expected to take place, it could make a real difference to the future of north Northamptonshire. We could even go as far as saying that if north Northamptonshire does not get a university and approval for its university challenge bid&mdash;I believe that it is the only one in the east midlands region out of the 27 successful bids so far&mdash;it is not clear to those involved in the process of regeneration and housing growth in the local area that the employment targets for the local area will be met.</p>
	<p pid="a.69.1/11">Of the 47,400 jobs that the Government plan to create by 2021, there is a shortfall of at least 19,000. Those jobs could be provided by the economic stimulus that a new university in north Northamptonshire would provide. If the university challenge scheme is unsuccessful, there will be a big black hole in the employment prospects for north Northamptonshire. We will not have a sustainable community, as the Government intend. Instead, we will have lots of houses, not enough jobs and insufficient infrastructure.</p>
	<p pid="a.69.1/12">My task is to impress on the Minister the importance of this bid&mdash;not just for local education opportunities, but as part of the Government's whole approach to getting some growth into the north of the county. I hope that when decision time comes on the issue, the Minister and HEFCE will look favourably at the proposals for a university in the north of Northamptonshire.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24a.70.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-03-24b.70.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

