<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.147.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.147.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.147.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.147.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.147.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.147.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.148.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.148.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.148.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.148.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.148.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.148.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.149.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.149.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.149.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.149.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.150.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.150.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.150.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1940" speakername="Peter Luff" colnum="150"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0001.htm#07041994000348">
	<p pid="a.150.0/1">I am most grateful to my hon. Friend for his intervention. Although not the subject of the debate, a different report on the work of the Nuclear Decommissioning Authority and the United Kingdom Atomic Energy Authority deals with nuclear fusion. The Committee is enthusiastic about the prospects for nuclear fusion, but like so many things, it remains about 15 years away. The evidence is that we are getting closer to plausible, commercially realisable nuclear fusion, and we are encouraging the Government to continue to support our international efforts, which are moving from Culham to the ITER&mdash;&mdash;international thermonuclear experimental reactor&mdash;&mdash;facility in the South of France.</p>
	<p pid="a.150.0/2">I agree with my hon. Friend that there are other technologies, such as locally distributed energy generation, which may in 30 or 40 years' time produce alternative sources of power. As new technologies come along, we may find that this is the last time that we need to renew the old fashioned large-scale power plants. I entirely agree with what he said.</p>
	<p pid="a.150.0/3">On security, the Office for Civil Nuclear Security expressed some concern about its ability to provide clearances for the likely influx of workers from other jurisdictions arising from a new build programme. We also heard about the traditional concerns&mdash;the transport by train of nuclear fuels and waste around the country. However, we were reassured on those points. Overall, the Committee felt that the security issue came down to the extent to which future nuclear power stations presented an additional risk over and above that which already exists in current nuclear installations. We did not believe that the risk would be significant.</p>
	<p pid="a.150.0/4">Turning to the positive things, there are four key principles for nuclear policy. In our inquiry, we received evidence from many different groups. Four issues above all stood out. There was consensus on the primacy of those issues across the waterfront, from electricity generators, regulators, academics and non-governmental organisations. I will go through them one by one.</p>
	<p pid="a.150.0/5">The first, if we are to renew the nuclear power stations, is the need for a broad national consensus on the role of nuclear power that has both cross-party political support and wider public backing. The energy review's conclusion in favour of nuclear power was widely foreseen following the Prime Minister's speech to the CBI in May 2006 in which he said that increasing dependence on gas imports</p>
	<p pid="a.150.0/6" class="indent">&quot;put the replacement of nuclear power stations, a big push on renewables and a step-change on energy efficiency, engaging both business and consumers, back on the agenda with a vengeance.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.150.0/7">That helped foster a high degree of cynicism about the energy review itself. Sir Jonathon Porritt told the Committee that</p>
	<p pid="a.150.0/8" class="indent">&quot;the way in which the Government is handling the process around the Energy Review is not clever. It is allowing an awful lot of people to assume...this is, indeed, an exercise in rubber-stamping&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.150.0/9">The Committee also concluded that the decision-making process was taking place too rapidly, before adequate consideration of the available evidence. That view was upheld in court earlier this year, following a case brought by Greenpeace, in which the judge concluded that the consultation process had been &quot;misleading&quot;, &quot;seriously flawed&quot; and &quot;procedurally unfair&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.150.0/10">In response, the Prime Minister said that it would not affect the policy at all. However, the Government have rightly committed themselves to holding another consultation on nuclear energy, which has delayed the energy White Paper to May.</p>
	<p pid="a.150.0/11">Overall, evidence to date suggests that there has been little opportunity for politicians to move towards a consensus on new nuclear build. I hope that that is something that today's debate will go a little way towards rectifying. It has also undermined the Government's ability to get the public to buy in to nuclear policy. I understand that a new nuclear consultation document will be published at the same time as the energy White Paper in May, and that timing may be enforced. However, that seems strange in view of the judge's criticism. The risk is that the White Paper could be seen to be pre-empted&mdash;or not to be pre-empted&mdash;by the consultation document. If the White Paper has green edges&mdash;in the consultative rather than the environmental sense&mdash;that means that important decisions on the future of energy policy risk being further delayed. That concerns me and I think that it would concern members of the Committee.</p>
	<p pid="a.150.0/12">A carbon-pricing framework that provides long-term incentives for investment in all low-carbon technologies is very important. We took a lot of evidence on the different costs of nuclear power and how that related to other sources of electricity. We concluded that the Government should make it clear that all the costs of building, operating and decommissioning new nuclear power stations should fall to the private sector investors who build those stations. In other words, the costs are a concern for investors, not the Government or the taxpayer.</p>
	<p pid="a.150.0/13">A policy framework that provided a level playing field, rewarding all low-carbon technologies, was seen as the only way in which the Government could cost-effectively tackle carbon emissions from the electricity sector. However, because of the long lead times for nuclear, and the period over which investors would seek returns, that framework would need to provide 15 to 20 years of certainty over a reasonably stable and foreseeable price for carbon if the private sector were to invest. Current carbon pricing arrangements such as the climate change levy and particularly the EU emissions trading scheme do not provide a sufficiently long-term stable carbon price.</p>
	<p pid="a.150.0/14">The energy review rightly commits the Government to continuing with the EU ETS as the main means of pricing carbon, but in my view that is not an adequate approach. Phase 2 will take us to 2012 and there will be no clear progress on phase 3 of the scheme until perhaps 2010. However, significant progress must be made urgently if the Government's objective of advancing nuclear power is to be achieved and the energy gap we all fear in the next decade closed.</p>
	<p pid="a.150.0/15">When we visited the European Commission in February, we were impressed by its commitment to making the EU ETS a success, but interested to learn of the scale of opposition among many member states to the very tentative steps in phase 1. It seems that the Commission has no option but to proceed in fairly short time frames until all member states are convinced of the need for a robust and enduring emissions trading scheme. Is the Minister convinced that the Commission is being strict enough in its review of allocations? Is it generally approaching the scheme in the right way? Are the other member states willing to abide by its decisions or is there a risk that, in practice, they will try to undermine them? What does he make of potential nuclear investors' concerns that we cannot wait for a third phase of the EU scheme? Investment decisions are needed now, and that means a UK initiative now, over and above the EU ETS arrangements.</p>
	<p pid="a.150.0/16">The third point is the need for a long-term storage solution for the UK's existing radioactive waste legacy, never mind that created by a new generation of reactors. The Government rightly expect the private sector to meet the costs of decommissioning and waste management for any new build. However, nothing is yet in place to dispose of the existing nuclear waste legacy, and the record of successive Governments in that respect has been abysmal. Without a solution, or at least the prospect of one, everyone will be in a difficult position. The Government could find, if they seek to introduce new build too quickly and underestimate the cost of nuclear waste disposal, that they might have to cover some of the cost of future disposal themselves if it proves higher than the industry expects as a result of Government indications.</p>
	<p pid="a.150.0/17">That is not what the industry wants, but the lack of progress is making it all difficult. The Committee on Radioactive Waste Management, or CoRWM, concluded last year that deep geological repository was the best means of providing a long-term solution to the UK's waste legacy. That was no surprise. We all knew that that was what CoRWM was going to conclude. It is not rocket science&mdash;an appropriate phrase, as one of the options was to fire nuclear waste into space. CoRWM concluded that site selection would need to involve a high level of local engagement. Again, I think that it is right. That is the experience in Scandinavia too. Nirex's estimate is that it could cost about &pound;10 billion.</p>
	<p pid="a.150.0/18">The Government published a response to CoRWM accepting its broad thrust, but we have not heard a great deal about what has happened since then. That is worrying. The principle of local community &quot;volunteerism&quot; is likely to mean that it will take longer to arrive at specific solutions than would have been the case with simple Government direction.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.152.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.152.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.153.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.153.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.153.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1940" speakername="Peter Luff" colnum="153"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0001.htm#07041994000350">
	<p pid="a.153.0/1">I am encouraged to hear that. It is not what I was able to determine during my researches for this debate, but it is encouraging. Perhaps the Minister could say some encouraging words in his response. I am glad to hear it, because the waste in the hon. Gentleman's constituency needs to be dealt with, irrespective of any decisions on new nuclear build. I sincerely hope that his optimism is well placed.</p>
	<p pid="a.153.0/2">We need clear, transparent funding arrangements for waste disposal. For example, will the Government charge marginal or average costs to the operators of new nuclear power stations for the disposal of their waste in a facility that the Government will have to construct anyhow? There are important questions not just about the practicalities but about the funding of disposal.</p>
	<p pid="a.153.0/3">The fourth principal point is the need for a review of the planning and licensing systems to reduce the lead time for construction. Those issues are not unique to nuclear power, at least as far as planning is concerned. However, nuclear power stations require a number of specific consents and approvals, for site licences and for planning consent. Under existing regulations, an optimistic projection for the time taken to gain all the necessary consents is around five years, and potential developers believe that that is too long.</p>
	<p pid="a.153.0/4">Proposals to shorten the regulatory process focus on pre-licensing and planning. Developers want the pre-licensing of generic reactor technologies to address design and siting issues right at the start, and to reduce the time required to license subsequent reactors. On planning, the industry wants the Government to set a road map for the process, restricting the ability of public inquiries to question the original policy and requiring them instead to focus on local issues. I know that the Government are moving in that direction. On publication of the energy review, the Government will produce a response to the consultation on the kind of reforms to the planning regime proposed by the industry. I hope that that will be available in May.</p>
	<p pid="a.153.0/5">Reform in this area is essential if we are to fast-track new build, but there are risks. Pre-licensing does not guarantee a faster outcome&mdash;a form of pre-licensing was used for Sizewell B, for example. Most of the reactor technologies are untested. A process that is perceived to be cutting corners will not engender public confidence, which is crucial to new nuclear build. Curtailing the planning process would work against encouraging public buy-in to new nuclear build.</p>
	<p pid="a.153.0/6">There have been newspaper reports of some electricity generators putting pressure on the Government to start the type approval of reactors even before the White Paper is published, to save time. I wonder whether those reports are true. Has the Nuclear Installations Inspectorate started work on pre-licensing generic reactor designs? What attitude are British Energy and the Nuclear Decommissioning Authority taking to the use of the sites of their current plants for new facilities?</p>
	<p pid="a.153.0/7">I have spoken already for roughly the time that I had hoped to speak for, but I want to say a few more things, briefly. I will therefore rush through a few other issues.</p>
	<p pid="a.153.0/8">There are big issues concerning where to site nuclear power stations. Most of the existing sites&mdash;where it is assumed that new power stations will go&mdash;are coastal. Rising sea levels resulting from climate change and endomorphic tilt will make some of them unviable in the coming decades. Most of those sites are owned by British Energy and the NDA. How will other developers gain access to them? What impact will the decommissioning work on older power stations have on the availability of adjacent land for new power stations?</p>
	<p pid="a.153.0/9">On reactor technology, traditionally, we have seen two frontrunners in the UK: the Westinghouse AP1000, and Areva NP's European pressurised water reactor, which is being built in Finland and is due to open in 2009. However, that is the only example in the world of either of those technologies being put to commercial use, so any new build in the UK will be using largely untested technology. That poses risks for the pre-licensing process. However, Atomic Energy of Canada Ltd is making a strong case for its advanced CANDU reactor to be licensed for use in the UK, and its experience and track record make it a strong candidate for being added to the list.</p>
	<p pid="a.153.0/10">There are also questions about the supply chain.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.154.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.154.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.154.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.154.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.154.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.154.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.155.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.155.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.155.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.155.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.155.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.155.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.155.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1940" speakername="Peter Luff" colnum="155"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0002.htm#07041994000356">
	<p pid="a.155.2/1">I am indeed aware of that technology. Once again, sadly, to the best of my recollection, the Committee received no evidence on that. Committees are driven by the evidence that they receive rather than what they may intuitively know or think. Such reactors are attractive in many ways, because, apart from anything else, it is easy to connect smaller power stations to the grid than the bigger stations with higher outputs that we are talking about in relation to these other technologies. Such reactors have considerable advantages and I would like to know more about that technology.</p>
	<p pid="a.155.2/2">On skills, the nuclear work force are ageing and many will be used to cope with decommissioning issues. However, it seems that more graduates are being drawn to the sector, so I think that we can be more optimistic.</p>
	<p pid="a.155.2/3">I mentioned uranium supplies. We would be entirely dependent on imported uranium; we will not have any domestic sources of fuel for economic and other reasons. The Committee was optimistic that the increased market price of uranium would lead to increased exploration and an adequate supply.</p>
	<p pid="a.155.2/4">On grid capacity, the UK has a centralised grid. It is the view of the Committee that, irrespective of what new technologies fill the generating gap, we need to renew the grid. That is also subject to the planning constraints that affect nuclear build. However, grid renewal is an important issue irrespective of whether we build new nuclear power stations.</p>
	<p pid="a.155.2/5">I have spoken for longer than I intended, for which I apologise. In conclusion, there are two questions that we did not ask in this report, but on which political judgment is needed before a decision is made to proceed with any new nuclear reactors. First, do we need to replace large-scale generating capacity with other large-scale generating capacity, or can energy efficiency and local energy close the gap? Secondly, if we do need to replace the coal and nuclear power stations that will be closing in the relatively near future, do we need nuclear energy to play a part in that replacement programme?</p>
	<p pid="a.155.2/6">My personal conclusions are based squarely on my understanding of declared Government policy&mdash;which I support&mdash;that no special favours or subsidies should be given to nuclear new build; it will be left entirely to the market. I agree with that approach, as do potential declared investors in new nuclear capacity. My view is simple, and here it is based upon another unanimous Committee report into local energy. The report concluded that we need new large-scale generating capacity. Energy efficiency and local energy cannot keep the lights on.</p>
	<p pid="a.155.2/7">I believe that diversity in energy supply is good. Clean coal, gas, renewables, nuclear, local energy and, crucially, energy efficiency, all have their part to play. However&mdash;rightly&mdash;all the Government intend to do is to create the conditions to make sure that the technologies can compete fairly and then leave the market to decide&mdash;within the targets set by the European Union for renewable energy, of course.</p>
	<p pid="a.155.2/8">Happily, most of the issues that will determine the viability of new nuclear build are issues that need to be addressed anyhow, and urgently, for the wider energy sector. They range from gas storage to grid renewal and wind farm developments. Two key matters that must be resolved are the planning regime and the price of carbon. Some issues, especially waste disposal and licensing, also need urgent decisions and are specific to the nuclear industry. However, waste disposal issues must be resolved to deal with the large historic legacy of nuclear waste in the constituency of the hon. Gentleman <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1511" name="Jamie Reed">the Member for Copeland (Mr. Reed)</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.155.2/9">I have concluded that it is likely that some new nuclear capacity will be built if the Government choose the correct technology-neutral policy framework. However, there is still a big &quot;but&quot;: how much capacity will be built? The Prime Minister has hinted that he wants to replace current nuclear capacity, but his Government have no means of delivering that objective. They can only facilitate it, sit back and see what happens.</p>
	<p pid="a.155.2/10">Given the substantial fall in wholesale gas prices and the increasing interest in carbon capture and storage, is the electricity generating industry showing the same interest in new nuclear build as it did a year ago, when gas prices were high and carbon capture looked further off? Is there any sign that City interest in financing such expensive, long payback projects is waning? In other words, will new stations actually be built, even if, in their second consultation, the Government finally conclude that replacing nuclear power stations is desirable?</p>
	<p pid="a.155.2/11">The cost of capital is the largest component of the cost of nuclear power, and the one thing that puts up the cost of capital is political uncertainty. Companies such as EDF are very interested in building new nuclear power stations in the UK, but the issues that we are debating will have to be settled&mdash;and fairly quickly&mdash;if that new build is to happen.</p>
	<p pid="a.155.2/12">As I said on the Floor of the House yesterday, the nuclear industry has an obsessively secret past. What we now need&mdash;to be fair, we are getting it&mdash;is the maximum possible openness. I am clear that, in such an open environment, the public can be shown that we have nothing to fear from new nuclear power, but I am far from clear that we will actually see substantial new nuclear build.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.157.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.157.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.157.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.157.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.157.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.157.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.157.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1511" speakername="Jamie Reed" colnum="157"  time="015:01:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0002.htm#07041994000359">
	<p pid="a.157.2/1">Thank you, Mr. Cook&mdash;I was momentarily elsewhere.</p>
	<p pid="a.157.2/2">I welcome this debate, which is long overdue. The Select Committee's report and the Government response illustrate an impressive and encouraging degree of unanimity on some of the key issues facing the industry and new nuclear build.</p>
	<p pid="a.157.2/3">I agree with what <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1940" name="Peter Luff">the hon. Member for Mid-Worcestershire (Peter Luff)</phrase> said about the Minister, who was indeed an excellent Energy Minister. I have had many in-depth conversations with him about the essential need for new nuclear generation and renewable generation in this country.</p>
	<p pid="a.157.2/4">I shall be brief, but I must declare an interest at the outset&mdash;or perhaps I should say 17,000 interests, because that is the number of jobs that the industry sustains in west Cumbria. It is a matter of fact that I, like many other Members here today, am an enthusiastic advocate of the industry. Indeed, there are currently five or six freedom of information requests against me about my links with the industry</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.157.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.157.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.157.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.157.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.157.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1511" speakername="Jamie Reed" colnum="157"  time="015:01:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0002.htm#07041994000361">
	<p pid="a.157.4/1">Well, there we go. I think that my interests have been declared and are well and truly understood.</p>
	<p pid="a.157.4/2">The report discusses nuclear skills, and the Government have done an awful lot on the issue in the past 18 months or so. The headquarters of the National Nuclear Skills Academy will shortly be based in the constituency of my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1942" name="Tony Cunningham">the Member for Workington (Tony Cunningham)</phrase>, and that &pound;30 million-plus project will be fundamental to this country's nuclear skills portfolio and ability to fulfil its nuclear ambitions, as I believe that it must and eventually will.</p>
	<p pid="a.157.4/3">The hon. Member for Mid-Worcestershire also mentioned uranium prices&mdash;for time reasons, he did so only fleetingly&mdash;which have increased by 70 per cent. over the past 12 months. The reprocessing of spent nuclear is therefore a live reality&mdash;I would, of course, say that, being a former Sellafield employee and having Sellafield in my constituency. This country is good at reprocessing and should continue doing it. There is an undeniable market need for reprocessing internationally, and it is matter of fact that China, Japan and other countries are looking to the British industry to fulfil their huge market requirements.</p>
	<p pid="a.157.4/4">There are four key issues in the report, which the Chairman of the Committee mentioned. Paragraph 5 of the report states:</p>
	<p pid="a.157.4/5" class="indent">&quot;A policy designed to enable the construction of new nuclear power stations would be credible only if it was based on four key elements:&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.157.4/6">The first of those&mdash;I do not want to play party politics with an issue of this importance, but it is a relevant issue&mdash;is:</p>
	<p pid="a.157.4/7" class="indent">&quot;A broad national consensus on the role of nuclear power, that has both cross-party political support and wider public backing&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.157.4/8">How can that be so&mdash;how can it be a qualifying factor in a nuclear policy&mdash;given that the Liberal Democrats are opposed to nuclear energy and the current net effect of the Opposition's policy would be no nuclear at all? Nuclear as a last resort means no nuclear ever. If we do not take the decisions now for the nuclear industry, our skills base will wither. That was exactly the argument used by Opposition Members in the Trident debate: if we did not take the decision, the skills would be lost, and we should have to outsource our manufacturing requirements and seek the products overseas. The same is true for the nuclear industry. The Conservative party's policy has to change.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.158.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.158.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.158.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1999" speakername="Michael Connarty" colnum="158"  time="015:01:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0002.htm#07041994000362">
	<p pid="a.158.0/1">My hon. Friend may know that I completely disagree with him if he is one of those who voted to renew weapons of mass destruction. On the question of the skills base and legacy and the policies of other parties, I am secretary of the all-party group on nuclear energy and have been studying the problem of energy, after many years of being opposed to nuclear energy. My hon. Friend will know that an election is now going on in Scotland. Liberal party policy is that no more energy should be produced in Scotland other than by renewable means. Yet nuclear now supplies 38.5 per cent. of the base-load electricity for Scotland. The Scottish National party would appear completely to have disregarded the report, though its leader is a Member of this House. What chance does my hon. Friend think there is of consensus when people stand for election to a devolved Assembly entirely on the basis that whatever happens to the lights&mdash;which, I am told, would be switched off in Scotland within 10 to 15 years without nuclear energy&mdash;they are opposed on an ideological but not logical basis to renewable nuclear energy?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.158.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.158.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.159.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.159.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.159.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.159.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.159.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.159.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.159.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1940" speakername="Peter Luff" colnum="159"  time="015:01:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0002.htm#07041994000366">
	<p pid="a.159.2/1">In fact my view is that my party's policy, because it is more robust on carbon pricing than the Government's current position, is more likely to deliver nuclear power than the Government's currently declared policy. However, I suspect that the Government will move.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.159.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.159.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.159.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1511" speakername="Jamie Reed" colnum="159"  time="015:01:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0002.htm#07041994000367">
	<p pid="a.159.3/1">I sincerely hope that the Conservative party will move on that, so that we can give the industry comfort that energy policy is above the vagaries of party politics and it can have the confidence to move forward. I would appreciate being able to sit down with the hon. Gentleman in future to discuss those issues. A cross-party approach is absolutely necessary. We should jettison the vanities of party politics with issues of this importance.</p>
	<p pid="a.159.3/2">The third element is:</p>
	<p pid="a.159.3/3" class="indent">&quot;A long-term storage solution in place for the UK's existing radioactive waste legacy&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.159.3/4">Key progress is being made. The CoRWM recommendations will be of pivotal importance in years to come. Finally, I absolutely and wholeheartedly agree on the fourth element:</p>
	<p pid="a.159.3/5" class="indent">&quot;A review of the planning and licensing system to reduce the lead time for construction.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.159.3/6">However, the report does not touch on a number of issues, and I should like to go into them now, if that is permitted within this debate. I seek your guidance, Mr. Cook. They are entirely germane to the subject.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.159.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.159.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.159.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.159.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.159.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.159.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.159.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.159.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.160.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.160.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.160.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.160.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.160.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.160.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.160.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.160.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.161.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.161.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.162.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.162.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.162.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.162.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.163.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.163.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.163.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1598" speakername="Quentin Davies" colnum="163"  time="015:22:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0003.htm#07041994000379">
	<p pid="a.163.0/1">I want to congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1940" name="Peter Luff">the Member for Mid-Worcestershire (Peter Luff)</phrase>, the Chairman of the Select Committee, on an excellent report and on achieving consensus in his Committee on what is always a controversial and emotive subject. He made a speech today that shows that he is a real master of the subject. So, there is not very much that I want or need to add. I only want to make two points.</p>
	<p pid="a.163.0/2">On my first point, I may be nuancing myself slightly from the position of my hon. Friend. He rightly said&mdash;here I agree with both him and the Government&mdash;that there is no need for, and it would be undesirable to have to resort to, some special form of subsidy in order to build new nuclear power stations. As my hon. Friend said, it is not the view of the industry that that is at all necessary. However, that does not mean that we should simply sit back and wait and see what the market delivers. It is important for the state&mdash;Government and Parliament&mdash;to be a little more decisive and to be prepared to take a number of strategic decisions about what eventual outcomes the country needs. There are several reasons for this.</p>
	<p pid="a.163.0/3">The first reason is that there is a co-ordination problem in energy; it is very important for anyone planning one particular increase in capacity&mdash;whether through renewables, burning hydrocarbons or nuclear&mdash;to know what others are doing. The economics of any one project will be affected by the existence or non-existence of other potential sources of energy. The lead times in this are such that one cannot launch down an investment that may involve 10 years before making any kind of return with the danger that the looked-for cash flows will not be available because of some intervening new investment, which one had not anticipated. A real co-ordination problem can mean market failures. There is a need for state action.</p>
	<p pid="a.163.0/4">The second reason is that an enormous number of the costs involved in building nuclear generating capacity are imposed by the state. As my hon. Friend said, those costs could be in licensing or the delays&mdash;any delay is very costly&mdash;in licensing and in the planning process. I think that I am right in saying that Sizewell B's planning inquiry took eight years. We should all be aware of that terrible example and try to avoid similar situations in future.</p>
	<p pid="a.163.0/5">We must also consider the costs imposed by the state in its role as regulator. We might be talking about the state in the form of the British Government, the nuclear installations inspectorate, the European Commission or the agency in Vienna&mdash;whatever it is called&mdash;that establishes norms for nuclear safety. Real uncertainties are involved. These costs are controlled by the state and could not possibly be within the control of the private sector. In so far as the state is in the position of determining a large number of costs, it must be in a position to give some assurance on their extent; otherwise, it cannot possibly expect the market to take account of what are uncertainties for the private sector but matters directly and explicitly under the state's control.</p>
	<p pid="a.163.0/6">The third reason why the state has a natural role to play, which would not normally be the case were one to be building a chocolate factory, a shoe button factory or something of that kind, is that there are enormous externalities in energy. The benefits of building a nuclear power station&mdash;this would apply in the case of any power station&mdash;are greater than those that are captured in the cash flow available to the company that owns and operates the station and sells electricity.</p>
	<p pid="a.163.0/7">Equally, there are negative externalities to consider: the negative costs of an economy running into energy shortages or sudden supply shocks, or of an undue dependence on natural gas being imported from unstable places such as Russia, have an enormous external effect on the economy of a negative kind. In other words, the losses to the economy as a whole are a vast multiple of the losses to the power station or generating company that is dependent on that natural gas.</p>
	<p pid="a.163.0/8">Those are reasons why we should not adopt a laissez-faire policy; we should not just sit back and say, &quot;We will do lots of studies and so forth, but we cannot control the outcome because it is all left to the market.&quot; Given the three factors that I have mentioned, the state must accept the responsibility of establishing a clear, explicit strategy and it must be prepared to take such measures as are necessary to ensure that it can be achieved.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.164.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.164.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.164.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.164.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.165.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.165.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.165.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.165.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.165.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1598" speakername="Quentin Davies" colnum="165"  time="015:22:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0003.htm#07041994000383">
	<p pid="a.165.1/1">I mean Mr. Cook. I never know whether I am supposed to say, &quot;Mr. Speaker&quot;, &quot;Mr. Cook&quot; or &quot;Mr. Chairman&quot;. I always get it wrong, whichever I say.</p>
	<p pid="a.165.1/2">There is an analogy with the railroads in the 19th century, when both major parties were totally committed to the idea that the state should not interfere in the economy at all, but realised that because of co-ordination and externalities, which I mentioned earlier&mdash;although they would not have used those words in those days&mdash;it was necessary for the state to take some action. So they did so. That is why a series of private Bills went through the House, without which we would not have built the railway system. The Americans had to do the same sort of thing in America. On the continent, the state took an even more explicit role in railway building.</p>
	<p pid="a.165.1/3">I should like to emphasise, as my hon. Friend the Member for Mid-Worcestershire did, the enormous urgency of the matter. I have been looking at the excellent report from my hon. Friend's Committee, which makes it clear that there is still some uncertainty about how far the advanced gas-cooled reactor stations' life can be extended. We still do not know about that. Originally, a lot of such stations&mdash;Hinkley and so on&mdash;were going to be taken out of commission in 2011-2012. We might get a few more years, possibly up to 10 more, but it is quite clear to me that from 2015 or so those AGRs will be retired. The Magnoxes, the total capacity of which does not add up to as much as 2 GW&mdash;they are not enormous&mdash;are being withdrawn at the present time.</p>
	<p pid="a.165.1/4">We have to act quickly if we are not to find ourselves in an absolutely appalling, disgraceful situation in which, although we proclaim our commitment to reducing carbon emissions in this country and our desire to have a reasonable balance and mix of dependence and a diversified set of risks in energy policy, we would allow the nuclear contribution to fall dramatically. That would be damaging and dangerous, on the grounds that I have just touched on, and it will happen within 10 years, unless we take action very quickly indeed. I hope that the Government will act even more rapidly than has been anticipated. I would like to see them introduce a Bill in the Queen's Speech in October this year that will bring about the necessary changes in the planning system to ensure that we do not have another disaster like the eight-year-long planning inquiry for Sizewell B, when Sizewell C happens&mdash;which I trust it will&mdash;or when Sizewell C's successors come along. That is unnecessary.</p>
	<p pid="a.165.1/5">I do not want to go into the mechanics and modalities that we might use to sort such matters out in future. Perhaps we should resort to private Bills. I remember, early on in my service in this place, sitting all night for a couple of nights on a private Bill on the Felixstowe dock and harbour scheme. <i>[</i><i>Interruption.</i><i>]</i> I think that my hon. Friend remembers that, too. We were both new in the House and, although it might be a traumatic memory, I do not think that I have ever spent 48 hours of my life more usefully. If we had not gone through two nights on that Bill the scheme would not have been built.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.166.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.166.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.166.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.166.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.167.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.167.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.167.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.167.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.168.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.168.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.168.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.168.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.168.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.168.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.168.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1850" speakername="David Drew" colnum="168"  time="015:40:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0004.htm#07041994000389">
	<p pid="a.168.2/1">I am delighted to follow <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1598" name="Quentin Davies">the hon. Member for Grantham and Stamford (Mr. Davies)</phrase>. I am also delighted to have the opportunity to debate on a report from the Trade and Industry Committee, which I think is a very balanced and fair report.</p>
	<p pid="a.168.2/2">I will start with a note of agreement with the previous speaker. I think that we have dilly-dallied for far too long and a degree of urgency is now required. There is no better person to demonstrate that to me than James Lovelock. I do not know how many other hon. Members had the opportunity to hear him, but he spoke in this place about a month ago. If one wanted a clearer explanation of why the nuclear option is inevitable, and also wanted to know how to dismiss some of the absolute rubbish that gets put about by those who call themselves members of the green movement&mdash;I believe that I myself am a member of the green movement&mdash;but have an obsession with finding reasons why we apparently have alternatives to nuclear energy, James Lovelock utterly dismissed their arguments that day, being someone of outstanding repute who, along with Patrick Moore, has become a great advocate of the nuclear industry. They see it as both inevitable and right that we choose to go along the route of at least replacement.</p>
	<p pid="a.168.2/3">There is some misunderstanding and I think we need to stress that nobody is asking for a complete change in our energy provision, so that we go over entirely to the use of nuclear power.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.169.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.169.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.169.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.169.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.169.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.169.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.169.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1598" speakername="Quentin Davies" colnum="169"  time="015:40:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0004.htm#07041994000392">
	<p pid="a.169.2/1">Would the hon. Gentleman agree that when we discuss renewables we are really talking about non-base-load, because most renewables that we can think of in this country, particularly solar and wind power, obviously only work when the wind is blowing or the sun is shining? So they are distinct from base-load. Would it not be more sensible conceptually to examine what we need in terms of base-load and what proportion of that might reasonably be generated by nuclear power, what we need in terms of renewables and what we need in terms of very flexible capacity, which can be switched on to replace the renewables when the renewables cannot provide the necessary power?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.169.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.169.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.171.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.171.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.171.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.171.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.171.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.171.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.171.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.171.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.174.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.174.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.174.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.174.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.174.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.174.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.175.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.175.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.175.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.175.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.177.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.177.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.177.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.177.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.177.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1999" speakername="Michael Connarty" colnum="177"  time="016:03:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0005.htm#07041994000404">
	<p pid="a.177.1/1">My understanding is that 29 per cent. of our electricity was generated by nuclear in 1979. That percentage is now lower at 19 per cent., and heading for 18 per cent. because the Magnox stations have been turned off. The profile in the 2003 report was that it would fall to 7 per cent. with only Sizewell B running by 2020.</p>
	<p pid="a.177.1/2">The replacement is not available and the idea that it does not matter is contradicted by the fact that I celebrated, as did the Liberal Democrats and all the supporters of renewables, that we reached 2 GW from wind power. That is fantastic, but it does not represent a great proportion of what we use. It is a question of whether the glass is half-full or half-empty. The hon. Gentleman would say that it is half-full when talking about renewables, but half-empty when talking about nuclear. I would be much happier if we had made a commitment to maintain that 30 per cent., and Patrick Moore made a good argument for showing that the carbon footprint would be much better if we considered going to about 60 per cent. That is not to say that the other 40 per cent. cannot come from renewables elsewhere, but we have a different perspective. The Scottish dimension worries me because we have parties committed to no nuclear rebuild, and that would be a problem for me.</p>
	<p pid="a.177.1/3">Turning to the legacy and reprocessing, I heard what my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1511" name="Jamie Reed">the Member for Copeland (Mr. Reed)</phrase> said about what goes on at Sellafield, and its 17,000 jobs. That may be a strong argument, but things must be done properly, and it cannot be good just to keep employing people. It is clear that Sellafield and reprocessing are vital to the nuclear industry, and it is important to me as a Scottish Member. We have no reprocessing facilities in Scotland, and we must reprocess Scottish waste somewhere in England. I am not sure how that squares with the policies of the parties who would abolish the use of nuclear power in Scotland.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.177.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.177.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.178.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.178.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.178.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1999" speakername="Michael Connarty" colnum="178"  time="016:03:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0005.htm#07041994000406">
	<p pid="a.178.0/1">I have always argued that, in the chemical industry, the polluter should pay, and it is certainly sensible to stay within the United Kingdom. I want an integrated energy-producing and waste-reprocessing unit. Otherwise, we will end up with problems and conflicts. I am happy to repeat that argument again and again between now and the Scottish elections.</p>
	<p pid="a.178.0/2">I have been looking at the new technologies. I have been to Canada and France to see what they do there, and I am extremely impressed by the passive safety technologies in the CANDU process. They are designed to prevent repeats of Chernobyl by incorporating features that cut out processing and other dangerous elements very quickly. The latest technology enables any problem to be completely locked off within 72 hours&mdash;automatically and without human intervention.</p>
	<p pid="a.178.0/3">Those who like to create hysteria&mdash;I call them siren voices&mdash;talk about waste and spent fuel rods, and pretend that there is a ticking bomb. They give the impression that when fuel rods are removed and set aside those rods could blow up at any minute. I was astonished, as would be any hon. Member who visited a nuclear power station, that one can actually swim in the tanks where the fuel rods are kept. Obviously that is not recommended, but it is possible to swim in the water above the fuel rods that have been removed for reprocessing without contamination being likely. No radiation is given off from the surface of the water at all, because 5 m of water completely cancels it out.</p>
	<p pid="a.178.0/4">The Canadian plan is that, after 10 years, the fuel will be taken into concrete bunkers that are open to the air, where it can be kept without any radiation registering on a Geiger counter. The Canadians talk of keeping fuel there for 100 years without nuclear pollution, so it is wrong to give the impression that a great reaction is going on.</p>
	<p pid="a.178.0/5">Reprocessing has moved on immensely. I am not sure about the company structure, but I believe that Areva owns EDF and Framatome and that it is a holding company that in turn is owned by the French Government. We went to look at its operations in the manufacture of MOX fuel&mdash;mixed oxide fuel, which is mentioned in the report. When people are asked how much of a spent fuel rod can be reprocessed, their guess is 10 or 5 per cent. They do not realise that the actual figure is 96 per cent. and that not only the uranium but the plutonium can be dealt with. The material is reprocessed into mixed oxide fuel pellets that are put back into rods and returned to the customer.</p>
	<p pid="a.178.0/6">At an Areva site in France, four bundles of spent fuel rods have been reprocessed from weapons-grade uranium. Britain's 100 tonnes of plutonium was described as a treasure. It might be stored in or near the constituency of my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1511" name="Jamie Reed">the hon. Member for Copeland (Mr. Reed)</phrase>, but in any event it is valuable because it helps in the creation of mixed oxide fuels, and the report says, I believe, that two nuclear power stations could be run throughout their life using the quantity of plutonium stored in the UK. The industry is sustainable and safe, and people should seriously consider the idea of &quot;plutonium for peace&quot;, because when plutonium is not a scare story it is very valuable.</p>
	<p pid="a.178.0/7">Those who wish to use wind, wave and tidal power&mdash;particularly in Scotland&mdash;have the problem of getting power from the generating point to the user. The report raises the issue of the choice between national grid systems and dispersed systems whereby power is used near to the generation site. There is a great debate on that topic, and I think that the nuclear contribution should be the one to use the grid system. The Liberal Democrats are leading a big campaign in Scotland against a reinforced grid system that would extend across Scotland, even though it would use the renewable energy generated in the highlands and islands and get it to the end users, who are mainly in England, not Scotland. The Government should talk not only about where they put the stations but about whether they have a commitment to putting the grids in place to allow the energy generated to get to the end user&mdash;not necessarily using a national grid system, but perhaps a dispersed grid system.</p>
	<p pid="a.178.0/8">The question of skills was raised by my hon. Friend the Member for Copeland. I have spent a long time considering the run-down of the skills that we require in the oil and gas industry. Despite the best efforts of the companies and associations&mdash;and the Government, through PILOT&mdash;there is a major skills problem in the UK. There is no doubt that we have to consider that as an EU question. For example, at the moment a refit, shut-down, maintenance job is going on in my constituency at INEOS, the company that bought the chemical olefins derivatives section of BP. Some 270 skilled workers were required, but we could not get more than 200 from the UK, even after asking all the associations and trade unions to supply them. Companies have had to bring in people from Poland, Portugal and elsewhere, paying them high rates of pay and additional expenses so that they can live in hotels. If we are to renew the build programme in the UK, we shall have to do that on a skill base at EU level. That underlines why it was so important for the EU to take those policies recently.</p>
	<p pid="a.178.0/9">The second issue is the capacity of the licensing body. We heard a bid from the hon. Member for Bournemouth, East, who argued for an additional consideration for the pebble-bed process that has been developed in South Africa, on top of the Areva, Westinghouse and CANDU processes. My understanding is that talk throughout the industry is that the Government are sending out signals that they cannot cope with more than two pre-licensing examples; they only licensed two of the three that were named, even though there was a bid for a fourth, because there is not the capacity.</p>
	<p pid="a.178.0/10">That is a sign of how far things have run down or of how many people, as my hon. Friend the Member for Copeland said, have left&mdash;because of age, not because of any lack of interest in the industry. There is a reigniting of interest in the industry at Birmingham, where there are nuclear industry courses, and among the trade associations. However, it will take a long time to get the capacity. If the licensing body does not have the capacity, all the aspirations in the report will come to naught. We will have to reduce the market and say that we can have only two players as we cannot cope with three&mdash;or, as I have been told, we will have to wait two further years if we want three. That leads me to disagree with my hon. Friend.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.180.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.180.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.180.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.180.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.180.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.180.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.181.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.181.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.182.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.182.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.182.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1473" speakername="David Howarth" colnum="182"  time="016:36:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0006.htm#07041994000411">
	<p pid="a.182.0/1">I start by congratulating the Chair of the Trade and Industry Committee on securing this debate, but I share his regret that, for various reasons, many hon. Members have been unable to attend today, including many who hold the same view as I.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.182.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.182.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.182.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.182.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.183.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.183.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.183.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.183.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.183.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1473" speakername="David Howarth" colnum="183"  time="016:36:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0006.htm#07041994000415">
	<p pid="a.183.1/1">It was significant that the Chairman of the Committee said that the finances are rapidly changing with the technology. I agree with him that left to the market, it is possible that carbon capture and storage will be able to outbid nuclear quite soon. The nuclear industry is always optimistic, but I think that it is being over-optimistic.</p>
	<p pid="a.183.1/2">I have never been able to grasp the point made by nuclear advocates on the security of supply because there is no domestic uranium and European supplies of uranium are insufficient to keep nuclear power plants going for long, especially if there is new nuclear build that uses up existing and known supplies. All usable uranium has to be imported, not only from Canada and Australia, but other countries such as Uzbekistan and Kazakhstan. On the other hand, wind, tide, sun and coal are local and there are plenty of suppliers within our political grasp, as it were.</p>
	<p pid="a.183.1/3">Instead of comparing itself with those sources of energy, the nuclear industry usually compares itself with the gas industry. True, gas will probably play a bigger part in the generation of electricity in the next few years regardless of the policy on nuclear new build, because gas is probably the source from which new electricity generating capacity will come as other sources decline, depending on the relative price of gas and coal. That is not in any way an argument for nuclear. By the argument that I have been using, nuclear will not be able to plug the gap in the time scale. The policy problem&mdash;the problem of a secure gas supply&mdash;applies regardless of nuclear policy.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.184.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.184.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.184.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.184.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.184.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.184.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.184.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.184.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.184.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.184.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.184.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.184.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.185.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.185.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.185.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.185.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.185.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.185.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.185.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.185.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.185.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1473" speakername="David Howarth" colnum="185"  time="016:36:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0006.htm#07041994000425">
	<p pid="a.185.3/1">I was not suggesting that the risks from nuclear power stations in this country and western Europe are in the same league as those from former Soviet bloc power stations. I was making a point about the cap on liability. A cap on liability is a massive subsidy to the whole nuclear industry. If the industry had to bear that liability itself, it would make the industry uneconomic. That fact cannot be denied. Nuclear plants are not as reliable as the hon. Gentleman has implied. There are various estimates for load factors in excess of 90 per cent. Last year, four Swedish plants had to be turned off at the same time because of an accident in one of them. That is a warning to those who propose that the Government should help the industry by ensuring that a single design for the new nuclear fleet is brought forward. The problem with that is if, as happened in Sweden, one discovers a very dangerous flaw in one plant, all the plants of the same design would have to be turned off at once. That is one of the biggest threats that one could imagine to security and continuity of supply.</p>
	<p pid="a.185.3/2">Similarly last year, a Spanish plant, which was responsible for 20 per cent. of the country's electricity demand, had to be turned off because it overheated in the hot weather. Even the French had to turn off the Dampierre plant this month. Members might remember an incident last year when the whole of northern France lost power for days on end. That happened because the connection between France and Germany was damaged. The French electricity system is predominantly nuclear-powered. It is massively inflexible and cannot cope with having its connection with another country broken. The French grid exports and imports vast amounts of electricity. Therefore, the claim made by <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1850" name="David Drew">the hon. Member for Stroud (Mr. Drew)</phrase> that the French independent grid system is the best in the world is quite false. The French depend on import and export because nuclear power is so inflexible.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.186.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.186.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.186.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.186.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.186.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.186.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.186.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.186.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.186.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1473" speakername="David Howarth" colnum="186"  time="016:36:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0006.htm#07041994000429">
	<p pid="a.186.3/1">No, it is not about the grid system; it is about any grid system with a high percentage of nuclear power. The 60 per cent. that the hon. Gentleman proposes would be as dangerous as the 80 per cent. used by the French. The problem is that nuclear power stations cannot easily be turned on or off. Therefore, they are very inflexible. All this talk about base-load&mdash;the concept of base-load is an artificial construct because it is only the minimum amount of electricity being used on the grid over a long period&mdash;reveals a misunderstanding of one of the basic problems of controlling a grid, which is that it has to be held in balance at every point. Nuclear power cannot do that.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.186.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.186.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.187.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.187.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.187.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.187.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.188.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.188.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.188.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.188.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.188.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.188.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.188.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1473" speakername="David Howarth" colnum="188"  time="016:36:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0007.htm#07041994000435">
	<p pid="a.188.2/1">I will not, because I need to finish my speech to allow the Minister and the spokesman for the official Opposition time to speak.</p>
	<p pid="a.188.2/2">I just want to make a final point, which arises out of several comments that have been made. The nuclear industry needs to be open. A number of hon. Members have said that it has had a terrible record. The Chairman of the Committee made a very eloquent statement yesterday in the House when he commented on the statement. The industry has a terrible record of secrecy, which undermines confidence. Many other people have also said that. Bill Nuttall, the academic, says exactly the same thing in his works on nuclear renaissance. That is the message of the CoRWM report and Professor Gordon MacKerron.</p>
	<p pid="a.188.2/3">However, there is a fundamental problem with that argument. That is, that nuclear power, because of its inherent technical links with nuclear weapons and weapons technology, can never be purely private. It will always have a security element. It is interesting, for example, that the person who was recently appointed to head the Civil Nuclear Constabulary is not a career police officer; he is a career intelligence officer from the Secret Intelligence Service. There will always be a link and, because of that link, the industry can never be wholly open. That applies both to techniques and to materials. I agree that the industry would do itself a lot of good by being as open as possible. However, I think that it is an impossible dream that the industry could be as open as other industries.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.188.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.188.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.188.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1913" speakername="Charles Hendry" colnum="188"  time="017:01:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0007.htm#07041994000436">
	<p pid="a.188.3/1">May I begin by drawing the attention of the House to my entry in the Register of Members' Interests, which shows that, last year, I went on a trip sponsored by E. ON to look at nuclear waste disposal in Sweden and a nuclear power plant in Finland? In case people fear that my soul has been bought, it is listed alongside the entry for a trip to look at onshore and offshore wind farms and oil and gas facilities.</p>
	<p pid="a.188.3/2">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1940" name="Peter Luff">the Member for Mid-Worcestershire (Peter Luff)</phrase> on the way in which he has introduced this debate and the extremely robust report that his Committee has produced. The way in which he drives these things forward and his energy and commitment are evident throughout not only in his speech, but in the thoughtful report that has been produced by his Committee.</p>
	<p pid="a.188.3/3">We have had some extremely good contributions in this debate. A lot of knowledge and constituency interest have been brought to bear. I will pick up on a couple of those points. My hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1598" name="Quentin Davies">the Member for Grantham and Stamford (Mr. Davies)</phrase> is quite right to say that decisions need to be made soon. This is not an issue where we have the luxury of time on our side and where we can put off decisions until a future date. We need to make progress quickly.</p>
	<p pid="a.188.3/4">I also pick up on the point that <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1850" name="David Drew">the hon. Member for Stroud (Mr. Drew)</phrase> makes, namely, that we need a strategy for waste disposal. Regardless of whether we have a new generation of nuclear power stations, it is to our shame as a nation that we have not addressed that issue more substantially and earlier.</p>
	<p pid="a.188.3/5">I listened with interest to the personal journey of <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1999" name="Michael Connarty">the hon. Member for Linlithgow and East Falkirk (Michael Connarty)</phrase> from old Labour leftie perhaps to Blairite, modern, new Labour luvvie, in a way that would bring joy to the hearts of the Labour Whips Office. However, I would not encourage him to take a swim in the tank in which the radioactive waste is stored. I understand that the water contains the radioactive waste and radioactive particles, and if he gets in it, he will be in very serious trouble indeed. That may also bring joy to the Labour Whips Office, but I would discourage him from doing so.</p>
	<p pid="a.188.3/6">My hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1437" name="Tobias Ellwood">the Member for Bournemouth, East (Mr. Ellwood)</phrase> made an interesting reference to fusion. Fusion has been 20 years away for the past 50 years. One day, we will get there. However, that makes the point that we are making decisions that will stand for relatively few years and, in time, some new source of energy, which as yet is perhaps not even thought of, may come through and address these issues.</p>
	<p pid="a.188.3/7"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1473" name="David Howarth">The hon. Member for Cambridge (David Howarth)</phrase> talked rather idealistically. He talked initially as though carbon capture and storage were a certainty, and under pressure from the hon. Member for Linlithgow and East Falkirk he said that it was quite possible that carbon capture and storage could outbid nuclear energy quite soon. I felt that that was quite a qualified comment in the circumstances.</p>
	<p pid="a.188.3/8">The challenge of this debate is that we are expected to make the decisions now, when the technology for many aspects of energy and electricity generation is not yet clear. We do not know what their potential will be.</p>
	<p pid="a.188.3/9">I agree with a great deal of what is said in the report; indeed, I agree with it overwhelmingly. The report is right to say that there should have been a more detailed assessment of future generating capacity before the energy review was published last year. I think it likely that the nuclear installations inspectorate will give life extensions to many of the power plants involved, but the Committee was being over-optimistic in saying that there was not a serious energy gap, because we do not know the role that coal can play. If carbon capture and storage can be made to be economically feasible, coal has a very bright future. However, without that feasibility, we would have a very serious energy gap opening up.</p>
	<p pid="a.188.3/10">I absolutely agree with the report as well that the Government should be technology-neutral in these matters. The Government should be setting a framework in which business decides how to invest. That is why we have recommended that there should be a system of cap and trade. Under such a system, the Government would say that, over a period of years&mdash;many years, 40 or 50 years ahead&mdash;if carbon is going to be produced in the course of generating electricity, a certificate should be required to do so and the number of certificates would decline year on year. Therefore, people could invest with great confidence and great knowledge of exactly what the price of carbon was going to be 20 or 30 years ahead. However, the Government absolutely should not be picking winners. They cannot build a dome, or a football stadium. What on earth makes anybody believe that they could decide on the right balance for our energy policy?</p>
	<p pid="a.188.3/11">The report is also right in saying that the public are more supportive of nuclear power when it is linked with a greater commitment to renewables. A YouGov poll said that 56 per cent. of the population backed nuclear power in conjunction with a greater commitment to renewables. I am sure that that is true, but I query a little the statement that my hon. Friend the Member for Mid-Worcestershire made about the need for a national consensus. That consensus is certainly desirable, but it is noteworthy that in Finland the public support followed the political decision and the decision of the Government. It is the case that, once that decision was made, the public have been moving more in favour of the nuclear debate.</p>
	<p pid="a.188.3/12">There is no doubt, however, that the Government are in something of a mess over the issue. There is no doubt that they should have consulted more on the nuclear aspect of this debate. As Mr. Justice Sullivan said in summing up the Government's consultation proposals, it contained information that</p>
	<p pid="a.188.3/13" class="indent">&quot;was wholly insufficient for them&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.188.3/14">that is, the public&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.188.3/15" class="indent">&quot;to make an intelligent response.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.188.3/16">I think that Greenpeace is largely right in saying that any consultation process requires clarity in identifying the problem; integration, to ensure that it ties in with wider energy policy and climate change debate issues; independence, in that it should be carried out by professional experts; a layered approach, so that the technical discussions should run alongside public engagement; and feedback, which shows how the consultation will affect the outcome of the Government's policy.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.190.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.190.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.190.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.190.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.192.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.192.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.192.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1523" speakername="Malcolm Wicks" speakeroffice="The Minister for Science and Innovation"  colnum="192"  time="017:13:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0007.htm#07041994000439">
	<p pid="a.192.0/1">I, too, think that this has been a useful debate. I have immense regard for the Select Committee system. I once chaired one myself. May I congratulate the Select Committee Chairman on the authoritative, lucid way in which he introduced its findings? The vast majority of the conclusions in the Committee's report reflect the position and proposals that we advanced in the energy review, which hon. Members know set out how the Government plan to meet the two major challenges facing us in the 21st century, namely, climate change and our energy security. We use the word &quot;security&quot; advisedly, rather than simply &quot;supply&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/2">It is worth reminding ourselves of the scale of those challenges. I have said before that when the history of the 21st century is written, not just for the UK, but globally, those twin issues will loom as importantly as some of the big issues about war and peace and the development of welfare states in the 20th century. Climate change is with us now. I was fortunate recently to visit Antarctica, where I talked to British scientists in the excellent British Antarctic Survey about their work on climate change.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/3">In simple terms, we set out in our energy review that, in the face of those challenges, a low carbon and diverse energy mix is crucial. Those proposals will now be taken forward in our energy White Paper, which will be published next month. The Government responded to the Select Committee report last October. Last year, I gave evidence to the Committee on the energy review, so I do not want to use the time that I have this afternoon to repeat myself. Instead, it will be more useful to update hon. Members on recent developments. I shall also address the key elements that the Select Committee said should be the basis of any new policy decisions on new nuclear.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/4">I have listened carefully to the views of hon. Members. We have had some important contributions from my hon. Friends the Members for Stroud (Mr. Drew), for Linlithgow and East Falkirk (Michael Connarty) and for Copeland (Mr. Reed), and of course I listened with great care to the interesting speech by <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1598" name="Quentin Davies">the hon. Member for Grantham and Stamford (Mr. Davies)</phrase>. We also heard speeches from two Front-Bench Opposition Members.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/5">The Select Committee discussed a broad national consensus on the role of nuclear power, a carbon-pricing framework, the long-term management of legacy waste and a review of the planning and licensing system. I should also acknowledge that it identified issues such as pre-licensing and site selection, which are important for nuclear new build. They would need to be dealt with to enable any new power stations to be built.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/6">Let me start with the judicial review. As hon. Members know, the Government accepted the High Court's judgment. We will publish a further consultation document next month alongside the energy White Paper. Our new consultation will endeavour to meet the Court's requirements, and it will bring together the evidence and analysis that the Government have collected and published since the energy review began. It will help people to reach informed views and to provide the Government with valuable contributions.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/7">Our preliminary view, which is, of course, subject to consultation, is that there is a case for having new nuclear power stations as one of the options open to developers of large-scale electricity-generating capacity. However, we will consider the comments that we receive before we reach any decision. This is not about nuclear for nuclear's sake; it is about the potential that nuclear has to reduce carbon emissions and to contribute to security of energy supply.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/8">The Select Committee commented on the need for a broad national consensus. We have already said that we are committed to further consultation and that we will need to consider carefully the responses that we get. The Government recognise that nuclear is a subject on which many people have diverse views. The consultation will enable us to hear and to understand those views, and will inform our decision in the autumn.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/9">Nuclear would only ever be one part of a future diverse energy mix. Renewables, other low-carbon technologies, energy-efficiency measures and carbon capture and storage will have to play an increasingly important role if we are to meet our challenging energy policy goals. The White Paper will set out the overall conclusions in respect of our energy strategy.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/10">The Chairman of the Select Committee asked whether there would be nuclear new build by the private sector, in view of the political uncertainty and its impact on cost of capital. Of course, political uncertainty is not purely in the hands of the Government. I listened carefully to the Conservative spokesman, but I am still a bit puzzled about the place of nuclear in the Conservative strategy. There are time scale problems that need to be addressed&mdash;I offer that advice freely, of course, in all senses.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/11">The Government's response to the question is that the private sector will come forward if the economics are attractive. Our current view is that, provided the prerequisites that the Select Committee identified&mdash; planning, licensing, carbon pricing&mdash;are addressed, the economics will become more attractive. Those are precisely the issues that were identified in the energy review and that, subject to the outcome of the consultation, would need to be dealt with to enable any new power stations to be built.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/12">There have been other developments. At the recent spring Council, EU leaders approved an ambitious climate change and energy package. The fundamental aim is to cut greenhouse gas emissions by 20 per cent. compared with 1990 levels by 2020, or by 30 per cent. if other countries also play their part. The targets are tough, but, through that package, the EU is sending a powerful message to the rest of the world that we are serious about tackling climate change and ensuring security of supply.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/13">We will also continue to work in Europe to address issues surrounding the European Union's emissions trading scheme. The Commission has been tough in assessing the caps for the second phase. The market is expecting the price of carbon to be about &euro;17 next year, which shows that the market believes that the scheme will have a real impact on emissions. That is encouraging. However, we will also keep the option open for further measures&mdash;I have listened to colleagues' views on that&mdash;in order to reinforce, if necessary, the operation of the scheme in the UK and to give greater clarity to investors. That answers another key point raised by the Committee concerning the framework of carbon pricing.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/14">I have listened to a number of colleagues' views on nuclear waste, including my hon. Friend the Member for Linlithgow and East Falkirk. Comment has already been made on his suggestion that the waters are safe enough to swim in. One always looks for a photo opportunity, but on this occasion I would simply offer to hold the towel for my hon. Friend.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/15">Since I last addressed the Select Committee, the Government have made progress on the issue of nuclear waste. We can be proud of the fact that we are the first UK Government to take decisive steps to resolve that issue. However, we are realistic and know that it will take concerted action to bring about a lasting solution. I should add that I visited Finland to examine its strategy on waste.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/16">As the Committee will know, we are currently developing plans for a consultation on geological disposal and how to take forward the CoRWM recommendations. We aim for that to take place this summer. There will be more in that about volunteerism. I am advised that managing radioactive waste supply is the name of the project to which I have referred.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/17">We all recognise the significance of planning, about which the hon. Member for Grantham and Stamford spoke in an interesting manner. The Committee rightly said that the current planning system can be a significant barrier to investment in all sorts of new infrastructure. All hon. Members are aware of that and we certainly came to the same conclusion. The system needs to be reformed to give us the infrastructure we need on the right timetable, whether it be for energy or other types of large infrastructure. To that end, the Government will shortly publish a planning White Paper, which will take forward proposals for the reform of major infrastructure planning. Energy will, of course, be an important part of that.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/18">The Committee has concerns on a number of other matters that I will now attempt to address, but I will start perhaps with another matter raised in the debate: reactor type and design. That is not a matter for Government per se, as it is, broadly, for the private sector to make judgments about that. Most of us would agree that that is the sensible approach. We have heard about a number of different companies and designs, so it is for the private sector to judge. However, of course, that must be subject to licensing. It is for private sector technology vendors to decide whether they want to have their technologies pre-licensed, and it is for the private sector generators to decide which licensed technologies to deploy if licensing shows that they are safe.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/19">Skills are now a frequent matter for discussion, not only in the energy sector, but in many other sectors about which we are concerned. The Committee's report concluded:</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/20" class="indent">&quot;Constraints in the domestic skills capacity could be overcome&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/21">In our energy review we agreed with that. We know that there are significant skill gaps in the decommissioning and waste management sector. We understand that the demography of the work force means that more people are closer to 50 than to 25&mdash;if I can summarise it in that way. Many of us have sympathy with that demography.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/22">We know that there are significant skills gaps in the decommissioning and waste management sector, but we believe that the Nuclear Decommissioning Authority, Cogent, which is the sector skills council, and the industry more widely, as well as the recently established National Skills Academy for nuclear are pulling together a strategy to deal with those gaps. As the Minister responsible for skills in the Department of Trade and Industry, I promise to take a close interest in those developments.</p>
	<p pid="a.192.0/23">Regardless of the decision on new nuclear build in light of the consultation, skills will continue to be an important issue. That applies both to existing nuclear power stations and to long-term decommissioning and waste management.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.195.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.195.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.195.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.195.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.196.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.196.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.196.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.196.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.196.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.196.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.196.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19b.196.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2007-04-19a.196.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1523" speakername="Malcolm Wicks" colnum="196"  time="017:13:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200607/cmhansrd/cm070419/halltext/70419h0008.htm#07041994000445">
	<p pid="a.196.3/1">I am not sure that I can explain it. I am not sure that I understand the question. Let me reflect on it, and if it is worthy of an answer I will reply in writing.</p>
	<p pid="a.196.3/2">The hon. Gentleman made some technical, but important points, no doubt, that the DTI energy review used non-standard discount rates and costs of capital. The model used in the energy review was extensively peer-reviewed by external experts who were satisfied as to its robustness. We took the arithmetic very seriously.</p>
	<p pid="a.196.3/3">My hon. Friend the Member for Linlithgow and East Falkirk asked about grid infrastructure, which is crucial in terms of any developments that we are proposing or hoping to see. Ofgem have recognised the need for increased investment in the distribution networks. In its last electricity distribution price control review, it increased funding allowances for investment for 2005 to 2010 by approximately 50 per cent. over levels spent in 2000 to 2005. That is an important point, which is often neglected and I thank my hon. Friend for raising it.</p>
	<p pid="a.196.3/4">It is interesting that, however few hon. Members are present in the Chamber, we always spend three hours debating, which is gratifying on a sunny afternoon. To sum up, the Government have reached their preliminary view on potential new nuclear build for two main reasons: the science of climate change is now very clear and we need to secure our energy supplies as the amount of oil and gas in the North sea declines.</p>
	<p pid="a.196.3/5">We will bring forward our consultation on nuclear next month. It is important that people engage with the arguments. If people have better solutions, then, of course, we are listening. We are faced with difficult choices, but any Government worth their name must surely be prepared to show leadership while listening to views on this crucial issue. That is what we intend to do. We have made a good, as it were, new start this afternoon. We have had an excellent discussion involving all hon. Members. Again, I thank the Chairman of the Select Committee for an excellent report and for introducing it with such clarity and authority.</p>
	<p pid="a.196.3/6" class="italic">Question put and agreed to.</p>
	<p pid="a.196.3/7" class="italic">Adjourned accordingly at twenty-nine minutes past Five o'clock.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

