<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.191.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.193.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.191.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.193.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.191.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.193.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.191.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.193.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.191.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.193.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.192.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.194.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.192.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.194.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.192.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1108" speakername="Alan Meale" colnum="192"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050118/halltext/50118h01.htm#50118h01_spnew3">
	<p pid=".192.1/1">It is interesting that the hon. Gentleman should say that, as I am about to name another one. His analysis is right. Unfortunately, as I said, Mr. Crichton is not the only one. There are many such people.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/2">Stranger still is the opinion purveyed by Myron Ebell, director of the business-sponsored Competitive Enterprise Institute, based in Washington DC, who recently outstripped previous first world critics when arguing that describing climate change as &quot;a crisis for humanity&quot; was based on</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/3" class="indent">&quot;a tissue of improbabilities, which really only had one true objective&quot;,</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/4">that being</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/5" class="indent">&quot;for Europe to attack America's economic superiority&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/6">He forgetfully, and rather conveniently, put aside the reality that most European member countries signed up for the Kyoto protocol at considerably higher levels than those proposed for the United States. He also failed to mention in his illogical analysis that leading American scientists have recently established that concentrations of carbon dioxide gases have risen to the unprecedented level of 375 parts per million. That is especially worrying, as the level was only 280 parts per million at the time of the industrial revolution.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/7">In order to discuss such detailed and complex substance, or, in the case of the examples previously mentioned, the lack of it, let us examine the facts. Hon. Members must realise from the outset that it is freely accepted in today's scientific community that CO <sub>2</sub> and other gases play a crucial role in global climates and that, without them, global temperatures would be much lower. Similarly, it is crucial to understand that global warming statistics have not been recently discovered or are mere theorised academic opinions. They have been well documented over many decades by eminent scientists and institutes the world over.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/8">The role of gases in the environment, in trapping heat close to the earth, was first recognised as far back as 1827 by Jean Baptiste Fourier. The phenomenon was then observed and proved in 1861 by John Tyndall, using the then novel technique of quantitative spectroscopy. In 1896, the Swedish chemist, Sven Arrhenius, promoted the idea that CO <sub>2</sub> emissions from the combustion of coal could enhance the greenhouse effect and thus lead to global warming, a subsequently proven theory.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/9">Since those times, the broad consensus of scientific opinion is that there has been an anthropogenic effect in our atmosphere. That is to say, changes stemming directly from human activities have taken place, which have consequently increased the amount of trapped heat close to the planet's surface, a view supported by work undertaken by United Kingdom scientist G.S. Callendar in 1949, when he directly linked the estimated 10 per cent. increase in CO <sub>2</sub> in the Earth's atmosphere from 1850 to 1940 with the warming of northern Europe and north America, which he calculated had begun as early as the 1880s.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/10">As importantly, further studies carried out as recently as in the 1970s identified that other gases, including chlorofluorocarbons, methane and nitrous oxides, were greenhouse gases. They also identified that global surface air temperatures had increased by between 0.3&deg;   C and 0.6&deg; C since the late 19th century, and that between 0.2&deg; C and 0.3&deg; C of that increase had occurred in the last 40 years. That warming had already led to considerable loss of snow coverage and noticeable weather variations.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/11">From those scientific discoveries emerged a series of converted academic programmes, which predicted that a doubling of CO <sub>2</sub> levels could eventually warm the Earth further, by anywhere from 1.4&deg; C to 5.8&deg; C. Bearing it in mind that a shift of less than 6&deg; C caused the end of the ice age, international climate programmes were rapidly established to enhance individual nations' ability to respond to climate variability, including improved forecasting techniques, international co-operation, research and assessment.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/12">Thankfully, and contrary to the views espoused by the likes of Lomborg, Crichton and Ebell, so successful was the evidence gathering that, by the mid-1980s, a major conference was held, sponsored by the United Nations Environment Programme, the World Meteorological Organisation and the International Council of Scientific Unions. That conference recommended that a global treaty addressing climate change should be promoted urgently.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/13">As we are all aware, the conference resulted in the establishment in 1988 of the intergovernmental panel on climate change, led by Government scientists, but also involving several hundred independent, academic scientists and researchers throughout the world. In 1990, that body calculated that a 60 per cent. reduction in CO <sub>2</sub> emissions could, if applied, halt the build up of global warming. So serious were its predictions taken that 116 countries took part in a second conference in 1990. By the time of the Rio summit in 1992, the panel's climate change convention had been signed by 155 nations and, by 1993, 50 had ratified its proposals and some had put them into effect.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/14">Inevitably, with so much evidence and concern, by 1997, there was general consensus that climate change was occurring because of human activity. That view ultimately led to international recognition of the Kyoto protocol&mdash;an agreement to reduce the emissions of greenhouse gases. Smaller targets than the 60 per cent. calculated as necessary in 1990 were set, but the protocol was an avenue that was thought necessary by industrial, first world nations as the first step in a long process of providing good faith to the lesser developed world.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/15">As well as recognising the magnificent efforts of the Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs, and especially the Minister present today, I want to pay tribute to my right hon. Friend the Deputy Prime Minister. Everybody knows that it was his steady chairmanship that went a long way towards delivering the essential landmark of the Kyoto protocol. I mention that because, contrary to some Fleet street cynics who seem at times interested only in his love of a certain type of motor car, it needs stating that he forced the pace to achieve that admirable and necessary objective. So strong was his determination to achieve an agreement that he and others, particularly the support team from the UK, tasted the success of their endeavours almost on the departure runway of the airport at the end of the conference.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/16">As we all know, President Putin and the Russian Duma recently signed the protocol, undoubtedly influenced by the predicted world shortage of oil and gas and their nation's ownership of at least 23 per cent. of remaining reserves. In February 2005, it will come into force legally in those countries that are signatory to it, with its targets binding upon all of them. The delivery of the protocol has been a vital stage in the global strategy for dealing with climate change and the planet's warming, not least because it represents, as I stated earlier, acceptance of its being caused by human activities.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/17">Of course, there will still be the doubters&mdash;those whom I mentioned earlier&mdash;together with a small number of others who continue to argue that &quot;measurements were incorrect&quot; and &quot;calculations wrongly based&quot;. However, the truth is that even President Bush has finally accepted that climate change is occurring. The debate has moved on, despite the doubters. Now the question is no longer whether we respond, but how we respond. In America's case, that has been settled by the White House. The President has decided to use taxpayers' dollars over the next 25 years to fund the American energy industry's research into cleaner technologies, and in particular into hydrogen and fuel cell technological development.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/18">Only time will tell whether we have 25 years and whether such a decision is correct. Perhaps chance, ingenuity and/or discovery will produce something that will halt or even reverse current worsening situations. However, if one looks at what is happening to our world, the signs are not good. For instance, the United Nations has recently compiled clear evidence of further worrying trends, which indicate that, despite the major collective efforts made by countries to counter world poverty, climate change that results directly from global warming continues to cause more consequential weather-related disasters&mdash;droughts and floods&mdash;and in doing so forces even more people into poverty and destitution.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/19">In relation to droughts alone, according to the United   Nations, between the mid-1990s and 2000, almost 300 sq km of land were turned into desert each year. The same study estimated that, at the present rate, by 2025, two thirds of arable land in Africa will have disappeared, along with one third of such areas in Asia and one fifth in south America. As a result, 135 million people are being put at risk of displacement. Most of those affected are likely to be from the edges of existing deserts&mdash;in particular, poor farmers currently barely able to achieve sustainability or even basic subsistence levels. There will also be others from areas where people do not at the moment struggle to eke out a living, thus adding to the numbers suffering. Many of them will be least able to help themselves. What the immediate future holds for them is crop failure, followed by loss of quality, fuelled by soil degradation and subsequent further demise.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/20">That is borne out by another recent United Nations study, which predicts that the proportion of people living in countries suffering significant water stress will double by 2025, proving conclusively that global warming is, as it has been described on the international stage,</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/21" class="indent">&quot;the mother of all ecological debts, owed by the North to the South&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/22">Contrary to what the sceptics think, poverty and climate change are inextricably linked, with the poorest paying the heaviest price.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/23">It is not just desert areas that will be affected by global warming. At the other end of the spectrum, changes are already taking place. For example, in the past few years, major areas of the earth's ice mass have already been lost. The Arctic and Antarctic continents regularly report big losses of ice shelves and major recessions of ice. In that respect, another recent report&mdash;one prepared for the eight-nation Arctic Council&mdash;reported a 10 per cent. loss of ice in the past 10 years. Worse still, it predicted that, if that continued, even at a slower pace, not only would it threaten present ecosystems, but another outcome could be the cooling of the gulf stream. If that occurred, according to the UK's Tyndall Centre for Climate Change Research, it would have devastating consequences, especially for northern Europe.</p>
	<p pid=".192.1/24">I mention that because, according to other expert opinion, it has been calculated that such combinations of cooling and melting could ultimately lead to a partial thawing of the Siberian tundra. If that occurred, it would subsequently release vast amounts of methane, the highest burning gas, which is eight times more volatile than CO <sub>2</sub> , into the Earth's atmosphere, thereby seriously spiralling the warming of our planet.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.196.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.198.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.196.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.198.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.196.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1108" speakername="Alan Meale" colnum="196"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050118/halltext/50118h01.htm#50118h01_spnew5">
	<p pid=".196.1/1">That is a good point. The Opposition should reflect on their policy on the use of HFCs in firefighting. It has been calculated that, by 2010, the use of HFCs to combat fire will be make up less than .0005   per cent. of total emissions. If one puts that against what I shall say a little later in relation to fires, it is more than balanced by how they will combat a range of fires.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/2">Is that alarmist nonsense? The reality is that we dismiss such warnings at our peril. Let us consider other likely outcomes if the problems of global warming and climate change are not tackled urgently. Many delicate indigenous native plants and wildlife eco-systems would disappear as temperatures rise or fall. Many marine species would either be lost or would migrate from their traditional breeding grounds. For example, according to recent reports by the British Antarctic Survey, climate change is already causing serious problems for aquatic life such as krill, the tiny shrimp-like life forms that flourish in their billions in cold waters, which are the staple diet of such species as penguins, seals, whales and others. In winter periods, those important life forms depend upon thick mats of green algae that flourish on the undersides of ice shelves. However, because of global warming, that foodstuff is either seriously retreating or is vanishing, leaving those species and many others without their necessary food supplies.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/3">On another front, large areas of forest would either die or be destroyed by fire caused directly by the change in heat patterns. Last but not least, vast amounts of property and infrastructure investment would either be lost or put at risk by rising sea levels, flooding, coastal erosion and ground subsidence. I cite as evidence what has already occurred on the roof of our world. Some scientists have recently calculated that the Earth's highest ice fields could completely disappear within the next 200 years unless urgent action is taken to combat global warming. In a recent study, &quot;The Glacier Inventory&quot;, produced by the Chinese Academy of Sciences, we were warned that, unless urgent measures are taken to stop further deterioration, those fields may be lost for ever. Proof for such claims are contained in the worrying statistics of that report, which reveal that at least 5.5 per cent. of the ice volume in China's 46,298 glaciers, representing 15 per cent. of the Earth's total, has already melted. That is equal to at least 3,000 sq km of ice.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/4">Changes are taking place not only on the tops of Chinese mountains or in far-off continents. The UK Government chief scientific adviser, Sir David King, recently stated that even the most ambitious targets may not be enough to avert the worst effects of global warming. He warned that by 2050 carbon dioxide emissions may have to be cut by as much as 80 per cent. to avoid such catastrophic effects as the melting of the Greenland ice sheets, which would raise sea levels by as much as 20 ft, putting a number of cities in northern Europe under water as a consequence, including London, Paris, Amsterdam, Copenhagen and Helsinki.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/5">At the same time, on the other side of the globe, because of similar ice loss, many small, poorer, vulnerable nations,&mdash;for example, small islands such as the Maldives, Mauritius and Tuvalou&mdash;could disappear entirely. Other countries would face horrendous and more regular flooding, especially such nations as India, Bangladesh, Sri Lanka and Indonesia&mdash;as if they have not suffered enough already.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/6">Finally, we need to consider what the financial effect would be if global warming continued unabated. The reality is almost incalculable and certainly unaffordable. In the UK alone, the cost has been initially estimated to be as high as &pound;26 billion at today's prices. To my mind, that is a surprisingly conservative figure when one considers the likely heavier and more frequent rainfalls, especially in winter periods. There will a further rise in sea levels, followed by more consequential flooding. On a much wider scale, the immediate causal effect world wide would be that public bodies and private property owners had to invest massively in flood protection, especially in urban areas and areas that house important but delicate structures such as nuclear power stations, chemical plants and transport infrastructure, especially underground railway networks.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/7">As the Minister is aware, some direct effects of global warming and consequential climate change have already been experienced around the globe, most recently on the home front in Cumbria. Carlisle was recently devastated by 100 mph winds and extreme flooding. In such an unlikely place as Florida, home of Disneyland and Mickey Mouse, inhabitants witnessed the awful, frightening and confusing reality of climate change when preparing for their fourth hurricane of the season. They experienced that traumatic event at the same time as the United States Congress debated and voted down some moderate and modest amendments to alter America's stance on the problem of climate change and global warming. That represents a lesson for all politicians at home and abroad, and particularly those in the United States Congress and Senate, who on that occasion let their people down badly, having been fooled, or should I say blinded, by misinformation readily supplied to them by industrial and commercial interests.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/8">Unsurprisingly, and no doubt because of Congress and Senate inaction at that time and since, it is the unlikely allies of corporate USA who are now calling for change. American companies large and small suddenly realise that they are trapped inside an environment creaking on its very foundations because of what modernisation and a lack of Government action have created&mdash;an environment with a polluted atmosphere that suicidally destroys its own safety by continuously depleting for naked profit whatever rain forests remain. It is a world whose very future is put at risk by the short-term combination of industrial power and financial greed, set against people's needs, welfare and aspirations.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/9">How do we combat the problem? Can we discover another way? Is choice dead? Can we trust business, or is it yet again performing corporate tricks to expand or just to keep its market share? Unfortunately, the truth is not as simple as that, as it is not only Government or business who are to blame, but all of us. Due to our selfish appetites, energy consumption is at its highest ever level and rising, with the numbers of individual electrical devices dramatically increasing year on year. Walkmans, iPods, mobile phones, and digital radios and TVs are standard tools for modern living.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/10">It is not just electronic gadgetry but our style of living that is making things worse. The worst example is that, while the use of public transport world wide diminishes, 26 per cent. of all harmful carbon emissions are linked to the cars we drive. If that were not enough, because of our insatiable appetite for fresh, &quot;exotic&quot; and even ordinary &quot;out of season&quot; food, we are responsible for flying such nutrients in the least fuel-efficient way. Planes produce 19 times the greenhouse gas emissions of trains and 190 times that of ships. We conveniently erase from our intellect the simple fact that it takes 66 calories of fuel to airfreight one calorie of carrot or no calories of orchid to London from South Africa or Singapore. Selfishly and stupidly, we daily develop collective economic amnesia and instead consider the immediate short-termism of taste, price and availability.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/11">Not purchasing modern energy eaters, using public transport more and altering our eating habits are only some of the many ingredients necessary for a solution. Things have already gone too far for the tempering of lifestyles alone to be the leading factor in achieving the necessary change. The urgent development of a series of concise, clear and coherent choices, which are understood and supported by everybody, is also required. That said, I accept, and suspect that the Minister will agree, that it will not be easy for politicians or Governments, but then again representation and responsibility rarely are.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/12">As I stated earlier, being positive is vital. We must not express the view that there are no solutions. Answers are there. It is simply a matter of best managing the present while trying to find them. To that end, we should all try to keep a clear head and to accept the scale of the problems connected with global warming, while at the same time not losing sight of the facts. For example, the natural cycling of carbon in the natural environment is 30 times greater than that released by human activities, and nature's main tool&mdash;plant life&mdash;is the most efficient, continuously converting solar energy into chemical energy and then releasing it back as oxygen into our atmosphere. Even if atmospheric particulate pollution is taken into account&mdash;it was recently identified as being responsible for the strange phenomenon of global dimming&mdash;heat from the sun, which touches our planet, is 15,000 times greater than the world's annual use of fossil burn and nuclear energy.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/13">Solutions may be found in any of those avenues of knowledge. In the meantime, a number of practical ways exist to help to ease the current situation. For example, using the knowledge outlined, we should, at the very least, consider why we are today producing more energy than we use and why we fail to conserve as well as we should. We should also establish whether it can be stored safely for longer periods and examine the extent to which alternative methods of creating it can play a role in future energy use and production.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/14">Before examining such questions, it is necessary to consider some of the many different energy options that are currently available, including solar energy, radiant energy from thermonuclear reaction, mechanical energy produced by machines, potential energy from water, chemical energy from molecule reaction, incineration, electrical energy produced by charged atoms, nuclear energy from the splitting of atoms and thermal energy from heated matter.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/15">In our modern environment, most of those energy converters are in operation every day, lighting, heating or cooling our homes and buildings, propelling vehicles and helping mankind to survive and to communicate. Mankind's problem is the maintenance of such energy supplies safely, efficiently and in sufficient quantity. There lies the nub.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/16">At present, most of the available energy production capable of providing the required scale of power either has low efficiency and causes pollution or has other faults such as high costs and safety worries. Improving the efficiency of such energy converters will help, but it will not solve our problems completely; it will merely move them on. For example, obliging car manufacturers to fit vehicles with catalysts substantially decreases carbon monoxide and nitrogen oxide in the environment, but the subsequent release of carbon dioxide, which is a greenhouse gas, affects the environment on a larger scale in the consequential greenhouse effect and what follows is global warming.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/17">At the heart of any solutions, whether in the short term or otherwise, lies the reality that the environment and energy sectors cannot be separated because they are intrinsically linked. Nowhere is that seen more starkly than in the coal sector, which produces more of the world's electrical power than is produced collectively from oil and gas&mdash;one third of our power in the United Kingdom, half of the power in Germany and the USA and, frighteningly, three quarters of the power in China.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/18">Contrary to its image, the reality is that that fossil fuel need not be as filthy a fuel as currently portrayed. Modern combustion techniques can both clean emissions and use less coal to reach energy production targets. Indeed, fluidised bed combustion&mdash;burning coal on a bed of particulates suspended in flowing air&mdash;can capture most emissions. Similarly, pulverised coal used with high temperature burn techniques can greatly increase productivity, while coal burnt with oxygen rather than air can be gassified and transferred to power gas turbines with surplus heat to supply conventional steam heating.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/19">Those cleaner methods are relevant to any solution to global warming, especially when the likely scale of future use of coal by countries such as China and India is considered. At present, such countries are relatively undeveloped compared with other first world nations, but they are beginning to achieve rapid periods of growth for their billions of citizens.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/20">The choice of oil and gas as Earth's long-term alternative fuels is not a realistic option. That will be starkly exposed to United Kingdom citizens next year, when, 40 years after the discovery of gas in the North sea, Britain will become a net importer of gas.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/21">The truth, as I am sure that the Minister will agree, is that today's large-scale world reserves of both oil and gas are estimated, based on current levels, to be sufficient only for the next 40 to 50 years. Many believe those predictions to be generous, particularly as they conservatively give major credit to as yet non-negotiated, non-developed conservation measures. Moreover, they take little account of the fact that such gains would be more than offset by rapid population, production and service growth. What is more, with such finite reserves, it is only a matter of time before huge price hikes occur, especially once fierce competition for them develops in the chemical, agricultural and other sectors. In such circumstances, it is almost certain that oil and gas will no longer be readily available as a primary energy production source, simply because of market economics. In time, that is also likely to be the case with related by-products, such as liquefied petroleum.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/22">I turn to the question of nuclear energy. In addition to the safety worries connected with that source of energy, together with its long-term, ongoing cost, there is, again, a problem with the availability of scarce chemicals. In that case, the chemical concerned is uranium 235, a rare isotope found only in certain types of ore. Based on present usage rates, its estimated lifespan is also less than 100 years. That factor, for the time being, bursts the bubble of the long-term availability of nuclear energy, as expounded by the pro-nuclear lobby.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/23">I accept that there are ongoing research programmes into ways of producing huge quantities of energy from fusion. I am advised, however, that, as yet, the scientific community is unsure about whether that is, or will be, safely possible.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/24">Therefore, there remain only two areas in which solutions might be found to provide sufficient energy production for the future. The first is renewables&mdash;the use of energy from biomass, geothermal hydropower, solar, wind and tidal flows. The second is the as yet undeveloped hybrid technologies such as methane hydrate extraction, although leading scientists predict that there will not be much immediate practical progress in that area for some time to come.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/25">As the Minister will be aware, our planet has an abundance of natural resources capable of generating energy via the use of renewable sources&mdash;wind, hydro, co-firing biomass schemes, tidal technologies and incineration. However, the reality is that, as we attempt to drive forwards a low-carbon economy, the current energy production technologies in those areas dictate that those sectors are not collectively capable of delivering the majority of our energy needs. The role of those sources will remain, for the foreseeable future, as a secondary, although important, part of a balanced, diverse energy mix.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/26">Cleaner energy is vital to any strategy that aims to combat global warming, and should be included, especially when one realises the amount of electricity that even comparatively small hydropower stations, offshore wind farms and co-firing biomass plants can contribute. Solar power, influenced especially by architectural and spatial planning processes, can also be an important contributor, as can tidal flow technologies.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/27">Last but not least, the vexed question of waste incineration offers a great deal, especially in relation to recycling and the problems of generations of landfilled waste, which is leaching gases into the atmosphere. However, before large-scale development of that sector can take place, there will have to be major development of purification processes.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/28">Based on such knowledge, we can clearly identify the problems facing mankind. First, the reality is that global warming is occurring due to human activities. Secondly, most current sources of energy are likely to be finite. Thirdly, the world's biggest polluters seem intent on not pursuing a collective approach and, fourthly, the Kyoto protocol represents only one small step in the right direction.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/29">As I have indicated, many as yet undeveloped hybrid technologies and structural theories are currently in their early experimental and/or theoretical stages&mdash;there are far too many of them to discuss today. However, even those in today's scientific community who are most optimistic are generally of the opinion that any major energy discovery&mdash;enough to take the place of what we are running out of at present&mdash;is too far ahead for future generations to rely on. We therefore have no alternative. We must discover new sources while at the same time conserving present reserves and using them in a way that will not worsen the damage that has already been done.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/30">Such aims lay at the heart of the IPCC process, so the question must be asked as to whether the latest conference of the parties, which was held in Buenos Aires in December, was a success. Being honest, I must admit that it represented a mere tap dance on the international dance floor rather than the vigorous south American tango for which all of us attending had hoped. Neither my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs nor the Minister for the Environment and Agri-environment should find any personal criticism in what I am saying. I know how hard they worked to get an agreement. For instance, both of them were involved in achieving agreement to allow the negotiations to continue. Compromises were reached only after lengthy discussions&mdash;36 hours after the conference had finished and following two all-night negotiating sessions.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/31">Of course, particularly troublesome were the representatives of the United States and several major oil-producing nations, which tried extremely hard to scupper progress. That factor bodes ill for the international community, as it flies in the face of President Bush's promises in 2001. He said that, although America was withdrawing from the Kyoto protocol, he personally would not obstruct other countries trying to reach agreements. Clearly, the United States has been jolted by its miscalculation of global energy economics and, in particular, by Russia's decision to ratify. Because of that, it has decided actively to adopt a significantly different and more aggressive strategy that is geared mainly to the sabotage of any further development of international measures, at least until such time as it can guarantee its vast energy needs.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/32">I do not make such criticism lightly. Examples of the USA's attitude at the conference of the parties were many. For instance, Chairman Raul Estrada Oyuela's proposals to hold a series of meetings in the next year to prepare the ground for talks were vigorously opposed at every turn by the USA contingent, which argued that there could be only one meeting and that no ideas that examined future scenarios should be tabled at such a conference. It even objected to a mention in the proposed conference description of the need to tackle global warming and argued instead for the phrase &quot;adapting to it&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/33">Even more stark and very worrying indeed was the delegation's support for the demand from Saudi Arabia that oil-producing nations should receive billions of dollars of compensation from the rest of the world if they sold less oil. That was an astonishing proposal, especially when one recalls the &quot;good faith&quot; purpose contained in the Kyoto protocol agreement by first world nations and the substances that have been found to be largely responsible for the need for such a protocol. Those of us who care about the environment know about the destruction, poverty, famine, death and misery that have been caused by global warming and climate change, the worst effects of which are felt most by those least able to cope with them. I mentioned some of those earlier. I was pleased that the Secretary of State gave assurances last week during Environment questions that the Government had no truck with deals such as that which I have just described.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/34">Thankfully, agreement was eventually reached in Argentina to hold the next meeting in May 2005. It will give more sensibly minded politicians another chance to work towards finding a global solution.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/35">In conclusion, I congratulate the Government and the Minister on the work that they are doing to deliver our commitments&mdash;and more&mdash;on Kyoto, in particular the decision to launch an extensive and open consultation on the nation's climate change programme and to build towards the Government's goal of reducing carbon dioxide emissions by 20 per cent. below 1990 levels by 2010. I also congratulate them on their support for the Carbon Trust, their agreement to give financial and other support to environmental improvements in our society and their encouragement of the EU emissions trading scheme, which is an important step towards a co-ordinated approach to tackling climate change. I hope that it will one day be extended beyond the 45 per cent. of industry that it currently covers and will move from being an EU-only scheme to a global one. I say that because it is important that we bring other industrial sectors into the emissions trading scheme, in particular the transport sector.</p>
	<p pid=".196.1/36">I also welcome the Government's leadership in Europe in pressing to include aviation emissions in the scheme from 2008, as I welcomed the UK aviation industry's pressure on all airports and airlines across the EU to support emissions trading for aircraft emissions. Last but not least, I praise the Prime Minister's own commitment, shown by his decision to put the Kyoto agreement, global warming and consequential climate change at the heart of his chairmanship of the G8.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.203.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.205.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.205.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.207.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.205.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.207.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.205.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.207.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.206.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.208.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.206.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.208.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.206.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.208.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.206.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.208.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.206.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.208.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.206.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.208.5" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.206.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1122" speakername="Elliot Morley" colnum="206"  time="010:15:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050118/halltext/50118h01.htm#50118h01_spnew14">
	<p pid=".206.5/1">I want to make it absolutely clear that the decision on targets has not yet been taken. The discussion in the committee of officials was not about determining a target, but about the future in relation to agreement within the Environment Council, which will have take place in the spring. It is not removing the figures; it is part of a process, a matter of when we put in the figures and what the figures are. In relation to scientific assessment of the 2&deg;, the figure may be more than 50 per cent.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.206.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.208.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.207.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.209.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.207.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.209.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.207.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.209.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.207.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1018" speakername="Robert Key" colnum="207"  time="010:32:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050118/halltext/50118h01.htm#50118h01_spnew18">
	<p pid=".207.2/1">This Government have spent eight years pandering to popular prejudice and patronising the public. The more they have established citizens' juries, focus groups, stakeholder forums or consensus conferences, the more we have seen the public disengaging from the real processes of democratic policies. The Government may think that that is participative democracy, but it has allowed them to say one thing and do another. Therefore, I am grateful to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1108" name="Alan Meale">the hon. Member for Mansfield (Mr. Meale)</phrase> for his tour d'horizon, which gives us the opportunity to look both at the record and to the future.</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/2">Speaking of saying one thing and doing another, what the Minister has just told <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/710" name="Norman Baker">the hon. Member for Lewes (Norman Baker)</phrase> will not wash. It is as clear as mud. Although the Minister said that the Government were not removing the figures, that is precisely what they were doing. When they sought to delete from the draft spring 2005 European Council conclusions 21 words that would secretly change policy on global warming and climate change&mdash;in the UK and throughout the EU&mdash;they were tampering with 21 words that could literally change the world. I hope the Minister will explain to an astonished world what on earth the Government were up to in Brussels. The explanation that he has given so far is completely inadequate.</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/3">Labour has been all talk on the environment. The Prime Minister personally committed himself and his Government to leading the march towards a more sustainable world. In the 1997 Labour election manifesto, he promised to go beyond the Kyoto commitment of a 12.5 per cent. reduction in greenhouse gas emissions and set a target of a 20 per cent. reduction in CO <sub>2</sub> emissions by 2010. A further goal was set: a 60 per cent. reduction in CO <sub>2</sub> emissions by 2050. In 2004, the Prime Minister reaffirmed his commitment to</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/4" class="indent">&quot;the single most important issue that we face as a global community&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/5">However, in December 2004, the Government admitted that, based on current policies alone, the UK will not achieve the 20 per cent. reduction target by 2010. Instead, current policies are likely to lead to a reduction of around 14 per cent.</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/6">Therefore, since coming to power in 1997, Labour has failed to deliver any measurable reduction in carbon emissions. In fact emissions rose in four of the first six years that Labour was in power. Interestingly, Conservative policies achieved a 7.3 per cent. reduction between 1990 and 1997. Carbon emissions in the transport and household sectors, which account for around 40 per cent. of the UK's emissions, are expected to grow.</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/7">Labour has let the country down on sustainable development. Even the green movement&mdash;at least 5   million citizens in the United Kingdom&mdash;has now declared war on the Government. The executive director of Greenpeace, Stephen Tindale, declared in November:</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/8" class="indent">&quot;So far Blair's record on climate change is almost entirely a record of fine words and no action.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/9">The Government have failed to resolve the energy crisis resulting from the decline of indigenous energy supplies and increasing reliance on imported gas. Energy production from coal fired power stations has increased since 2000 and now represents about one third of electricity production. Between 1997 and 2000, Labour blocked the construction of 15 gas-fired stations, which would have cut CO <sub>2</sub> emissions by 5.5   million tonnes a year.</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/10">The Government have also failed to deliver on renewable energy. They set a target for 10 per cent. of overall energy use to be renewable by 2010, but it now stands at 3 per cent. They have put all their eggs in the wind farms basket and alienated many local communities, which have been bypassed in the planning process. They have neglected to stimulate the growth of other renewable technologies, such as tidal and wave power, in which Britain should have an obvious natural advantage. Even the Prime Minister revealed his own nimby instincts when he opposed a wind farm in Sedgefield.</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/11">Labour has failed the combined heat and power industry miserably. The target of producing 5 GW of energy by 2000, which was set by the Conservative Government in 1993, has only just been reached. Combined heat and power output fell between 2000 and 2003, and 64 CHP plants have been mothballed.</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/12">The Government have broken their pledge to assist the most vulnerable in eliminating the blight of fuel poverty. They have even reduced insulation standards in social housing, causing extra CO <sub>2</sub> emissions and leaving nearly 2 million people in cold homes and fuel poverty.</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/13">The Government have piled unnecessary tax burdens and regulations on business, while failing to provide incentives to improve environmental performance. According to the CBI, environmental regulation costs business &pound;4 billion a year in compliance. The CBI has also criticised too much environmental regulation as being</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/14" class="indent">&quot;badly designed and poorly implemented.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/15">The Government have alienated the business community by failing to provide certainty and a secure framework of targets and objectives for long-term investment. The business community does not deny that it has a role to play but, if the targets and objectives are not clear, it is bad for everybody. Industry has looked for transparency, long-term certainty and fairness but has suffered from delay, vacillation, incoherence and short-termism.</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/16">The Government's notion of a green transport strategy is also called into question, because it seems to consist of trying to tax people out of their cars. Fiscal support for alternative fuels and cleaner cars has been so limited that the greenest fuels and cars still have less than 0.2 per cent. of their respective markets. Meanwhile, aviation emissions have risen by 85 per cent. since 1990 and are set to double again by 2020.</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/17">The Prime Minister has committed his Government and himself personally to lead the march towards a more sustainable world. He played a leading part at the United Nations Rio plus 5 conference in 1997, which led to the Kyoto agreement, and again at the world summit on sustainable development in 2002. Last April, he reaffirmed his commitment to, in his own words,</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/18" class="indent">&quot;the single most important issue that we face as a global community&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/19">In a speech on climate change last September, he said that timely action to cut carbon dioxide emissions was essential to &quot;avert disaster.&quot; During the speech, he cited the Royal Commission on Environmental Pollution's report and the need to reduce emissions by 60 per cent. by 2050, and stated:</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/20" class="indent">&quot;We are committed to this change.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/21">However, the latest prediction from the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs is for a reduction of about 14 per cent. in CO <sub>2</sub> emissions by 2010 on the basis of current policies. According to DEFRA's estimated emissions and removals of greenhouses gases on an IPCC basis, carbon emissions have risen for four years out of Labour's six years in power from 1997 to 2003, and emissions are 100,000 tonnes of carbon higher for the latest period for which figures are available than when Labour came to power. That is largely due to the continuing increase in the use of coal for electricity generation. Last February, the Government revealed that carbon dioxide levels had jumped by 1.5 per cent. over the previous year.</p>
	<p pid=".207.2/22">Then we have seen the spectacle of a feud between DEFRA and the Department of Trade and Industry, involving the intervention of the Prime Minister, which has caused an unnecessary delay in the submission of our national allocation plan for the European emissions trading scheme, which started on <phrase class="date" code="2005-01-01">1 January 2005</phrase>. A new plan was submitted requesting a more generous allowance in October 2004, but then the Prime Minister stepped in on the side of the DTI, which argued for a more generous base allocation. Meanwhile, the Commission has approved allocations for 9,108   installations in 21 member states, representing 4.6   billion tonnes of carbon dioxide over the period 2005&ndash;07. The Government have thus subjected business to delay and uncertainty. Will the Minister please explain to us what on earth they are up to in this row between DEFRA and the DTI over the national allocation plan?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.210.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.212.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.210.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.212.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.210.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1018" speakername="Robert Key" colnum="210"  time="010:32:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050118/halltext/50118h01.htm#50118h01_spnew20">
	<p pid=".210.1/1">Yes. We want to know what the Government's position is. <i>[Laughter.] </i>If the hon. Gentleman will listen for a moment, he will understand where we are coming from.</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/2">On <phrase class="date" code="2005-01-16">16 January</phrase>, <i>The Observer</i> revealed that the Government were secretly trying to have key commitments to long-term targets deleted from European documents. We have discussed those already. There is no doubt&mdash;I have the document in my hand&mdash;that the Government sought to delete the words:</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/3" class="indent">&quot;developed countries will need to reduce their aggregated greenhouse gas emissions by up to 60&ndash;80 per cent. by 2050 compared to 1990 levels&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/4">For the Minister to say &quot;It is not removing the figures&quot;, which were his exact words, is frankly absurd. Will he take this opportunity to own up to that blunder and stop trying to pretend that Greenpeace knew all along exactly what the Government were doing and understood the Government's tactics? He must do better than that.</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/5">On <phrase class="date" code="2004-09-14">14 September 2004</phrase>, the Prime Minister made a keynote speech on climate change, in which he reiterated that this was</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/6" class="indent">&quot;the world's greatest environmental challenge&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/7">and said that it would be a &quot;top priority&quot; for Britain's presidency of the G8. He highlighted the three key parts of the Government's G8 strategy:</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/8" class="indent">&quot;First, I want to secure an agreement as to the basic science on climate change and the threat it poses. Such an agreement would be new and provide the foundation for further action.</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/9" class="indent">Second, agreement on a process to speed up the science, technology, and other measures necessary to meet the threat.</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/10" class="indent">Third, while the eight G8 countries account for around 50 per cent. of global greenhouse gas emissions, it is vital that we also engage with other countries with growing energy needs&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/11">So say all of us. However, it is notable that climate change or global warming did not feature in the Prime Minister's 2004 Labour party conference speech, and domestic measures to tackle this global problem did not form any part of his 10 priorities for a third term of Labour Government.</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/12">The Minister has implied that he did not think there was much in my comment about the environmental groups declaring war on the Government. That is certainly not true of Greenpeace, because Mr. Tindale said in <i>The   Independent </i>in November 2004 that Mr.   Blair's reheated, tub-thumping speeches on the world stage were   undermined by his failed record in Britain. Tony   Juniper, executive director of Friends of the Earth, pointed out that there was a gaping gap between the Prime Minister's rhetoric and leadership on the world stage and his record in the UK:</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/13" class="indent">&quot;The leadership position of this country is jeopardised by the position at home.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/14">He went on:</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/15" class="indent">&quot;The credibility of this country on climate change is essentially derived from the policy choices taken by the Conservatives in the 1980s when they decided to shift from coal to gas generation&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/16">Charles Secrett, former head of Friends of the Earth, who now heads Active Citizens Transform, said that Mr. Blair was</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/17" class="indent">&quot;all talk and no action&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/18">He went on to say:</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/19" class="indent">&quot;Blair thinks he can get away with boosting his green credentials by making a big speech every year on climate change. It's always about the grand scenario and when it comes to putting his own house in order it is always business as usual.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/20">I pay tribute to the Government's chief scientific adviser, Professor Sir David King, who will be retiring far too soon for our liking. In a recent interview, he talked about the imperatives for action and warned that measurements of atmospheric CO <sub>2</sub> taken at the Mauna Loa observatory in Hawaii and published earlier this year showed that, while carbon levels had increased in recent years by an average of 1.5 parts per million annually, in 2002&ndash;03, the increase was more than 2 parts per million. Levels have risen so much that, according to Sir David:</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/21" class="indent">&quot;This is taking us up into relatively dangerous levels of CO <sub>2</sub> for our planet.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/22">Anyone who is sceptical about the concept of climate change should listen to Sir David King. They do not need to look further than the Thames barrier. It was built to protect London from catastrophic floods and was used six times a year, not once every three to five years as planned. Sir David said:</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/23" class="indent">&quot;It's a damned good thing we put it up. A flood would knock out the City of London and cost about &pound;30bn.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/24">Quite so.</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/25">What would we do instead? Where are we coming from on this? We believe fundamentally in conservation of the past and preservation for the future. We have always supported the dual concepts of citizenship and duty as related to environmental stewardship and protection of the environment and countryside. Environmental goods and services are a common advantage and present generations should save and enhance such benefits for the good and security of future ones.</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/26">Conservatives do not see environmental protection and economic growth as mutually incompatible. We believe that market mechanisms can achieve sustainable development. We believe that excessive regulation may be bad for business but that targeted taxation and fiscal measures that provide industry with a long-term framework for investment are more likely to deliver environmental benefits. We support the proximity principle, which encourages localised decision making and local procurement. Local sustainable communities require and deserve more local empowerment and more local autonomy in decision making, such as over planning decisions.</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/27">We uphold the polluter pays principle. We acknowledge that pollution costs and hence we support life cycle costing&mdash;the internalisation of environmental costs in design, production, construction and operation. If products included the cost of pollution in their production, the marginal social cost would be higher. Thus, if all goods and services had to internalise their external environmental costs, only those most environmentally sensitive should succeed within the free marketplace. We would devise a policy framework to incentivise responsible consumption or the purchasing of environmental goods rather than environmental bads. The consumer should be able to make environmentally sensitive choices. Therefore, we support clear and coherent labelling of products to indicate the environmental consequences of design, production and distribution.</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/28">Conservatives are fully committed to the Kyoto process and the 2050 target for a 60 per cent. reduction in carbon emissions. We will pursue policies in government to achieve a 21st century world of resource efficiency and sustainable consumption in order to achieve climate stability.</p>
	<p pid=".210.1/29">Any Government must have the courage to consider all the options. They must look at scientific evidence, not scaremongering, for their policies. They cannot afford to resort to easy attention-grabbing fixes. To deal with climate change, Britain must become a low-carbon economy. It is the only option and we are committed to achieving that goal.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.212.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.214.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.214.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.216.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.214.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.216.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.216.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.218.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.216.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.218.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.218.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.220.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.218.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1122" speakername="Elliot Morley" speakeroffice="The Minister for the Environment and Agri-environment"  colnum="218"  time="010:59:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050118/halltext/50118h02.htm#50118h02_spmin0">
	<p pid=".218.0/1">I want to make it clear that no decision has been taken on Thames tideway, so it is quite wrong to say that it has been abandoned.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.219.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.221.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.219.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/773" speakername="Vincent Cable" colnum="219"  time="010:59:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050118/halltext/50118h02.htm#50118h02_spnew1">
	<p pid=".219.0/1">I hope that the Minister is right. I was only reading from a House of Commons Library note, which states that</p>
	<p pid=".219.0/2" class="indent">&quot;particular concerns have been raised about the abandonment of the Thames Tideway Project.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".219.0/3">If that is not the case, I am delighted to hear it, and I am sure that the residents will be, too.</p>
	<p pid=".219.0/4">I will conclude by posing a series of questions to the Minister that arise out of the background that I have described. First, the Department has laid a good deal of store by the ability of local councils&mdash;mainly Hounslow, but to some extent Richmond&mdash;to issue abatement notices against the water company when odour pollution is a nuisance, and now the way has been cleared for action to be taken. Is the Minister satisfied that the sanctions available through that route are on a scale that is appropriate to the problem? We are dealing with billion-pound companies and rather nominal fines under environmental legislation. I simply ask him whether he is satisfied that the legislation is robust enough to deal with a problem of this kind.</p>
	<p pid=".219.0/5">The second point is that DEFRA has now undertaken a helpful exercise: a code of practice. There is a lot of technical detail that I do not understand, but clearly a great deal of work has gone into it with the industry and the regulators. That is all welcome. How does the Minister see the code of practice acquiring greater statutory force? I know that he has been giving consideration to how it can be included in the Clean Neighbourhoods and Environment Bill, which is passing through the House. Certain aspects of the code of practice, particularly relating to mosquito nuisance, could be included in the Bill, and that is planned.</p>
	<p pid=".219.0/6">Why, though, is it not possible to include odour nuisance in that framework legislation? My colleagues and I strongly support it, and it would seem to be an appropriate vehicle. I know that there are difficulties with objective measures in relation to smell&mdash;that is somewhat more difficult than in relation to noise&mdash;but given that a great deal of effort has gone into producing quantitative measures, it does not seem totally impossible that the code of practice could acquire statutory force. I invite the Minister to give me some hope that that might be taken on board in the Standing Committee.</p>
	<p pid=".219.0/7">The third point relates to funding. The Minister has already intervened, so he may be able to give me some reassurance. I am concerned that even if it was generally agreed that major investment was required, it seems that there could be some difficulties in funding the investment stream required to make things happen. I invite him to tell me whether he believes, after the Ofwat determination, that those needs can be met.</p>
	<p pid=".219.0/8">The fourth point relates to independent monitoring. It is clearly crucial to the maintenance of high environmental standards that there should be a genuinely independent assessment of the ability of Thames Water, and other utilities in other parts of the country, to meet their capacity requirements. At the moment, as I understand it, the Environment Agency is totally dependent on the company to produce estimates of flows in and out of the works, so there is no basis for independent monitoring of its performance. Perhaps the Minister can tell me whether any thought has been given to strengthening the element of independence.</p>
	<p pid=".219.0/9">My final point is perhaps offbeat. On Saturday, I attended the annual conference of the National Association of Plumbing Teachers at my local tertiary college, the high-level Richmond upon Thames technical college, which does excellent work on trades and is a centre of excellence for plumbing teachers. I was questioned by some of the country's leading authorities on plumbing who said that a major crisis is emerging&mdash;I have no basis on which to judge whether this is a technically sensible point&mdash;as a result of large-scale installation of condensing boilers. The point was made that condensing boilers issue about 2 litres of acid into the sewerage system every hour. A typical sewerage works with 10,000 condensing boilers in its vicinity could probably generate 140 million litres of acid every year. Even if diluted substantially, that could, and is beginning to have, a damaging effect on the bacteriological processes necessary for the treatment of sewage. The Minister may be unfamiliar with that problem, as I was when it was put to me. Could his technical advisers consider whether the problem is real and whether any action has been taken?</p>
	<p pid=".219.0/10">It is clear that there is greater awareness now of the problems, particularly that of odour, generated by Mogden and other sewerage works. A substantial momentum has built up for action. I would like some reassurance from the Minister on my specific points about enforcement, providing a statutory basis for the code of conduct and ensuring that there is adequate investment to ensure that improvements take place.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.220.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.222.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.220.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1122" speakername="Elliot Morley" speakeroffice="The Minister for the Environment and Agri-environment"  colnum="220"  time="011:17:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050118/halltext/50118h02.htm#50118h02_spmin1">
	<p pid=".220.0/1">I congratulate the hon. Gentleman on securing this debate and on the detailed and measured way in which he made important points that are of concern to local residents. As he rightly said, my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1012" name="Ann Keen">the Member for Brentford and Isleworth (Ann Keen)</phrase> has also been active on the issue and arranged for my noble Friend Lord Whitty to visit the sewerage works to see for himself and to talk to Thames Water about some of the issues.</p>
	<p pid=".220.0/2">Some of the points raised by the hon. Gentleman are right, including that about insects. We are dealing with that matter in the Clean Neighbourhoods and Environment Bill, which will provide the power to deal with issues such as mosquito nuisance, although such issues may not currently exist.</p>
	<p pid=".220.0/3">The hon. Gentleman asked about making the code statutory. As he rightly said&mdash;I shall touch on this in more detail in a moment&mdash;it has been established in court that local authorities can apply abatement notices in relation to odours, so regulation is in place. The problem with a statutory code for smell nuisance touches on issues that he recognised; how can a subjective test be devised?</p>
	<p pid=".220.0/4">The hon. Gentleman also mentioned independent monitoring. It is true that the Environment Agency relies on the figures provided by companies on matters such as flows. However, those figures comprise part of their investment programmes in relation to the size capacity of treatment plants, and their business plans are subject to careful scrutiny by Ofwat, as he knows. There is an element of independent assessment.</p>
	<p pid=".220.0/5">The hon. Gentleman also referred to storm overflows and I should like to deal with that straight away because I do not want any misunderstanding about the Thames tideway. Mogden is one of four major treatment works that are currently unable to deal with storm flows, and that leads to a discharge from the treatment plants into the River Thames. I am pleased to assure the hon. Gentleman that, with the business plans that Thames Water put to Ofwat, there has been approval for a considerable investment in the upgrade of those treatment works, including Mogden, to enable them to cope better with storm flows. That in itself should considerably improve the River Thames.</p>
	<p pid=".220.0/6">The working group examining the Thames tideway has been considering whether there are quicker and potentially cheaper ways of dealing with combined sewage overflows in the long term. In the end, there may not be and, in the final analysis, the tideway scheme may be the best option. I do not rule that out. I am waiting for the group's report at the end of this month or the beginning of next month, and we will make an evaluation based on it. I want to see rapid progress, and that is why I am very pleased about the investment in the four sewage works.</p>
	<p pid=".220.0/7">The Thames tideway project will be five years in development; it will be five years just working it up. It will be at least another decade in construction. It is a long-term scheme that will cost billions of pounds. We must consider that option. I do not want the hon. Gentleman to think that the scheme has been abandoned, because it has not. We are just waiting for that report.</p>
	<p pid=".220.0/8">The hon. Gentleman will understand that the prime responsibility for tackling odour problems rests with the water company; in this case, Thames Water. I do not know the history of the site, but I wonder what was there first; the treatment plant or housing. If housing was built there, I wonder what consideration the planning authority gave to those issues. The hon. Gentleman knows the history better than me. Again, I can provide him with some assurance, because the original determination by Ofwat allowed Thames Water &pound;10.8   million for odour works, mainly at Mogden where, it is recognised, there is a major problem. That would have covered the inlet works in the first determination. The final determination has almost quadrupled that allocation to &pound;42.8 million. In addition to the inlet works, that will allow Thames Water to cover storm tanks and some of the sewage tanks. A considerable amount of money is available. The work programme is for Thames Water to decide, but, based on the business plan that the company put forward, Ofwat has made a considerable amount of money available for the approved programme.</p>
	<p pid=".220.0/9">The hon. Gentleman is right to say that we need an effective regulatory scheme. There must be a stick and a carrot. The stick is regulation and enforcement, including fines on occasions, and reasonable standards and real action to deal with complaints, which is the job of local authorities. The carrot is ensuring that the company is in a position to fund its operations. That is a matter for Ofwat.</p>
	<p pid=".220.0/10">The legal position has been clarified by court judgments on odour. The High Court judgment confirmed that odours from sewage treatment works can be considered a statutory nuisance within the terms of the Environmental Protection Act 1990. As a consequence, local authorities have a duty to investigate such problems, and they have the corresponding enforcement powers. I understand that in this case the local authority has used its powers to issue abatement notices.</p>
	<p pid=".220.0/11">The Government published on <phrase class="date" code="2002-12-23">23 December 2002</phrase> the outcome of our first public consultation on odour, and that is where we developed the policy of supporting the use of a statutory nuisance regime to resolve odour problems at sewage works. We also recognise that local authorities and water companies need a clear idea of what procedures and standards ought to be met under that regime, and we have been working with them to try to clarify the situation. As a result, we launched a new consultation on the draft code of practice and local authority guidance on odour nuisance from sewage treatment works. Responses are invited up to <phrase class="date" code="2005-04-04">4 April 2005</phrase>, and our aim is to implement the code by the summer. At the same time, DEFRA and UK Water Industry Research are collaborating on best practical means guidance that will be aimed primarily at the water industry.</p>
	<p pid=".220.0/12">We recognise that there are obvious local problems with odours from sewage treatment works. Water companies do not have to wait around for the outcome of the consultation and guidance, but should act now. As I said, funds have been made available in respect of the business plans.</p>
	<p pid=".220.0/13">If water companies need to do more at particular sewage works to manage odour problems, it may mean that better management or maintenance is required. We recognise that capital investment is a consideration, but I emphasise to the hon. Gentleman my understanding that the way in which sewage treatment plants are operated also has a bearing on odour. Issues of good practice, good management, good operation and good maintenance are separate from the capital programme. Ofwat rightly has an obligation to scrutinise the business plans in order to ensure good value for money.</p>
	<p pid=".220.0/14">Nationally, companies propose in their final business plans to spend more than &pound;292 million between 2005 and 2010 to fund works on odour control. Ofwat allowed &pound;96 million for that in the draft version. In the final version, the amount was increased to &pound;134 million, which is a recognition of the representations that Ofwat received, including those of the hon. Gentleman and my hon. Friend the Member for Brentford and Isleworth. Considerable progress is being made on the matter, and we expect work to be carried out during the next five years. I very much hope that progress is made on the issues raised by the hon. Gentleman.</p>
	<p pid=".220.0/15">The hon. Gentleman asked whether enforcement was adequate, given the steps that can be taken. Ofwat will lend weight to the proposed code of practice by not allowing the cost of any fines that might be incurred by water companies as a result of prosecution under odour nuisance regulations to be passed on to customers. The company will have to pay for any fines directly out of its profits and not pass them on in consumer bills. I make that point to the hon. Gentleman, as that is an important assurance.</p>
	<p pid=".220.0/16">Fines of up to &pound;20,000 may be levied for such nuisances, but we should not forget that all water companies&mdash;Thames is no exception&mdash;take very seriously their image, environmental commitments and customer relations. They do not want to be seen as being in breach of any of the regulations, whether on odour, pollution or discharges, and they spend a great deal of time on ensuring that they have the mechanisms and management in place to deal with such matters.</p>
	<p pid=".220.0/17">As I said, there is also the issue of capital investment. I hope that I have assured the hon. Gentleman that significant capital investment has been allowed for in the current price review. On enforcement, there are court judgments, and DEFRA is finishing its consultation on the code of practice, which will help people who suffer from the problem. It will also help companies, which clearly need some guidance and some certainty as to how they should approach the matter. Those are important issues, and I am optimistic that the hon. Gentleman will see considerable progress, which will be of benefit to his constituents.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.223.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.225.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.224.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.226.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.224.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.226.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.224.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.226.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.224.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.226.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.224.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/925" speakername="Jane Griffiths" colnum="224"  time="015:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050118/halltext/50118h03.htm#50118h03_spnew2">
	<p pid=".224.3/1">Thank you, Mr. Deputy Speaker.</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/2">My constituent reported that his daughter had led him to warn the Environment Agency of pollution to the River Loddon at the bottom of his garden. He stated:</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/3" class="indent">&quot;My daughter was at the bottom of the garden on Wednesday evening and she noticed a terrible smell and a substance floating on top of the river. It looked like oil and smelled of petrol. With our neighbours we called the Environment Agency and people came out to remove the swans. I am sure if they hadn't been taken out they would have died. We have been feeding the family of swans since they were very small. There is a mum and a dad and seven cygnets.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/4">As an aside, I am not a fan of swans. They cannot break a man's arm, as reputed, but they are nasty, fascist birds, and I do not like them.</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/5">Some of the pollution reached nearby Dinton Pastures, and a spokesperson for the country park said that staff there smelled the oil and contacted the Environment Agency. So far, wildlife has not been badly affected. A spokeswoman for the agency stated:</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/6" class="indent">&quot;There are rainbow colours on top of the water which means that the oil there is minimal. The main problems are aesthetic, it doesn't look or smell nice. But in large quantities oil can be toxic so we advise the public to be aware of what they put in the water.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/7">The leak is believed to have come from a school via a surface water drain. That report was not from the national media, all of which beat a path to the door of my constituent, but from the local <i>Reading Evening Post.</i> It comprised the sole report of the incident.</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/8">The following are not my words but those of the Environment Agency in its February 2004 position statement on oil pollution of inland waters:</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/9" class="indent">&quot;Oil and fuels are the most frequently reported type of pollutant of inland waters in England and Wales.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/10">Oil is a persistent and toxic pollutant. Agency figures show that there are more than 5,000 oil spill incidents a year in England and Wales. Although some of them affect land, the vast majority affect the water environment: rivers, streams and ground water, including sources of drinking water, which can be tainted at very low concentrations, making them unsuitable for use.</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/11">In one example, a root was left in the base of a newly installed oil tank. It punctured the tank, and the oil headed towards a water borehole. The only way to deal with the problem was to drill a borehole into the polluted area and try to pump out more oil than was emptying into the ground. The water borehole at risk provided the water for four or five villages, and there was no other nearby source.</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/12">The effects of oil spillages may be long term. They can and do harm or kill wildfowl, mammals and fish. Of course, oil is carcinogenic to humans. As I indicated, I am aware of spillages that have had damaging effects in particular areas. They have been reported in local newspapers and on local radio.</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/13">The problem is by no means confined to spills from commercial premises. I am happy to say that those have been addressed by measures on agricultural fuel oil storage dating from 1991 and 2001 which set minimum standards for oil storage at industrial, commercial and institutional premises. Ten per cent. of all sites designated as contaminated by local authorities were contaminated as a result of domestic oil spillage, according to the journal <i>Property Matters </i>in March 2003.</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/14">Although it can be hard sometimes to track the exact source of oil pollution because of the diffuse nature of the problem, the Office of the Deputy Prime Minister estimated that between 1995 and 1998 there were</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/15" class="indent">&quot;on average 1,250 substantiated pollution incidents in the domestic and residential sector. However, in 1999 the number of incidents rose significantly to 2,855.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/16">The latest Environment Agency statistics show that the problem persists. The agency believes that the current level of pollution of inland waters by oil is unacceptable and that, according to the position statement on oil pollution of inland waters of February 2004,</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/17" class="indent">&quot;effective steps need to be taken to reduce the number and severity of such incidents.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/18">Oil fired domestic heating has been a growth area. Since 1993&ndash;94 the market for oil-burning appliances has doubled. Oftec, the Oil Firing Technical Association, estimates that 80,000 tanks were sold to the domestic market in Great Britain in 1998, half of them with a capacity in excess of 2,500 litres. The industry estimated that in 1997&mdash;the latest statistic that I have&mdash;the market was growing at about 30 per cent. per annum. The vast majority of oil tank installations are plastic, with the balance being steel. Half of them have a capacity of over 2,500 litres.</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/19">The ODPM has expressed the following concern:</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/20" class="indent">&quot;It is thought that many of these new installations are being constructed by non-specialists and that nearly all of these installations lack satisfactory means of containing escaping oil and detecting and warning of leakage.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/21">That is from of the regulatory impact assessment on part J of the building regulations on combustion appliances and fuel storage systems. However, the problem goes beyond that. Spills sometimes occur during delivery. There is evidence of vandalism being a significant factor. According to Oftec:</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/22" class="indent">&quot;Steel tanks fail, mainly due to age, and plastic tanks split. Across the board manufacturers have reported disfiguration due to rapid filling.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/23">On that basis the condition of an oil tank stands out as a prime candidate for inspection and report during the   forthcoming home condition inspection process. Alternatively, could the tank be inspected at the same time as the householder has their boiler inspected? I would be grateful for the Minister's views on those points.</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/24">There are 1 million domestic oil storage tanks of which only 10 per cent. are bunded. Bunding is the addition of a secondary containment system, a second skin. Oil is five times more likely to be lost from a non-bunded tank, mainly because leaks and overflows from a tank will be contained by a bund. The new Control of Pollution (Oil Storage)(England) Regulations 2002 are welcome as far as they go. Under those, oil tanks must have a secondary containment system with a capacity of at least 110 per cent of the tank's storage capacity.</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/25">There is, however, an exemption from those controls on oil tanks for private dwellings where the storage capacity is 3,500 litres or less; in contrast, they bite on industrial premises where the storage capacity exceeds 200 litres. It stretches belief that an industrial tank containing 201 litres is somehow more hazardous than a domestic tank containing 3,499 litres. I would be grateful if the Minister could explain why the requirement to bund should not be extended to new domestic tanks, at least the larger ones.</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/26">Another part of the answer may lie in professionalising Oftec. Oftec was set up in 1991 as part of the Government's competent persons scheme in a broad and commendable attempt to improve standards in the construction industry. Every Oftec-registered technician must hold a current certificate of competence. Under the building regulations self-certification scheme, Oftec may exempt individuals and companies from the requirement to notify local authorities of work to install oil-fired combustion appliances and oil storage tanks and pipes.</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/27">In 2003, the ODPM undertook an assessment of Oftec's success. At that time&mdash;12 years after its establishment&mdash;Oftec covered around 30 per cent. of all installers, but membership is voluntary. Oftec registration is merely a sign of quality within the industry, not a requirement. The Department noted that 1,600 registrations lapsed in December at the end of the three-year registration. Given the ODPM's express concern about non-specialist installers, I suggest that oil-fired systems should be installed only by properly qualified and competent technicians. A healthy Oftec with an equivalent status to the Council for Registered Gas Installers&mdash;CORGI, as it is known&mdash;and with 100   per cent. coverage of installers is highly desirable. Would the Minister consider making membership of Oftec mandatory for installers and services? Oftec could then play a leading role in professionalising the oil heating installation industry in the pursuit of higher standards and environmental protection. I believe that there is scope to raise training requirements for Oftec registration and for Oftec to assume a greater regulatory and supervisory role.</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/28">Taking effective action against this problem stands to be a net benefit to the economy as well as the environment. It was estimated that the benefits of the oil storage regulations on existing tanks would amount to &pound;250 million, from avoiding clear-up costs, reimbursement to the Environment Agency and the cost of replacing lost fuel, together with between &pound;15 million and &pound;56 million a year from regulating new tanks; and that is from a limited assessment of benefits.</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/29">Let us not forget also the costs to householders and businesses. An oil leak can spread the fumes and smell of the heating oil throughout the house. In one extreme case a house had to be demolished because the oil had got so far into the foundations that it was the only way the problem could be treated. Yet most householders are not aware of the possible problems.</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/30">The United Kingdom is required by European Union directives on dangerous substances and groundwater to prevent pollution of the water environment. That is simply good sense. It is much better for the environment if we prevent pollution rather than having to clean it up afterwards.</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/31">The Environment Agency's latest survey shows what a steep hill this will be to climb. It must be right to batten down now on this avoidable source of pollution. No wonder the agency is currently calling for</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/32" class="indent">&quot;Government to consider further measures which could reduce the environmental burden of oil pollution. This should include a review of the scope of the Oil Storage Regulations, a review of Part J of the Building Regulations and alternative measures, such as a requirement for technicians installing oil fired equipment to be appropriately qualified and registered.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/33">It would be helpful to know how the Government will respond to this call. I hope that, as I have had an opportunity to give the Minister advance notice of some of those points, he will be able to respond in some detail.</p>
	<p pid=".224.3/34">I conclude by saying that when hon. Members' constituents have a gas boiler installed in their home, they can be confident that the person coming to install it will do a quality job. Our constituents with oil fired heating systems and tanks have a right to have similar confidence.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.227.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.229.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.227.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/971" speakername="Phil Hope" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Office of the Deputy Prime Minister"  colnum="227"  time="015:44:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050118/halltext/50118h03.htm#50118h03_spmin0">
	<p pid=".227.0/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/925" name="Jane Griffiths">the Member for Reading, East (Jane Griffiths)</phrase> on securing this debate on oil installations. I was interested in what she said on pollution incidents, on the way in which they are being controlled now and might be controlled in future and in her suggestions. I also congratulate her constituent on an excellent choice of name.</p>
	<p pid=".227.0/2">Addressing oil pollution risks is an important part of the Government's overall policy on sustainability. In relation to oil installations, sustainability means using oil efficiently to avoid extravagant consumption and carbon emissions as well as limiting oil spillage in transit, dispensing and through leaks from storage installations, so that pollution incidents and expensive clean-up operations are minimised.</p>
	<p pid=".227.0/3">I want to begin where my hon. Friend began&mdash;with the problem of oil pollution affecting fresh waters. Throughout the late 1990s, the Government introduced legislation to set minimum standards for oil storage facilities at industrial, commercial and institutional premises in England. Similar regulations have been proposed for Scotland and Northern Ireland, and the Welsh Assembly Government are also considering their introduction.</p>
	<p pid=".227.0/4">The control of pollution regulations for oil storage for England were introduced, as my hon. Friend said, on <phrase class="date" code="2001-09-01">1 September 2001</phrase>, and they are being implemented in three phases. The final phase, starting on <phrase class="date" code="2005-09-01">1 September</phrase> this year, will affect all oil storage tanks not previously covered and associated pipe work at industrial, commercial and institutional installations and tanks above a 3,500-litre capacity serving dwellings, a point made by my hon. Friend.</p>
	<p pid=".227.0/5">The regulations will provide minimum standards for larger domestic installations, but there are no other requirements under those regulations aimed at controlling pollution risks arising from the majority of domestic storage installations, which generally have a much smaller capacity&mdash;600 to 1,000 litres is most common. However, it is a statutory offence under the Water Resources Act 1991 to cause or knowingly permit the pollution of controlled waters, including ground and surface water. In 2002, there was a 10 per cent. fall in the number of all categories of oil pollution incidents&mdash;the second successive year of reduction since the regulations were introduced. It is obviously too soon to make positive judgments about the overall effect of the regulations, but the signs are pointing in the right direction. We will not be able to evaluate them all in practice until there is a full year of incident data following the final enforcement date of September this year.</p>
	<p pid=".227.0/6">Although the oil storage regulations do not address the risk arising from most oil tanks that serve dwellings, those have been controlled on a risk basis in England and Wales under part J of the building regulations introduced in April 2002. Similar provisions again apply in Scotland. My hon. Friend mentioned part J, the regulatory impact assessment that was published in support of it in October 2001 and the possibilities for improving the controls on storage tanks. The requirements for measures against oil pollution in those regulations came into effect on <phrase class="date" code="2002-04-01">1 April 2002</phrase>. They require that oil storage tanks and the pipes connecting combustion appliances be properly constructed to reduce the risk of oil escaping and causing pollution, and that tanks bear durable notices containing information on how to respond to an oil escape.</p>
	<p pid=".227.0/7">Approved document J, which was published in support of the regulatory requirements, provides guidance on how to comply with the regulations. To control the risk of oil pollution, it calls for risk assessments. Where the risk is considered unacceptable, it calls for storage tanks to be protected by secondary containment. My hon. Friend described them. There are impervious bunded enclosures and catchpits, and there are also certain types of double-skinned tanks that serve this purpose.</p>
	<p pid=".227.0/8">It is true, however, that views are changing about the pollution risk from domestic central heating. It seems that the provisions in approved document J may only partially address the risks as they are now perceived. I am pleased to say that my officials have therefore begun discussions with representatives of the Environment Agency and the oil industry to see what additional guidance might be needed and how best it might be conveyed.</p>
	<p pid=".227.0/9">My hon. Friend mentioned the Oil Firing Technical Association, Oftec. It is one of the organisations approved under the building regulations to operate competent persons schemes. Membership of its scheme enables firms to carry out oil installation work covered by the building regulations and to self-certify the compliance of their work with all relevant requirements. The Oftec scheme began in April 2002. In order to register, firms must demonstrate their competence at meeting building regulation requirements, including those covering pollution.</p>
	<p pid=".227.0/10">Periodic, random inspections by Oftec help to ensure that the standards of scheme members do not slip following their registration. Although a number of registrations are not renewed each year, I am told that, overall, numbers are healthy and rising, and I welcome that. The approved Oftec scheme covers the installation of oil fired combustion appliances and related storage tanks and pipe work. It does not deal with maintenance, because those ongoing activities are not covered by the building regulations.</p>
	<p pid=".227.0/11">The competent persons scheme relieves much of the regulatory burden and allows local authority building control departments to concentrate more on checking the activities of unregistered firms. I am also pleased to say that my officials are pursuing with local authorities, industry and others how such enforcement can be improved.</p>
	<p pid=".227.0/12">My hon. Friend raised a number of questions in her presentation, and I shall try to address them now. First, on the issue of inspecting existing tanks&mdash;<i>[Interruption.]</i> My hon. Friend the Under-Secretary of State for Defence has just walked in and sat down. When I say &quot;tanks&quot;, I am referring not to anything in his Department, but to oil installation tanks. I wanted to ensure that he did not feel that there was a cross-departmental&mdash;</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.229.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.231.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.229.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.231.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.232.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.234.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.232.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.234.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.234.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.237.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.234.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/784" speakername="Ivor Caplin" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence"  colnum="234"  time="016:13:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050118/halltext/50118h04.htm#50118h04_spmin0">
	<p pid=".234.0/1">I begin by congratulating my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/860" name="Brian H Donohoe">the Member for Cunninghame, South (Mr. Donohoe)</phrase> on securing this debate to discuss the important case of his constituent, Mr. Garry Hope. My hon. Friend will realise that, because he advised my office only a little over an hour ago of the details that he related to the Chamber, I will not be able to be specific about Mr. Hope in my response. However, I will write to him about his constituent and I can respond to the general points that he made this afternoon.</p>
	<p pid=".234.0/2">This Government have always given the concerns of the 1990&ndash;91 Gulf veterans the highest priority. This important and highly complex issue will continue to receive the close attention that it deserves. However, I remind the House of the Government's approach to Gulf veterans' illnesses, about which my hon. Friend concluded his comments.</p>
	<p pid=".234.0/3">By way of background, I can tell the Chamber that more than 53,000 UK armed forces personnel were deployed to the Gulf in 1990&ndash;91, a minority of whom are ill. We all want to know why that is, but there is no medical or scientific consensus on the cause or causes of ill health among some Gulf veterans.</p>
	<p pid=".234.0/4">I remind the House about the key facts concerning Gulf veterans' mortality. The latest statistics, which were published yesterday, <phrase class="date" code="2005-01-17">17 January 2005</phrase>, show that, overall, there have been 687 deaths compared with 688 in a comparison group that was not deployed to the Gulf. That is significantly lower than would be expected in the general UK population, for which the equivalent number is 1,085.</p>
	<p pid=".234.0/5">I am sure that my hon. Friend will recall that in July 1997 we published a policy statement, &quot;Gulf Veterans' Illnesses: A New Beginning&quot;, which set out how we proposed to address the health concerns of veterans. Many of the commitments that we made in that document have been fulfilled, but I assure the House that it continues to underpin our activities at the Ministry of Defence.</p>
	<p pid=".234.0/6">The policy statement says:</p>
	<p pid=".234.0/7" class="indent">&quot;First, that all Gulf veterans will have prompt access to medical advice from the&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p pid=".234.0/8">Gulf veterans&mdash;</p>
	<p pid=".234.0/9" class="indent">&quot;Medical Assessment Programme. Second, there will be appropriate research into veterans' illnesses and factors that might have a bearing on these. Third, the MoD will make available to the public information it possesses that is of potential relevance&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".234.0/10">This afternoon I will say something about each of those areas.</p>
	<p pid=".234.0/11">I shall deal first with the medical assessment programme, which has been running since 1993. In that time it has seen more than 3,400 patients, some more than once. Mr. Hope attended the programme on <phrase class="date" code="2004-11-22">22 November 2004</phrase>. I strongly recommend that veterans of the 1990&ndash;91 Gulf conflict and of Operation Telic attend the programme if they have any concerns about their health.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.235.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.238.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.235.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.238.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.235.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/784" speakername="Ivor Caplin" colnum="235"  time="016:13:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050118/halltext/50118h04.htm#50118h04_spnew2">
	<p pid=".235.1/1">If my hon. Friend will forgive me, I will come back to him on that issue. I want to talk about further details that are available about the programme on the MOD website&mdash;<a href="http://www.gulfwar.mod.uk">www.gulfwar.mod.uk</a>. We plan to publish a revised information pack about the programme next month.</p>
	<p pid=".235.1/2">I have stated the importance of research in this area to the House before. There is scientific evidence that 1990&ndash;91 Gulf veterans report more ill health than comparable groups, but the pattern of ill health is not unique to Gulf veterans. They report the same symptoms and conditions as do UK Bosnia veterans and UK military personnel who did not deploy to the Gulf. The only difference is the increased frequency with which Gulf veterans report such symptoms.</p>
	<p pid=".235.1/3">It is worth recalling that specific diseases, disorders or medical conditions and syndromes each have common features such as a set of physical signs and/or symptoms that distinguish them from other medical conditions. Gulf veterans do not present with an identifiable and distinct pattern of symptoms or signs. The consensus of the international scientific and medical community, following extensive research on the matter, continues to be that there is insufficient evidence to enable that ill health to be characterised as a unique Gulf-related illness or syndrome.</p>
	<p pid=".235.1/4">I know that my hon. Friend will accept that the Government's approach must be guided by the scientific and medical evidence. That is why we do not recognise Gulf war syndrome as a medical condition. The term &quot;Gulf war syndrome&quot; is not found in the international standard used around the world by physicians and scientists for distinguishing diagnosable disease categories, which is stated in the World Health Organisation's &quot;International Classification of Diseases&quot;, 10th edition. Therefore, the Government simply cannot accept the recommendation in the report by Lord Lloyd that the term &quot;Gulf war syndrome&quot; be used as a label.</p>
	<p pid=".235.1/5">However, that does not stop Gulf veterans who are ill from receiving a war pension and attributable benefits under the armed forces occupational pension schemes. Such pensions are not awarded for a list of disorders but for any disablement that can be accepted as having been caused or made worse by service. That will be the case for Mr. Hope.</p>
	<p pid=".235.1/6">At the end of September 2004, about 2,800 Gulf veterans were in receipt of a war disablement pension. Additionally, 2,290 Gulf veterans had received a gratuity for disablement assessed at less than 20 per cent. There will be some overlap between those figures as some individuals will have received first a gratuity and then a pension. Those figures include awards for both Gulf-related and non-Gulf related injuries or illness, because our statistics do not enable us to distinguish the origin of the disablement. MOD officials liaise with their colleagues in the health service to ensure that periodic reminders are issued to hospitals and GPs about the priority treatment arrangements available to Gulf and other veterans for injuries and conditions for which they receive pensions. Veterans of the Gulf conflict can and do receive compensation in the form of war pensions and armed forces pensions on the same basis as all other veterans.</p>
	<p pid=".235.1/7">We see no case for another of Lord Lloyd's recommendations&mdash;that one group of veterans should be singled out for preferential treatment by way of an ex gratia payment on top of the pensions they already get.</p>
	<p pid=".235.1/8">We want to find out why some Gulf veterans from that first conflict are ill. Our current research programme, to which my hon. Friend referred, will cost at least &pound;8.5   million to complete. The Medical Research Council provides independent, scientific advice on the research programme. It has undertaken an independent, scientific review of all the UK research work that has been carried out into Gulf veterans illnesses in an international context. The results of that review, including recommendations for future research, were published in May 2003. The MOD has noted the MRC's conclusions and recommendations for further research, and additional funding will be made available as necessary.</p>
	<p pid=".235.1/9">The third strand of our approach is openness. We have made an enormous amount of information public in response to inquiries from veterans and others and we will continue to do so. I stress that the well-being of personnel whom we deploy is of the greatest importance to us, and we have made some important improvements since the 1990&ndash;91 Gulf conflict. For example, we have introduced a new operational medical record form that is now in use. We ensure that troops are immunised routinely so that personnel do not receive a combination of vaccines upon deployment, and we have arrangements to limit the effects of post-traumatic illnesses within the armed forces which have been developed over a number of years. They will continue to be reviewed in light of medical developments in the field of stress management and treatment.</p>
	<p pid=".235.1/10">On <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-04">4 November</phrase> last year, I announced the publication of a paper entitled &quot;The 1990&ndash;91 Gulf Conflict: Health And Personnel Lessons Identified&quot;. That set out what we have already done to improve policies and procedures since the Gulf conflict and assesses how those have been applied to the current Iraq deployment. Of course, the MOD is aware of the report of the US research advisory committee on Gulf war veterans illnesses, and we have noted it with interest. Its report is a review of some existing research with which we were already familiar.</p>
	<p pid=".235.1/11">There are areas in the report that we believe are not supported by the balance of scientific evidence. For example, it does not take into account a recent important paper by the US Institute of Medicine, which states that there is insufficient or inadequate evidence to determine whether an association exists between low-level exposure to sarin and long-term adverse health effects. We also note that much of the research that is drawn on to formulate the recommendations was carried out by members of the committee, which raises some concerns about objectivity. I also say to my hon. Friend that the US does not, as he stated, recognise the term &quot;Gulf war syndrome&quot;; I have explained why in relation to the WHO document.</p>
	<p pid=".235.1/12">MOD officials work closely with their US counterparts to ensure that the UK has full visibility of all American research into Gulf health issues. A senior international forum meets regularly at official level, and includes representatives of the United States, Canada, New Zealand and Australia who share information of benefit to all veterans, not just those from the 1990&ndash;91 Gulf conflict. I have invited ministerial colleagues from those countries to a summit on veterans issues in the UK, which will be held in March.</p>
	<p pid=".235.1/13">My hon. Friend raised the matter of Lord Lloyd's report. I have touched on some of its recommendations, but I would like to take the opportunity to comment on it further. We have studied it carefully, but we believe that it contains no new substantive or scientific evidence to support its conclusions and recommendations. It also fails to take into full account the large amount of written evidence and material provided by the MOD to Lord Lloyd's inquiry. We did not participate in person in his investigation because we believe that it is only through independent scientific and medical research that we are ever likely to establish the causes of ill health in some Gulf veterans. The possibility remains that we may look again at the issue of a public inquiry on this matter, but Lord Lloyd's report does nothing to change the Government's view that an inquiry will not answer the basic question about why some Gulf veterans are ill.</p>
	<p pid=".235.1/14">The report gives the impression that 6,000 veterans are suffering from ill health due to their service in the conflict. I must point out that only a minority are receiving a war pension for Gulf-related illnesses. Although these veterans served in the Gulf, many of the claims relate to physical injuries suffered in the Gulf or to disablements and illnesses unrelated to their service in the Gulf conflict. The number of veterans in receipt of pensions or gratuities for unspecified symptomatic Gulf-related illnesses is approximately 1,400, less than 3   per cent. of the personnel who served in the Gulf.</p>
	<p pid=".235.1/15">Additionally, only about 100 claimants have failed to receive an award for Gulf-related illnesses, not the 272 recommended for review by the Lloyd report. Other claims, as I said to the House at the time, relate to physical injuries suffered in the Gulf or to disablements and illnesses unrelated to their Gulf service. As my hon. Friend will be aware, I announced at Defence questions on <phrase class="date" code="2005-11-29">29 November</phrase> that the MOD will re-examine the 100 or so cases that do relate to Gulf-related illnesses, where those can be identified. I can tell the House that that review is advancing well.</p>
	<p pid=".235.1/16">In conclusion, we at the MOD have been surprised by Lord Lloyd's reluctance to disclose who sponsored and funded his investigation. That contrasts directly with the Government's policy of openness and transparency, set out in our policy document, &quot;Gulf Veterans' Illnesses: A New Beginning&quot;, which we have consistently followed for eight years and will continue to follow in the future.</p>
	<p pid=".235.1/17" class="italic">Question put and agreed to.</p>
	<p pid=".235.1/18" class="italic">Adjourned accordingly at twenty-seven minutes past Four o'clock.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.238.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.238.1" matchtype="missing"/>
<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.238.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="238"  time="016:13:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050118/halltext/50118h04.htm#50118h04_head1">
	CORRECTION
</major-heading>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.238.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.238.1" matchtype="missing"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.238.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="238"  time="016:13:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050118/halltext/50118h04.htm#50118h04_head1">
	<p pid=".238.1/1">Westminster Hall, Wednesday 12   January 2004: In col. 123WH, before the last paragraph, insert:</p>
	<p pid=".238.1/2">3.10 pm</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.238.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.238.1" matchtype="missing"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.238.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1115" speakername="Andrew Mitchell" colnum="238"  time="016:13:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050118/halltext/50118h04.htm#50118h04_spnew3">
	<p pid=".238.2/1">I start by apologising to you, Mr. Deputy Speaker, and to the Minister for my late arrival. I apologise, too, to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/695" name="Graham Allen">the hon. Member for Nottingham, North (Mr. Allen)</phrase> who, with great courtesy, gave me a copy of his speech. The irony is that while he was delivering it, I was reading it, close to this Chamber. I hope he feels that although he did not have my presence I was with him in spirit.</p>
	<p pid=".238.2/2">I congratulate the hon. Gentleman on securing the debate. Neighbourhood policing is a matter about which he has frequently expressed his concern. The hon. Gentleman and I entered the House on the same day in 1987 when he was elected for a central constituency and I for a suburb of Nottingham. I have the greatest possible affection for the city, which is a great place.</p>
	<p pid=".238.2/3">In November, the hon. Gentleman secured a debate in which he explained that it was his view that we could</p>
	<p pid=".238.2/4" class="indent">&quot;effectively increase the amount of time that police officers currently spend on the streets by 25 or 30 per cent.&quot;&mdash;<i>[Official Report, Westminster Hall,</i> <phrase class="date" code="2004-11-09">9 November 2004</phrase>; Vol. 426, c.   227.]</p>
	<p pid=".238.2/5">On <phrase class="date" code="2005-12-08">8 December</phrase>, he asked a question to the Prime Minister about linking the criminal justice system nationally with local policing and crime reduction initiatives. During a debate on the Serious Organised Crime and Police Bill, which is closeted in Committee, where I am leading spokesman for the Opposition, he made it clear that he saw the beat officer as a central pillar of neighbourhood policing in a constituency such as his, where beat officers are not being replaced and vacancies are not being filled.</p>
	<p pid=".238.2/6">In another debate, the hon. Gentleman also said:</p>
	<p pid=".238.2/7" class="indent">&quot;The people of Nottinghamshire know that we have a record number of police officers in post in Nottinghamshire, but they also ask, &quot;Where are those police officers?&quot;.&mdash;<i>[Official Report, </i>15 November 2004; Vol. 246, c. 1018.]</p>
	<p pid=".238.2/8">Those are very fair points. I attach particular importance to what the hon. Gentleman says because he has recently been on the police parliamentary scheme, and he knows what he is talking about.</p>
	<p pid=".238.2/9">The hon. Gentleman mentioned the five key components of neighbourhood policing and I very much agree with what he said about it. I also agree very much with what <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1136" name="Mark Oaten">the hon. Member for Winchester (Mr. Oaten)</phrase> said about the importance of knowing who the beat officer is. I am impressed that he has 22 names to go with the 22 beats in his constituency. That is enormously important and I strongly agree with the proposition that the telephone numbers of the relevant beat officer should go out with the council tax form. That is a very good idea, which I hope the Minister will consider.</p>
	<p pid=".238.2/10">The hon. Member for Nottingham, North paid tribute to the local commanders in his constituency. I, too, pay tribute to Douglas Paxton, a superb policeman, who is chief of police in Sutton Coldfield. He is leaving shortly, although he has been in that post for a decent length of time. In the 18 months after I first became Member of Parliament for Sutton Coldfield, there were three chiefs of police. I complained on behalf of my constituents that that was wrong. I very much support the work that the police in Sutton Coldfield are doing on antisocial behaviour, which has been a common theme in the debate.</p>
	<p pid=".238.2/11">The hon. Gentleman mentioned the importance of community support officers, but emphasised that they are not a substitute for properly trained policemen and women. I strongly agree with him. Conservative Members believe that there is an important role for CSOs in being visible; the public like them. We are extremely concerned, however, that the Government see them as a substitute for police officers.</p>
	<p pid=".238.2/12">I would welcome an assurance from the Minister that CSOs will be properly evaluated. There has been some evaluation but we want more independent evaluation before what the hon. Member for Winchester referred to as the tag-on of more powers takes place. We will discuss that next Tuesday in the Serious Organised Crime and Police Bill Committee. It is important that there should be independent evaluation of CSOs.</p>
	<p pid=".238.2/13">The third component is neighbourhood wardens. I was distressed to hear <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/853" name="Andrew Dismore">the hon. Member for Hendon (Mr. Dismore)</phrase> say that a Conservative council had removed them from his constituency. A Conservative council in Birmingham has just given my constituency two of those wardens, and we are delighted to see them there.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.240.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.238.1" matchtype="missing"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.240.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/853" speakername="Andrew Dismore" colnum="240"  time="016:13:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050118/halltext/50118h04.htm#50118h04_spnew4">
	<p pid=".240.0/1">The council have not removed them; they have downgraded them by reducing their hours and diluted their effect by expanding their responsibilities, so that they are far less effective than when they were first instituted under the then Labour-controlled councils.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.240.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18a.238.1" matchtype="missing"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-01-18.240.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1115" speakername="Andrew Mitchell" colnum="240"  time="016:13:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050118/halltext/50118h04.htm#50118h04_spnew5">
	<p pid=".240.1/1">I am glad to have put on the record that they have not been removed by a Conservative council.</p>
	<p pid=".240.1/2">I strongly agree with the point made by the hon. Member for Nottingham, North about the community and neighbourhood watch. I believe that neighbourhood watch is enormously important. I hope that the Minister will be able to say something about neighbourhood watch today that may encourage people who are feeling bruised by what happened last year. I hope that she will feel able to say something to encourage neighbourhood watch, which, in Sutton Coldfield, plays an important part in our deterrence of crime.</p>
	<p pid=".240.1/3">My final point on multi-agency working is to say that I agree with the hon. Members for Nottingham, North and for Winchester on the importance of deterring antisocial behaviour. That is something common to all of us, as has been emphasised by the debate today.</p>
	<p pid=".240.1/4">My hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/973" name="John Horam">the Member for Orpington (Mr. Horam)</phrase> stood up, as ever, for policing in his constituency, and underlined his point by saying that mobile phone numbers are a good way of contacting local beat officers and assimilating local intelligence. He gave some examples from New York, a topic that I also hoped to talk about but may not. He also talked about the importance of a fair deal for the suburbs, on which he made common cause with the hon. Member for Hendon, and about the fact that antisocial behaviour is a big problem in his constituency, as it is in mine. He asked several questions, to which I look forward to hearing the Minister's answers.</p>
	<p pid=".240.1/5">The hon. Member for Hendon agreed on the point about a fair deal for the suburbs, and he also asked a number of questions. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1283" name="Mark Todd">The hon. Member for South Derbyshire (Mr. Todd)</phrase> talked, with some reservations, about ASBOs and about the importance of the zero-tolerance approach to crime locally, with which I strongly agree. He also made an important point about the use of specials&mdash;indeed, he adopted a Conservative proposal to give a bounty to special constables. The number of specials has declined significantly under this Government&mdash;by some 45 per cent. since 1997. I hope that the Minister will feel able to comment on the importance of specials and what she and her colleagues intend to do to promote them.</p>
	<p pid=".240.1/6">Finally, I should like to emphasise the point made by the Liberal spokesman, the hon. Member for Winchester: that in local policing we must avoid top-down set models, which were a serious error of judgment by the former Home Secretary. We must ensure that local solutions are used to deal with local problems. I do not necessarily expect the Minister to agree with me and the hon. Gentleman, but I hope that she will take that point on board, because it will lead to much better neighbourhood policing.</p>
	<p pid=".240.1/7">I again congratulate the hon. Member for Nottingham, North&mdash;my former parliamentary near neighbour&mdash;on securing the debate and on the consistent theme that he has brought to his comments in the House on neighbourhood policing. It is greatly to be welcomed that there now appears to be a degree of cross-party agreement on how the matter should be taken forward.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

