<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.455.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.455.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.455.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.455.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.455.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.455.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.456.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.456.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.456.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.456.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.456.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.456.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.456.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.456.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.458.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.458.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.458.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.458.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.458.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1519" speakername="Laura Moffatt" colnum="458"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060524/halltext/60524h0105.htm#06052454000382">
	<p pid="a.458.1/1">As chair of the all-party group on maternity, I am very aware of the issues facing the Stroud birthing unit. I also know that my hon. Friend is a keen supporter of the nurses there and that he is keen to ensure that that excellent unit survives. He is right about nurse education and continuing education, and when trusts face difficulties&mdash;I shall speak a little more about this&mdash;they should be wary of cutting budgets in ways that result in their not training as many of those entering the profession or continuing their education afterwards. That would be a false economy, and none of the innovations that I described would have happened without a well educated, empowered work force. I thank my hon. Friend for raising the subject.</p>
	<p pid="a.458.1/2">I have talked about how different training has become. Today's nurse education includes increased practice-based learning, which we called for very strongly. We felt that in the Nursing 2000 initiative there was an overemphasis on classroom activity and not enough emphasis on practice-based activity, and the change has been warmly welcomed.</p>
	<p pid="a.458.1/3">My hon. Friend mentioned training, and I want to put the issue to the Minister in the hope that we can have an ongoing dialogue to ensure that training budgets are secure and ring-fenced. That would give acute trusts and primary care trusts the ability to continue investing in their most precious commodity&mdash;their staff.</p>
	<p pid="a.458.1/4">Nurses who are in practice now are having a very different time from their predecessors, and I look with envy at some of the activities and innovations that are taking place. I like to keep in touch with what is happening and I have assisted in the Royal College of Nursing leadership programmes for modern matrons, which has helped me to understand some of the issues that those people face.</p>
	<p pid="a.458.1/5">Nurses continue to press for greater autonomy, and nurse organisations across the board, including trade unions such as Unison and the RCN, continue to ensure that nurses introduce new ways of practising. Talk of evidence-based practice is now typical in every nurse setting, as nurses ensure that they continue to deliver the best care to patients.</p>
	<p pid="a.458.1/6">Nurses who have been through nurse education have a responsibility to other team members. I am delighted that more than 80,000 more nurses are working in the NHS, but there has also been a huge increase in health care assistants, and nurses have a responsibility to ensure that those assistants receive the best training so that they can assist in care giving. No one is better placed than nurses to ensure that health care assistants receive the training, education and continuing development that they desperately need.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.459.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.459.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.459.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.459.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.461.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.461.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.462.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.462.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.462.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.462.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.462.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.462.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.462.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.462.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.463.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.463.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.463.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.463.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.463.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.463.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.463.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.463.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.464.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.464.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.464.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.464.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.464.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1755" speakername="Andrew Smith" colnum="464"  time="010:07:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060524/halltext/60524h0105.htm#06052454000395">
	<p pid="a.464.1/1">I do not want to get into partisan fights on the matter. I simply made a passing reference to the fact&mdash;it is a fact&mdash;that the principal Opposition party did not vote for the resources that were necessaryto increase health funding in the way that the Government have increased it. Therefore, it is true that the position would have been worse, not better, if they had had their way. The change is to be welcomed.</p>
	<p pid="a.464.1/2">As I said, I wish to raise three key issues in this contribution. The first was touched on earlier when my hon. Friend the Member for Crawley discussed pathways into nursing and the importance of professional development. I wish to stress the point and invite my hon. Friend the Minister to respond on the question of health care assistants and opportunities to qualify, whether through secondment or the other routes to which my hon. Friend the Member for Crawley referred.</p>
	<p pid="a.464.1/3">The point is worth stressing because health care assistants are an enormously important part of the modern health care team. They bring experience and a set of life skills that can be invaluable in nursing.For many of them, especially those with family responsibilities, the secondment route is financially the most viable way into nursing. It is a great loss to the profession if people have that potential and want to qualify as nurses but are held back because they are unable to get a secondment place. That is why I invite my hon. Friend the Minister to set out the Government's thinking on how we can maintain and, where possible, expand that important route. Such opportunities are crucial to making the most of those individuals' potential.</p>
	<p pid="a.464.1/4">Those opportunities are also important in confronting nursing shortages, as we have done on many occasions in the past. Especially in areas of high-cost accommodation such as Oxford, the challenge for the future must be not simply to fill gaps by recruiting nurses from overseas, although they have made an invaluable contribution, or by increasing training for the future, although that is important, but to do more to retain the staff whom we have and to ensure that people who already live in an area and who have the potential to become qualified nurses have a route into nursing. Such people already have accommodation in the area, so they do not face the burden of high prices and rents. That is particularly important in constituencies such as mine.</p>
	<p pid="a.464.1/5">The second key area is the impact of current financial deficits. It is a coincidence that as we meet here today, staff at the John Radcliffe hospital in Oxford will be briefed on the likely implications for them of correcting the local deficit. Last week, headline leaked reports stated that as many as 600 posts might go, so staff are understandably apprehensive. I have met RCN representatives, Unison and others to discuss that difficult situation.</p>
	<p pid="a.464.1/6">The crucial thing is that patient care must be safeguarded. The nurses whom I met have undertaken to alert me if there is any threat to patient care so that I can raise it at the highest level, but it is unfortunate indeed that people are being subjected to anxiety. The situation is terrible for people who face losing their job. I believe that that apprehension informed some of the anger voiced at the RCN conference. Certainly the nurses who came to see me in the recent lobby said that that was the reason for it, although I echo what others have said about the impact that it had and how it came across.</p>
	<p pid="a.464.1/7">The other dimension to the deficits, to which my hon. Friend the Member for Crawley referred, was covered in the excellent briefings from the Councilof Deans, which warn that the biggest cuts in commissioning of nurses going into training appear to be in those strategic health authority areas where the deficits are largest. In some areas, cuts of up to 30 or40 per cent. in the current financial year are being spoken about. After all that has been done to improve nurse training and recruitment, it would be an utter tragedy if we returned to the bad old pattern of feast and famine by allowing those short-term financial pressures to cut recruitment for the future.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.465.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.465.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.465.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.465.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.466.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.466.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.466.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.466.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.466.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.466.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.468.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.468.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.468.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1830" speakername="John Pugh" colnum="468"  time="010:27:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060524/halltext/60524h0106.htm#06052454000401">
	<p pid="a.468.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1519" name="Laura Moffatt">the hon. Member for Crawley (Laura Moffatt)</phrase> on her opening speech in this important debate, to which she contributed a good deal of expertise. I marvel at her commitment&mdash;there is hardly a health meeting that I go to in this building to which she does not show up and make a valuable contribution.</p>
	<p pid="a.468.0/2">I am not an expert, like the hon. Lady, but I have something in my CV that is vaguely relevant. In a gap year, when I was a student, I worked as a nursing assistant in an old-fashioned mental hospital in Maidstone, Kent called Oakwood hospital. I started there with not a day's training and no secondment. I was simply given a white coat and set off, and I ended up on refractory and block wards. There must be few other MPs who have shown people into padded cells, administered electroconvulsive therapy and seen a straitjacket used.</p>
	<p pid="a.468.0/3">In those days, I was familiar with the division between state-enrolled nurses and state registered nurses&mdash;one could tell them apart by their varying epaulettes and colour-coding&mdash;and the further division between them and the lower grade of nursing assistant, which I was. As such, I was completely unqualified and untrained, and I muddled through as best I could. We were aware that SRNs were the cr&egrave;me de la cr&egrave;me, who were going somewhere. They would become the charge nurses and, for those who were very fortunate, the matrons. However, my impression was that the training then was not anything like as intensive as it now is and that monitoring of performance was somewhat weak. I was aware at only one stage in my work of being inspected, and that was when the boards of hospital visitors, or whoever they were, trooped through from time to time and took more interest in the state of the floors than in the condition and happiness of the patients. That seemed to be their major and fundamental preoccupation.</p>
	<p pid="a.468.0/4">In those days, one was aware of the clear demarcation between the nurses, who saw the patients very often, knew a great deal about them and could do much for them, and the doctors, who were of course the experts without whom nobody could move, who none the less saw patients relatively infrequently.</p>
	<p pid="a.468.0/5">My brief experience of nursing before going off to study philosophy at university was intensely interesting and enjoyable. It was also a good preparation for other career moves. I say that because someone recently described this place as the last Victorian asylum. That may be a little unfair, but this place is full of people talking out loud to no one in particular.</p>
	<p pid="a.468.0/6">Things have changed radically in nursing. I start on a good note by saying that the Government and the profession are to be congratulated. We have an increased supply of nurses&mdash;more than ever before&mdash;and we depend less on foreign staff, who ought to be working and providing health services in their own countries. We have increased salaries and improved career paths for nurses and others in the nursing profession. We also have improvements in the quality and variety of nursing education, and the link with higher education is an important boost in status, which the hon. Lady said was much needed and which is firmly to be welcomed. Nursing training also encourages career development and builds on nurses' skills.</p>
	<p pid="a.468.0/7">I warm to the concepts of nurse practitioners and of nurses being able to prescribe. Those long overdue and necessary reforms will break down the strict divisions that hitherto existed between nurses and doctors and their relevant areas of expertise. If we are to have decent medical care in the community, we need greater qualifications among the nursing profession. If we are to take pressure off the accident and emergency departments by having more minor injury units, we shall need nurses who can deal with a variety of unexpected conditions. If we are to advance the healthy living agenda and have flexible and effective care we will need expert and skilled nurses, and we are getting them stage by stage.</p>
	<p pid="a.468.0/8">The Government's strategy is essentially correct. I doubt whether anyone would speak against it. The strategy is correct and the profession is to be congratulated on endorsing it. However, it is a long-term strategy, as evidenced by the comments that we remember hearing when we remember our own experiences, and my concern is that it will be blown off course by short-term financial needs, or that it will be cross-grained with other initiatives. I think specifically of payment by results, and the drive to turn every NHS unit, whatever it be, into a financially autonomous, solvent, trading and entrepreneurial unit almost overnight.</p>
	<p pid="a.468.0/9">The system cannot bear that sort of stress, because it effectively asks organisations to wipe out in one year deficits that have been built up over many years. That is what led to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1755" name="Andrew Smith">the right hon. Member for Oxford, East (Mr. Smith)</phrase> talking about feast and famine in nursing training in relation to recent resource cuts. It was also referred to as stop-go in a briefing that we all received. They are all phrases that will be familiar to the Minister after his Treasury experience. Boom and bust is another. I assume that he is agin it.</p>
	<p pid="a.468.0/10">It is clear that SHA training budgets are often raided, that they are sometimes underspent, and that they are only notionally ring-fenced. They can therefore become a source of brokerage, top-slicing or centre-saving. Whatever one calls it, the money just goes&mdash;especially in those areas that have the biggest problems. It is in those areas with larger deficits that existing staff are most fearful, job security is declining and additional training prospects are worsening. To cite a personal example, the acute trust in my constituency has a substantial deficit. It has announced 200 redundancies, but it has said that nurses will not be made redundant, which is welcome. I should declare an interest. My son's partner, who has trained as a children's nurse cannot gain employment and is looking for a job outside nursing that will use her considerable talents.</p>
	<p pid="a.468.0/11">Setting that against the general complaint of the royal colleges and the strategic liaison group about the lack of clinical academic pathways, one can begin to see a problem emerging. They complain about the difficulty of combining the service and the education roles. That can only bring about a reduction in effective mentoring. People's experiences cannot easily be traded in both areas as effectively as they might. They also complained&mdash;this point, too, was made by the right hon. Gentleman&mdash;about a lack of work force planning and the fact that we have not linked training places to needs, as has happened for the medical profession.</p>
	<p pid="a.468.0/12">What is happening is not something that could be dressed up in tabloid headlines as a meltdown, collapse or crisis in nursing; however, it is a genuine and serious problem, which can and should be tackled, and which calls into question the coherence of what the Government are doing and the haste with which they are acting. Hon. Members have spoken warmly about the Government's support of the nursing profession and nurse training, but they are in danger, on this issue in particular, of snatching defeat from the jaws of victory.</p>
	<p pid="a.468.0/13">What is required is a broad view, consistency and sensible pragmatism&mdash;all of which I associate with the Minister and elements of the ministerial team. The strategy can be right, and we agree that it is, but if the tactics are wrong we end up with a bit of a mess.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.471.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.471.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.471.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.471.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.471.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.471.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.472.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.472.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.472.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.472.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.473.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.473.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.473.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.473.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.474.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.474.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.474.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1467" speakername="Ivan Lewis" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Health"  colnum="474"  time="010:47:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060524/halltext/60524h0106.htm#06052454000409">
	<p pid="a.474.0/1">It is always a pleasure to serve under your chairmanship, Mr. Cook. I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1519" name="Laura Moffatt">the Member for Crawley (Laura Moffatt)</phrase> on securing this Adjournment debate and on the passionate and knowledgeable way in which she described the development of nursing over a relatively short period. She described experiences that she had when she was a front-line nurse in the national health service and some of the challenges and difficulties that nurses faced. She also described the sense of reward that she got from being a nurse and recognised how significantly things have changed in recent times.</p>
	<p pid="a.474.0/2">It was good to hear it highlighted that it is the Labour party that, since 1997, has welcomed the election of not only my hon. Friend the Member for Crawley, but my hon. Friends the Members for Brentford and Isleworth (Ann Keen), for East Lothian (Anne Moffat) and for Livingston (Mr. Devine)&mdash;all serving nurses who have been elected to the House of Commons. That is a step forward for democracy. When my hon. Friends the Members for Crawley and for Brentford and Isleworth were elected, it was the first time in history that nurses had been elected to Parliament. I am very proud that all of them are Labour Members of Parliament. They are some of the best colleagues in the parliamentary Labour party, as I am sure everyone agrees.</p>
	<p pid="a.474.0/3">My hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" name="David Taylor">the Member for North-West Leicestershire (David Taylor)</phrase> always turns up to make a contribution. However much he goes on about my talents as a Minister, I am not in a position to make announcements today on additional resources for midwifery bursaries, but I take on board the general concern that he expressed about retention of midwives, particularly on some courses. What are the obstacles getting in people's way and what issues do I need to address in my new role to deal with that?</p>
	<p pid="a.474.0/4">My right hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1755" name="Andrew Smith">the Member for Oxford, East (Mr. Smith)</phrase> made a very important contribution to the debate. I think that the last time we both participated in a debate in Westminster Hall, we were discussing cash machines and access to cash. This is a slightly different subject&mdash;such is the nature of Government. He referred to health care assistants and secondment programmes. As I understand it, that is very much left to local discretion, depending on the market and on supply and demand. However, I am willing to look into secondment programmes for health care assistants&mdash;that specific opportunity to get into nursing&mdash;and into what is happening and what we want to happen.</p>
	<p pid="a.474.0/5">My right hon. Friend also drew attention to the important role that Oxford Brookes university plays. It is a centre of excellence for social and health care and has been for some time, offering significant training opportunities. He also referred to the sad news that some of his constituents will receive today at John Radcliffe hospital. Although I cannot comment on the specific circumstances, I am sure that he will be making very strong representations about the decisions made by the hospital management, particularly in the context of any impact on patient care, and that he will maintain a dialogue with members of the ministerial team on those issues.</p>
	<p pid="a.474.0/6">My right hon. Friend and others talked about cuts in training in certain areas and asked what the pattern was. We should begin by saying that there has been a massive increase in the number of training places made available since the Labour Government came to power. As a consequence, there is a massive number of new entrants into nursing. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1830" name="John Pugh">The hon. Member for Southport (Dr. Pugh)</phrase> was good enough to acknowledge that. However, in every public service there is a tendency to regard the training budget as the first to go&mdash;the soft target&mdash;and as former Minister with responsibility for skills, I am highly aware of that. We need to monitor the impact of decisions on training budgets, and we will do that, but it would be wrong to use words such as crisis and decline; we have to adopt a measured approach and should always look at the issues in context.</p>
	<p pid="a.474.0/7">My hon. Friend the Member for Brentford and Isleworth talked from personal experience about the realities of nursing in the past. What she said about academic snobbery is absolutely true of the way that this country treats vocational education and training generally. Frankly, we are to be successful in our public service ambitions and in the economic challenges that we face, we have to change that almost uniquely English snobbish approach to vocational education and training&mdash;I can feel myself making one of my speeches as a former Minister for Young People and Adult Skills. That is a real problem that is endemic in the culture of this country, and we have to attack it in every way that we can.</p>
	<p pid="a.474.0/8">My hon. Friend also referred to the Chancellor's role in ensuring unprecedented levels of investment in the national health service, year on year. Frankly, it was an act of political leadership for him to tell people not long ago that increasing national insurance by 1 per cent. was merited and morally right if we wanted the kind of national health service that this country deserves. What was interesting about that decision and that leadership is that&mdash;if we remember the political climate at the time and the electoral consequences of that decision&mdash;people actually endorsed it. It was right to be honest and to say that to achieve the growth in NHS investment required, difficult decisions would be necessary. People in this country cherish and value the national health service and believe that there is nothing more important than investing in it and ensuring that it continues to be something that we can be proud of in any international context.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.475.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.475.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.476.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.476.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.477.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.477.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.477.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.477.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.477.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.477.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.478.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.478.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.478.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.478.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.479.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.479.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.480.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.480.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.480.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.480.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.480.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.480.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.482.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.482.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.482.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1446" speakername="Barry Gardiner" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs"  colnum="482"  time="011:16:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060524/halltext/60524h0107.htm#06052454000420">
	<p pid="a.482.0/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" name="David Taylor">the Member for North-West Leicestershire (David Taylor)</phrase> on securing this debate, which is timely given the end of the consultation and the importance of animal welfare to the Government and all hon. Members present.</p>
	<p pid="a.482.0/2">I am encouraged that our consultation on the priorities for the next rural development programme in England, which closed on Monday, has provoked a debate about the best way to use the funding available to tackle the challenges facing rural communities in England. In addition to the feedback that we have received from regional events during the consultation, I understand that at the last count we had received about 150 written submissions. Of course, we will carefully analyse those responses, and we will make our decision on the priorities for the next programme in the light of the comments received and my hon. Friend's remarks today.</p>
	<p pid="a.482.0/3">In the consultation, we set out a number of key principles for the use of rural development funding. What I want to get across today is that one of the most important of those principles is that programme funding should demonstrably add value. I am sure that the budget available for the next programme will be limited, as budgets always are, so we must be aware of the need to spend money where it will have maximum impact.</p>
	<p pid="a.482.0/4">We are still not clear exactly how much will be allocated to the UK, and we have yet to take decisions on what use to make of voluntary modulation and associated match funding. My hon. Friends the Members for North-West Leicestershire and for Stroud (Mr. Drew) both asked about the December budget. I have received the RSPCA briefing on that issue, which I know other hon. Members have also received, but it does not take into account the fact that the budget is to be supplemented by compulsory modulation and the EU budget for rural development in the EU15. Because of that supplement, which must be co-financed by member states, we expect that the amount of EU funding available for the next RDP in England will be slightly higher than for current programmes. I want to correct any misunderstanding on that situation, because the briefing was perhaps misleading in that respect, although not intentionally, I am sure.</p>
	<p pid="a.482.0/5">The key point to stress is that we acknowledge that December was the occasion for cutting a deal and, as my hon. Friend suggested, whenever a deal is cut there are compromises to be made, but we must not lose sight of the great victory that we won then: the review of the common agricultural policy in 2008 and all that that will mean for the pattern of spending in rural communities that we have piloted. We are establishing the approach and we are at the forefront in Europe in trying to pull money away from pillar one and into pillar two precisely on the areas of spending that we have all said are so important.</p>
	<p pid="a.482.0/6">As my hon. Friends have highlighted, the framework for the next programme&mdash;the rural development regulation&mdash;is broadly drawn, allowing for a wide range of activities. That flexibility recognises that rural development needs vary across the EU. New member states may need to focus the available funding on achieving basic community standards, including those on animal welfare, but that may not represent the best value for money in other member states.</p>
	<p pid="a.482.0/7">I take up the challenge that my hon. Friend laid down in his three final points. I am happy to write to him on the first point: what evidence there is that farmers exceed baseline compulsory legal minimum standards of animal welfare in England. In my discussions with ministerial colleagues in the Department who have responsibility specifically for animal welfare, I was assured that they are confident that many farmers in England achieve higher&mdash;in some cases substantially higher&mdash;standards of animal welfare.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.483.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.483.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.484.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.484.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.484.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.484.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.484.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.484.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.484.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.484.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.484.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.484.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.486.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.486.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.487.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.487.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.487.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.487.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.487.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.487.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.487.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1596" speakername="Peter Viggers" colnum="487"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060524/halltext/60524h0108.htm#06052454000428">
	<p pid="a.487.2/1">Thank you,Mr. Bercow, for this opportunity to raise the issue of community hospitals. First, I would like to pay tribute to workers in the national health service, especially those who are involved in patient care. I am sure that anyone who has been directly involved personally or through a family member will wish to join in that tribute to NHS workers.</p>
	<p pid="a.487.2/2">A local journalist asked me on the telephone, &quot;Will this be your usual Haslar speech, Peter?&quot; I said that it would not be my usual Haslar speech, but I would of course be referring to Haslar, specifically the Royal hospital Haslar, which I would claim has become one of the best known hospitals in Parliament.</p>
	<p pid="a.487.2/3">The background is that the Royal Naval hospital Haslar, which had become the only hospital within the armed forces, became the Royal hospital Haslar. It was, in effect, operating as a second district general hospital in the Gosport area when in 1998, to everyone's astonishment, it was announced that it would close not earlier than 2000. That caused serious problems in the armed forces. They studied various sites where they might locate a hospital and eventually settled, not with great enthusiasm, on the Selly Oak site in Birmingham. They were cheered by the fact that &pound;200 million would be spent on an all new, all-singing and dancing centre that would provide them with messing, sports and other facilities in Birmingham. Unfortunately, however, that project was cancelled. Within the armed forces now, there are serious shortages in most of the important faculties. I shall return to the issue of armed services medicine later in my speech.</p>
	<p pid="a.487.2/4">The reaction in the south Hampshire area to the closure was one of anger and disbelief. I shall not recount all the facts, as they are very much on the parliamentary record, but there was an unprecedented march of some 22,000 people demonstrating against the closure of the hospital. We demonstrated in every way we could think of to catch the public eye. Wehad &quot;Save Haslar&quot; in lights photographed from a helicopter, we had a relay taking a petition to Downing street, we had demonstrations outside Downing street, and we had many debates in Parliament. After much pressure was applied, a deal was cobbled together with the health authorities whereby Haslar would indeed be saved and would continue to be used for local medical facilities and for the armed forces as well.</p>
	<p pid="a.487.2/5">Unfortunately, in what I regard as a shameful chapter in the history of health care in south Hampshire, the primary care trust went back on the agreement. It &quot;consulted&quot;. Whenever one uses that word in connection with the NHS, one has to put it in inverted commas, because the result of a consultation is usually well known before the consultation takes place. There was local discussion, aided by the consultation, of whether Haslar or Gosport War Memorial hospital should continue as the local community hospital. The votes for Haslar were overwhelming, but at a meeting in a church in Fareham, the PCT unanimously voted against popular wishes and decided to close Haslar and continue the Gosport War Memorial hospital, on the basis of what I have to say was some very unreliable information on matters such as costings, car parking and so on.</p>
	<p pid="a.487.2/6">Later, I chaired a packed meeting in St. Mary's church, Alverstoke, in Gosport. I believe that 800 people were present, with many standing at the back of the church. We took a vote on whether we wished Haslar or Gosport War Memorial hospital to continue. To my disbelief, every single hand went up in favour of Haslar. I remember asking, &quot;Is there no one here who wishes to say anything in favour of the primary care trust's proposals?&quot; but not a single soul supportedthe PCT.</p>
	<p pid="a.487.2/7">We went through the statutory procedure. Hampshire county council's overview and scrutiny committee referred the matter to the Minister for reference to the Independent Reconfiguration Panel. I went to see the Minister, who turned down reference to the IRP. The Minister's veto means that Gosport is the only place in the whole of the United Kingdom that the IRP cannot investigate. It has widened its brief, but the only place in which it cannot take an interest is Gosport.</p>
	<p pid="a.487.2/8">So there we stand. The Royal hospital Haslar is to have its Ministry of Defence support withdrawn with effect from <phrase class="date" code="2007-03-31">31 March 2007</phrase>. Arrangements are in hand for the local hospitals trust to take over responsibility for the hospital until summer 2009, when the private finance initiative bid at Queen Alexandra hospital will be completed, and the plan is that Haslar will close thereafter. However, the plan was that Haslar would close in 2000; it is now 2006 and Haslar is still there.</p>
	<p pid="a.487.2/9">I turn now to the general picture in the national health service as it relates to hospitals. Spending has increased&mdash;it has almost doubled&mdash;from &pound;40 billion to &pound;76 billion, but most of that increase has gone on salaries, drugs and compensation, and there has been a 66 per cent. increase in the number of managers. There have been various problems: we all know, for example, that it is much easier to admit someone to a district general hospital than to transfer them out of one, particularly because the Government, in the their wisdom, have changed the standards for nursing homes and required them to widen their doors, raise their ceilings, put in en-suite bathrooms and so on. As a result many nursing homes have closed, and the loss of nursing home places has made it difficult to get people out of district general hospitals and into nursing homes. The Government have therefore resorted to the rather shabby process of fining councils that do not have enough nursing home places. Hampshire county council, to give one example, has had to build places in nursing homes.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.488.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.488.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.489.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.489.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.490.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.490.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.490.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.490.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.490.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.490.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.490.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.490.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.491.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.491.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.491.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.491.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.491.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.492.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.492.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.492.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.492.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1596" speakername="Peter Viggers" colnum="492"  time="015:16:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060524/halltext/60524h0108.htm#06052454000436">
	<p pid="a.492.0/1">I was pointing out that armed service personnel are no longer treated within the armed forces but are treated within the national health service, where they are supposed to receive priority. There are two problems with that. First, reservists, when they are dismissed from active service, do not get priority. Secondly, there is no point in having priority if there is no service to have priority within. I specifically cite mental health services. A significant number of service personnel, particularly reservists who have served in Iraq, are suffering from post-traumatic stress disorder but there are no facilities within the national health service to treat them and the only residential unit has closed. Within the Hampshire Partnerships NHS trust, which treats mental health patients in the south of Hampshire, there were no new consultations at all for many months last year. For both those reasons, I maintain that the present arrangement is not satisfactory. I know that service chiefs are seriously worried about the medical provision for armed services personnel.</p>
	<p pid="a.492.0/2">There is such a difference between the Americans' attitude and ours. In America, the attitude is, &quot;If we put our boys and girls in harm's way, we will do anything to put them right if they are injured.&quot; The attitude in the British armed forces is that if someone is injured, facilities are available in the national health service and one must go and seek them. It is not satisfactory and service chiefs are worried.</p>
	<p pid="a.492.0/3">There is a model that we could develop. The Aldershot centre for health is a partnership between the Army and Blackwater Valley and Hart primary care trust. It provides excellent facilities, including GP practices and nursing teams, health promotion, diagnostics, counselling services, and drug and alcohol teams. It also has an Army medical reception ward, general practice and psychiatric services, and a standing medical ward. That is the kind of facility that I believe should be used as a model for the constituency hospital of Haslar in Gosport.</p>
	<p pid="a.492.0/4">I tabled a question last week asking the Secretary of State</p>
	<p pid="a.492.0/5" class="indent">&quot;whether his Department has assessed the Aldershot Centre for Health as a model which could be followed at The Royal Hospital Haslar.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.492.0/6">Rather encouragingly, the Ministry of Defence states that it</p>
	<p pid="a.492.0/7" class="indent">&quot;will be assessing options for innovative partnerships...particularly in the light of NHS developments and future military basing. However, it would be premature&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.492.0/8">not wrong, but premature&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.492.0/9" class="indent">&quot;to model another facility on the Aldershot Centre for Health until the functional success of the project has been evaluatedand any lessons have been identified.&quot;&mdash;[<phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2006-05-17.958"><i>Official Report</i>,17 May 2006; Vol. 446, c. 958W</phrase>.]</p>
	<p pid="a.492.0/10">I hope that the Ministry of Defence and the Department of Health will work together and, even now, find a way ahead for the Royal hospital Haslar.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.492.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.492.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.493.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.493.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.493.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.493.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.494.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.494.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.494.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.494.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.496.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.496.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.496.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.496.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.496.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.496.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.498.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.498.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.498.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.498.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.498.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.498.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.498.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1382" speakername="Tony Baldry" colnum="498"  time="015:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060524/halltext/60524h0109.htm#06052454000447">
	<p pid="a.498.2/1">Thank you,Mr. Bercow. I will try to be brief.</p>
	<p pid="a.498.2/2">The NHS in Oxfordshire is in freefall. Today, the Oxford Radcliffe NHS trust is telling its staff that between 650 and 700 posts will be lost&mdash;the exact number will be known tomorrow. By my calculation, that is equivalent to about 8 per cent. of the work force. The loss is occurring as a consequence of &pound;33 million of savings imposed on the trust, in addition to the&pound;17 million of savings that Oxfordshire PCTs have been obliged to make. As a result, the new and enlarged Bicester community hospital promised by <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1527" name="Alan Milburn">the right hon. Member for Darlington (Mr. Milburn)</phrase> when he was at the Department of Health has now become a complete fantasy.</p>
	<p pid="a.498.2/3">The White Paper was another fantasy. &quot;Our health, our care, our say&quot; repeated the promise made at the previous general election about having a new generation of community hospitals. Can the Minister tell the House where that new generation of community hospitals is? It is figment of the Minister's and the Department's imagination. There are no community hospitals. Then we are told that community hospitals no longer need beds and that the Government's new concept of primary care centres&mdash;better, larger GP practice centres&mdash;are somehow new community hospitals. It will not wash.</p>
	<p pid="a.498.2/4">Last week, I met the acting chief executive of the PCT, who said that because of the enormous squeeze on its budget it is concerned only about acute care. Anything that can be moved off into social care&mdash;anything that can be means-tested by the county council&mdash;will be moved. An article in one of the Sunday newspapers referred to a new kind of nursing homes in Hampshire, in which people are moved from NHS beds simply to die under the responsibility of social care.</p>
	<p pid="a.498.2/5">We will see an increasing number of people who would have expected in the past to be treated at community hospitals shunted off to somewhere else in means-tested social care, because the NHS no longer has the funds to manage such cases. The PCTs say that they no longer wish to look after such patients. Somehow, they will become lost in the community. It is a disgrace. We are not going to see a new community hospital in Bicester. If we were to have a new generation of community hospitals of the sort that was promised at the Dispatch Box by the Secretary of State in the mid-1990s, one would have expected it to have been delivered. It is a fantasy.</p>
	<p pid="a.498.2/6">I want to know this from the Minister: what from this White Paper has ever been delivered? It is a public policy disgrace that Ministers come along and waste taxpayers' money with a fake consultation. No public meetings were ever organised in Oxfordshire on &quot;Our health, our care, our say&quot;; what the Government had was a fake meeting in Birmingham with a hand-picked audience. People are becoming increasingly cynical about what the Government are delivering, and I say to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1850" name="David Drew">the hon. Member for Stroud (Mr. Drew)</phrase> that the part of the Stroud newspaper that he ought to start reading is the appointments page, because given the way the Government are cutting&mdash;he used terms such as cuts and sacrifices&mdash;come the next election I fear he will be looking for another job. Clearly, as is evidenced in our debate, across the country, county by county, this Government are waging war on community hospitals and community medical services.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.499.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.499.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.499.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1801" speakername="Andrew George" colnum="499"  time="015:46:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060524/halltext/60524h0109.htm#06052454000448">
	<p pid="a.499.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1596" name="Peter Viggers">the hon. Member for Gosport (Peter Viggers)</phrase> on securing the debate. Many useful points have already been made. The hon. Gentleman said that the Royal hospital Haslar is one of the best known in Parliament. That is true; it comes a close second after West Cornwall hospital.</p>
	<p pid="a.499.0/2">I wish to raise a single issue, which I hope the Minister will respond to. It is to do with the thesis&mdash;or, as I would argue, mantra&mdash;that has been coming from the NHS Confederation, which is, as I understand it, the provisional wing of the NHS; it certainly puts out a lot of the arguments that Ministers might not be prepared to argue. Its argument is that the acute sector requires fewer hospital beds. It is a thesis that has become a mantra in the style of the management consultant culture that seems to have pervadedthe NHS.</p>
	<p pid="a.499.0/3">What worries me is the way in which that approach relates to the future of community hospitals, which is a very pertinent question. When I have debated this matter with GPs nationally and locally and with the trusts that argue that we should push for such an approach, I can understand the frustration of those running the acute sector about large numbers of patients are going into acute hospitals who they argue should not even be going through their front doors. In other words, they are saying that there are unnecessary admissions to acute hospitals. That may well be the case, and there is also another argument that has been made today and which is repeated regularly with regard to the difficulty of discharging patients once they have come into acute hospitals.</p>
	<p pid="a.499.0/4">The approach taken by the NHS Confederation&mdash;and supported by Ministers, I would argue&mdash;is causing a great deal of difficulty for acute hospitals and nursing staff, who have to cope with other Government targets on communicable diseases. In many acute hospitals, bed pressures mean that there is a lot of hot-bedding. Severely and acutely ill patients are being moved around hospitals or discharged from them, and other patients are moved in. One of the best ways of getting on top of infection control issues is to manage beds so there are surplus beds in acute hospitals, not too few.</p>
	<p pid="a.499.0/5">In order to achieve the outcome of fewer acute hospitals, which may be desirable in the longer run, the Government need to address such issues, many of which they have in fact contributed to. The way in which the primary care GP out-of-hours service is currently managed means that many patients are not seen by their GPs out of hours. Given an environment in which there is an increasingly litigious public, ambulance-chasing lawyers and so forth, on the precautionary principle many patients are admitted to acute hospitals when they do not need to be. That trend will inevitably continue, and it may get worse.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.500.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.500.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.500.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.500.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.501.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.501.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.502.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.502.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.503.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.503.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.503.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.503.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.504.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.504.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.504.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1743" speakername="Steve Webb" colnum="504"  time="016:02:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060524/halltext/60524h0110.htm#06052454000454">
	<p pid="a.504.0/1">It is appropriate that the final contribution before the winding-up speeches should highlight the issue that underlay many of the other contributions, but which was not made explicit: accountability. What has run throughout the debate is the notion that local people are clearly expressing their preferences&mdash;the term &quot;sham consultation&quot; keeps coming up in these Westminster Hall debates&mdash;but that we can do nothing about it when nobody listens.</p>
	<p pid="a.504.0/2">That causes me to ask the fundamental question of whether we need to look at accountability in the national health service and decide whether we are satisfied with the present arrangement, whereby just one person&mdash;obviously, she is not present today&mdash;is accountable for the 1.3 million people who work in the NHS, or whether there needs to be closer, more local accountability. We have that in embryo form in local authorities' overview and scrutiny committees, but they are weak, and one of the few things that they can do&mdash;this links to the introductory remark made by <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1596" name="Peter Viggers">the hon. Member for Gosport (Peter Viggers)</phrase>&mdash;is to refer a decision to the Secretary of State and ask her, in turn, to refer it to the independent reconfiguration panel.</p>
	<p pid="a.504.0/3">I was interested in the hon. Gentleman's remarks, because his experiences are identical to mine. I had a hospital closure in my area, and the local authority asked the Secretary of State to have it looked at independently, but she refused. There is history in that respect. Although there is an independent panel, it does not, on average, get asked to look at the things that local authorities want it to consider, because the Secretary of State stands in the way. We therefore have no serious local accountability, and the one bit of local accountability that we do have gets overridden by the Secretary of State, who refuses to let someone independent look at things.</p>
	<p pid="a.504.0/4">We therefore need to look at serious local, democratic accountability in the NHS, and it will be interesting to find out in the Conservative winding-up speech whether there is anything in the Conservatives' plans, to the extent that they exist, to deal with local democratic accountability and to determine whether the people who make the decisions&mdash;it is rude to call them faceless, but they are the people whom we cannot get rid of&mdash;should be replaced or answerable to elected representatives, because, at the moment, they are not. That is the frustration.</p>
	<p pid="a.504.0/5">We have heard some important points. The hon. Member for Gosport, who secured the debate&mdash;I congratulate him on that&mdash;gave some powerful examples of micro-management and of targets distorting the NHS. I met a woman only this morning who had a specific need to see a particular consultant. She said that she was happy to wait to see the right person, but was told that she could not wait because she would go past the target. She was told that she would be sent to someone else and said that that specialist would not know about her. She was told that that did not matter and that she had to see a consultant so that she would be off the list. She went to see the other consultant, who asked, &quot;What are you doing here? I cannot help you.&quot; She said that she knew that but that she had been sent so that the box could be ticked. That is the sort of absurdity that arises.</p>
	<p pid="a.504.0/6">I was interested to hear from my constituency neighbour, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1850" name="David Drew">the hon. Member for Stroud (Mr. Drew)</phrase>, about the situation in his area. He came up with a criterion with which many of us have sympathy. None of us is emotionally wedded to bricks and mortar. Buildings that were once fit for purpose may no longer be so or may be in the wrong place. No one is saying that nothing must ever change, but we want proper public engagement without a preconceived agenda.</p>
	<p pid="a.504.0/7">It was good to hear the hon. Gentleman and <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" name="David Taylor">the hon. Member for North-West Leicestershire (David Taylor)</phrase>&mdash;the Statler and Waldorf of the Labour Back Benches&mdash;pointing out that Government health policy rhetoric is fine, but the disjunction between the rhetoric and reality shows that the Department of Health is out of touch with what is really happening. The classic example is the White Paper on community hospitals. The disjunction is that when something goes wrong locally, the decision was made locally, but when 500 new or upgraded community hospitals are planned, they are the Government's responsibility. How can both be true simultaneously? The Government are responsible for good news and new hospitals, but bad news and closed hospitals are due to local decision making and nothing to do with the Government. Both cannot be true, so which is?</p>
	<p pid="a.504.0/8">In this very Chamber <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1696" name="Philip Dunne">the hon. Member for Ludlow (Mr. Dunne)</phrase> properly raised the issue of his local community hospitals and <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1382" name="Tony Baldry">the hon. Member for Banbury (Tony Baldry)</phrase> raised another critical point about the absurd division between health and social care. While we have different budgets and something can be shunted into someone else's budget, the welfare of the individual will come second to the financial pressures. Again, the logic of the argument that we have heard today is that budgets should be merged and pooled with a single stream of health and social care funding and democratic, local accountability. Those are two big steps, but that is what I want and it would deal with many of the points raised. We would then have responsive public consultation and effective social and health care.</p>
	<p pid="a.504.0/9">My hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1801" name="Andrew George">the Member for St. Ives (Andrew George)</phrase> properly raised the issue of capacity and the extraordinary situation that when beds are cut, occupancy rates rise well beyond the level at which even experts in infection control believe they can do a good job. There will then be another Government target, initiative and action plan to tackle MRSA or whatever the bug of the day happens to be. There is no joined-up thinking in the whole process.</p>
	<p pid="a.504.0/10"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1905" name="Edward Vaizey">The hon. Member for Wantage (Mr. Vaizey)</phrase> made an important and incisive point about the difference between care closer to home and care in the home. People often slide between the two. It is assumed that we all want care closer to home, but many of us need specialist and local NHS facilities close to where we live that we can get to even when the A34 is blocked. The Government increasingly do not mean beds close to home; they mean people going from their homes to a super-GP clinic or something like that. There is no intermediate step.</p>
	<p pid="a.504.0/11">What is it about community hospitals that we favour? It is localness. Being treated close to home has a medical benefit, because loved ones can pop in and friends and family are nearby. It is the human scale of such hospitals. People do not want one dirty great hospital for the whole county. They want local hospitals where they know the names of the staff and can build a relationship. Caring for people locally is evidence-based medicine on a human scale and takes pressure off the large acute trusts.</p>
	<p pid="a.504.0/12">We must not allow the myth to continue that community hospitals are inefficient and bad value for money. Putting someone in a small community hospital instead of tying up an expensive acute hospital bed is good value for money and good for the individual.</p>
	<p pid="a.504.0/13">We need a merger of health and social care budgets to avoid cost shunting and we need serious local accountability. We also need funding&mdash;funding is not irrelevant&mdash;and I have supported that, but we need more than funding and the Government should listen to what local people are saying because, at the moment, local people have no voice.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.506.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.506.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.506.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1922" speakername="Andrew Murrison" colnum="506"  time="016:09:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060524/halltext/60524h0110.htm#06052454000455">
	<p pid="a.506.0/1">We need to be clear about what we are dealing with. We are dealing with closures that have been prompted by deficits, which is the responsibility of Ministers. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1743" name="Steve Webb">The hon. Member for Northavon (Steve Webb)</phrase> asked what the Conservatives would do to improve accountability. Accountability rests squarely with the Secretary of State for Health who, ultimately, is responsible for the closures that we have seen. Most Conservative Members would, for reasons to which my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1596" name="Peter Viggers">the Member for Gosport (Peter Viggers)</phrase> alluded, attribute the deficits to the actions of the present Government, and I would like the Minister to answer for the 80 or so closures that are threatened up and down the country.</p>
	<p pid="a.506.0/2">I admit a constituency interest. On Friday, I visited the four community hospitals in my constituency, all of which are threatened with the axe. There was a fifth&mdash;Bradford-on-Avon&mdash;but it has already closed. I also visited an EMI&mdash;elderly mental illness&mdash;unit for 26 in-patients in Trowbridge, which caters for a large part of Wiltshire. That, too, is threatened with closure, together with the maternity unit, so I have some sympathy for <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1850" name="David Drew">the hon. Member for Stroud (Mr. Drew)</phrase>. All those facilities will go.</p>
	<p pid="a.506.0/3">The hon. Member for Northavon talked about evidence-based medicine. I do not think he really understands what evidence-based medicine is. There is no evidence that the plans that the primary care trust has produced would do anything other than destroy what we have traditionally enjoyed in my part of Wiltshire&mdash;good local health care. All the evidence suggests that we would lose a great deal and pick up very little in return. The PCT, in the spirit of the age, will talk about taking health care closer to patients, and of course we would all wish to be treated in our home if that were possible.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.507.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.507.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.507.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.507.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.507.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1922" speakername="Andrew Murrison" colnum="507"  time="016:09:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060524/halltext/60524h0110.htm#06052454000457">
	<p pid="a.507.1/1">I agree. What my hon. Friend describes is what Ministers have told us should happen. It is clear from the White Paper that short-term budgetary fixes should not result in the closure of community hospitals, so he is right. I have visited a couple of his local community hospitals and I am as distraught as he is to hear of their closure. We are told that intermediate care teams will sally forth and look after people in their own homes. Come on, we live in the real world. We all know that people will not receive proper hospital care at home. The best that people can hope for is health care in homely settings in the community. That is what people have at the moment in areas that are blessed with community hospitals. I understood from the White Paper that the community hospital model would be expanded across the rest of the country, but it appears that that will not happen. We hear about new-generation community hospitals, but the reality is that well before they appear, we see hospitals such as Bradford-on-Avon and those in my hon. Friend's area closing. At the very least, we are putting the cart before the horse.</p>
	<p pid="a.507.1/2">We have to accept that when those institutions close, a whole generation of health care workers will be lost. People who work in community hospitals are very special. They are often seen to be on the margins of health care, and often they are. They usually work in community hospitals for particular reasons. They choose to work in those hospitals, yet there seems to be an assumption that when the hospitals close, the workers will all march off and rebadge themselves as community nurses or district nurses, or perhaps work in acute centres. Clearly, many of them will not do so and many of the particular skills that they have will be lost. I do not think that the Minister has thought that through adequately.</p>
	<p pid="a.507.1/3">I shall not dwell at length on sham consultations. Suffice it to say that I am as incensed as most other hon. Members who have spoken are that a culture of cynicism should be built up around what should be a perfectly reasonable thing for us to do&mdash;ask people what they want in terms of health care delivery in their locality. I now have to say to my constituents, &quot;Please respond to the primary care trust's consultation because it will take your silence as assent to the plans.&quot; However, most people are reluctant to take part, because they see themselves putting a great deal of time and effort into consultation in good faith and then finding the PCT simply proceeding with an agenda that it created beforehand.</p>
	<p pid="a.507.1/4">The White Paper makes a number of referencesto community hospitals, and it actually refers to Trowbridge community hospital, which is interesting, because under the primary care trust proposals, that is one of the community hospitals that will close. It says, in bold, that</p>
	<p pid="a.507.1/5" class="indent">&quot;PCTs taking current decisions about the future of community hospitals will be required to demonstrate to their SHA that they have consulted locally and have considered options such as developing new pathways, new partnerships and new ownership possibilities.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.507.1/6">There is very little room for weasel words there.</p>
	<p pid="a.507.1/7">There is a delicious irony, because many of the hospitals had what I suppose, in retrospect, were new partnerships, which were created by the communities that they served. They were often the gift of a local benefactor and they have been supported royally over the years through local effort. I am intrigued and, in all candour, I am interested to hear the Minister's take on exactly what those words mean, and to hear how he will encourage new partnerships and new ownership possibilities. What does he have in mind, and how will he make sure that those partnerships happen? I actually think that partnerships are quite an imaginative solution for the future, but they will not happen if the Government do not support them, and they will certainly not happen if PCTs do not support them. His comments on that point would be most welcome.</p>
	<p pid="a.507.1/8">On Monday, the NHS Confederation produced what is best described as a leaflet. It was much trumpeted but it contains very little apart from anecdote, and it does not mention community hospitals at all, really. The issue of what on earth will be done as the number of acute hospital beds continues to be reduced is left hanging in the air, but people will have to go somewhere.</p>
	<p pid="a.507.1/9">Interestingly, a couple of months ago, Dr. Foster, a body that is in some level of partnership with the Department of Health, published a paper in the <i>British Medical Journal</i> that compared health care in America with health care in this country. Of course there are differences between the two countries, but it is instructive to note how much more reliance America puts on intermediate care, and how little time people spend in acute hospitals in America compared with people in this country. America also has greater reliance on intermediate care beds, which of course are cheaper.</p>
	<p pid="a.507.1/10">Health maintenance organisations that manage health care in America are, of course, run by accountants, and they are very exercised by how much health care costs. Primary care trusts are getting it all wrong in trying to save costs by disestablishing the intermediate care level. The Minister looks surprised, but I am surprised that he has not been given the paper by members of Dr. Foster&mdash;they came to see the Opposition Front Bench team earlier this week&mdash;because it has a partnership arrangement with the Department of Health, and it seems that the research is crucial to what we are discussing today. I shall not send it to him, but I point out that it is in the BMJ of March this year, so he can look it up for himself. It seems that we have been given a false prospectus by primary care trusts, which hold that we will save money, as we will, of course, in the very short term, in terms of balancing the books in-year, but in the longer term the result will simply be more cost.</p>
	<p pid="a.507.1/11">We are rusticating cost from one part of the public purse to another. We heard earlier about how social services will bear much of the burden for all this. Likewise, voluntary organisations will pick up the bill for things such as palliative care, and of course carers will pick up a lot of the burden, as well. So when we talk about cost, we must ask: the cost to whom? That is extremely important.</p>
	<p pid="a.507.1/12">I apologise to the hon. Member for Stroud for intervening on him, but we take a particular interest in what is going on in Stroud. I am pleased that his contribution was so powerful, because it is all very well for my hon. Friends to debate the issue, but the fact that someone on the Labour Benches is doing so will, I hope, have more impact on the Minister that we have had hitherto. In connection with Stroud maternity hospital, it will be particularly interesting to hear which of the following holds: the January 2006 operating framework for 2006-07, which said:</p>
	<p pid="a.507.1/13" class="indent">&quot;All NHS organisations should plan to recover deficits for previous years and balance their books for 2006-07&quot;,</p>
	<p pid="a.507.1/14">or the Secretary of State's letter dated <phrase class="date" code="2006-04-12">12 April</phrase> to my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1476" name="Andrew Lansley">the Member for South Cambridgeshire (Mr. Lansley)</phrase>, who was here earlier. That letter says that</p>
	<p pid="a.507.1/15" class="indent">&quot;organisations which are overspending will be required to show improvement and by the end of 2006-7&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.507.1/16">be in monthly balance. That is, monthly expenditure should cancel out or equal monthly income. It will be interesting to know which one of those propositions holds true, because clearly both of them cannot be true. There appears to have been something of a difference, and clearly Gloucestershire is working to the former proposition, not to the latter. That is important in the context of Stroud maternity hospital.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.509.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.509.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.510.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.510.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.510.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.510.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.510.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.510.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.510.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.510.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.511.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.511.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.511.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.511.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.511.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.511.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.511.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.511.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.511.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.511.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.513.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.513.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.514.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.514.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.514.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.514.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.515.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.515.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.515.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.515.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.515.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.515.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.516.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.516.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.517.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.517.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.517.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1858" speakername="Michael Gove" colnum="517"  time="016:41:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060524/halltext/60524h0111.htm#06052462000162">
	<p pid="a.517.0/1">It is a pleasure to serve under your chairmanship today, Mr. Bercow. May I thank my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1610" name="Greg Hands">the Member for Hammersmith and Fulham (Mr. Hands)</phrase> and the Minister, who is in her place, for giving me permission to speak in this debate?</p>
	<p pid="a.517.0/2">As my hon. Friend said, home information packs mark a significant state intervention in the property market, with potentially disruptive consequences for consumer confidence. That is why I would like to give the Minister the opportunity today to try to reassure consumers. Her work is formidable; if one examines the scale of opposition to HIPs, one will see that nearly every interested group in the property market has deep worries about the implementation of the scheme. Independent estate agents, and indeed the National Association of Estate Agents, have outlined deep opposition to the scheme. Only this week, 80 per cent. of building society chief executive officers have said that they believe that HIPs will have a negative impact on the housing market.</p>
	<p pid="a.517.0/3">Why does the Minister believe that that is so? Building society chief executive officers say that HIPs will add costs to the home-buying process, not reassure prospective buyers or speed up the process and reduce the number of properties in the market. If those with a direct stake in the effective functioning of the market are so worried, what can the Minister say to reassure them? It is not just building societies; the Law Society has also signalled its concern, as has the Royal Institution of Chartered Surveyors.</p>
	<p pid="a.517.0/4">The Council of Mortgage Lenders has also tried its best to ensure that the scheme will work, but only this week it spelled out its concerns again. The majority of lenders have made it clear that in a significant number of cases the home condition report, to which my hon. Friend the Member for Hammersmith and Fulham referred, will simply not be enough to guarantee a loan; an evaluation or survey will be required. There will be additional costs for both seller and buyer, additional taxation for the Chancellor and additional pain in the market.</p>
	<p pid="a.517.0/5">The Minister is fond of saying that consumer groups favour the home information pack. Will she tell us which groups&mdash;in the plural&mdash;actually favour the pack? As far as we can see, only one organisation representing consumers has made representations in favour of the pack. Will she tell us on what statistical basis she can say with confidence that consumers welcome it?</p>
	<p pid="a.517.0/6">Talking of a statistical basis, the evidence basis for the introduction of the HIP is, as I am sure we all know, the &quot;Key research on easier home buying and selling&quot; document produced by the Department of the Environment, Transport and the Regions in 1998. However, that evidence was based on fewer than30 transactions. Will the Minister tell us what evidence base she has for her belief that HIPs will bring the benefits of which her Department has boasted?</p>
	<p pid="a.517.0/7">Talking of rigorous evidence, my hon. Friend referred to the need for a dry run. In an answer that the Minister was kind enough to give me, she said that a dry run would operate on an entirely voluntary basis. Indeed, we understand that it will be overseen by the HIPs providers themselves. How can the providers sit as judge and jury in their own case?</p>
	<p pid="a.517.0/8">In November 2004, the Lord Rooker indicated that a compulsory dry run would take place in a local area. Has that promise now been abandoned? Will clear benchmarks and criteria be published by which we can judge the success of the dry run or will providers of the packs will simply be encouraged to give them to buyers, say they have been a tremendous success and allow the Department to proceed willy-nilly without the firm guarantee of consumer confidence that we need? If we are to have a successful dry run we need home inspectors. How many home inspectors are qualified? We know that there are only 200, because of the extensive investigative work of Valerie Elliott, the consumer affairs correspondent of <i>The Times</i>.</p>
	<p pid="a.517.0/9">The Minister says that 4,000 home inspectors are in training. It takes only five days for someone who knows something about property to qualify. However, before Christmas 1,750 people were in training, and five months&mdash;not five days&mdash;later, only 200 have qualified. What guarantees do we have that there will be enough home inspectors and that those people will have any real background in the construction industry, surveying or any of the skills required to provide consumer confidence? Those matters go to the heart of ensuring that the housing market functions effectively.</p>
	<p pid="a.517.0/10">The Minister will be aware that there is a new consensus, led by my right hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1932" name="David Cameron">the Member for Witney (Mr. Cameron)</phrase> and my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1868" name="George Osborne">the Member for Tatton (Mr. Osborne)</phrase>, on the need to increase housing supply and help first-time buyers. It would be a tragedy if that new consensus were disrupted by the introduction of an ill-thought-through intervention in the market. I invite the Minister to join me and <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1410" name="Frank Field">the right hon. Member for Birkenhead (Mr. Field)</phrase> and <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1744" name="Ian Gibson">the hon. Member for Norwich, North (Dr. Gibson)</phrase>, who have signed my early-day motion, and to forge a new cross-party consensus to find a voluntary way forward.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.518.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.518.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.518.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.518.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.519.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.519.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.519.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.519.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.520.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.520.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.520.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.520.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.520.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.520.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.520.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.520.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.520.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.520.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.520.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.520.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.521.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.521.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.522.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.522.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.522.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.522.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.523.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.523.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.524.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.524.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.524.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.524.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.524.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1992" speakername="John MacDougall" colnum="524"  time="017:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/cm060524/halltext/60524h0112.htm#06052462000177">
	<p pid="a.524.1/1">I am pleased to have secured this debate and to have this opportunity to raise the subject of solvent abuse, particularly abuse of cigarette lighter fuel.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/2">I congratulate my hon. Friend the Minister on his new responsibilities. I wish him well and every success.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/3">I welcome the document from the Home Office and the Department of Health, in partnership with the Department for Education and Skills, entitled &quot;Out of Sight?...not out of mind&quot; on children, young people and volatile substance abuse. It is difficult to work out the reason for trends, but I note from page 6 of the document that they seem to exist. In 1993, there was a tremendous amount of substance abuse, particularly in males, which increased slightly in 1994, but generally fell in 1997. I cannot say that that was because of the change in Government, because there seems to have been a dramatic increase from 1997&mdash;with the exception of 1998 when no male death were evident&mdash;when the trend increased again, as opposed to that from 1993 to 1997 when it fell. There must be a reason for that trend and that reason is important in trying to assess how we can deal with this serious matter more effectively.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/4">I bring this Adjournment debate before the Chamber because of the tragic death of my constituent, Lee O'Brien, who died in January 2003 after inhaling lighter fluid. Lee was only 16. I pay tribute to Lee's father, John O'Brien, and his family who set up the Lee O'Brien Solvent Trust&mdash;LOST is, sadly, an appropriate name. I believe, as do Lee's family, that highlighting such tragic cases is educational for young people. The message&mdash;not just legislation&mdash;must go out to young people that solvent abuse, even the first time, can cost them their life, because it is a life-threatening practice.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/5">Lee's family immediately started a campaign calling for a change in the legislation on the sale of solvents so that the terrible tragedy that happened to Lee would be less likely to happen to other young people. The family have campaigned tirelessly and have achieved a great deal. The Queen gave her seal of approval at a gala dinner not long ago to honour pioneers of the nation.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/6">I was pleased to receive John O'Brien and the LOST campaign here in Westminster when we presented a massive petition with more than 15,000 signatures to the Prime Minister at No. 10 Downing street. I tabled an early-day motion, which, with no effort, instantly gained the support and backing of more than 70 MPs who wanted to show that we are dealing with a serious issue.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/7">Lee's death was not an isolated incident. According to Re-Solv, a national organisation that was set up in 1994 to prevent solvent abuse, volatile substances kill more young people than any controlled drug. I would like to thank Re-Solv for all its work on this matter. It works hard with the all-party group on solvent abuse and was established because of the scale of the problem.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/8">Figures from the European Monitoring Centre for Drugs and Drug Addiction reveal that one in seven 15 to 16-year-olds in Britain abuse solvents. Thousands of teenagers are putting their lives at risk by sniffing glue, lighter fluid and other substances. I have heard of some remarkable and inventive cases of youngsters setting fire to plastic bins because the make-up of the bins and the toxic fumes from them can give them a kind of high. Sadly, that inventiveness is all going to the wrong purposes&mdash;purposes that can bring about tragedies.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/9">Some 1,700 deaths related to such substances were recorded among young people in the UK between 1983 and 2000. On average, more than one young person dies in the UK every week because of solvent abuse. More worryingly, great concern remains about the level of deaths among under-18s from the abuse of cigarette lighter fluid. Statistics gathered before 1999, prior to the introduction of regulations on cigarette lighter refills, show that the figures almost doubled in 2000. Butane cigarette lighter refills now account for 64 per cent. of all substance abuse deaths. The statistics go on and on. St. George's hospital medical school's current report provides figures for 2001 on deaths from solvent and volatile substance abuse. For the first time, there was strong evidence that disposable cigarette lighters were involved in substance abuse deaths.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/10">For under-18s, there has been no sustained decrease in deaths since 1999. It is therefore clear that we face a nationwide problem. It is not confined to one area of the UK. Young people remain the group most associated with solvent abuse. Between 1971 and 2000, most deaths from substance abuse occurred in the 14 to 18-year-old range. There are even recorded cases of children under the age of 10 dying from the effects of solvent abuse.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/11">The statistics in the graph show that solvent abusers can be male or female. There seems to be no connection, other than a general trend up and down over the years. Abusers can be male or female, although the graph indicates higher numbers of solvent-related deaths among boys. There is no stereotypical solvent abuser. People who abuse solvents can come from any social, cultural or ethnic background, and we have to take that into account in addressing the problem. We cannot tackle the issue by targeting one problem area. It covers a range of areas and does confine itself to one location or type of person. We must therefore combat the problem nationally.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/12">One of the most distinctive factors about solvent abuse is that the products involved have a legitimate everyday use. The age at which young people experiment with such substance abuse is generally much younger than for controlled substances. We all know that there have been many debates, questions and early-day motions in the House on solvent abuse, and it is time to ask the Government to strengthen the regulations even further, particularly on the sale of cigarette lighter fuel.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/13">Re-Solv was started 10 years ago to combat the problem, and young people are still dying despite its best efforts. There are great antisocial behaviour problems, as well as crime-associated problems, with substance abuse. There are many reports of serious crimes being committed while people are high on lighter fuel. That is not to mention the impact that solvent abuse has on the people around those involved, such as their family, and the wider community.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/14">In Scotland, the Lee O'Brien Solvent Trust&mdash;LOST&mdash;campaign has already prompted the introduction of a test-purchasing scheme, which was piloted in my local region of Fife. It was aimed at stamping out the illegal sale of lighter fluid to young people. Test purchasing should be increased. One crucial method of preventing deaths by inhalation is to investigate vigorously the prospects of making the habit abhorrent. Reducing the cans' capacity would result in there not being enough lighter fuel to achieve a temporary high.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/15">On the preventive side of the problem, a retail campaign working with the British Retail Consortium, the Government and schools is essential to make clear through educational programmes the dramatic and immediate threat that exists, even when someone is inhaling for the first time. It does not take a number of occasions to cause death, as Lee O'Brien showed, tragically.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/16">Encouraging vigilance among shopkeepers not to sell several canisters of lighter fuel at once should be paramount in any campaign by the British Retail Consortium. We have to increase awareness of the tragedy behind the fact that a shopkeeper may make a profit from selling six tins of lighter fuel but the youngster who has purchased them has no intention of using the fuel for lighting cigarettes&mdash;although that in itself would kill them, never mind the inhalation of the fuel. It is quite clear why that purchase is being made, and through the British Retail Consortium we must seek co-operation with shopkeepers to ensure that they are vigilant and wise about discouraging such purchases.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/17">The way forward is much tighter and stricter enforcement of the law. In Staffordshire, the council has three trading standards officers to police the sale of cigarette lighter fuel. Perhaps, therefore, consideration should be given to the nomination of an enforcement agency, which could well be trading standards. It would achieve a great deal if consideration were given to such a measure.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/18">I am sure that the measures that I have outlined, taken together as a package, will make less likely unnecessary deaths such as that of Lee O'Brien. I re-emphasise that there are no safe levels with solvent abuse; as I said, it can kill the first time or the 100th time. As I mentioned, education is vital on the preventive side. With that in mind, I gave evidence to the Scottish Parliament's Public Petitions Committee, recognising, of course, the role of the devolved structures and the differences in terms of the educational role. However, solvent abuse is a UK issue, and consumer legislation is UK-wide. My efforts in Scotland and in Glenrothes have included working with the voluntary sector, and I congratulate all of those bodies on their important, unselfish and caring work.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/19">I congratulate the Home Office and the Department of Health on their findings in the document &quot;Out of Sight?...not out of mind&quot;, which recommends better education, and that we should deal with volatile substances locally and reduce their availability and accessibility. They are commendable areas to emphasise and concentrate on for the future. If we do so collectively, that will make a profound difference in reducing the number of deaths from this appalling practice; young people do not realise the life-threatening nature of the experience that they are about to encounter.</p>
	<p pid="a.524.1/20">I call on Government agencies and Departments to implement the recommendations as soon as possible. All too often, we reach an awareness stage, we collate and note the information and the drive is there to amass the information&mdash;I hope that that drive does not end and that the Minister, in his new position, will take the matter forward with great vigour. It is our task to make children and young people aware and to protect them from such dangers.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24a.527.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2006-05-24b.527.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

