<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.413.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="413"  time="unknown" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_head0">
	[Mr. John McWilliam in the Chair]
</minor-heading>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.413.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="413"  time="unknown" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_head1">
	Scottish Regiments
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.413.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="413"  time="unknown" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_head1">
	<p pid=".413.2/1" class="italic">Motion made, and Question proposed, That the sitting be now adjourned.&mdash;[Mr. Watson.]</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.413.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1333" speakername="Pete Wishart" colnum="413"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew0">
	<p pid=".413.3/1">Here we are again, Mr. Deputy Speaker, back in Westminster Hall with Scottish regiments on the agenda. I wish I could say that it was a pleasure to be here, but given the confusion surrounding the fate of the Scottish regiments, I cannot be that generous. It is the same venue and the same plot&mdash;perhaps I should say the same arms plot&mdash;but with a slightly different cast. In place of the Secretary of State we have the Minister of State, Ministry of Defence, the Armed Forces Minister, who I am sure will respond to the debate in his usual congenial, consensual and constructive manner.</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/2">Before going any further, on behalf of my colleagues I extend sympathy and condolences to the family of Private Paul Lowe, whose funeral will take place today. That follows the funeral yesterday of Scott McCardle and precedes the funeral of Sergeant Stuart Gray. Those three brave young men lost their lives in the deserts of Iraq. I have come to know the Black Watch pretty well during the past few months. It is more than a regiment: it is a community, and I am sure that it will offer all necessary support and comfort to those bereaved families.</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/3">This is our last opportunity to debate the fate of our regiments before the Army Board or the Government meet to decide their fate. It is the last chance that hon. Members will have to put their case for the retention of the regiments. We debated the subject two months ago, so it is worth looking to see whether any real progress has been made. I have considered what has gone on during the past couple of months, listened to some of the debates and read some of the press comments, but I do not know. Are we any clearer about the Government's intentions about the future of the Scottish regiments? Most important, are we any closer to reassuring the many constituents that we represent that the Scottish regiments, to which they have such an attachment, are any closer to being saved?</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/4">The campaign to save our regiments goes on; it has started to grow in strength. Indeed, it has been encouraged during the past couple of weeks because the Government have started to buckle under its pressure. That makes me wonder why the campaign to save our regiments has been so passionate and vocal. The campaign has galvanised communities and has touched every part of Scotland. Every newspaper in Scotland is running a campaign to save the Scottish regiments&mdash;and last week, some prematurely claimed credit for saving them.</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/5">What is it that people like about the regiments? It might be tradition. People like the fact that the regiments have a past, especially the distinguished and illustrious past of our regiments. It might be that our regiments enjoy fantastic community links&mdash;the fact that father, grandfather and son may all have served in the same regiment. It might be that, historically, our regiments have performed an almost unimaginably dangerous task on behalf of us all. I am sure that many shared that sentiment at the Remembrance services on Sunday.</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/6">All that might be true, but the campaign to save the Scottish regiments has an extra potency and bite in Scotland. I do not want to talk about the war in Iraq. I do not want to talk about the deployment of the Black Watch in the American sector. However, we must all recognise&mdash;I choose my words carefully&mdash;that in Scotland the war in Iraq is at best controversial. We can at least say that there was unease about the deployment of the Black Watch in the American sector. It is in that context that the campaign to save the Scottish regiments takes place.</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/7">The thing that the Scottish people singularly cannot understand is that, while those regiments and those brave young men are out there doing the Government's bidding in Iraq, the Government plan to stab them in the back by amalgamating the regiments out of existence. That is a heady brew, and it is particularly unpalatable in Scotland. That is why the campaign is gaining strength. That is also why the Government's attempt to spin and brief their way out of the situation completely backfired last week.</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/8">Yesterday, we heard that the Black Watch may be coming home in advance of the expected date of <phrase class="date" code="2004-12-03">3 December</phrase>. There was even talk of the regiment arriving home in the next few days. Let us hope so; if one group of people deserves to come home before the end of the mission, it is the brave young men who are fighting in the desert. If they remain in the desert, we will at least know that the decision is political. General Walker was quite clear about that yesterday. He said that the decision to keep British troops deployed in Iraq</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/9" class="indent">&quot;would be a political decision and militarily irresponsible.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/10">So, we now know that if the Black Watch does not get home in the next couple of weeks, the decision will have been political. Will the Minister confirm that there is a view to having these brave young men home ahead of schedule?</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/11">That brings us to the politics of what is going on. Just for a moment last week, the Government seemed as if they were prepared to consider the issue seriously and perhaps to offer a few concessions to those of us who care very much about the future of our Scottish regiments. However, that moment disappeared almost as quickly as it had appeared. I am sure that I am not alone in seeing last Tuesday's spinning, briefing and counter-briefing exercise as bordering on appalling. To brief and spin about the future of our Scottish regiments when they stand in the line of fire was a particularly cynical act.</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/12"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1008" name="Eric Joyce">The hon. Member for Falkirk, West (Mr. Joyce)</phrase> scuttled backwards and forwards to Millbank, briefing anybody who was prepared to listen that the Prime Minister and No. 10 were going to get involved, but that was as duplicitous as it was thoroughly wrong. We know how determinedly on message the hon. Gentleman is, and it is unfortunate that he is not here, but as you know, Mr. Deputy Speaker, I had a conversation with him yesterday and I said that I would mention his activities. The hon. Gentleman would not get out of bed for a scuttle without the full tacit acknowledgement and endorsement of No. 10. So, we have to ask why he was put up to it or, if he was not put up to it, why he did it. Finally, why was he left hanging out to dry?</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/13">To the hon. Gentleman's credit, however, he did a fantastic job. I am not praising the things that he did, but he managed to get on the front pages of all the newspapers. The headline in the <i>Daily Record </i>is &quot;Saved&quot;; in <i>The Herald</i>, it was &quot;Blair signals fresh hope for campaign to save regiments&quot;; and in <i>The Scotsman </i>it was &quot;Blair orders MoD to 'save the regiments'&quot;. It was a fantastic exercise, and it was a real credit to the hon. Gentleman that he did such a fantastic job&mdash;the only problem is that the regiments were not saved. The Prime Minister decided that this was not a matter for the Government&mdash;it was a case of &quot;Nothing to do with me, guv.&quot; He actually thought that we would swallow that and that the fate of the British infantry had nothing to do with the British Prime Minister. That has to be the biggest pyramid of piffle since the time of the ancient Egyptians.</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/14">If that is what the Prime Minister thinks, he should perhaps have told his Defence Secretary, who appeared on &quot;Jonathan Dimbleby&quot; on Sunday, saying that he hoped that the Black Watch might get something out of the changes; he thought that it might be able to preserve its name. Of course, he said that it was a matter for the Army Board, but his ambition was that the Black Watch would get something out of the review. So, we have the Prime Minister saying, &quot;It's nothing to do with me, guv&quot;, the Defence Secretary saying, &quot;We've got some ambitions for the Black Watch beyond this change&quot;, and the Army Board seemingly left to make the decision. The problem is that the restructuring of our infantry has everything to do with the Government, because they set the parameters for the review, said that four battalions had to go and made the final decision about the fate of the Scottish regiments.</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/15">The Minister is a member of the Army Board, as is the Secretary of State. Do they just sit in silence when the board deliberates? They could put the case for the Scottish regiments if they were that way inclined, but no&mdash;the only case that we have heard them put in the past few months is the case for amalgamations and disbandment.</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/16">Speaking of the Army Board, I come to our good friend General Sir Michael Jackson. It is probably he who has thwarted the ambitions of the hon. Member for Falkirk, West and other Scottish Members who thought that they had brokered a solution at last Tuesday evening's briefing meeting. Some of my hon. Friends and I were at that meeting, which was hosted by <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1211" name="Mohammad Sarwar">the hon. Member for Glasgow, Govan (Mr. Sarwar)</phrase>, and I found some merit in the case that was put. I could not believe, two hours later, that the meeting, which had been described as a get-out-of-jail clause for the Government, had become the &quot;Saved&quot; clause in the <i>Daily Record.</i></p>
	<p pid=".413.3/17">I do not know what happened in the intervening two hours, but the proposals that were discussed had some serious merit. The idea for the Scottish Brigade&mdash;the coming together with the rest of the regiments&mdash;was reasonably sound. The fact that the Royal Scots and the King's Own Scottish Borderers would be disbanded was very disappointing. There were problems with the solution, and I say that candidly. We saw only two sides of a bit of paper on the proposal; we did not see the details.</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/18">It takes more than a cap badge, a regimental name and a regimental dinner to make a regiment. Community links and recruitment are important. However, there was merit in the compromise; it is even said that the Prime Minister liked the plan. According to Downing street sources, he found it attractive. He thought that it might get him out of a hole&mdash;that, apparently, is what he told General Sir Michael Jackson. Unfortunately, the general was not in a mood to play, and told the Prime Minister that selection and retention of aim is a fundamental principle of war. Seemingly that is military language for &quot;Go and get stuffed.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/19">The general believes that if the Black Watch or any other Scottish regiment is allowed to remain independent, that would run a coach and horses through what he is trying to achieve, the one-regiment solution for the existing Scottish regiments.</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/20">So, what is the future for the Scottish regiments; where does all this chaos and shambles leave us? Well, not in a very satisfactory place. The only encouraging sign that I have detected in the past couple of months is that the Government seem to be buckling under pressure from campaigners. I hope that that pressure will now be piled on until we get a satisfactory response and conclusion.</p>
	<p pid=".413.3/21">I come to my questions to the Minister. Will the Government accept that the future of the Scottish regiments is a matter for Government&mdash;a political decision&mdash;and stop hiding behind the Army Board? Will the Government reject the Jackson plans and respond positively to the widespread and overwhelming opposition to them? Finally, will the Minister or any of his colleagues here this morning look members of the Black Watch, deployed in the desert of Iraq, in the eye and tell them that their regiment has a future?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.416.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1059" speakername="Iain Luke" colnum="416"  time="009:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew1">
	<p pid=".416.0/1">I am glad to be called to make this contribution to the continuing debate on the role and future of the Scottish regiments and commend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1333" name="Pete Wishart">the hon. Member for North Tayside (Pete Wishart)</phrase> for having secured a further debate on the issue. It is highly charged both because of its local implications and because of its significance for the future effectiveness of the British Army.</p>
	<p pid=".416.0/2">On the local side, I am happy to concede that I have major concerns, as do many of my constituents, about the future of our local regiment, the Black Watch, in the light of the MOD's intention to create a Scottish super-regiment. I, and many others, believe that a super-regiment would submerge and eventually extinguish all the individual loyalties, traditions and histories of the Scottish regiments as we know them. That might not matter to the MOD or to General Jackson, but it has created a profound reaction in Dundee, which has traditionally supplied the industrial muscle to balance the rural brawn that recruits from areas such as north Tayside and Perthshire have brought to the regiment.</p>
	<p pid=".416.0/3">I am not sure, Mr Deputy Speaker, whether you have ever been in Dundee, or are aware of the city. I am sure that you are, given that you are well travelled in Scotland.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.417.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1086" speakername="John McWilliam" colnum="417"  time="009:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew2">
	<p pid=".417.0/1">Order. I did work in the Dundee, East by-election.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.417.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1059" speakername="Iain Luke" colnum="417"  time="009:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew3">
	<p pid=".417.1/1">I remember your telling me that, Mr. Deputy Speaker, so you will know that Dundee is an industrious, hardworking, radical town. Throughout its turbulent history, it has faced change and change again. One of the greatest assets of the city is its people. They are very conscious and proud of their family ties; they are creative, determined and, if sometimes prone to internal dispute, united in the face of intrusion from outside the city boundaries.</p>
	<p pid=".417.1/2">Given the long history of recruitment to the Black Watch, virtually every family has a connection with the regiment. My grandfather and great-grandfather served in it. My father, unfortunately, was a Gordon Highlander, but we did not hold against him the fact that he was not one of the &quot;gallant Forty Twa&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".417.1/3">So close is the relationship that many claim that the drumbeat of the Black Watch band echoes the city's collective heartbeat. Indeed, a drum of the Black Watch sits high on a ledge above the city chambers in the city square, where I served in the council for 18 years, commemorating the proud ties between the city and the regiment. The regiment has the freedom of the city of Dundee, and has the right and honour to parade through the city, bayonets fixed, colours flying and drums beating.</p>
	<p pid=".417.1/4">It is to be hoped that on its return from Iraq&mdash;we hope earlier than the prescribed period&mdash;the Black Watch will again take the opportunity, as it has done so many times, to exercise that right and to allow the city to rejoice in its safe homecoming from Iraq following a successful tour of duty. Obviously, the dead will be honoured. I associate myself with the comments made by the hon. Member for North Tayside about the sad funerals taking place, in Fife in the main.</p>
	<p pid=".417.1/5">That would also be a chance for Dundee to renew its commitment to the campaign for the retention of its own regiment: the Black Watch. Many people in Dundee believe that, if the MOD has its way, the spectacle of the Black Watch marching through the city, as is its right, the members of it being freemen of the city of Dundee, will be lost for ever and will become a thing of the past. The opposition that the Minister faces from this part of Scotland should come as no surprise to him. The issue unites politicians from across the political spectrum.</p>
	<p pid=".417.1/6">While stressing the unanimity at a local level, I have to make clear where I diverge from the hon. Gentleman. It has to do with how I see the role of the Scottish regiments, which I hope will&mdash;as is widely speculated and as is touted by my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1008" name="Eric Joyce">the Member for Falkirk, West (Mr. Joyce)</phrase>, who is missing&mdash;be brought together in a Scottish Brigade, serving, as they have throughout their proud history, Crown, flag and country. They make a unique Scottish contribution to the British Army in the service of the monarch and carry out their duty under the Union jack, within which the cross of St. Andrew provides a strong and patriotic background setting. They act in defence and promotion of the interests and security of the United Kingdom: an entity to which, as a Scot, I am deeply committed.</p>
	<p pid=".417.1/7">I am a strong supporter of the British Army and the British Government in their efforts, as active participants in NATO and other alliances, to ensure the security and well-being of all the countries of Europe, and throughout the world. On those points, perhaps I differ with the hon. Member for North Tayside and his party, but we are united in wanting to ensure that the Black Watch is retained as a unit in the British Army.</p>
	<p pid=".417.1/8">The point is: what would be the rationale behind the long histories of those regiments, and what would their brave, selfless and professional service in the British Army amount to if we did not think about those things in the terms that I alluded to earlier when talking about Crown, flag and country? That was the rationale that lay behind my great-grandfather and grandfather joining the ranks of Dundee's regiment, the 42nd Regiment of Foot, in the first and second world wars. Their patriotism was channelled through that regiment and that is why such regiments are so important to the Scottish scene, and why I and so many people are passionate in the cause.</p>
	<p pid=".417.1/9">My concern at the threats to the Black Watch and the reduction from six to five Scottish regiments in the new round of cuts is based not only on my family connections, but on a wider concern that the Government are embarking on the cuts and the reorganisation at a critical time, when the security of this country and our allies is under threat from random attack.</p>
	<p pid=".417.1/10">The message that we, collectively, should send out from this debate is our commitment to campaign for the Scottish regiments to remain as fully functional separate units in a Scottish Brigade, in the British Army, to support the needs and requirements of the UK Government in countering the growing wave of terrorism. I am glad that the hon. Gentleman has put aside his and his party's&mdash;I see his party leader here today&mdash;separatist agenda to join us in putting a strong case for the Scottish regiments to retain their unique identities within the British Army. To assist in that cause, we must combine to put the case.</p>
	<p pid=".417.1/11">In conclusion, I reiterate the call made by my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1211" name="Mohammad Sarwar">the Member for Glasgow, Govan (Mr. Sarwar)</phrase> last week, when he asked the Prime Minister to take note of the concern in Scotland over the future of the Scottish regiments. I further ask the Government to rethink the proposals for the reduction in the strength of the British Army and to do all that they can to promote and encourage recruitment to both regular and territorial units of the Army throughout the UK.</p>
	<p pid=".417.1/12">I call for the Government to signal that they are willing to scrap the proposals to create a royal regiment of Scotland and to commit themselves to creating a Scottish Brigade that all the Scottish regiments will operate under, keeping their individual identities. That is the message that Scotland wishes and waits to hear. It is the message that the Black Watch deserves to hear.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.418.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1086" speakername="John McWilliam" colnum="418"  time="009:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew4">
	<p pid=".418.0/1">Order. I offer no criticism of those who have spoken thus far. I have no power to control the length of Members' speeches, but I remind them that the purpose of the debate is for the Member initiating it to get an adequate reply from the Minister.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.419.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1109" speakername="Patrick Mercer" colnum="419"  time="009:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew5">
	<p pid=".419.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1333" name="Pete Wishart">the hon. Member for North Tayside (Pete Wishart)</phrase> on having procured this debate.</p>
	<p pid=".419.0/2">I want to lay out my credentials. What on earth is an Englishman and a former English Army officer doing here, speaking about Scottish regiments? The answer is simple. I am married to a Skye girl; I served with the Queen's Own Highlanders with great pride and pleasure, despite being described during the whole of a four-month tour in Northern Ireland as &quot;that redcoat&quot;; and a cousin by marriage is about to command the Royal Highland Fusiliers, if it continues to exist.</p>
	<p pid=".419.0/3">It seems extraordinary that at the present time of emergency, difficulty and tension, the Government are planning to axe four infantry battalions&mdash;it does not matter whether they are Scottish, English, or Welsh. The infantryman is the single most flexible soldier in the British Army. Despite the great phrases, &quot;boots in the mud&quot; and &quot;boots in the dust&quot;, technology can never replace the hugely experienced Tommy, Jock or Taffy on the ground, doing his job, killing when necessary, rebuilding when necessary and dishing out sense, kindness and justice wherever he goes. That is what all our soldiers are good at, be they Scottish, English, Welsh or Irish.</p>
	<p pid=".419.0/4">To lose four of our battalions now is madness and I want to challenge two comments by the Prime Minister and the Secretary of State for Defence that the size of the Army is not about to shrink. That is just not true. On <phrase class="date" code="2004-07-21">21 July</phrase>, the Secretary of State for Defence made it very clear that the target for the Army is currently 108,500. The Army has failed to meet that, more of which later, but the new target will be 102,000. Whichever way it is cut&mdash;&quot;cut&quot; is the word&mdash;that is a defence cut. On the back of that, I fear that we shall lose regiments such as the Royal Scots and the King's Own Scottish Borderers, which have survived untainted for 300 years. The Royal Scots came into service in this country in 1633. It has never been amalgamated and has never been merged with any other unit. It has won countless honours and Victoria crosses for this country. Why tinker with a regiment like that? Why tinker with the King's Own Scottish Borderers? That must be wrong.</p>
	<p pid=".419.0/5">A second argument is that recruiting in Scotland cannot support six infantry battalions. That is complete and utter rubbish. The Royal Scots Dragoon Guards&mdash;I know that it is not an infantry battalion&mdash;has been seriously under strength for almost 10 years. When the recruiting restrictions on that fine regiment were removed and it was allowed to spread its wings and to use every tactic and technique allowed to regiments, recruiting to the RSDG rocketed to full manning, only for the Government to slash 100-plus of its well trained men. I believe that any Scottish regiment can bring itself up to full strength if it is allowed to. I did that with my regiment and I am sure that the situation in north Nottinghamshire is no different from that in parts of Scotland. I believe that this country has the potential to maintain six fully manned Scottish infantry battalions, and if the Government would remove the recruiting cap and put the proper resources into the Army Training and Recruiting Agency, that could be achieved. Let us have no more nonsense about recruiting.</p>
	<p pid=".419.0/6">Interestingly, anyone who read <i>The Times</i> <i>on Sunday</i> will have seen a picture of Colin Campbell commanding that famous regiment, the 1st Battalion, the Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders in Crater. It seems that we are stuck in time in some sort of aspic. We seem to be in the same position as in the late 1960s and the Argylls are under threat yet again with a certain officer leaving his regiment to come into Parliament to argue the case for the Argylls. Anyone who looks carefully at the picture will see what he is wearing on his hat. We used to call the Argylls' cap badge a soup plate. That may be slightly rude, but there we are. He does not have an Argylls' cap badge in his glengarry; he has a super-regiment cap badge of the Scottish Brigade, which came into existence in the mid-1960s and was scrapped in the late 1960s because it failed. What are we again to have? Another super-regiment because of tired, thoughtless and exhausted thinking and because no one in the Ministry Defence has been able to produce anything that is fresh and original.</p>
	<p pid=".419.0/7">Yes, we must move forward, the arms plot must go, and more battalions are coming back from Northern Ireland. However, even with the add-back from Ulster and the battalions that are no longer involved in the arms plot, the 24-month gap between battalion deployment tours is nothing like 24 months. It will still average out at less than that.</p>
	<p pid=".419.0/8">That is not right. It is an unfair deal, not just for Jock and Tommy but, more importantly, for the wives and children who need to spend time with those men. That is why recruiting is suffering and people are not staying in the Army. The departure of corporals and sergeants&mdash;experienced men&mdash;adds to the recruiting problem. The Government have embarked on an evil spiral.</p>
	<p pid=".419.0/9">The other greatly misguided comment that we have heard in the past couple of days is that the infantry is already half large regiments and half single battalions. That is not the case. The Prince of Wales's, King's, Guards and Scottish divisions are all single battalion organisations. Only the Queen's and Light divisions have gone down this path.</p>
	<p pid=".419.0/10">If one were to take, let us say, the Argylls and put their name in brackets after the 4th Battalion of the Royal Scots Regiment, would the name and identity survive? Would the tartan, hat and cap badge survive? Ask the Royal Lincolnshire Regiment or the Royal Leicestershire Regiment. Their names were in brackets after battalions of the Royal Anglian Regiment for a while. Where are they now? If one were to go nine miles from my house and try to join the Royal Lincolnshire Regiment, the response would be, &quot;What on earth is that? I have never heard of it.&quot; That regiment, with all its wonderful history, is gone&mdash;it has died.</p>
	<p pid=".419.0/11">The proposal is desperately misguided and dangerous for the country. It dishonours Scotland's dead, and, militarily, it is enormously foolish. I urge the Minister to think in a fresh direction, as it is not yet too late to save those wonderful regiments.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.420.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/757" speakername="Russell Brown" colnum="420"  time="009:58:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew6">
	<p pid=".420.0/1">I shall begin by echoing the comments of <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1333" name="Pete Wishart">the hon. Member for North Tayside (Pete Wishart)</phrase> in paying respect to all those who have lost loved ones in recent months, especially in the terrible conflict in Iraq, in which we are still engaged. I welcome the opportunity to speak in this debate. The hon. Gentleman has managed to achieve another debate some two months after the previous one that was held in Westminster Hall on this very issue. It is basically the same debate, but its name is slightly different.</p>
	<p pid=".420.0/2">I wish to thank the Minister for taking time on two occasions to meet me and talk about this issue. I also wish to put on record my thanks to the Secretary of State for managing to schedule in his diary meetings with me, in particular the meeting last week with three colleagues from the Liberal Democrat party: <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/724" name="Alan Beith">the right hon. Member for Berwick-upon-Tweed (Mr. Beith)</phrase> and the hon. Members for Roxburgh and Berwickshire (Sir Archy Kirkwood) and for Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale (Mr. Moore). There were also ex-serving members of the King's Own Scottish Borderers at that joint meeting. As individuals with a military background, they were allowed to put their case to the Secretary of State, which is very important.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.421.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1119" speakername="Michael Moore" colnum="421"  time="009:58:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew7">
	<p pid=".421.0/1">I acknowledge the hon. Gentleman's comments. The meeting that we had last week was productive. Does he agree that the passion that Donald Fairgrieve and the other KOSB representatives brought to it was very telling? The single most important issue for them was the prospect of the KOSB losing its identity in an ill-judged merger with the Royal Scots, which they found ludicrous, even offensive.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.421.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/757" speakername="Russell Brown" colnum="421"  time="009:58:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew8">
	<p pid=".421.1/1">I thank the hon. Gentleman for his intervention. He is exactly right. His comments return to those made by the hon. Member for North Tayside. It is a matter of communities and the feeling of the wider family. I remember saying to the Secretary of State last week that if we look at the south of Scotland, only one thing links the east coast with the west coast, and that is the King's Own Scottish Borderers. We have our differences in a number of other areas, but that is the one link across the south of Scotland.</p>
	<p pid=".421.1/2">We are all incensed by what appears to be going on and with what the future may hold for our Scottish regiments. I am so incensed that I have even managed, albeit for a couple of minutes, to have a one-to-one-face with the Prime Minister earlier to further make the case. We should leave no stone unturned when it comes to what we feel.</p>
	<p pid=".421.1/3">Doing nothing is not an option. We have all met constituents over recent weeks and months, some of whom have absolutely no contact or connection with the military. Others are widows of ex-serving members of the armed forces and, in my area, of the King's Own Scottish Borderers, or those who have brothers and uncles who have served. Some are serving at the moment. The future of our armed forces has to be secured.</p>
	<p pid=".421.1/4">After the Remembrance day parade and church service in Dumfries on Sunday, it was interesting to take the opportunity to speak to a number of personnel. As one would expect, different people have different views. Some people wanted absolutely no change, but it was good to hear them recount their stories of the time that they served&mdash;10, 15 or 20 years plus, for many of them. They said that they wanted absolutely no change, and that we must secure the individual identity of the King's Own Scottish Borderers.</p>
	<p pid=".421.1/5">Others, when we got into deeper conversation, realised that today's young men and women are perhaps looking for a secure future with the regiment, but realise that serving in the modern Army is different from 15 or 20 years ago. Some of our young men and women spend a significant amount of time with their regiment, and are then drawn away to support other regiments and to supplement and complement what those regiments are doing because of recruitment shortages.</p>
	<p pid=".421.1/6">The question has to be asked: who are we to determine that the same old ways should remain, especially when we consider the future of married personnel? The Government have talked long and hard since they came into power in 1997 about family-friendly policies. We should also, as best we can, have family-friendly policies for those who serve in our armed forces. They are doing a job of work, just like any other member of society who is gainfully employed. Will a political decision be made as soon as we reach the end of the road, or a military decision?</p>
	<p pid=".421.1/7">If we look back to the early 1990s, many of us have been in this situation before, although some of us were not in this place at the time. It happened then. We saw the highland regiments amalgamated; we should consider the difficulties from then until now. Recruitment and retention have been serious problems.</p>
	<p pid=".421.1/8">The thing that sticks in my craw more than anything else is the suggestion by the Scottish Council of Colonels that we should merge the Royal Scots and the King's Own Scottish Borderers. The council has come up with the worst of all scenarios, as far as I am concerned. I do not say that from a political point of view, but the idea beggars belief. To be open and honest about what happened in the early 1990s, there was a regrettable problem with the Royal Scots in terms of its recruitment and retention. A decision was made then not on military grounds but on political grounds to save someone's political neck. That mistake has come back to haunt us today.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.422.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1237" speakername="Robert Smith" colnum="422"  time="009:58:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew9">
	<p pid=".422.0/1">As <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1059" name="Iain Luke">the hon. Member for Dundee, East (Mr. Luke)</phrase> will remember, it was the Gordon Highlanders that paid the price to save that political neck.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.422.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/757" speakername="Russell Brown" colnum="422"  time="009:58:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew10">
	<p pid=".422.1/1">I bow to the hon. Gentleman's greater wisdom. I know that there was a problem that should have been dealt with properly and that there should have been no political shenanigans in the early 1990s.</p>
	<p pid=".422.1/2">From what I can gather from speaking to ex-members of the King's Own Scottish Borderers, it was also said in the early 1990s that the shortfall in some of the other regiments would be made good. Lo and behold, that commitment was not fulfilled. I say to the Minister today what I have said to the Secretary of State previously. If at the end of the process there is a commitment to 36 sound and strong regiments that can do a job at any time for this country, whether that is on behalf of this country or to help another nation, that is what we should aim for. If the commitment is to make up those numbers and regiments, we in the House and throughout the country want to see it fulfilled and not merely swept aside, as has happened in the past.</p>
	<p pid=".422.1/3">I have heard this morning about the issue of names in brackets. The English language is strange, and the use of brackets or parentheses can mean different things to different people. As I have said all along, I want to see young men and women in my locality in southern Scotland&mdash;and further afield, as the footprint for the King's Own Scottish Borderers stretches further than merely south Scotland&mdash;have the opportunity to join our armed forces and the KOSB for many years to come. That is vital.</p>
	<p pid=".422.1/4">If the King's Own Scottish Borderers name has to be retained, we must put the recommendation from the Scottish Council of Colonels in the bid immediately. I have written to General Sir Mike Jackson saying that I believe that we had a positive meeting last week with the Secretary of State for Defence. I made the case in that letter for him to consider what is being said. There are ways out, not just for the Government, the Secretary of State for Defence or the Prime Minister, but for the military, which appears to be making recommendations that make no sense to anyone.</p>
	<p pid=".422.1/5">I hope that the Minister will take on board what has been said today&mdash;I am sure that he will, because he has done so in the past. We are looking for a positive outcome, and it is vital that the individual identities of the regiments remain.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.423.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1086" speakername="John McWilliam" colnum="423"  time="009:58:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew11">
	<p pid=".423.0/1">Order. Three Members are trying to catch my attention, but I cannot call them all. However, if the next two are brief, I can get them both in.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.423.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/724" speakername="Alan Beith" colnum="423"  time="010:09:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew12">
	<p pid=".423.1/1">I thank <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/757" name="Russell Brown">the hon. Member for Dumfries (Mr. Brown)</phrase>. My hon. Friends and I have been glad to work with him in meetings and campaigns about the future of the King's Own Scottish Borderers, including in what I thought was a constructive meeting with the Secretary of State last week.</p>
	<p pid=".423.1/2">The King's Own Scottish Borderers has its regimental headquarters in the barracks in Berwick-upon-Tweed, where its regimental museum and association are also based. The regiment has the freedom of the borough, and it marches through it on Minden day every year and on many other occasions. We are proud of the regiment, which recruits in Berwick, the borders, Dumfries and Galloway, and Lanarkshire. It has an excellent recruiting record: over the past 10 years, it has regularly been the first or second-best recruited Scottish regiment and in the top half of all infantry regiments.</p>
	<p pid=".423.1/3">Regimental pride is of great importance to the community support that former members of a regiment and their families extend to one another and that communities extend to them. It is also a potent factor in recruitment. Although it would be easy to dwell on the sentimental, nostalgic and honourable reasons for keeping the separate identity of the King's Own Scottish Borderers, the reasons that should be persuasive with the Army Board and the Minister are sensible, practical and highly relevant to the future of the Army&mdash;in particular the regiment's ability to recruit throughout the area.</p>
	<p pid=".423.1/4">What came as a real body blow to serving and former members of the regiment, as well as to the local community, was the completely ill-judged proposal to force an amalgamation with the Royal Scots, a regiment that has had serious recruitment difficulties over the years and is being pushed into the merger to deal with that problem. As the hon. Gentleman said, the problem should have been dealt with some time ago and is not a problem for the King's Own Scottish Borderers. Why damage success in this way? The foremost consideration in the minds of everyone concerned with the KOSB is to maintain its identity because of its practical value in recruiting for the British Army and providing good soldiers.</p>
	<p pid=".423.1/5">On closer examination of the figures, one realises that recruitment in some regiments, including the Royal Scots, depends heavily on Commonwealth citizens. Some of them are extremely good soldiers&mdash;for example, Fijians are superb soldiers and we are glad to have them. However, that is also an index of the weaknesses of recruitment in some regiments. The King's Own Scottish Borderers has about nine Commonwealth citizens compared with 89 in the Royal Scots. That is a measure of relative recruitment ability.</p>
	<p pid=".423.1/6">It was a bad day when the Scottish colonels&mdash;the colonel of the King's Own Scottish Borderers was away in Afghanistan&mdash;made a recommendation that did not recognise the key judgment supposed to be at the heart of how to configure these regiments, which is the sustainability of future recruitment. That phrase was used in the official documents concerned. On that count, the KOSB should remain a clearly defined unit of the British Army, preferably a regiment.</p>
	<p pid=".423.1/7">There are alternative solutions for the Royal Scots name. It could go to the brigade, to the overall structure, to the TA or be used in a different kind of merger. However, it certainly does not make sense to sacrifice the qualities of the King's Own Scottish Borderers to find somewhere to put the Royal Scots. Therefore, I hope that the Minister, the Secretary of State and the Army Board have already agreed that they must reconsider the one extremely misguided merger in the Scottish proposals.</p>
	<p pid=".423.1/8">We can all see the writing on the wall and the amount of military pressure for the creation of a single Scottish super-regiment. People have different views on that. Clearly, some problems have to be addressed, such as the ridiculous and inefficient disruptions of the arms plot, and the destruction of the relationship between a regiment and its region, which is particularly marked in England by the circulation of regiments. It is right to address those problems, but some people find it hard to accept that a super-regiment is the right solution.</p>
	<p pid=".423.1/9">Of crucial importance to us in the borders is that the King's Own Scottish Borderers continues to contribute its flow of recruits and its regimental traditions and qualities to the British Army. The borders want that to happen and it is the logical course to follow. Therefore, I ask the Minister to pose the right questions to the Army Board to ensure that the ill-advised recommendation of the Scottish colonels is set aside and the issue is reconsidered.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.424.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/879" speakername="Annabelle Ewing" colnum="424"  time="010:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew13">
	<p pid=".424.0/1">As the Member of Parliament for Perth, where the Black Watch has its regimental headquarters, I am pleased to have been called to speak briefly today. I add my condolences to the family of Private Paul Lowe, whose funeral will take place early this afternoon, and I extend my condolences to the families and loved ones of the other six Black Watch soldiers who have died in Iraq.</p>
	<p pid=".424.0/2">This is a sad day for the Black Watch, but it will also be a historic day for it and the other Scottish regiments because this may be the last opportunity for debate before the Government implement their plans to axe the entire regimental system in Scotland. We should be clear that the ultimate decision lies with the UK Government&mdash;a fact recognised by my constituents, many retired and serving military personnel, and even the Secretary of State for Scotland during Scottish questions on <phrase class="date" code="2004-10-26">26 October</phrase>. It is a pity that neither the Secretary of State nor his deputy, the Under-Secretary of State for Scotland, is present at this important debate.</p>
	<p pid=".424.0/3">We should also be clear that the impetus for the decision came from the Chancellor and his Department. That was recognised by Colonel Tim Collins, who, speaking to the BBC on Sunday, said:</p>
	<p pid=".424.0/4" class="indent">&quot;These reductions are about saving money for the Treasury. It is not about making the army better and it is not about fixing something that is broken.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".424.0/5">We have also heard much from the Government about the arms plot argument. That is the apparent basis for the proposed scrapping of the entire regimental system in Scotland. However, senior military figures including Brigadier Gary Barnett, who retired last year having served as colonel of the Black Watch for the preceding 12 years&mdash;a man, therefore, of immense military experience&mdash;have challenged that purported rationale for the scrapping of the regimental system in Scotland; Brigadier Barnett termed it a red herring. The Minister will be aware of the brigadier's recent detailed submission to the Secretary of State for Defence.</p>
	<p pid=".424.0/6">The proposals make no sense militarily, particularly at a time when there is overstretch of our armed forces. A Black Watch officer serving at Camp Dogwood, directly in the line of fire&mdash;I am not in a position to release his name&mdash;wrote to me and said:</p>
	<p pid=".424.0/7" class="indent">&quot;Recently, the Black Watch moved from Germany to the UK to become the Army's training battalion. In this role, we should train other battalions for operations, but not deploy ourselves. However, for the first time in the Army's history, and because of troop shortages, we have returned to Iraq a year after we left.</p>
	<p pid=".424.0/8" class="indent">The contradiction between deploying the training battalion on the one hand and yet cutting four battalions on the other, needs to be addressed. The Army has a policy of a 24 month tour interval between 6 month tours. And yet we are back here&quot;,</p>
	<p pid=".424.0/9">in Iraq,</p>
	<p pid=".424.0/10" class="indent">&quot;after 12.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".424.0/11">That point was echoed by many other Black Watch soldiers who have written to me from Iraq, young serving soldiers who want their regiment to be retained and who reject utterly the Government's proposal. I will briefly quote one of those young serving soldiers, currently at Camp Dogwood:</p>
	<p pid=".424.0/12" class="indent">&quot;The recent decision to reduce the armed forces can only add to the stress and pressure put on us and our families what with the ever increasing commitments and deployments we are volunteered for. Some of us have been separated from our families for 400 days in the past 2 years.</p>
	<p pid=".424.0/13" class="indent">I am writing to you to fight on my behalf to reverse the decision to reduce our Armed Forces, as I am fighting for my life out here in Iraq in support of the politicians&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".424.0/14">In conclusion, it is clear that the Black Watch wants to keep the regiment. It is also clear that the people of Scotland want to keep the Scottish regiments. Will the Minister take the opportunity afforded to him today to end the endless spin and uncertainty that has caused so much anger and distress among the soldiers and their families? Will he tell us today whether soldiers in the Black Watch are coming home to their regiment, or whether they will be amalgamated out of existence?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.426.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1086" speakername="John McWilliam" colnum="426"  time="010:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew14">
	<p pid=".426.0/1">I thank hon. Members for their co-operation. If <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1211" name="Mohammad Sarwar">the hon. Member for Glasgow, Govan (Mr. Sarwar)</phrase> is brief, I shall call him.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.426.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1211" speakername="Mohammad Sarwar" colnum="426"  time="010:19:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew15">
	<p pid=".426.1/1">I am grateful for the opportunity to speak, and I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1333" name="Pete Wishart">the hon. Member for North Tayside (Pete Wishart)</phrase> on securing this timely debate.</p>
	<p pid=".426.1/2">Hundreds of my constituents have raised the future of the regiments with me in recent weeks. Last Tuesday, I organised a cross-party meeting with my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1059" name="Iain Luke">the Member for Dundee, East (Mr. Luke)</phrase> to discuss the issue with the Keep Our Scottish Battalions campaign. I am grateful to the hon. Member for North Tayside and others who attended that lobbying. We met Clive Fairweather, a former commanding officer of the Scottish Division Depot, and Stuart Crawford, who was previously a lieutenant-colonel in the Royal Tank Regiment. The following day, I asked the Prime Minister about the future of the Scottish regiments during Question Time. My right hon. Friend the Prime Minister and the Minister are certainly aware of the depth of feeling about the issue throughout Scotland.</p>
	<p pid=".426.1/3">I appreciate that the Chief of the Defence Staff is still considering how best to proceed with changes to infantry deployment and that the Army will make its decision soon. I hope that the weight of public opinion in Scotland will lead to a positive response that retains the regiments' unique historic identities and traditions.</p>
	<p pid=".426.1/4">Simply merging Scotland's infantry regiments would be a mistake. Each of them has a proud history of service to our country. The idea of a Scottish Brigade that incorporates our regiments without losing their special identity, as proposed by the Keep Our Scottish Battalions campaign, is worth considering. For centuries, Scottish soldiers have shown professionalism in serving around the world. I am particularly troubled that disbandment could be considered while the Black Watch sees active service in the most dangerous region of Iraq. While the Minister will be aware that I did not support military action in Iraq, we all share a deep respect for those who have served there during the past two years.</p>
	<p pid=".426.1/5">I want to pay tribute to my constituent, Russell Beeston, a Territorial Army soldier in the 52nd Lowland Regiment who was killed 15 months ago in southern Iraq. When I joined thousands of Glaswegians in George square on Sunday, we all remembered his sacrifice and that of the Scots and British serving our country from all our regiments. In Glasgow, the Royal Highland Fusiliers has a proud local history of recruitment in my constituency. That could be lost with the merger.</p>
	<p pid=".426.1/6">I turn now to the training of Scottish recruits. When infantry recruits in both the regular Army and the Territorial Army were trained in Scotland, they were able to maintain close contacts with their families at home. Now all members of the Scottish infantry are trained in Yorkshire and it is more difficult for families to visit or support young recruits. Far more recruits drop out of training. The Minister has always taken a keen interest in improving the standard of training for all recruits throughout the United Kingdom, and we should reconsider training Scottish recruits in Scotland.</p>
	<p pid=".426.1/7">My right hon. Friend the Minister might say that he cannot give us further assurances at this time. The hon. Member for North Tayside and others may consider that this debate is the last chance to make the case for Scotland's regiments and the last opportunity for the Government to make their position clear. I am sure that the Minister is listening carefully to the genuine concerns that have been expressed about the matter. I am also certain that the debate will not be the final word on the matter. Two strong grassroots campaigns will continue to lobby their elected Members of Parliaments about the issue, as will many of our constituents. We must all respond accordingly.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.427.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1185" speakername="Alan Reid" colnum="427"  time="010:23:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew16">
	<p pid=".427.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1333" name="Pete Wishart">the hon. Member for North Tayside (Pete Wishart)</phrase> on securing a second debate on the future of our Scottish regiments. It comes at a particularly appropriate time, a few days after Remembrance Sunday when we commemorated the sacrifice of the men and women who served in our armed forces. That sacrifice continues to this day with the war in Iraq.</p>
	<p pid=".427.0/2">The large number of hon. Members who have contributed to the debate have shown what great importance we attach to the future of our Scottish regiments. For many months, great uncertainty has been hanging over the future of the regiments and that uncertainty cannot be good for morale. The uncertainty started in July when the Secretary of State announced that one Scottish battalion would be axed and that the Army structure would in future consist of regiments made up of two or more battalions. It can be deduced from simple arithmetic that the Government intend to reduce the number of Scottish regiments from six to either one or two.</p>
	<p pid=".427.0/3">I am not arguing that the status quo should prevail for ever. Naturally, time and circumstances change and the Army must change with the times. However, while changing we must keep the best of what we have inherited from past generations, and the British regimental system, based on geographic areas with which people identify, is an important inheritance that we must keep. Surely one of the lessons of Iraq and Afghanistan is the importance of highly trained and motivated infantry. The British regimental system, based on recruitment from geographical areas, has produced the finest infantry soldiers in the world.</p>
	<p pid=".427.0/4">Now is not the time to reduce infantry numbers. In recent years, the infantry has seen action in Iraq, Afghanistan, Sierra Leone, Kosovo and Bosnia and has carried out peacekeeping duties in many other parts of the world. It is also often called on to help out at home, such as during the firefighters' strike and the foot-and-mouth epidemic. That epidemic should serve as a warning for the Government that Army assignments can appear unexpectedly out of the blue. Our armed forces are already overstretched; the future is uncertain, so infantry numbers should not be reduced.</p>
	<p pid=".427.0/5">Many hon. Members have referred to the proposal of the Council of Scottish Colonels to merge the Royal Scots and the King's Own Scottish Borderers into a single battalion, reduce the other four Scottish regiments to battalion status and make the five battalions form one new regiment. I do not know what remit the colonels were given, but it looks suspiciously as if they were told to go into a room, play a form of Russian roulette and not come out until they had decided which two regiments should be merged. The Royal Scots and the KOSB were the regiments that lost out.</p>
	<p pid=".427.0/6">Like all hon. Members who have spoken this morning, I urge the Government to reject the proposal, which would mean a loss of identity for two regiments that have a long and proud tradition of service to the country. The other four regiments would also suffer a loss of identity by being reduced to battalion status. Recruitment is bound to suffer if the six regiments are merged to form one or two large super-regiments. Throughout Scotland, people identify with the local regiment, which in my case is the Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders. That was obvious at Sunday's Remembrance day parade, when the vast majority of veterans were wearing the famous red and white Glengarry. The message from recent history is that abolishing regiments is not a successful strategy. For example, when the Cameronians were disbanded, 17 per cent. of that regiment's soldiers left the Army.</p>
	<p pid=".427.0/7">Several hon. Members have referred to the Scottish Brigade solution. I have a suggestion for the Government that would streamline efficiency but keep regimental identity. They should reverse an earlier round of cuts under which the Scottish division headquarters was moved from Edinburgh castle to Warminster. The existing six Scottish regiments should be kept, but made part of a Scottish division with headquarters in Scotland that has an effective command and control function instead of simply an administrative function, as at present. That would provide a streamlined command and control structure, yet retain the six distinctive Scottish regiments.</p>
	<p pid=".427.0/8">Those regiments have contributed so much to the defence of our country through their long and proud history. If the Government see sense, our six Scottish regiments will remain and make a vital contribution to the country's defence for many years to come.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.428.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/868" speakername="Peter Duncan" colnum="428"  time="010:29:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew17">
	<p pid=".428.0/1">I add my congratulations to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1333" name="Pete Wishart">the hon. Member for North Tayside (Pete Wishart)</phrase>, and I express my sympathy with his remarks on the recent bereavements. They remind us of the high price paid by the British Army, and it has been paid by our forces over generations.</p>
	<p pid=".428.0/2">There is a considerably improved turnout on the Government Back Benches for this debate, which is obviously related to the Minister's appearance today. However, the gap between him and his Back Benchers is tangible. I see plenty of room for <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1008" name="Eric Joyce">the hon. Member for Falkirk, West (Mr. Joyce)</phrase>, if he had managed to join us, and for the Under-Secretary of State for Scotland, who could have joined us today for this important debate for Scotland.</p>
	<p pid=".428.0/3">It is not the first time that we have debated this issue, and if the Government press ahead with their agenda of cuts, it will not be the last. The proposals have upset and astounded many people in Scotland and throughout the UK. Despite the Defence Secretary's attempts to finesse them, there is no doubt that they signal the end of the six Scottish regiments as we know them. Imprecise talk of identities and traditions is no smokescreen for radical change. A cap badge in a super-regiment is no substitute for a single-battalion regiment in its own right. To pretend otherwise is misleading and ultimately futile.</p>
	<p pid=".428.0/4">People have been upset not only by the cuts but by the way in which the Government have handled the issue, especially in recent weeks. In the past month or so, the position has changed more times than I care to remember. First, the Defence Secretary said that the only option was abolition of the Scottish regiments and their merger into one or two super-regiments. Then at Prime Minister's Question Time, the Prime Minister said that no decision had been made. Then at Scottish questions, the Scottish Secretary told me that it was important to take account of public opinion. During First Minister's questions in the Scottish Parliament, the First Minister then said that he supported retention of the regiments, before my colleague David McLetchie caught him out and forced him to admit that he was in favour of the proposals for cuts.</p>
	<p pid=".428.0/5">Last week, the soldiers and their families had to endure the ultimate insult: Downing street sent that loyal foot soldier, the hon. Member for Falkirk, West, on a spin mission to the Scottish press on Tuesday night to say that four of our regiments would be saved in their current form. That was a partial victory, we thought, but it lasted all of 12 hours, until the Leader of Her Majesty's Opposition obtained a response from the Prime Minister declining to back up the Falkirk, West line. Instead, he said again that no decision had yet been made.</p>
	<p pid=".428.0/6">If the No. 10 spin machine believes that communities throughout the south of Scotland can be persuaded to support a compromise involving the loss of two independent historic regiments&mdash;the King's Own Scottish Borderers and the Royal Scots&mdash;it is seriously mistaken. Three hundred years of history and some of the strongest community ties in the British Army cannot be cast aside. My constituents, in particular, will continue to fight any Labour proposal to scrap the KOSBies. I support the traditional regimental structure in Scotland and throughout the British Army, and I will continue to fight for the independence of the KOSB.</p>
	<p pid=".428.0/7">What is happening is simply not good enough. Soldiers, their families and the whole of Scotland need to know what their fate is. I urge the Minister, in replying to the debate, to tell us today when there will be an answer. The Black Watch would especially welcome that. Her Majesty's Opposition realise that the deployment of Black Watch troops to central Iraq was a military request in a time of war, and we stand by the Government in that undertaking. As tragic events have unfolded, we have continued, and will continue, to support the Government when we think that they are taking such hard but necessary decisions. Unlike some in the House, we will never use the deaths of Scottish soldiers as a vehicle to score political points. To do so would be extremely questionable. However, we will continue our campaign, which is ruthlessly focused on saving all six of our historic regiments.</p>
	<p pid=".428.0/8">Scotland's six regiments have battled for Britain for hundreds of years. Our soldiers have fought, bled and died in the name of freedom. In the past century alone, they have protected this island's liberty in two world wars. They have defended our interests in Korea and the Gulf. They have dealt with our internal troubles in Northern Ireland and sought to keep the peace in the Balkans. They have fought to give others, in Afghanistan and now in Iraq, the same freedom as we enjoy. All six regiments have a proud and distinguished history. Four have seen action in the continuing liberation of Iraq. Speculation continues that the Highlanders and the Royal Scots are being readied to go to Iraq, which would mean that all six regiments would shortly have been at the forefront of operations in that theatre.</p>
	<p pid=".428.0/9">As I said, the way in which the Government have treated soldiers and their families, especially those of the Black Watch, disgusts me. Families of troops are well aware that their loved ones live a dangerous if incredibly rewarding life. Our soldiers have wives and children, and mothers and fathers, and they deserve to be treated with the utmost respect and admiration, especially at times of war. That has not happened in the past few weeks. That is why I urge the Government to tell Parliament today when they will announce the final decision on Scotland's regimental structure. If they do not know the date for that, the least they can do is admit it. I hope that between now and then the Government take stock and re-evaluate the consequences of the action they seem intent on taking.</p>
	<p pid=".428.0/10">Let us not pretend that the Army has asked for this. Yesterday, General Sir Mike Jackson said:</p>
	<p pid=".428.0/11" class="indent">&quot;I would much prefer increasing the size of the Army but that's simply not on offer. I can either accept what's on offer&mdash;a reduced size of the Army&mdash;or go.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".428.0/12">This is a political decision that goes right the way up to the Prime Minister. It is not a military decision, and that shows. We would be hard pressed to find an Army man who thought that this was a good idea in any respect.</p>
	<p pid=".428.0/13">If the Government had set out to choose the most inappropriate, ill-informed and insane time to cut our armed forces, they could not have picked a better time than now. We as a nation have been involved in several conflicts in recent years&mdash;not to mention our ever-increasing peacekeeping obligations. Nobody ever said that preserving freedom and helping others to do the same was easy. It comes at a price; that price is maintaining our full fighting force. This is not the first time that cuts in our armed forces have been proposed. However, I cannot remember cuts being proposed at a time of such severe military overstretch. As well as being a wretched betrayal of our troops, it undermines the security of our country.</p>
	<p pid=".428.0/14">Many Members in attendance this morning are committed to saving our Scottish regiments.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.430.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/757" speakername="Russell Brown" colnum="431"  time="010:29:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew18">
	<p pid=".430.0/1">I am listening intently to what the hon. Gentleman is saying, and if he is going to come on to the topic that I am about to mention, I apologise. I have not heard what his party's position is. He is talking about cuts and financial constraints. Is his party in favour of retaining all the regiments in their current form? If his party were in power, how would they achieve that on a declining budget?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.431.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/868" speakername="Peter Duncan" colnum="431"  time="010:29:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew19">
	<p pid=".431.0/1">Our policy certainly is to retain all the regiments as they are at present. I have made that perfectly clear, and I will restate it shortly.</p>
	<p pid=".431.0/2">The hon. Gentleman mentions a declining budget. That contradicts what the Secretary of State for Scotland said yesterday in this Chamber; he suggested that the budget was increasing. The hon. Gentleman and his colleagues should get their figures correct.</p>
	<p pid=".431.0/3">Many Members are committed to saving our Scottish regiments, and I am delighted to see so many of them present. No matter which party they belong to, they must be realistic about how that will be achieved. Scottish National party members argue&mdash;somewhat hypocritically&mdash;for the maintenance of Scotland's full complement in the British Army. That will add to the momentum of our campaign, but in the final analysis whether the six Scottish regiments are retained is a matter of political will-power. The final decision will depend on who is Prime Minister. Members must be realistic and concede that, notwithstanding a humiliating U-turn by the Government, the only way to save the regiments is for the Conservative party to form the Government after the next general election. For the information of <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/757" name="Russell Brown">the hon. Member for Dumfries (Mr. Brown)</phrase>, the Leader of the Opposition has stated that within the very first week of our being in power, the next Conservative Government will reverse any Labour cuts to our Scottish regiments.</p>
	<p pid=".431.0/4">This is a noble cause that is supported by the majority of Scots; even the Minister has to acknowledge that.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.431.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/990" speakername="Adam Ingram" speakeroffice="The Minister of State, Ministry of Defence"  colnum="431"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spmin0">
	<p pid=".431.1/1">I thank <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1333" name="Pete Wishart">the hon. Member for North Tayside (Pete Wishart)</phrase> for securing this debate on the role and future of the Scottish regiments. I also acknowledge the contributions made by my hon. Friends the Members for Dundee, East (Mr. Luke), for Dumfries (Mr. Brown) and for Glasgow, Govan (Mr. Sarwar), by <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/724" name="Alan Beith">the right hon. Member for Berwick-upon-Tweed (Mr. Beith)</phrase>, and by the hon. Members for Argyll and Bute (Mr. Reid), for Newark (Patrick Mercer) and for Perth (Annabelle Ewing), and of course the contribution of <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/868" name="Peter Duncan">the hon. Member for Galloway and Upper Nithsdale (Mr. Duncan)</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid=".431.1/2">In recent debates and elsewhere my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Defence and I have made clear the importance of Scotland's relationship with the armed forces and, more widely, with the Ministry of Defence. I am conscious of the fact that a good number of Members present never attend defence debates. I excuse <phrase class="honfriend" id="unknown" name="MultipleMatch">the hon. Member for Newark and the hon. Member for Mid-Norfolk (Mr. Simpson)</phrase> who, of course, is on the Conservative Front Bench, but I welcome the new converts to the cause of defence. I look forward to them standing side-by-side with the Secretary of State and me when we campaign for more resources for defence, something that they have not done to date.</p>
	<p pid=".431.1/3">The debate centres on the restructuring of the infantry. It is perhaps the most high profile area of change announced in July by my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State. I welcome the opportunity to explain once again what we are doing, why we are doing it and what the implications of not doing it would be.</p>
	<p pid=".431.1/4">I am, of course, aware of the debate that surrounds the future of the Scottish regiments. After all, I represent a Scottish seat. The debate highlights how much the Army matters in Scotland. Scotland's infantry regiments have a proud history and continue to serve this country courageously. That was most recently demonstrated by the Black Watch deployment. I commend the bravery of the deployment and offer my condolences to the bereaved families. This is a sad period for the Black Watch. I accept that everyone in the House supports that sentiment.</p>
	<p pid=".431.1/5">I wish, however, that we could get a bit more honesty from the party that <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1333" name="Pete Wishart">the hon. Member for North Tayside (Pete Wishart)</phrase> represents. The SNP does not want to preserve the Scottish regiments as we know them. It has made it clear that, in an independent Scotland, we would withdraw from NATO and would not participate in EU missions, as they are linked to NATO. The SNP would downgrade the Scottish regiments to occasional peacekeeping missions. It is difficult to know precisely where those missions would be because the SNP opposed what our forces were asked to do in the Balkans, in Afghanistan and in Iraq, and questioned our engagements elsewhere.</p>
	<p pid=".431.1/6">So, I question the motives of the SNP on the issue. I doubt whether its argument is about preserving the capability of the Scottish regiments. I remind the House of the statement made by an SNP spokesman, who called the Union flag &quot;the butcher's apron&quot;. That is an outrageous slur on the courageous men and women of the British Army, not least those serving in the regiments that we are considering. So it is little wonder that I do not take the hon. Member for North Tayside or his party seriously when we are discussing the future of the armed forces.</p>
	<p pid=".431.1/7">Throughout its history, the Army has been subject to change&mdash;sometimes that change has been dramatic. It must evolve and adapt to meet future challenges. The reason is simple. To ignore reality would be foolhardy and damaging to the high standards expected of a modern fighting force. The changes planned for the infantry are part of that evolution. There are two key reasons for those changes.</p>
	<p pid=".431.1/8">The first reason is the conclusion by the Army Board that the infantry arms plot no longer represents the best way to deliver operational capability. I note what the hon. Member for Perth said when praying in aid for a retired brigadier, but the weight of military experience on the Army Board is substantially against her. I expressed my views about where the SNP is coming from. I am only commenting about that particular issue.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.432.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/879" speakername="Annabelle Ewing" colnum="432"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew20">
	<p pid=".432.0/1">Will the Minister of State give way on that point?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.432.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/990" speakername="Adam Ingram" colnum="432"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew21">
	<p pid=".432.1/1">If I have time, I will give the hon. Lady an opportunity to speak.</p>
	<p pid=".432.1/2">I read the report from the brigadier in question and I recognise his considerable experience. However, we must set that against the breadth of experience on the Army Board.</p>
	<p pid=".432.1/3">So, one reason why we are implementing this change is the considerable arguments that have been advanced&mdash;not for the first time&mdash;that there is a need to change the arms plot and dispose of it.</p>
	<p pid=".432.1/4">The second issue is the progress towards lasting peace in Northern Ireland. I will deal with the impact of events in Northern Ireland. The improved security climate helped us judge that we could remove four battalions from the 14,500 troops allocated to the Province. That provided an opportunity to consider how best to organise the Army for expeditionary warfare. The judgment was that the Army would be best served and best prepared for the challenges of the future if infantry battalions were less reliant on reinforcements when deployed on operations and our forces had the right balance of key enablers: logisticians, engineers, signallers and intelligence personnel. We decided that some 550 posts freed up by the change in Northern Ireland would be reinvested into the infantry to develop more robust, resilient units, and the rest would be used to strengthen the key enablers who are crucial to sustainable operational capability.</p>
	<p pid=".432.1/5">However, the most important factor in changes to the structure of the infantry is the decision to end the infantry arms plot&mdash;a process whereby we have moved infantry battalions from role to role and place to place every few years. Although the arms plot maintained broad experience and variety, it also hampered the availability of infantry battalions. Currently, only 26 to 27 of the 40 infantry battalions are available for deployment at any time and some seven to eight battalions&mdash;about 20 per cent. of the total infantry strength&mdash;are unavailable due to the arms plot. I shall give some examples.</p>
	<p pid=".432.1/6">In March 2003, the Highlanders moved to Germany to begin their armoured infantry training, which meant that they were unavailable for some seven months. In September 2003 the Scots Guards began their conversion and were unavailable for six months. The Black Watch has been subject to similar disruption, which was brought home to me recently when I visited Black Watch families in Warminster. Not to put too fine a point on it, that is impractical and inefficient and no one has argued against it today, apart from the hon. Member for Perth. I do not think that anyone can deny its impracticality and inefficiency.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.433.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/879" speakername="Annabelle Ewing" colnum="433"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew22">
	<p pid=".433.0/1">I was quoting Brigadier Gary Barnett, and I am pleased that the Minister recognises his breadth of military experience as a colonel of the Black Watch for some 12 years. The suggestion that the scrapping of the Scottish regiment system is a precondition for the phasing out of the arms plot is, as Brigadier Barnett said, a red herring.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.433.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/990" speakername="Adam Ingram" colnum="433"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew23">
	<p pid=".433.1/1">I suggest that the hon. Lady reads again the totality of what has been argued. If she is now saying that the brigadier accepts the removal of the arms plot, perhaps we have unanimity in the Chamber. Let us understand the importance of what is driving this change: the need to have a more efficient and effective means of utilising our infantry battalions.</p>
	<p pid=".433.1/2">Ending the arms plot will make most of the 36 battalions available for deployment, as opposed to the 26 or 27 at present. The logic and benefits of that change are undeniable. Ceasing the arms plot will increase our operational capability, not reduce it. Doing so will also assist in achieving a more predictable tour interval across the infantry. I do not gainsay some of the problems that we are experiencing in some areas on tour intervals. We are trying to get back into a better balance.</p>
	<p pid=".433.1/3">In future, the battalions will be fixed by role and, largely, by location, which will release the resources that are routinely tied up in moving location or retraining. The Army will, therefore, be more capable and effective, because as well as more battalions being available for operations, the new structure will provide continuity of expertise and role and greater brigade stability. In future career development for officers and senior non-commissioned officers could be much more carefully planned, and individuals would be able to move between battalions for career development and increased breadth of experience. At present that is largely dependent on the role played by an individual battalion, which is restrictive and inefficient.</p>
	<p pid=".433.1/4">I could mention many anecdotal comments that I have heard. I probably meet more members of the armed forces than anyone else&mdash;probably even more than a good number of generals&mdash;because it is the nature of my job to meet them and their families. I have many anecdotes, some from Scottish regiments, many of which come from serving warrant officers, who say &quot;Keep going, because this is about the future Army structure, not about the past Army structure.&quot; We can trade comment on this matter, but the important thing is that the debate is out there and many people realise its benefit. It is about career development and the capacity within the armed forces to best use essential resources.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.434.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1227" speakername="Keith Simpson" colnum="434"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew24">
	<p pid=".434.0/1">Will the Minister give way?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.434.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/990" speakername="Adam Ingram" colnum="434"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew25">
	<p pid=".434.1/1">No.</p>
	<p pid=".434.1/2">Multi-battalion regiments are not a new concept. A substantial part&mdash;we could argue over whether it is half or one third&mdash;is organised that way, and operates effectively. That concept has been a success. Let me make it clear that we value highly the benefits and traditions of the regimental system; that is not in dispute. What is being proposed will not undermine the system, but will underpin it.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.434.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/868" speakername="Peter Duncan" colnum="434"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew26">
	<p pid=".434.2/1">Does the Minister think that a multi-battalion single regiment will assist or take away from Army recruitment in Scotland?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.434.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/990" speakername="Adam Ingram" colnum="434"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew27">
	<p pid=".434.3/1">There is an important debate to be had on that, and I will come to recruitment issues later, but that point is hard to prove one way or the other.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.434.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1227" speakername="Keith Simpson" colnum="434"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew28">
	<p pid=".434.4/1">Will the Minister give way?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.434.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/990" speakername="Adam Ingram" colnum="434"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew29">
	<p pid=".434.5/1">No, because I want to deal with some of the issues raised.</p>
	<p pid=".434.5/2">The frequent moves caused by the arms plot are destructive to family life, and have an adverse impact on retention. It is reflective of the change in wider society that family stability has become much more of an issue for people. As my hon. Friend the Member for Dumfries pointed out, the Government seek to be more family friendly. That is one benefit to ending the arms plot.</p>
	<p pid=".434.5/3">The end of the arms plot will also mean that single-battalion regiments, including the Scottish regiments, will need to reorganise themselves to meet the requirement for regiments of two or more battalions.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.435.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1333" speakername="Pete Wishart" colnum="435"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew30">
	<p pid=".435.0/1">Will the Minister give way?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.435.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/990" speakername="Adam Ingram" colnum="435"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew31">
	<p pid=".435.1/1">If I get time. <i>[Interruption.]</i> Mr. Deputy Speaker, I will give way when I am ready to give way. If hon. Members want me to answer the issues raised&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.435.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1086" speakername="John McWilliam" colnum="435"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew32">
	<p pid=".435.2/1">Order. If the Minister gives way, he gives way; if he does not, he does not.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.435.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/990" speakername="Adam Ingram" colnum="435"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew33">
	<p pid=".435.3/1">If <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1333" name="Pete Wishart">the hon. Member for North Tayside (Pete Wishart)</phrase> rose to apologise for his butcher's apron comment, I may be prepared to accept his contribution.</p>
	<p pid=".435.3/2">I was making the point that the end of the arms plot will have consequences on the structure and organisation of the Army, and on what will then happen to single battalions. My right hon. Friend the Prime Minister has made it clear that no decisions have been made. It is important that the Army is given the opportunity to determine the structure that will best deliver the operational effectiveness that we need. When it is ready, the Army Board will make recommendations on the future organisation of the infantry, with a final decision being announced before the Christmas recess.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.435.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1333" speakername="Pete Wishart" colnum="435"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew34">
	<p pid=".435.4/1">I thank the Minister for tearing himself away from the traditional and usual Ministry of Defence speech. I know that he is an avid reader of the <i>Daily Record</i>; can he therefore account for why we saw those headlines last week? What on earth happened on Tuesday night? Why were the regiments saved on Tuesday night, only to be told that it was nothing to do with the Prime Minister on Wednesday morning?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.435.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/990" speakername="Adam Ingram" colnum="435"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew35">
	<p pid=".435.5/1">I could say, &quot;Stupid boy&quot; to the hon. Gentleman. I wish that he would not ask me to account for newspaper headlines. I do not write the newspapers; I do not even read many of them, because the quality of information imparted is not good and does not deal with the breadth of issues. I take his point that I am an avid reader of MOD speeches. That is because these are important and technical matters, not debating points. The reason why I am setting this out at some length is so that, hopefully, the audience outside the Committee will understand the misrepresentation that has been going on.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.435.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1086" speakername="John McWilliam" colnum="435"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew36">
	<p pid=".435.6/1">Order. This is not a Committee.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.435.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/990" speakername="Adam Ingram" colnum="435"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew37">
	<p pid=".435.7/1">I apologise for that technicality, Mr. Deputy Speaker. I mean outside the arena in which we are debating this issue. We hope also to get our argument over. That is important, because there has been a great deal of misrepresentation and misinformation.</p>
	<p pid=".435.7/2">I answered my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="unknown" name="None">the Member for Glasgow, Govan (Mr. Sarwan)</phrase>, who asked when we would impart that knowledge. I said that the plan is to do so before the Christmas recess.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.436.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1227" speakername="Keith Simpson" colnum="436"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew38">
	<p pid=".436.0/1">Will the Minister give way?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.436.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/990" speakername="Adam Ingram" colnum="436"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew39">
	<p pid=".436.1/1">No, I will not give way to the hon. Gentleman. We have many opportunities to debate these issues in defence debates, and I want to deal with the issues that have been raised this morning.</p>
	<p pid=".436.1/2">We have not set out to destroy the regimental system, or, as some have argued&mdash;although I have not heard it raised in this debate&mdash;to create a corps of infantry. Those accusations are simply not true. The regimental system has served the British Army extremely well, and we recognise that it is at the heart of the British infantry. It is vital that we maintain the traditions of the infantry, but that does not mean that the current structure is the right one for the future. That is where the debate lies.</p>
	<p pid=".436.1/3">Very few regiments and corps exist in the same form today as in the past. There has been a constant process of change and regeneration; new organisations have been created, which have maintained previous traditions while developing their own. Some of Scotland's regiments are perfect examples of that. The Royal Highland Fusiliers, which recruits in my area of East Kilbride, was formed in 1959 from the amalgamation of the Royal Scots Fusiliers and the Highland Light Infantry. They were previously the 21st Regiment of Foot and the 73rd Regiment of Foot. We can see the long traditions when we unravel what is inherent in the amalgamated and reformed regiments. It is important that traditions carry on in the new structures.</p>
	<p pid=".436.1/4">I have no doubt that the new structure for the infantry will not only contain existing geographical linkages, but enhance them. With soldiers and their families having the chance of greater stability, the result can only be even greater identity between regiments and their local communities. It is important that hon. Members understand that the decision to reduce the infantry by one battalion in Scotland and three in England was taken only after careful consideration of a number of factors. It was not a case of members of the Army Board meeting in a smoke-filled room and being told to get on with it: there was careful analysis by military planners and people who have spent all their lives serving their country.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.436.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1211" speakername="Mohammad Sarwar" colnum="436"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew40">
	<p pid=".436.2/1">Will my right hon. Friend give way?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.436.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/990" speakername="Adam Ingram" colnum="436"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew41">
	<p pid=".436.3/1">I will give way in a moment. Had the Army Board looked only at the sustainability of manning, the options for the future of the infantry would be very different.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.436.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1211" speakername="Mohammad Sarwar" colnum="436"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew42">
	<p pid=".436.4/1">Does my right hon. Friend accept that if the historic and unique names of the regiments were lost, that would be detrimental to future recruitment?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.436.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/990" speakername="Adam Ingram" colnum="436"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h01.htm#41117h01_spnew43">
	<p pid=".436.5/1">That becomes a point for debate, and I am coming on to recruitment. Over the past 10 years, compared with other regiments, Scottish regiments have had difficulty recruiting and retaining personnel. Of the six most undermanned regiments in the infantry, four were from the Scottish division. On average, over that period, the Royal Scots were undermanned by 126; the Royal Highland Fusiliers by 69; the King's Own Scottish Borderers by 39; the Black Watch by 73; the Highlanders by 83; and the Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders by 32. That is not a criticism; that is a recognised fact.</p>
	<p pid=".436.5/2">I was speaking to a regimental sergeant-major of the Argylls recently, who said that Scotland cannot sustain six regiments. That was his opinion, but the fact of the matter is that he understands what many people have not grasped: demographic problems are affecting recruiting in Scotland. There is a declining population in the key areas of recruitment. Given the number of Scottish battalions, there is also an imbalance, and they struggle to recruit sufficient personnel. Per head of population, Scottish battalions need to recruit roughly three times the numbers of soldiers than other battalions. These demographics will become much more difficult in future. We must attend to the matter now, as we are thinking of the future.</p>
	<p pid=".436.5/3">I have tried to set out a range of issues that we are addressing within the Ministry of Defence, and I appreciate that there is a deep feeling about these matters. I am conditioned by it too because I represent a Scottish constituency, but I really do question the motives of some who raised the debate.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.438.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="438"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h02.htm#41117h02_head0">
	Benefit Office Closures
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.438.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1279" speakername="Simon Thomas" colnum="438"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h02.htm#41117h02_spnew0">
	<p pid=".438.1/1">I shall commence as the highland retreat beats its way from the Chamber. I am pleased to have the opportunity to introduce a debate on benefit office closures, which are taking place not only in Wales but throughout the United Kingdom. I want to talk in particular about the impact of such closures on service delivery, as Parliament has not yet had an opportunity to explore that aspect&mdash;in fact, we have not had an opportunity to explore any aspect of the closures. The announcement was made at the very last hour on the very last day of the now defunct September recall, and we did not have time to digest it. We returned to our constituencies only to have jobcentre staff furiously phone us on Friday saying, &quot;We must talk.&quot; It is a great pity that there was no consultation with members of the public, staff and unions before the announcement was made.</p>
	<p pid=".438.1/2">Since the announcement, in my constituency&mdash;I am sure that this is reflected throughout the UK&mdash;there has been a wave of concern, protest and real anger that the Government are implementing the plan. The anger has arisen in Wales because we have seen such a proposal before: the Conservative Administration brought in a blueprint for change about 10 years ago. The unions, Welsh Labour MPs, Plaid Cymru and, I am sure, the Liberal Democrats fought it tooth and nail, and we were successful. Benefits Agency offices, local processing facilities and not only jobs but services, too, were kept going in communities. The lack of response, particularly from Welsh Labour Back-Benchers, to the impact of the Labour Government's plans is therefore extremely disheartening.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.438.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1053" speakername="Elfyn Llwyd" colnum="438"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h02.htm#41117h02_spnew1">
	<p pid=".438.2/1">Like me, my hon. Friend is concerned that the bulk of the jobs that are likely to be lost&mdash;some 6,000 of them&mdash;will be lost from an objective 1 area in Wales, and that the whole change is predicated on the idea that the vulnerable in society will make their first contact by telephoning an office.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.438.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1279" speakername="Simon Thomas" colnum="438"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h02.htm#41117h02_spnew2">
	<p pid=".438.3/1">I agree with my hon. Friend, and later I shall expand on that point. It is deeply ironic that whereas high street financial institutions are now reaching out to us saying, &quot;We are opening branches again, you can contact us in person and you can have direct personal customer care,&quot; the Government are saying that any level or quality of service can be delivered via telephone or e-mail. I shall address the effect that that will have on disabled people, people with learning difficulties and the most vulnerable people in society, who use such services.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.438.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1143" speakername="Lembit pik" colnum="438"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h02.htm#41117h02_spnew3">
	<p pid=".438.4/1">It is indeed ironic that the private sector is genuinely decentralising but the public sector is centralising through such closures, and doing so in an entirely arbitrary way. The staffing levels that have been set for the centralised offices bear absolutely no relation to what it is possible to achieve in rural areas such as the hon. Gentleman's and mine. Customers will suffer because accountants are calling the shots.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.439.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1279" speakername="Simon Thomas" colnum="439"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h02.htm#41117h02_spnew4">
	<p pid=".439.0/1">It always pains me to say this, but the hon. Gentleman has a good point. He is right to draw attention to the fact that an arbitrary staffing level has been set for call centres and that it cannot be sustained in rural areas. A whole swathe of territory in mid and west Wales&mdash;I am sure that many other parts of the UK are similarly affected&mdash;of more than 100 square miles, with 350,000 people in it, will not have a single office with a processing facility. All such work will be shoved to what I call the periphery of Wales, but other people prefer to call its main corridors, along the M4 or the A55 in the north. The hon. Gentleman is right to say that the exercise is accountant-driven.</p>
	<p pid=".439.0/2">I wish to thank the staff and the union at my local office, the Aberystwyth benefit office and jobcentre. They have reacted magnificently to this threatening and disturbing news. They have come together and united behind local councillors and organisations such as Access Ceredigion, which is a disability rights organisation in my constituency, and Age Concern. We have persuaded <i>Cambrian News</i>, the newspaper for all mid-Wales, to run a campaign among its readers to retain the services in my constituency&mdash;and, I think, in that of <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1143" name="Lembit pik">the hon. Member for Montgomeryshire (Lembit &Ouml;pik)</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid=".439.0/3">We are discussing public services that at the moment are delivered directly to the public. They are worth fighting for. Civil servants do a decent job and deliver a good-quality service; we should not endanger the quality of services for the most vulnerable and needy.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.439.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/879" speakername="Annabelle Ewing" colnum="439"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h02.htm#41117h02_spnew5">
	<p pid=".439.1/1">In my constituency, the Department for Work and Pensions plans to close the social security office completely, with the loss of 54 jobs. As my hon. Friend rightly says, those people are not faceless bureaucrats; they provide key front-line services to vulnerable members of our society. Does he agree that if the proposed closure goes ahead, it is likely that voluntary bodies and local authority welfare departments will be expected to pick up the pieces on the cheap?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.439.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1279" speakername="Simon Thomas" colnum="439"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h02.htm#41117h02_spnew6">
	<p pid=".439.2/1">I am sure that my hon. Friend is right. As might be expected, all the hon. Members who have intervened have anticipated what I was about to say.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/2">When the pension credit was introduced in my neck of the woods&mdash;I do not know about Perth&mdash;there was a huge increase in the number of pensioners who had difficulty contacting offices and understanding the system. Many pensioners came to see me, but I am sure they were only a fraction of those who approached the citizens advice bureau, the local authority, Age Concern or similar organisations that were trying to pick up the pieces on a voluntary basis, without being properly funded to do so.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/3">It is convenient for the Government, as it has been for many financial institutions, to move the cost of accessing services from themselves to the individual, so that it is members of the public who pay for the national telephone call, the e-mail, to log on to the internet, or to be kept on the line for 10 minutes because the person they are talking to says they cannot find their record or their number. Companies have used that trick and now the Government want to use it as well, but that will not do, because we are talking about people who are receiving what the Government say is the minimum that they should have to live on&mdash;the minimum to which they are entitled because of a disability or other circumstances. There is a real threat in the Government's actions.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/4">Wales has a problem with continuing disability and sickness benefits. Although it has been announced today that unemployment has increased slightly, it has generally decreased; despite that, the uptake of disability and sickness benefits is on the increase in Wales. That could in part have happened because the Benefits Agency has&mdash;rightly&mdash;reformed its culture in the past few years: it no longer refuses to tell people what they are entitled to, as it used to do under the Conservatives. The increase in take-up of such benefits is also due to a trend of moving people off the unemployment register and on to sickness and disability payments. The Government say that they now want to reverse that trend, but it will be difficult to do that and to deal with people without having the staff in the offices who understand what is going on in the community and the reasons why people make such claims.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/5">We expect at least 6,000 job losses across the civil service in Wales. That is what the Public and Commercial Services union has forecast, and I think it is a fair estimate. It is a pro rata forecast based on the fact that we in Wales have a slightly higher number of civil servants per capita than elsewhere in the United Kingdom and a much greater reliance on public sector jobs: about 60 per cent. of our gross domestic product is public sector, compared with the UK average of 40 per cent. We are particularly concerned about the first wave of cuts, which will result in 2,000 jobs being lost as local offices are closed and centralised benefit processing centres are created. Those centres will have the minimum number of employees&mdash;150 or 200&mdash;needed to function. The Government have said that they must have that number of people.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/6">The current system has many virtues. I will talk about my local Benefits Agency office, although practices may vary. The staff there have allocated claimants alphabetically. They know the claimants, so that when someone goes in to consult a member of staff, they talk to a person they met last week, or the week before that, or the previous year. They know that there will be face-to-face contact and that the member of staff will have local knowledge. The fact that the office is local means that a huge support mechanism is in place. In the public meeting that we called to discuss the closure&mdash; a very well attended public meeting in Aberystwyth&mdash;several people said how grateful they were to the staff for helping them, for example, through periods of bereavement when they did not know where to turn. It is difficult to provide that type of help on the phone, and impossible by e-mail. We all know how psychologically important it is to have eye contact with somebody who is in a state of distress and searching for advice and help. That eye contact will be lost if the office is closed.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/7">I hope the Minister will be able to tell me what alternative procedures will be put in place. Obviously, I am arguing against any closures, particularly in mid-Wales, because we need to retain some provision between Llanelli and Wrexham, but if there are to be closures in Wales or elsewhere in the United Kingdom, what arrangements will be made so that a face-to-face service can continue to be delivered?</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/8">With pension credit, surgeries were set up. The only reason that pension credit worked at all in my constituency was that the local service in Swansea made a huge effort to hold local surgeries in the towns and villages of Ceredigion. They are still doing that, but one of the unseen side effects of the new policy that was not much publicised in the announcement is that that service, too, will be reduced. Both benefits processing and the Pension Service are to be hit by a 10 per cent. cut, which will remove the face-to-face link with pensioners. Furthermore, the Child Support Agency is to be hit with up to 50 per cent. cuts in face-to-face services. I have a large pile of CSA cases that I have been wrangling with for four or five years&mdash;I am sure that all hon. Members have similar piles. How much more frustrating will it be it if those individuals are not able to call in to a local office for an update about the problems that they are having with the Child Support Agency? Throughout mid and west Wales we will lose that service.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/9">Owing to historical accident, we in Wales have a higher proportion of claimants than the rest of the UK. Our population is much more geographically dispersed than that of the UK. Closing the Aberystwyth office will mean that there are no offices between Llanelli and Wrexham. People living an area where&mdash;despite the fact that it is rural&mdash;car ownership is lower than average will be asked to travel longer distances.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/10">As my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/879" name="Annabelle Ewing">the Member for Perth (Annabelle Ewing)</phrase> remarked, the change will put pressure on voluntary organisations, councils, politicians and councillors to fill the gap. The primary disability rights organisation in my area, Access Ceredigion, has just lost its local authority funding and it closed last week. At the same time as these cuts are happening, the organisation that brought millions of pounds in extra benefits to Ceredigion is closing. Ten thousand people in Ceredigion claim some form of disability benefit, which is what happens when there is an ageing population in a seaside constituency. Those people will lose their direct contact and their ability to access support through the social fund, bereavement benefit and maternity allowance payments. The whole process will be removed from the local community and relocated at the other end of a phone, where it might not be got hold of.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/11">We all know the history of numerous Government IT projects. One only has to consider the CSA&mdash;and when are the magistrates courts going to get their integrated computer system? I think that that system is about seven years overdue. We are putting a lot of faith in technology. We have kept two magistrates courts in Ceredigion, which shows that we have a record of fighting for local services and keeping them. We will try to do so again.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/12">Services are being replaced by unreliable technology that cannot meet human needs, especially the needs of vulnerable people who are suffering and are uncertain about their rights and their future. As my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1053" name="Elfyn Llwyd">the Member for Meirionnydd Nant Conwy (Mr. Llwyd)</phrase> remarked, it is ironic that this is happening in an objective 1 area&mdash;precisely the type of area that, as the Government acknowledged to the European Union, needs to be uplifted and supported. That means more than just an increase in wage levels in such areas. If people are in need of Government support, they should receive it.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/13">It is doubly ironic that jobs are being lost from Aberystwyth just as the National Assembly decides to decentralise and put jobs back into Aberystwyth. Before anyone thinks, &quot;Oh well, jobs are coming to Aberystwyth so I shouldn't be concerned,&quot; let me point out that the jobs in question were centralised 10 years ago by the Conservatives, so we are getting back only what was centralised by the previous Government, and now a Labour Government are centralising again. We are dealing with fashions and trends that go around but do not actually take service delivery into account. I am particularly concerned about that.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/14">I have had lots of correspondence from those who use the service, and I want to read briefly from one constituent's letter, which I received at the start of the week. My constituent writes:</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/15" class="indent">&quot;As a client of Aberystwyth Benefits Office I am hoping that the Government can be made to 'see sense'&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/16">I agree 100 per cent.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/17" class="indent">&quot;I am . . . on Income Support with a Disability Premium at age almost 58. I have no car&quot;,</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/18">and my constituent lives five miles outside Aberystwyth, in the country.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/19" class="indent">&quot;I have found the staff at Aberystwyth Benefits Office very helpful and I am angry at the thought of them losing their jobs. If saving money is the Government's objective would it not be a better plan to avoid involvement in dodgy wars?&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/20">The public know what is going on, even if some politicians do not.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/21" class="indent">&quot;If the Government can treat Ceredigion in this way, then I really feel the sooner we have control over all decisions for Wales, the better.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/22">That is what is happening. The Government's policy is driving people to nationalism, so perhaps we should support that policy, but the fact is that the cuts are seen as an attack on local services and delivery. People are asking why a Labour Government are introducing them when the Labour party has always stood for local services and delivery and always opposed what the Conservatives have said. I see that there are no Labour Members from Wales present apart from <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1347" name="Huw Irranca-Davies">the hon. Member for Ogmore (Huw Irranca-Davies)</phrase>, who I understand is on duty this morning.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/23">Finally, I turn to future savings. The statement that we received on <phrase class="date" code="2004-09-16">16 September</phrase>&mdash;we have not had anything since&mdash;said simply that the modernisation programme</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/24" class="indent">&quot;will lead to more efficient and effective services for our customers&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/25">That broad statement in no way addresses service delivery. It refers to the Government's objective of saving money, but it does not address the quality of services. However, I want to put on record my understanding that the maintenance and ownership of the buildings has now been put out to Land Securities Trillium Ltd., so when the buildings or offices are closed or run down, there is no huge saving for the Government, because the financial benefits of the offices go to the private company.</p>
	<p pid=".439.2/26">The plans need to be re-examined. It is a disgrace that we have not had an opportunity to debate them in detail in Parliament. I have not been able to go into great detail in the short time available, so I have concentrated on examples from my constituency and mid and west Wales. I know that my hon. Friend the Member for Meirionnydd Nant Conwy is to meet the Minister before long to discuss these matters further. As well as a delivery system for mid and west Wales, we need the Government to think again about how they treat the most vulnerable people in our society.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.443.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1162" speakername="Chris Pond" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Work and Pensions"  colnum="443"  time="011:18:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h02.htm#41117h02_spmin0">
	<p pid=".443.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1279" name="Simon Thomas">the hon. Member for Ceredigion (Mr. Thomas)</phrase> on his impeccable timing in securing the debate&mdash;within hours of learning from the latest employment figures that 103,000 more people in Wales are in work, partly as a result of the contribution of Jobcentre Plus and partly because of the Government's overall macro-economic policies. More than 2 million people throughout the country are better off because of the individual efforts that staff have made in the past two years to help people claim the right benefit to move into work and to ensure that employers get the right people to fill their vacancies.</p>
	<p pid=".443.0/2">I was pleased to see in the <i>Cambrian News</i>, which I often read, that the hon. Gentleman regards the services provided by civil servants in Ceredigion as first class&mdash;indeed, he reiterated that point in his contribution. On their behalf, I thank him for those comments, and I add my own tribute to their work.</p>
	<p pid=".443.0/3">As Members of Parliament, we all have a responsibility and duty to fight to improve services in our local communities, but I say to the hon. Gentleman and to others who have contributed to the debate that fighting to improve services is not the same as fighting to maintain buildings. Through Jobcentre Plus and our range of other services, we are working in new ways. Of course, as we have made clear, the focus is to ensure efficiencies in the provision of services where possible, but it is also to ensure that we provide the highest-possible quality of service to the people whom we serve.</p>
	<p pid=".443.0/4">The ways of working are now different. Gone are the days when we expected jobseekers or pensioners to traipse along to a benefit office to collect their benefit, and then off to an employment office or a jobcentre to look for vacancy information. People physically had to go to the jobcentre to look at a bewildering array of jobs, and had very little support. Jobcentre Plus is not just about offices; it is about the service that we provide, day in, day out, to thousands of people. We are making sure that people can access services without having to go to a Jobcentre Plus office. Comprehensive information is available in local libraries and other places, as well as on the internet. Also, there is a touch-screen service through the job points, an increasing number of which are being installed in convenient locations, including our own offices. They are making more than 400,000 vacancies readily accessible. We are consulting locally on the most appropriate form of provision in each area.</p>
	<p pid=".443.0/5"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1143" name="Lembit pik">The hon. Member for Montgomeryshire (Lembit &Ouml;pik)</phrase> claimed that the changes were being made in an arbitrary way, and the hon. Member for Ceredigion supported him in that.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.444.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1143" speakername="Lembit pik" colnum="444"  time="011:18:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h02.htm#41117h02_spnew7">
	<p pid=".444.0/1">My point&mdash;and, I am sure, the hon. Member for Ceredigion's&mdash;was that the threshold for how many staff are required to make a centre viable is arbitrary. We think that more than 100 members of staff are needed. That threshold is the arbitrary measure that makes it pretty much impossible for any centre in my constituency or the hon. Gentleman's to be viable.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.444.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1162" speakername="Chris Pond" colnum="444"  time="011:18:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h02.htm#41117h02_spnew8">
	<p pid=".444.1/1">Questioning how viable some of our jobcentres are is inevitable, since we are talking about very few staff serving very few people in some jobcentres. However, the numbers are not arbitrary. There is no clear and fixed threshold, although there are guidelines. District managers have to make a decision on how best to provide the highest-quality service to customers in each area. In doing that, they have been consulting with local MPs, local voluntary organisations, staff, the trade unions and many other organisations, including welfare groups, to find out how we can provide our service most efficiently and at the highest quality to the people whom we serve.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.444.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1053" speakername="Elfyn Llwyd" colnum="444"  time="011:18:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h02.htm#41117h02_spnew9">
	<p pid=".444.2/1">I confess that I have not been consulted at all about the closures. Let me mention one thing that disturbs many of us present today: at the beginning of May, the Secretary of State for Work and Pensions met the First Minister in Cardiff, and they discussed a range of subjects, but the Secretary of State did not even mention that the closures were on the horizon. Why did he not even consult the National Assembly for Wales?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.444.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1162" speakername="Chris Pond" colnum="444"  time="011:18:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h02.htm#41117h02_spnew10">
	<p pid=".444.3/1">I understand that the hon. Gentleman is having a meeting in the near future with my ministerial colleague, which will provide an ideal opportunity to run through some of his concerns. We would be happy for other hon. Members who have contributed to this debate to sit down with us and discuss some of the issues face to face, because we all recognise that these are important issues for our constituents. Valuable though today's opportunity to raise the issue is, it is not possible for us to talk through precisely how we will move ahead at local level during such a short debate, especially when we are talking about several different communities.</p>
	<p pid=".444.3/2">In trying to work out the best way forward, our plan is to take account of a wide range of factors in relation to the location of new centres. In some places, such as Aberystwyth, we can refurbish existing premises; in others, we are investing in brand-new acquisitions. We are to open a new 250-seat contact centre in Bangor by December 2005; that contact centre will play a pivotal role in the provision of Welsh language services. I am sure that hon. Members accept that that is one of the ways in which we can improve the provision of Welsh language services in a way that is not always possible through the current office structure. It is also important to stress that the choices remain subject to detailed planning, which is still ongoing. We welcome the discussions with Members on how we should move forward.</p>
	<p pid=".444.3/3">When a full Jobcentre Plus presence is neither practicable nor viable, we will adopt more flexible approaches, such as the installation of job points, the use of telephones that give direct access to our facilities and other services delivered through the premises of some of our partners&mdash;I am talking mainly about local authorities. Such approaches may be particularly helpful in some areas. We can also consider ways&mdash;postal signing, for example&mdash;of helping people who find it physically difficult to make the journey to a Jobcentre Plus building. We are running a pilot to establish how telephone signing might work, while making sure that the tailored provision of the personal adviser service is available to people who are able to visit the jobcentre. Sometimes, we shall be able to meet the travel costs of people who are not on a regular signing cycle so that they can get face-to-face support.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.445.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1279" speakername="Simon Thomas" colnum="445"  time="011:18:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h02.htm#41117h02_spnew11">
	<p pid=".445.0/1">In response to my hon. Friend the Member for Meirionnydd Nant Conwy, the Minister talked about consultation and achieving the best way of delivering services to our communities. The statement of <phrase class="date" code="2004-09-16">16 September</phrase> said clearly that the 37 sites will cease to be viable and will close altogether. Is the Minister now saying that if a strong case can be made on service delivery grounds for retention or for a change in those plans, he and his Department will be open to persuasion?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.445.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1162" speakername="Chris Pond" colnum="445"  time="011:18:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h02.htm#41117h02_spnew12">
	<p pid=".445.1/1">I am saying that we will have real discussions with hon. Members. However, they have to accept the fact that we seek to achieve two objectives: greater efficiency and better-quality provision. The assumption in this debate has been that there is a trade-off between the two, but I believe that we can achieve an improvement in both. We shall be happy to discuss the way forward with hon. Members in more detail than is possible in this debate.</p>
	<p pid=".445.1/2">In the last few minutes remaining, I should like to focus on staff, particularly those in Aberystwyth. That issue was also raised when we had to make rationalisations in office provision. I want to send out the message that we are committed to doing everything that we can to provide help and support for our staff, whose work we value greatly. We shall continue in our discussions with the trade unions. As we have said, redundancy will only be a last resort in this case, as elsewhere. We will do everything we can to help people to relocate, if that is necessary. We are talking to other Government Departments nationally to establish whether there are alternative forms of employment that people could pursue within the public service&mdash;we know of people's commitment to public service. We are currently in discussions with the Welsh Assembly and the Welsh Development Agency to establish whether, given their timetable and ours, we can work more closely together to make sure that jobs are available.</p>
	<p pid=".445.1/3">I emphasise that although we have to rationalise some of our processing procedures, we are increasing the overall number of front-line staff. Jobcentre Plus will increase customer-facing staff by 17 per cent. Through the substantial investment that we have made in recent years, we hope to achieve a more efficient system that will provide a better quality of service for the people whom we serve. That will allow us to continue to deliver a high-quality service, and although any job losses are regrettable, we are doing everything we can to minimise them. At the end of the day, the improvement in efficiency will release resources to make further progress towards achieving the objectives that everyone in this Chamber shares: dealing with the problems of child and pensioner poverty, and getting even closer to full employment than today's figures show.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.445.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="446"  time="011:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h02.htm#41117h02_time2">
	<p pid=".445.2/1" class="italic">Sitting suspended until Two o'clock.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.447.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="447"  time="011:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_head0">
	Lebanon
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.447.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1059" speakername="Iain Luke" colnum="447"  time="014:07:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew0">
	<p pid=".447.1/1">I rise to speak with some trepidation as a relative newcomer to this elevated plane of international relations. I was pleased to secure this debate because I have had a long-standing interest in Lebanon, and the British people have closely followed the issue for decades. Obviously, it was on television much more frequently during the dreadful happenings of the 1970s and 1980s, with the civil war and the Palestinian refugee camps, and the Israeli invasion in the 1980s, followed by occupation and events such as hostage taking, which is now commonplace in Muslim countries such as Iraq and Afghanistan. No one can forget the trials and tribulations experienced by the three hostages, Terry Waite, John McCarthy and Brian Keenan, in Lebanon during the 1980s. I have read all the accounts of their time in captivity when they were stowed away in darkness in a country that is full of light. They inspired this debate and my involvement in the all-party group on Lebanon.</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/2">Issues relating to Lebanon no longer appear so much on our television screens, and some people&mdash;such as Nabih Berri and Walid Jumblatt&mdash;who became household names as leaders of militia groups during the 1970s and 1980s have now moved into mainstream politics. I was a member of the parliamentary delegation&mdash;to which I shall refer later&mdash;and was lucky to visit Lebanon in September to meet both those people and other representatives of political parties in Lebanon.</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/3">One of the reasons why I am speaking in the debate is that I have been involved with the all-party group on Lebanon, which was formed last year to improve relations between ourselves and Lebanon and which has been reasonably active. I know that a lot of its members are not here today because they are abroad or because they have been delayed by the Division, but I want to pay tribute to people such as my hon. Friends the Members for Erith and Thamesmead (John Austin) and for Edmonton (Mr. Love), and the hon. Members for East Devon (Mr. Swire), for South-East Cornwall (Mr. Breed) and for Wantage (Mr. Jackson), who have formed the nucleus of the all-party group. Those people are much more experienced in international relations than me, and they have helped me to feel my way through my role as an office bearer and as part of the deputation that went out to Lebanon in September.</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/4">I want to draw attention to the fact that this is the first time that Lebanon has been debated for a considerable period. The two previous debates took place on <phrase class="date" code="1994-07-15">15 July 1994</phrase>, when John Gunnell, who was then the Member for Morley and Leeds, South, was successful in securing a debate on the refugee problem in Lebanon, and on <phrase class="date" code="1989-07-28">28 July 1989</phrase>. Those debates took place a long time ago and since then there has not been much discussion in Parliament of the situation in Lebanon. It is worth making the point that when <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/751" name="Julian Brazier">the hon. Member for Canterbury (Mr. Brazier)</phrase> stood up on <phrase class="date" code="1989-07-28">28 July 1989</phrase>, he said that he was grateful for the opportunity to have that Adjournment debate. Like the one in 1994, it was a half-hour debate. I am glad to have an hour and a half for this debate, although I know that the Minister is supposed to go to Brussels today, and is stretched in that regard, so I will try to limit my comments.</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/5">The hon. Member for Canterbury said:</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/6" class="indent">&quot;The public view is of a country filled with warring factions all as bad as one another, but I believe that that is not so and that, although no one faction or side is wholly blameless, we can make some sense of Lebanon, and it is in the West's interest, as well as being its duty, to do so.&quot;&mdash;[<phrase class="offrep" id="debates/1989-07-28.1460"><i>Official Report</i>, 28 July 1989; Vol. 157, c. 1460</phrase>.]</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/7">Those words about the west's understanding Lebanon and doing all that it can to aid it are as relevant today as they were then&mdash;even more so given what has happened internally in Lebanon in the past four or five months.</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/8">As part of a deputation from the Inter-Parliamentary Union, I was lucky to visit Lebanon at first hand and meet a wide range of people, from President Lahoud all the way through to people at the grass roots who were involved in health issues throughout the country. It was an interesting and informative visit, which was heavily promoted by our sister organisation in the Lebanese Parliament, the all-party UK friendship group, which is chaired by Mr. Yassine Jaber.</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/9">Yassine Jaber is an influential person. He is an MP for the southern part of Lebanon, which we visited as his guest. We visited the Fatima gate, as many people do, to see the border between Lebanon and Israel. It is a guarded frontier post, from which shots often come, but it was relatively quiet when we were there. Yassine Jaber took a lot of time to show us the country from the north to the south.</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/10">Yassine Jaber has played an influential role in creating in Lebanon a sense of the need to build bridges between the UK and the Lebanese Parliament. He was a Minister at some stage, and since the resignation of Prime Minister Hariri, he has been promoted on a temporary basis&mdash;I believe that the Administration in a formal sense is still being considered. He is now a Minister serving Lebanon. I am sure that, in that post, he will continue to highlight the need for better relationships between us and Lebanon.</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/11">Indeed, that was one of our major aims when we set up the all-party Lebanon group, with the Lebanese ambassador, Mr. Jihad Mortada, in attendance. We were looking to strengthen the ties between our two countries. It is amazing that most of the politicians in Lebanon have a dual existence. Obviously, they are based in Lebanon, but they have strong contacts elsewhere&mdash;many of them with the UK, if not with America and western Europe. They are keen to stress the need for better relationships to be struck between our two countries.</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/12">I also pay tribute to the hon. Members who came on the trip. The leader of the deputation, who cannot be here today, was my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/807" name="Ann Clwyd">the Member for Cynon Valley (Ann Clwyd)</phrase>, who is active on the issue of reconstruction of Iraq. We also had my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1144" name="Diana Organ">the Member for Forest of Dean (Diana Organ)</phrase>, and my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/763" name="Richard Burden">the Member for Birmingham, Northfield (Richard Burden)</phrase>, who is certainly interested in the Palestinian situation. I will refer to that issue in my summing-up.</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/13">It was important that we went and listened to what was being said. We went at a time when things were stable, despite all the troubles of the 1970s, 1980s and 1990s. An impressive range of reconstruction programmes are going on, primarily in Beirut, which is an impressive centre for any country. However, it was also a time when, despite that reconstruction, there was a lot of uncertainty in the country about where it stands politically, and about where politics there stand.</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/14">Just before we arrived, there had been the issue of the extension of President Lahoud's term of office, which was believed by many to be at the behest of the Syrians. That issue certainly caused a lot of controversy. A fairly substantial vote had carried that measure, but a significant number of people in Walid Jumblatt's group, and others&mdash;specifically the Maronite Christians&mdash;were unhappy about it.</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/15">Prime Minister Hariri was under a great deal of pressure while we were in Lebanon. He was the one politician whom we were unable to meet, because he was in Spain accepting an award, from the UN, I think, for the reconstruction of Beirut. He has gone because he was under considerable pressure, and has been replaced on a temporary basis by an MP from Tripoli, Prime Minister Omar Karameh. He has been Prime Minister before, but there are a whole set of uncertainties about the President, the status of the Prime Minister and the relationship between Lebanon and its closest ally and partner, Syria.</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/16">We arrived just after UN resolution 1559 was passed by the General Assembly in New York. That was the major issue of contention. Many people asked why that had been done, especially in Lebanon. There is an outstanding remit for the Syrian troops to leave Lebanon. I tabled an oral question and received a written answer from the Minister on that subject. People accept the need for the Syrians to go at some stage, but they are concerned about the strategic need for some Syrian presence to balance what they see as a threat to their integrity and independence from the Israelis.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.449.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1008" speakername="Eric Joyce" colnum="449"  time="014:07:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew1">
	<p pid=".449.0/1">On that point, my hon. Friend speaks about things flying over the border from the Israeli side. On Monday, two rockets were fired in the other direction, into Israel. My hon. Friend will recognise that our relationship with Lebanon has the Syrian perspective and experience and the Lebanese experience of Syria in Lebanon bound into it. Given that Syria opposes the middle east peace plan, does he not think that if Syria took a more constructive position that would be good for us, the Lebanese and the Syrians?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.449.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1059" speakername="Iain Luke" colnum="449"  time="014:07:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew2">
	<p pid=".449.1/1">I do not support the occupation, and a lot of people were unhappy about the occupation&mdash;or rather the presence, as it is not an occupation, of Syrian troops in the Lebanon. They feel that it is necessary for strategic reasons. It is a breach of the agreements set down in the Taif agreement in 1989, which talked about the eventual withdrawal of Syrian troops. However, there is a great deal of tension. The south of Lebanon is now dominated by the Hezbollah group, which has been on a war footing against the Israelis in the past and has taken the credit for moving the Israelis out of Lebanon. There is a series of tense border issues. The big issue put to us by the Members that we met was that they wished to keep as calm as possible. The Lebanese do not want to get involved in any conflict with Israel. They told us that they want to work constructively to discuss and resolve some of the issues that have been left open by the occupation.</p>
	<p pid=".449.1/2">Water is such an issue. There is a river in the south of Lebanon that flows through parts of the area still occupied by the Israelis, for example the Shebaa farms. That water needs to be used in the north of Lebanon for agriculture and cultivation as well as by the Israelis. The Lebanese want to discuss the arrangements positively with the Israelis.</p>
	<p pid=".449.1/3">There are tensions and the Syrians heighten them, so it is to the benefit of everyone to work for an agreement and that the Syrian presence is removed. It is not merely the Syrian presence that upsets people opposed to such actions in Lebanon. As well as the 15,000 troops placed there as a strategic force to balance out the Israelis, there are rumoured to be about 5,000 intelligence officers or people who are not attached to that force and who have an undue influence in Lebanese civil society. There is a need, under the Taif agreement, struck I think in September 1989, to modernise civil society and bring it up to date to what would be considered an acceptable norm for western countries. There is still progress to be made and the physical reconstruction has perhaps not been mirrored by such modernisation and the withdrawal of the Syrian troops.</p>
	<p pid=".449.1/4">That modernisation is an end goal. People in Lebanon accept that, but they are still worried about strategic issues related to ongoing problems with the Israelis. The point was made that it is only a 45-minute drive from the Israeli border to Damascus. One of the reasons that the troops are there is perhaps to hold back the threat if there were ever a war between those countries again. It is in everybody's interests to find a lasting and peaceful settlement to all the existing issues, and there are problems on all sides.</p>
	<p pid=".449.1/5">The problems I have mentioned were all raised on our visit and resolution 1559 is a specific ongoing issue. Part of our role was to discuss how the parliamentary scene in Lebanon could be safeguarded and improved, and how we could build links and act as a bridge. Lebanon has been a bridge between the west and Arab countries in the middle east, but we wanted to see how we, as parliamentarians from Westminster, could form another part of that bridge and bring about a two-way exchange of knowledge, friendship, understanding and, I hope, economic aspects.</p>
	<p pid=".449.1/6">The political situation is fluid at the moment rather than fixed. A lot of impressive work has been done in Beirut, but there is still a big economic problem. Most of the work has been done on borrowed money and there is a large deficit that will need to be controlled if Lebanon is to make economic progress. Despite the fact that Beirut is a cosmopolitan and westernised city, certain areas in the Beka'a valley, the north and the south, are very rural and poor and need attention. The British Council works in those areas. We did not get a chance to visit any British Council programmes&mdash;we would have liked to do so, but time was short and we needed to address a series of other ongoing issues during our time in Lebanon.</p>
	<p pid=".449.1/7">There is still the question of the 400,000 Palestinian refugees, some of whom have been in Lebanon since 1948, and some have been displaced in subsequent wars. There are issues about their ability to work and discrimination against them. There is a law that Palestinians are not able to hold jobs that would be done by professional people. I was not able to visit camps such as Shatila as the numbers allowed in were restricted, but my Liberal Democrat colleague did.</p>
	<p pid=".449.1/8">We met the United Nations Relief and Works Agency chief in Beirut. He raised the problem of money that has been received from organisations such as the Department for International Development but that cannot be used to put in proper sanitation or to make sure that medical services work properly because of the Lebanese Government blocking it. UNRWA operates all the medical centres and schools for those who live in the camps.</p>
	<p pid=".449.1/9">The British Government can do a lot to help reform and modernisation. The Westminster Foundation for Democracy has been doing a lot of work throughout eastern Europe and the middle east to see how we can assist people to improve and reform their situations. We should be taking a much more active role.</p>
	<p pid=".449.1/10">I come now to the Lebanese economy. We saw quite a bit of wealth in Lebanon. We were guests of the Deputy Prime Minister on his yacht. It would not embarrass the Queen to have such a yacht. He was flying out the next day to raise with the UN his unhappiness with resolution 1559. Such wealth, however, is not mirrored throughout the country.</p>
	<p pid=".449.1/11">We visited a new health centre in the south of the country. Although it was an impressive building, its equipment and treatment left much to be desired. It was a charitable institution, created by the Speaker of the National Assembly, Mr. Berri, and his family. Such institutions are set up by charitable establishments, not through Government or foreign aid.</p>
	<p pid=".449.1/12">The relationship of Syria and Lebanon must be addressed. In answer to a written question, my hon. Friend the Minister stated:</p>
	<p pid=".449.1/13" class="indent">&quot;My Rt hon Friend the Foreign Secretary discussed the implications of UNSCR 1559 with Syrian Foreign Minister Shara'a when they met in London on <phrase class="date" code="2004-10-18">18 October</phrase>. We will work for the withdrawal of Syrian presence and a strengthening of the Lebanese institutions.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".449.1/14">Given that commitment, we would like to see more work done on such matters. My hon. Friend continued:</p>
	<p pid=".449.1/15" class="indent">&quot;We expect all Lebanon's neighbours to respect Lebanon's sovereignty, territorial integrity and independence.&quot;&mdash;[<phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2004-11-09.623"><i>Official Report</i>, 9 November 2004; Vol. 426, c. 623W</phrase>.]</p>
	<p pid=".449.1/16">I sincerely hope that that happens.</p>
	<p pid=".449.1/17">Lebanon has made startling progress since its troubles. To an extent, it is a modern, vibrant society&mdash;more modern than Syria and other middle eastern countries. It is a country that prides itself on its relationship with the west, specifically the United Kingdom. We need to build on that to make sure that we have a strong ally in that area and that peace can emanate from that country throughout the region. I hope that the Government will do whatever they can in that area. I am sure that the all-party group and the Inter-Parliamentary Union will continue their activities. I am glad to have had a chance to initiate a debate on Lebanon and I am looking forward to hearing what others have to say.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.452.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/752" speakername="Colin Breed" colnum="452"  time="014:27:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew3">
	<p pid=".452.0/1">I wish to echo many of the thoughts of the initiator of the debate, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1059" name="Iain Luke">the hon. Member for Dundee, East (Mr. Luke)</phrase>. I congratulate him on securing the debate because, when we returned from the IPU visit to Lebanon, we were all determined to raise issues in connection with that country. We want people to recognise the incredible change that has taken place within Lebanon in the past 10 years or so. It is impressive how the Lebanese have reconstructed Beirut, which so many of us remember from newsreel reports. It is a modern, vibrant city with new shops. It is the sort of place that it was perhaps 25 years ago.</p>
	<p pid=".452.0/2">Although the economy is undoubtedly fragile, improvements are taking place. Since my return, I have noted in the travel press much publicity to attract tourists back to Lebanon. Its enormous wealth of archaeological history would be extremely interesting to many people, and I encourage people to visit that country, which has not been on the tourist destination map for some time, to see its impressive display.</p>
	<p pid=".452.0/3">We received an amazing welcome and hospitality. For some time, Lebanon has felt a little isolated within the world community and it wants to welcome people back to the country. I hope that people will respond. Inevitably, it has difficulties and we caught glimpses of them from time to time. The Syrian influence is a two-edged sword. Clearly, some people feel that the Syrian presence has enabled the country to reach a more stable position and to sort itself out. However, others feel that the Syrians have outstayed their welcome and become rather too engaged in some aspects of public life. A case can be made for both those views.</p>
	<p pid=".452.0/4">Nobody whom we met&mdash;whatever their political stance and whether they were from the poorer or richer end of the economic spectrum&mdash;wanted to go back to how it was 10 years ago. They will do anything that is necessary to ensure that that does not happen. That is the strength of their desire to go forward; they recognise and remember the terrible things that happened during the civil war and do not want to return to that situation. Although things are not perfect, politically or economically, there is a great will and desire to make things better and not to go back.</p>
	<p pid=".452.0/5">Let me say a few words about the Palestinian camps. I was able to visit Shatila. To those who have been to Gaza, I can say that Shatila camp is every bit as bad, except that one can step outside and, within some 25 m, can be on a modern highway with the impressive buildings of an ordinary city, Beirut. Not only Palestinians live in the camp; Syrians, Lebanese and others live there. Nevertheless, there is undoubtedly a need to try to establish some basic living conditions. The camp is in need of proper clean water, sanitation and protected power. It was horrific to see major electric cables snaking along the alleyways, through puddles of water, with five to seven-year-old children playing next to them. Those of us who have been brought up with health and safety measures and security concerns were horrified. Those are some of the basic things that could be achieved. I hope that, whatever difficulties the Lebanese authorities have&mdash;I know that they have some; we discussed the matter with the ambassador&mdash;it will be possible to bring some health and safety measures and basic sanitation and water to the people there, regardless of who they are.</p>
	<p pid=".452.0/6">Let me also mention our visit to the border with Israel. That was an interesting experience, in that there is a wire fence and it is very clear that Israel is on one side and Lebanon is on the other. Inevitably, there is a feeling that &quot;If you stay on your side and we stay on our side, we can get on.&quot; I suspect that there will not be a meeting of minds, but the fact that there is a clear border, respected by both sides, whatever their continuing animosities and political situation, provides an opportunity for peaceful coexistence.</p>
	<p pid=".452.0/7">I hope that many of the things that we saw in Lebanon&mdash;the creation of an agreed border and the maintenance of people living either side of it&mdash;can be translated into the situations in other parts of the middle east that are experiencing difficulties. Beirut can give hope to the sorts of places that we have seen in the occupied territories and now, sadly, in Iraq, in Falluja&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.453.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1008" speakername="Eric Joyce" colnum="453"  time="014:27:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew4">
	<p pid=".453.0/1">Does the hon. Gentleman think that there is a case for persuading Hezbollah to change its behaviour on the border? Was that what he said? We would all want that to happen.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.453.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/752" speakername="Colin Breed" colnum="453"  time="014:27:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew5">
	<p pid=".453.1/1">As I said, there is no doubt that people in Lebanon do not want to go back to the past. They recognise the difficulties but do not want to magnify them. They recognise that there will be differences of opinion, but they certainly do not support a return to violence in any way. I think that some influence can be brought to bear on the militia that still have some camps and still have a presence in Lebanon. I think that they are beginning to understand that the Lebanese people do not want such a situation in their country. They want to get on with their lives, pursue peace, build their economy and get away from the things that we saw in the past. Perhaps they can provide an example to others in the way that they handle the militia and the terrorists within their borders.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.453.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1056" speakername="Andrew Love" colnum="453"  time="014:27:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew6">
	<p pid=".453.2/1">First, I apologise profusely to you, Mr. Deputy Speaker, and to my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1059" name="Iain Luke">the Member for Dundee, East (Mr. Luke)</phrase>, who initiated the debate, for arriving late. I would like to press <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/752" name="Colin Breed">the hon. Member for South-East Cornwall (Mr. Breed)</phrase> on Hezbollah's role on the border. Surely a militia such as Hezbollah should be replaced by the Lebanese army in the border area. That would give confidence to everyone in the region.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.453.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/752" speakername="Colin Breed" colnum="453"  time="014:27:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew7">
	<p pid=".453.3/1">I agree and I hope that such a move will take place. The Lebanese want to control their own security. In line with that, they would ultimately like the Syrian presence to be removed, so that they can deal with the proper security of their own people. That may be a little way ahead, but they are moving in the right direction all the time. To an extent, the passage of time assists the process. As I said, people are determined not to go backwards but to look for ways to improve their democratic processes, which are not perfect as yet, and their internal economy, which is still subject to considerable corruption. People recognise that and are trying to bear down on it. They recognise that they have a critical role to play in the middle east, not least because of the Palestinian refugees who are still within their borders. I wish them well. I was impressed and came away from Lebanon far more optimistic than perhaps I was when I went there. I hope that that optimism will be seen to be well placed as we see the country make progress in future.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.454.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1119" speakername="Michael Moore" colnum="454"  time="014:38:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew8">
	<p pid=".454.0/1">I pay tribute to my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/752" name="Colin Breed">the Member for South-East Cornwall (Mr. Breed)</phrase>, who understands the situation in the middle east and has a strong commitment to it and particularly to issues relating to Palestine, which was reflected in his speech. I pay particular tribute to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1059" name="Iain Luke">the hon. Member for Dundee, East (Mr. Luke)</phrase>, who initiated the debate. He modestly suggested that he was not qualified to do so, but clearly he and his colleagues in the IPU have done the House a very important service through their work in Lebanon. We hope that they will continue and develop that in future.</p>
	<p pid=".454.0/2">Given the time constraints on the Minister and others, and given the strange business in the main Chamber this afternoon, I hope to be brief, although perhaps I shall not quite be finished before the next interruption. I shall seek to avoid repeating points that hon. Members have already made, except in a couple of cases.</p>
	<p pid=".454.0/3">Most of us associate Lebanon with the difficulties of the 1970s, '80s and '90s. That region of the world was barely out of the television headlines, for terribly sad reasons, throughout that period. It has still had its troubles recently, although there has been a great deal of progress. As both contributors so far have highlighted, the economic situation in the country is fragile, even if it is making progress. Many problems still surround the politics of the country, not least because of the complex demographics and the religious mix. All that has been reflected in the recent, slightly difficult goings-on to do with the country's constitutional arrangements. Lebanon has important democratic credentials in a region where that is sometimes a rare experience. Our concern is that what we have seen in recent times might lose the Lebanese people those valuable credentials. The political crisis in the country has created real unease, to a sufficient degree that the United Nations Security Council passed resolution 1559, expressing anxiety about the need for free elections, to disarm the armed militias and for foreign forces to be withdrawn. Syria's 15,000 or so troops are clearly the main concern, and we should certainly like to see them being withdrawn in line with that UN resolution as quickly as possible.</p>
	<p pid=".454.0/4">The security situation in Lebanon is difficult, both internally and because of its strategic significance in the middle east. The proximity of Israel and Syria has led to much conflict and the threat of further conflict. Understandably, Syria has a concern about Lebanon and has been a key player at many of the crucial moments of Lebanon's history and development. However, our fear is that Syria is now overplaying its hand, and must recognise that the concerns of the international community are legitimate by complying with the recently passed resolution.</p>
	<p pid=".454.0/5">It is understandable that Israel has concerns about its own security situation. For decades, Lebanon has been used&mdash;by Lebanese or others&mdash;as a base from which to attack Israel. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1008" name="Eric Joyce">The hon. Member for Falkirk, West (Mr. Joyce)</phrase> rightly pointed out the recent attacks from Hezbollah, and there is evidence that they have developed new technology and new capabilities that can only make that situation more difficult. The whole position centres around, and will come to bear on, the middle east peace process. I conclude by saying that we have heard, since President Bush was re-elected and the Prime Minister visited him, that the middle east peace process will be the cornerstone of their foreign policy. We must hope that we shall see the fruits of that in Lebanon, sooner rather than later.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.455.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1259" speakername="Gary Streeter" colnum="455"  time="014:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew9">
	<p pid=".455.0/1">I start by congratulating <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1059" name="Iain Luke">the hon. Member for Dundee, East (Mr. Luke)</phrase>, not just on securing the debate but on reporting to us on his recent interesting visit to Lebanon. We pay tribute to the work of the all-party Lebanon group, which is designed to increase relations with that country, and we hope that that goes well. Although the hon. Gentleman has described himself as a newcomer to international relations, both in this debate and in others in which he has taken part, he in fact speaks like a veteran and brings depth and understanding to our debates, for which we thank him.</p>
	<p pid=".455.0/2">I also thank <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/752" name="Colin Breed">the hon. Member for South-East Cornwall (Mr. Breed)</phrase>, whom I know well as a near neighbour, for his encouraging report on what the all-party group found in Lebanon on its visit. I am aware that I am about to be interrupted, but I should like to put on the record a few thoughts about that strategic country. In biblical times, the name Lebanon was synonymous with prosperity and riches, and many references to cedars and wine from Lebanon were a tribute to its fertility, fruitfulness and prosperity. It was, perhaps, the most prosperous part of the region.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.455.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1059" speakername="Iain Luke" colnum="455"  time="014:42:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew10">
	<p pid=".455.1/1">The hon. Gentleman refers to the cedars of Lebanon. The Lebanese are still very proud of them, although the actual number of cedar trees is being reduced. There is, however, a very progressive programme&mdash;I do not know how well it is going&mdash;to reforest much of Lebanon with cedars.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.455.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="455"  time="014:44:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_time4">
	<p pid=".455.2/1" class="italic">Sitting suspended for a Division in the House.</p>
	<p pid=".455.2/2" class="italic">On resuming&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.455.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1259" speakername="Gary Streeter" colnum="455"  time="014:56:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew11">
	<p pid=".455.3/1">Sadly, to anyone growing of our generation, the names of Lebanon and Beirut are synonymous with conflict, destruction, civil war and strife. However, we have had a happier report from the two hon. Gentlemen who have just come back from Lebanon. Indeed, since the Taif accord there has been a growing measure of stability in the country, which is extremely welcome. Beirut is once again a bustling and safe city, and prosperity is returning, although, as has been mentioned, Lebanon has a debt overhang problem, which it must tackle. None the less, we welcome those more positive reports and, as we know, there is a strong Lebanese community in the United Kingdom, which makes a positive contribution to this country.</p>
	<p pid=".455.3/2">Issues of concern have been raised, including Hezbollah's continued presence in Lebanon, particularly on the southern border, and its aggressive attitude towards Israel. I hope that the Minister will touch on Government policy towards Hezbollah.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.456.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1056" speakername="Andrew Love" colnum="456"  time="014:56:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew12">
	<p pid=".456.0/1">If one reads the reports about activity at the border, one sees that they normally speak of finely tuned rules working between Hezbollah and the Israeli authorities. Does the hon. Gentleman accept that although there continues to be friction on the border, it is well controlled?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.456.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1259" speakername="Gary Streeter" colnum="456"  time="014:56:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew13">
	<p pid=".456.1/1">I think the hon. Gentleman is right. In the turmoil of the middle east, the current situation on the border is relatively calm and peaceful, although there are incidents. It was he, I think, who suggested that Hezbollah's presence on the border should be replaced by a proper Lebanese border control, and that would be most welcome.</p>
	<p pid=".456.1/2">The continued presence of Syrian forces and Syria's continued reach into Lebanese politics are, of course, matters of concern. We have heard reference to Security Council resolution 1559, which was passed recently and which we support. It would be interesting to hear how the Government intend to continue the conversation with Syria on complying with that resolution. I would be interested in the Minister's assessment of the Lebanese population's attitude towards the Syrian presence. We have heard that it takes some comfort from their presence because of concern about Israeli attitudes, and that is understandable, but it would be interesting to hear the Minister's take on that.</p>
	<p pid=".456.1/3">The hon. Member for Dundee, East expressed concern at recent events, including the extension of President Lahoud's term of office. Such things sometimes happen around the globe, although they nearly always happen in controversial circumstances and nearly always turn out to be a mistake. I would be interested to hear the Government's view of that extension, of the resignation of Mr. Hariri and his Cabinet, and of the implications the new Prime Minister might have for stability in the country.</p>
	<p pid=".456.1/4">It is reassuring to hear from the hon. Member for South-East Cornwall that the people of Lebanon do not want to go back to the old days of strife and civil war, but it would be interesting to know the Government's assessment of the implications for stability of recent changes. We have also heard about recent opportunities for a new initiative on the middle east peace process. Those opportunities are there&mdash;with the Prime Minister's commitment and President Bush's recent words and, we hope, a new Palestinian leader to be elected on <phrase class="date" code="2004-01-09">9 January</phrase>, whom the Palestinian people will get behind and who will support engagement in the peace process and withdrawal from Gaza. All of those things are positive.</p>
	<p pid=".456.1/5">Will the Minister comment on the engagement, or lack thereof, of Syria and Lebanon in the road map and the middle east peace process? Does he think that there should be a greater buy-in to that process by and for them, and that they should be bound to an overall settlement? Does he intend to raise the situation in Lebanon with President Chirac while he is in the country, to see if the President of France can shed any light on the situation, given their long relationship?</p>
	<p pid=".456.1/6">Is not the situation in Lebanon an example of how complex it is to try to increase democracy in the middle east? That country has some kind of elections, but not as we know them. Whatever we do to encourage democracy in any middle east country, or anywhere else in the world, is it not important that any such democracy has its own local flavour and grows out of the community, provided that the rule of law, freedom of speech and some kind of representative governance are part and parcel of that democratic process? It should not be about exporting Westminster or US-style democracies, or about imposing anything on those people; it should be about encouraging their version of democratic principles to take root and take hold.</p>
	<p pid=".456.1/7">Is it not also the case that, of necessity, the pace of change will be slow in most middle east countries, and that we would be mistaken to try to force the pace of change at an unsustainable rate? We can take some encouragement from the progress that Lebanon has made over the past 10 years. It will be interesting to hear the Government's view on the likely impact of recent changes.</p>
	<p pid=".456.1/8">The plight of Palestinian refugees has been mentioned. What future does the Minister think they will have if we are fortunate enough to see some kind of final status agreement reached between Israel and Palestine in the next three to six months? How will that affect the 400,000 Palestinians living in the refugee camp that was described so vividly by the hon. Member for South-East Cornwall? Does the Minister believe that some of them will have the opportunity to return to Palestine or Israel under the right-to-return proposals, or is their future to remain in Lebanon? If so, I strongly support the call for improved facilities for them.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.457.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1179" speakername="Bill Rammell" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs"  colnum="457"  time="015:03:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spmin0">
	<p pid=".457.0/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1059" name="Iain Luke">the Member for Dundee, East (Mr. Luke)</phrase> on securing the debate, throughout which he demonstrated his knowledge and understanding of the political situation in Lebanon. His comments, and those of other hon. Members, showed a degree of modest confidence that progress is being made in the Lebanon; that came through strongly in several hon. Members' contributions. I welcome this chance to set out the Government's view, not only of the difficulty facing the Lebanon, but of the opportunities that exist for it to prosper and make a real contribution to peace and stability in the region.</p>
	<p pid=".457.0/2">Britain has had long, close and constructive relations with the Lebanon. The two countries are joined by ties of affection dating from the Lebanon's achievement of independence, with British support, in 1943. Lebanon's sovereignty and independence continue to be of special importance to us. Lebanon has historically done a great deal to develop modern political thought in the Arab world as a whole, and has brought to that role the tolerance, learning and openness that are marks of its society. Lebanese educational institutions retain their leading place in the region, and the vigorous, lively ethos of the Lebanese media, which enjoys a wide degree of freedom, has been a positive stimulus to the emergence more widely of an increasingly open and free Arab press. Those elements&mdash;modern education and a free press&mdash;are essential to the development of what the people of the region aspire to more than anything else. Many of us who travel to that part of the world would underline that point.</p>
	<p pid=".457.0/3">Democratic forms of government derived from the Arab world's long and rich culture are also important; that relates to the point made by <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1259" name="Gary Streeter">the hon. Member for South-West Devon (Mr. Streeter)</phrase>. Such government does not mean that we simply transplant the systems that we have in the west; it means the emergence of a home-grown version of democracy from the needs and aspirations of an increasingly articulate Arab public opinion&mdash;a version that fits the culture, mores and traditions of the country. That is how the process should go forward.</p>
	<p pid=".457.0/4">I started by describing Lebanon's cultural influence on the region. It would not be enough to consider the situation in Lebanon without setting that in the wider political, international and regional context; that is why Britain attaches particular importance to the health of Lebanon's democratic institutions, which reflect a long tradition of parliamentary rule successfully practised in the region. Those institutions are under pressure at the moment, and our concerns should be directed towards them.</p>
	<p pid=".457.0/5">My hon. Friend raised the issue of United Nations resolution 1559. One of the reasons that led the Government to support that resolution was our concern that foreign intervention in the operation of Parliament, the Government and the judiciary is unacceptable, and is degrading and damaging the ability of Lebanon to face important policy challenges with the necessary commitment and support of the Lebanese people. We share the concern of many Lebanese citizens about corruption in the public sector, the ultimate inability of Governments over a number of years to provide adequate economic and social policies and the weaknesses of the judicial system.</p>
	<p pid=".457.0/6">My hon. Friend asked a question about resolution 1559. I shall paraphrase him; I think that his point was that he recognised the need for Syria to withdraw from Lebanon, but had worries in the short term about the results of complete withdrawal and what would fill the vacuum. In response, I say that we welcome the withdrawal of Syrian troops that has already taken place. With the international community, we will work with the Lebanese Government to assist them in the development of their own security forces. That has to be a key factor. One of the key terms of resolution 1559 is the disarming of the militia, particularly of Hezbollah. A number of hon. Members have raised that issue, which is a key element of the process.</p>
	<p pid=".457.0/7">The concerns that I have addressed are shared by many of Lebanon's other friends abroad. The strategic aim of the European Union's Mediterranean programme and the new European neighbourhood policy, with Britain's full support, is to bring improvements to the quality of governance in countries such as Lebanon. Only with such improvements, based on a strict respect of the rule of law and for Lebanon's independence, will Lebanon be able to meet its many challenges.</p>
	<p pid=".457.0/8">Lebanon borders the European Union, and its stability, prosperity and success, like that of all countries in the region, is a major European interest to which we fully subscribe. That is why Europe is offering assistance to Lebanon in the form of the technical co-operation offered under the European Union-Lebanon association agreement, and that is an important, positive step forward. I believe that that mechanism will soon be ratified. We also have a small bilateral assistance programme, and, as my hon. Friend said, the British Council contributes to education and the cultural industries. As important is the consistent political support that we give the principles of democracy and independence that were recently enshrined in the Security Council resolution to which I referred.</p>
	<p pid=".457.0/9">As my hon. Friend said in his opening comments, Lebanon has an integral role to play in the search for a just and lasting settlement of the conflict between Israel and the Palestinians, which would include a solution to the conflict between Israel and its neighbours Lebanon and Syria. Since the implementation of UN Security Council resolution 425, Lebanon has had no fundamental quarrel with Israel, and that has been a welcome development. The occupation by the latter of Shebaa farms, which Lebanon claims is its territory and which Israel and the United Nations Security Council considers to be Syrian, is as much a symptom as a cause of the continuing tension in the wider region. That and other territorial issues will ultimately be solved by negotiation between the parties concerned, within the road map framework. That has to be the way forward.</p>
	<p pid=".457.0/10">The long-standing division between Israel and Palestine is at the core of the problem in the middle east, but there are associated conflicts that must also be addressed within the road map process.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.459.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1056" speakername="Andrew Love" colnum="459"  time="015:03:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew14">
	<p pid=".459.0/1">I rise to take up the point of <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1259" name="Gary Streeter">the hon. Member for South-West Devon (Mr. Streeter)</phrase>. There appears to be no room in the road map process for some of the states that any solution will have an impact on. That is strongly felt in Lebanon. When the road map process begins again, can efforts be made to involve all the states in the region?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.459.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1179" speakername="Bill Rammell" colnum="459"  time="015:03:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew15">
	<p pid=".459.1/1">That was the point that I was trying to make. The concerns of neighbouring states where there are residual and continuing conflicts that impact on the overall middle east peace process must be taken into account. That is set out in the road map process; those issues must be resolved.</p>
	<p pid=".459.1/2">It is a matter of real concern to us that the Hezbollah militia continues to maintain a state of tension along the blue line, with the encouragement of Iran and Syria and the acquiescence of the Lebanese authorities. Israel also bears its share of responsibility for that tension as a result of its frequent illegal and provocative invasions of Lebanese air space. However, we are discussing Lebanon, and the UN Security Council has made clear the requirement on the Lebanese Government to end the operations of the Hezbollah militia and to extend their effective control over all their territory. That obligation extends equally to those states that fund and support Hezbollah. We urge restraint and good sense from all parties.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.460.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1059" speakername="Iain Luke" colnum="460"  time="015:03:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew16">
	<p pid=".460.0/1">The Minister has referred to Hezbollah, but would he pay tribute to Ayatollah Fadlallah in Lebanon, who is very moderate and preaches co-operation and dialogue between communities&mdash;Sunni, Shi'a and Maronite Christian&mdash;in order to build a new understanding that bridges the religious divides in the country?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.460.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1179" speakername="Bill Rammell" colnum="460"  time="015:03:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew17">
	<p pid=".460.1/1">Progressive voices that preach moderation, tolerance and understanding are to be welcomed from wherever they come.</p>
	<p pid=".460.1/2">We welcome Lebanon's commitment to fighting terrorism, which it recently demonstrated by arresting al-Qaeda terrorists who were planning to attack the Italian embassy in Beirut in September. We would like to help the Lebanese to build a better counter-terrorism capacity within the rule of law, through more effective policing, better border control, and aviation and maritime security. Earlier this year, the Metropolitan police visited Lebanon to review how we might help its internal security force and we are considering how to take that assistance forward. I think that all parties would welcome that.</p>
	<p pid=".460.1/3">I understand that some hon. Members visited the camps housing Palestinian refugees during the IPU visit in September. To echo some of the concerns expressed in the debate, the Government are concerned by the living conditions of Palestinians in camps in Lebanon. We have made that known to the Lebanese Government on a number of occasions. We would welcome action from them to improve the situation of the Palestinian population living in Lebanon by allowing them easier access to education and opportunities for better paid employment.</p>
	<p pid=".460.1/4">Ultimately, the answer to the problem is a permanent peace settlement of which a just resolution of the refugee question would be a part. It would be best if that were pursued as part of the road map. The UK fully supports the Quartet's efforts to achieve a political solution that will deliver a better future for all Palestinians.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.460.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1056" speakername="Andrew Love" colnum="460"  time="015:03:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew18">
	<p pid=".460.2/1">I thank the Minister for his generosity in giving way. I wanted to touch briefly on the Palestinian camps. The important point to stress is that the hopelessness in those camps breeds terrorist activity. If we are not careful, that will become a factor not only in the Lebanese situation, but more widely. It is therefore important that the Government make that entirely clear and known to the Lebanese authorities.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.460.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1179" speakername="Bill Rammell" colnum="460"  time="015:03:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew19">
	<p pid=".460.3/1">I need to be clear: nothing justifies terrorism. Nevertheless, I understand the thrust of my hon. Friend's point. The issue of the injustice felt by refugees in those camps has to be addressed; that was my point. We put our views about the condition of the refugees in those camps to the Lebanese Government.</p>
	<p pid=".460.3/2"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/752" name="Colin Breed">The hon. Member for South-East Cornwall (Mr. Breed)</phrase>, who is leading for the Liberal Democrats, referred to the middle east peace process and the Government's recent initiatives to re-inject some urgency into the process. I can tell him that the issue is genuinely consuming time within Government; it is a real priority for us. Nothing could contribute more towards beginning to rebuild and tackle divisions in the world than finding a solution to conflict in the middle east. However, that is easier said than done, although it is a priority for the Government. The Prime Minister has made it clear that it is a personal priority, and that was a central feature of his discussions with the US President at the end of last week.</p>
	<p pid=".460.3/3">The hon. Member for South-West Devon talked about the Syrian presence flowing from the internationally supported Taif accord. It is important to make it clear that that has contributed to the past decade's stability in Lebanon. The Lebanese people recognise that, but they want to move on. Parliamentary elections are due in 2005, and we are certainly of the view that territorial integrity, independence and democracy in Lebanon are paramount in that process. It is fundamentally for the people of Lebanon to determine their country's relationship with Syria.</p>
	<p pid=".460.3/4">I finish by again congratulating my hon. Friend the Member for Dundee, East on securing this debate, which has allowed us to discuss a number of issues affecting Lebanon. As highlighted by the recent UN Security Council resolution, it remains a country of great interest to the United Kingdom and the wider international community. My hon. Friend referred to the fact that it has been a long time since there has been an Adjournment debate on the subject, and I hope that it will not be too long before we have another opportunity. I also thank all hon. Members involved in this debate for their co-operation in helping me with my personal commitment to get to a train in time.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.461.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1086" speakername="John McWilliam" colnum="461"  time="015:03:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h03.htm#41117h03_spnew20">
	<p pid=".461.0/1">I should explain what is about to happen. In this place, time is relative&mdash;well, it is relative anyway, in a mathematical sense, but in this place it is very relative. The next debate is due at 3.30 pm, as we have now caught up the time lost. If there is a Division before then, the sitting will be suspended for 15 minutes from the start of that Division. That Division has to be no later than 3.31 pm precisely. The sitting is suspended.</p>
	<p pid=".461.0/2" class="italic">Sitting suspended.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.462.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="462"  time="015:18:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h04.htm#41117h04_head0">
	Guantanamo Bay (UK Detainees)
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.462.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/916" speakername="Roger Godsiff" colnum="462"  time="015:23:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h04.htm#41117h04_spnew0">
	<p pid=".462.1/1">First, I welcome the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs, my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1127" name="Chris Mullin">the Member for Sunderland, South (Mr. Mullin)</phrase>. I am particularly pleased that he is here. It has been a long time since we crossed swords&mdash;in fact, I believe it was in the early 1980s, when my good friend was at the forefront of the Bennite crusade for socialism in the Labour party while I was on the side of sanity. Since then I have watched with interest his progress along the road to ministerial office, moving from Bennite to born-again Blairite. I make those points because I hope that in this debate my hon. Friend will revert to his old self and show some of the campaigning principles that he showed when fighting the case of the Birmingham Six, who were unjustly imprisoned on charges that subsequently proved to be totally false. He played an honourable role in that fight.</p>
	<p pid=".462.1/2">Sadly, there are many hundreds of prisoners of different nationalities currently detained at Guantanamo Bay, including four British citizens: Feroz Abbasi, Martin Mubanga, Richard Belmar and my constituent Moazzam Begg. Let me say at the start that I have consistently supported action by the international community against international terrorism, which is a threat to us all; the civilised values that we stand for must be upheld and fought for. The perpetrators of 9/11, the Bali bombings and the Madrid outrages have to be pursued and destroyed, but we stand for bringing people accused of such crimes before courts of law, for democracy, for freedom of speech and for the rule of law. If we not prepared to offer those rights to people who are accused of such serious crimes, we bring ourselves down to the same level as international terrorists.</p>
	<p pid=".462.1/3">I first raised the incarceration of my constituent, Moazzam Begg, nearly three years ago. Had anybody told me then that three years later I would still be raising his case, I would not have believed it; nor would I have believed that he would still be imprisoned at Guantanamo Bay. Although the process is currently suspended, Moazzam Begg and Feroz Abbasi still face the possibility of being brought before a US-style military commission, where the military personnel acting as interrogators, prosecutors, defence counsel, judges and&mdash;in cases where the death penalty is imposed&mdash;executioners are all appointed by the US Defence Secretary.</p>
	<p pid=".462.1/4">Three years ago, I would not have believed that Moazzam Begg and other British citizens could remain in the legal, physical and mental black hole of Guantanamo Bay, even though no charges that are recognisable in international law have been laid against any of them, no evidence has been presented of their guilt, and no access to independent legal counsel has been provided for them. I would not have believed that we could have a US Government who make no pretence that Guantanamo Bay is covered by the Geneva conventions&mdash;the men are designated enemy combatants, not prisoners of war. Equally, I would not have believed that representatives of the US judiciary have, almost unanimously, had to petition courts in America, including the Supreme Court, to make it clearly known that Guantanamo Bay is unconstitutional.</p>
	<p pid=".462.1/5">Each person who is detained in Guantanamo Bay is kept in a wire-mesh cell 6 ft 8 in by 8 ft and allowed out for 20 minutes solitary exercise three times a day. There is growing evidence that torture has been used at the camp. The simplest considerations that any detainee should have&mdash;for example, the right to be visited by members of his or her family&mdash;have been denied to the four British citizens in Guantanamo Bay, including my constituent.</p>
	<p pid=".462.1/6">Originally, I went along with the Foreign Office viewpoint that publicising Moazzam Begg's case could damage his long-term prospects. The Foreign Office suggested that if I raised the profile of the case, it could impede any future visits to Mr. Begg by his family, when such visits were allowed, and the flow of news about their son that the family so desperately needed. However, that was before the true nature of what has been happening in Guantanamo Bay came out&mdash;and that was more than three years ago.</p>
	<p pid=".462.1/7">Freedom is something we in the House seek to uphold as democrats. A former American Republican presidential candidate, Wendell Wilkie, who stood just after the second world war, once said:</p>
	<p pid=".462.1/8" class="indent">&quot;Freedom is an indivisible word. If we want to enjoy it, and fight for it, we must be prepared to extend it to everyone, whether they be rich or poor, whether they agree with us or not, no matter what their race or the colour of their skin.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".462.1/9">Let me add to that the first paragraph of an editorial from the <i>The Mail on Sunday</i> on <phrase class="date" code="2003-07-06">6 July 2003</phrase>. I do not wish to be disrespectful, but that paper is not noted for its libertarian attitude towards civil rights. None the less, the editorial stated:</p>
	<p pid=".462.1/10" class="indent">&quot;Let us be blunt here. If the men involved were white and Christian, and if the country behaving like this was anywhere but the USA, the Prime Minister would already have sent the Foreign Secretary on wings of wrath to demand their handover for trial here.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".462.1/11">It is certainly the belief of the wider Muslim community in this country that double standards are being applied in respect of the British Government's attempt to get those four British citizens returned to the United Kingdom.</p>
	<p pid=".462.1/12">It appears that the Prime Minister&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.462.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="463"  time="015:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h04.htm#41117h04_time1">
	<p pid=".462.2/1" class="italic">Sitting suspended for a Division in the House.</p>
	<p pid=".462.2/2" class="italic">On resuming&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.463.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/916" speakername="Roger Godsiff" colnum="463"  time="015:37:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h04.htm#41117h04_spnew1">
	<p pid=".463.0/1">As I was saying, it would seem that the Government's position as enunciated by the Prime Minister, who is a lawyer, as is his good wife, is that the British detainees should be either tried fairly in accordance with international standards or returned to the United Kingdom. I welcome that. The Government have expressed strong reservations to the US Administration about the use of military commissions and legal proceedings against two British detainees have been suspended. I welcome that, too. The Government requested that nine British detainees be returned to the UK, and five were returned in March. All British detainees have now been informed of the combatant status review tribunals and of their right to challenge in United States courts the legality of their detention with regard to their status as enemy combatants and not as prisoners of war. I welcome all those things&mdash;I welcome all the work done by the Government and the Foreign Office to try to resolve the situation&mdash;but is it enough? Was it ever enough? How much longer will the process run? For months? For years?</p>
	<p pid=".463.0/2">Last weekend, the Prime Minister went to the United States to renew our special relationship with the new Administration. I would like to know whether the four British detainees, including Moazzam Begg, were discussed while he was there. The clear perception of the community in Birmingham is that the Government are feeding off crumbs from the American Administration. In the meantime, the family of Moazzam Begg have to survive on welfare reports passed on by the Foreign Office.</p>
	<p pid=".463.0/3">My constituent and those other British citizens still live under threat of being tried by a military commission, so I ask the Minister to state for the record what the British Government will do if the Bush Administration decide to continue with the commissions. Will the Government deem that the process has been a failure? Will the Prime Minister refuse to accept his congressional medal of honour? Will the FCO continue to deliver welfare reports to the Begg family when Moazzam faces possible execution, or a life sentence with no prospect of early release? In short, do the Government have a plan B. and if so, would the Minister like to tell us what it is?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.464.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/687" speakername="Diane Abbott" colnum="464"  time="015:37:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h04.htm#41117h04_spnew2">
	<p pid=".464.0/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend on securing this important debate. Last week, I had the privilege of meeting the families of Richard Belmar and Martin Mubanga. The lives of those men and their families are the small change of international diplomacy, but, as my hon. Friend said, two or three years after these events started, the families remain desperate. They do not understand why a Prime Minister who is supposedly the Bush Administration's best friend in the world cannot secure a charge and a proper trial for the men. It may be that Ministers, as in the Birmingham Six case, have given a nod and a wink and asked, &quot;What were the men doing out there anyway, to get picked up?&quot; but I would argue that, as British citizens, the men are entitled to be charged and subjected to a fair trial.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.464.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/916" speakername="Roger Godsiff" colnum="464"  time="015:37:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h04.htm#41117h04_spnew3">
	<p pid=".464.1/1">I entirely concur with my hon. Friend. Again, I make it plain that we must pursue international terrorists who carry out evil atrocities. As an individual MP, I consistently supported the war against international terrorism and the invasion of Afghanistan in pursuit of the al-Qaeda organisation. I opposed the invasion of Iraq because I believed that it was a distraction in the war against international terrorism. However, what separates us from the international terrorists is the fact that we respect the rule of law that underpins our democratic society. When we catch people who we believe are involved in international terrorism, we undermine our own values unless we try them in accordance with our laws.</p>
	<p pid=".464.1/2">I return to the editorial in <i>The Mail on Sunday,</i> to which I referred earlier. It begins:</p>
	<p pid=".464.1/3" class="indent">&quot;More than 200 years after they were written, the words of America's Bill of Rights still speak clearly and forcibly: 'In all criminal prosecutions, the accused shall enjoy the right to a speedy trial by an impartial jury . . . and to be informed of the nature and cause of the accusation; to be confronted with the witnesses against him; to have compulsory process for obtaining witnesses in his favour; and to have the assistance of counsel for his defence.'&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".464.1/4">The basic rights that were written into the American constitution are being denied to four British citizens who are incarcerated at Guantanamo Bay. I end by quoting the words of Moazzam Begg himself. In a letter written by him and published recently, he states:</p>
	<p pid=".464.1/5" class="indent">&quot;I am a law-abiding citizen of the UK and attest vehemently to my innocence before God and the law of any crime&mdash;though none has ever been alleged. I have neither ever met Osama Bin Laden, nor been a member of al Qaida&mdash;or any synonymous paramilitary organisation, party or group. Neither have I engaged in hostile acts against the USA, nor assisted such groups in the same . . . I reiterate my intention to seek justice at every possible level available&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".464.1/6">Is not that the least that we can give him?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.465.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1127" speakername="Chris Mullin" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs"  colnum="465"  time="015:44:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h04.htm#41117h04_spmin0">
	<p pid=".465.0/1">Let me say at the outset that I share the frustration of my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/916" name="Roger Godsiff">the Member for Birmingham, Sparkbrook and Small Heath (Mr. Godsiff)</phrase> at the circumstances in which his constituent and others have been detained. I assure him that the Government have been doing everything in their power to resolve the matter&mdash;in fact, I would go so far as to say that no Government with citizens detained at Guantanamo Bay have worked harder to try to resolve the situation.</p>
	<p pid=".465.0/2">Since the first British national was transferred to Guantanamo Bay in 2002, we have repeatedly and persistently pursued the issue with the United States authorities including, as my hon. Friend acknowledged, at the highest level. The Prime Minister has raised it with President Bush; the Foreign Secretary has raised it with the Secretary of State, Colin Powell; the Attorney-General has led talks with the US Government; and Ministers, senior officials and lawyers have pursued the matter relentlessly and will continue to do so.</p>
	<p pid=".465.0/3">We have achieved some success. The release of five of the nine detainees earlier this year was the result of representations by the British Government. We have blocked the trial by military commission of two of the remaining four detainees and, as my hon. Friend acknowledged, we have secured improvements in the conditions in which the detainees have been held. The most recent example of that is the removal of Moazzam Begg and Feroz Abbasi from a form of solitary confinement and into the main detention camp. That was a response to our concerns about their isolation and lack of access to daylight.</p>
	<p pid=".465.0/4">The UK's overall position in relation to British nationals at Guantanamo Bay has been made clear from the outset. It is more or less the same as the one enunciated a moment ago by my hon. Friend: British detainees should either be tried fairly, in accordance with international standards, or they should be returned to the UK. With regard to the four remaining detainees, discussions at official level explored whether there was any prospect of providing an alternative trial process to the military commissions, but it has not proved possible to reach an agreement. In June, the Prime Minister personally repeated our request that the four be returned to the UK, and he raised Guantanamo again with President Bush during their talks in Washington last week. The United States Government has expressed its reluctance to return the remaining detainees because of security concerns. Our discussions with the US are continuing and we are seeking to address their concerns in the hope that the four might be returned.</p>
	<p pid=".465.0/5">It might be helpful if I explain the various legal proceedings surrounding the detainees. My hon. Friend will be aware of the habeas corpus cases in the US district court, one of which has been brought on behalf of his constituent. The cases follow the Supreme Court's June ruling that detainees have the right to challenge the legality of their detention. US lawyers have now visited those involved in those cases, including Mr. Begg, and we welcome that. The Government have been asked to submit an amicus curii brief in one of the cases, and we are now examining the petition. My hon. Friend will also be aware of the ruling last week in a US district court in the case of Guantanamo detainee Salim Hamdan. The court rejected the US Government's argument that the third Geneva convention did not apply to al-Qaeda detainees captured in Afghanistan. It decided that a detainee must be afforded prisoner of war status until a competent tribunal decides otherwise, and stated that neither a combatant status review tribunal nor the US President is a competent tribunal for those purposes.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.466.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/687" speakername="Diane Abbott" colnum="466"  time="015:44:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h04.htm#41117h04_spnew4">
	<p pid=".466.0/1">Is the Minister able to say that the Government are confident that there is no substance to the allegations of physical torture at Guantanamo Bay?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.466.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1127" speakername="Chris Mullin" colnum="466"  time="015:44:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h04.htm#41117h04_spnew5">
	<p pid=".466.1/1">I shall come to those allegations, but at the moment I am dealing with the ruling of the US district court last week, which I think is relevant to the situation of the detainees. The court held that trial by military commission would be unlawful as long as the rules of procedure allowed for the use of secret evidence and the exclusion of the accused from proceedings for reasons unconnected with his conduct. The US Government has indicated that it will appeal the court's ruling, and we are, of course, following the case.</p>
	<p pid=".466.1/2">Following the Supreme Court ruling, combatant status review tribunals have been established by the US to determine whether Guantanamo Bay detainees are properly classified as enemy combatants and to permit each detainee the opportunity to contest that classification. The Government are not a party to the tribunals, but we are following their progress and monitoring the case of the British detainees. I understand that Mr. Abbasi's tribunal has been completed with the conclusion that he is an enemy combatant, and his family have been informed of the decision.</p>
	<p pid=".466.1/3">From the outset, the welfare of the detainees has been a priority for the Government. We were the first to visit our nationals in Guantanamo Bay, and British officials have made nine welfare visits to the British detainees, the most recent of which was between 2 and <phrase class="date" code="2004-10-05">5 October</phrase>. As on all other occasions, a written statement on the visit was made to Parliament, and it might be helpful if I repeat the key points:</p>
	<p pid=".466.1/4" class="indent">&quot;The British detainees appeared in sound physical health, are frustrated by their continued detention but heartened by recent access to legal representation, in the case of three of the detainees. Individual medical and detention matters raised during this and previous welfare visits by the detainees were pursued with the Camp authorities. Most have now been addressed. The Government will continue to pursue the outstanding matters. All the detainees say that they welcomed the welfare visits.&quot;&mdash;[<phrase class="offrep" id="wms/2004-11-04.15"><i>Official Report</i>, 4 November 2004; Vol. 426, c. 15WS</phrase>.]</p>
	<p pid=".466.1/5">As well as providing a written statement to Parliament, the Government have given the families of the detainees a detailed report on their condition, and we shall continue to keep them informed.</p>
	<p pid=".466.1/6">My hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/687" name="Diane Abbott">the Member for Hackney, North and Stoke Newington (Ms Abbott)</phrase> raised the allegations of mistreatment at Guantanamo Bay. I covered the issue in the previous Adjournment debate on the subject in July, but I want to take this opportunity to update hon. Members.</p>
	<p pid=".466.1/7">My hon. Friends will be aware that the British detainees who returned to the UK this year subsequently made a number of allegations of mistreatment. Despite the opportunity to do so during our repeated welfare visits to Guantanamo Bay, none of the men alleged to us while they were detained there that they were systematically abused. Furthermore, none of them has raised the allegations of mistreatment with the Government since their return to the UK. We have, however, taken up a number of their allegations with the US authorities. In response, they have said that the men were treated humanely, but they are continuing to investigate some of the other allegations made by former British detainees.</p>
	<p pid=".466.1/8">There is particular concern about the treatment of Moazzam Begg, who is a constituent of my hon. Friend the Member for Birmingham, Sparkbrook and Small Heath, so perhaps I should address that case specifically. My hon. Friend will be aware of a letter written by Mr. Begg from Guantanamo Bay, which was recently made public. He has never alleged to us that he has been systematically abused at Guantanamo Bay in the way that is now being suggested; on the contrary, he said that he had been treated well, and he confirmed that to a British official who saw him in Guantanamo a few days after the letter was reported in the media. However, Mr. Begg has said that he was mistreated when he was detained at Bagram air base in Afghanistan, and we asked the American authorities to investigate. They have told us that they can find no information to support that claim, and we have asked them to carry out a second, more detailed investigation.</p>
	<p pid=".466.1/9">My hon. Friend will be aware of a request by Azmat Begg, Mr. Begg's father, that he, Dr. James MacKeith and Lord Rea visit Moazzam at Guantanamo Bay to carry out an independent psychiatric assessment. Baroness Symons has supported that request. We have written to the US authorities to make the request and we continue to pursue it. We await a US response.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.468.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/687" speakername="Diane Abbott" colnum="468"  time="015:44:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h04.htm#41117h04_spnew6">
	<p pid=".468.0/1">What is being done to secure family visits for the other British detainees, particularly Martin Mubanga and Richard Belmar?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.468.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1127" speakername="Chris Mullin" colnum="468"  time="015:44:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h04.htm#41117h04_spnew7">
	<p pid=".468.1/1">As I said, we have repeatedly made representations to the Americans on the subject of visits for families, but so far those requests have been denied.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/2">Throughout the past two or three years, the Government have sought to meet the twin objectives of pursuing the fight against international terrorism and safeguarding the interests of British citizens detained overseas. It is important to remember the context in which the detentions at Guantanamo took place: <phrase class="date" code="2004-09-11">11 September</phrase> was the most appalling terrorist attack ever&mdash;more than 3,000 people, including 67 British nationals, died on the US mainland. Following the attack, thousands of individuals who were believed to be al-Qaeda or Taliban fighters or their supporters were detained. The majority were released in Afghanistan, but the US sent those whom it deemed to pose a substantial risk to Guantanamo Bay for detention and questioning about their knowledge of al-Qaeda. As a result, valuable information has been gained, which has helped the international community fight terrorism.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.468.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/916" speakername="Roger Godsiff" colnum="468"  time="015:44:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h04.htm#41117h04_spnew8">
	<p pid=".468.2/1">Does the Minister not agree that any organisation that detains people, even the Birmingham Six&mdash;he had experience of that miscarriage of justice&mdash;should not keep them incommunicado for three years?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.468.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1127" speakername="Chris Mullin" colnum="468"  time="015:44:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h04.htm#41117h04_spnew9">
	<p pid=".468.3/1">Yes, the British Government and I agree with everything that my hon. Friend said about the need to treat suspects according to the rule of law. There is no difference between us on that.</p>
	<p pid=".468.3/2">I hope that I have been able to reassure my hon. Friend about the Government's commitment to work for the release of the remaining detainees and to ensure their well-being while they remain detained at Guantanamo Bay. Our discussions with the US authorities continue in relation to both issues. As I said at the outset, I understand the frustration of my hon. Friend and his constituents' relatives, but the Government are doing all in their power to bring an end to the unhappy situation and we will continue to do so.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.468.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1086" speakername="John McWilliam" colnum="468"  time="015:44:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h04.htm#41117h04_spnew10">
	<p pid=".468.4/1">In order to protect the last Adjournment debate and bearing in mind that there will be a Division in the House at one minute past 4 at the latest, I suspend the sitting until a quarter past four.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.468.5" nospeaker="true" colnum="468"  time="015:56:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h04.htm#41117h04_time4">
	<p pid=".468.5/1" class="italic">Sitting suspended.</p>
	<p pid=".468.5/2" class="italic">On resuming&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.468.6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1086" speakername="John McWilliam" colnum="468"  time="016:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h04.htm#41117h04_spnew11">
	<p pid=".468.6/1">Order. It appears to me that there is going to be a run of votes in the House&mdash;perhaps as many as 12, although that is unlikely. I am therefore going to suspend until five minutes after the last of those votes, when it becomes clear that there are not going to be any more. We shall then all assemble here and see whether we can get the debate in before we get interrupted again.</p>
	<p pid=".468.6/2" class="italic">Sitting suspended</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.470.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="470"  time="016:15:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h05.htm#41117h05_head0">
	Pensioner Poverty (West Edinburgh)
</major-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.470.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/716" speakername="John Barrett" colnum="470"  time="016:25:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h05.htm#41117h05_spnew0">
	<p pid=".470.1/1">The first report of the Pensions Commission made stark reading for the Government and hon. Members. It set out clearly and fairly the tough choices that lie ahead in respect of pensions, and the even tougher consequences of any failure to act. One of the true measures of a decent, fair and free society is how it treats its older citizens. Surely one of the most important social issues facing any Government is the need to ensure that older people can, after a lifetime of contributing to their country, retire with dignity, free from poverty. That challenge can be broken into two basic parts: how do the Government alleviate the pensioner poverty of today, and how do they prevent the pensioner poverty of tomorrow?</p>
	<p pid=".470.1/2">I am pleased to have secured this Adjournment debate, because it will allow me to raise some problems faced by pensioners in my constituency. The Minister for Pensions, whom I am delighted to see in his place, is well known for his considered replies and I look forward to such a response today. In that spirit, I say at the outset that the position in my constituency is far from being all doom and gloom. The fact is that pensioner incomes vary enormously. Many pensioners in my constituency enjoy a high standard of living, often because of the extra savings that they made throughout their working lives. However, too many others in Edinburgh, West do not enjoy the standard of living that they should be able to expect.</p>
	<p pid=".470.1/3">Given that 2 million pensioners still live below the poverty line in this country&mdash;the fourth richest in the world&mdash;there is no room for complacency. However, it would be wrong of me not to acknowledge the measures that the Government have taken to benefit pensioners in my constituency. I do not want to steal the Minister's thunder, but it does not take much foresight to predict that he will refer to such measures as the winter fuel payment, free television licences, the Christmas bonus, the &pound;100 towards council tax bills and pension credit. I recognise that each of those measures has, in its own way, benefited a section of people in my constituency. However, I have to warn the Minister against simply rattling off that list as a defence, because as welcome as many of the measures are, if the Government really have done everything right and delivered a fair deal for pensioners, I must ask why I receive so many letters and telephone calls from older people in Edinburgh, West arguing to the contrary.</p>
	<p pid=".470.1/4">The Government hold up the pension credit as their flagship mechanism for tackling pensioner poverty. The latest information from the Department for Work and Pensions shows that more than 2.5 million pensioner households benefit from the pension credit. That figure is not to be sniffed at, but it stands short of the 2.8 million target set by the DWP for October 2004. The Minister will also know that the rate of increase in claims is falling off sharply. The September 2004 increase of just 15,000 new claims was the lowest monthly increase since the take-up campaign started. If the number of claimants is plateauing, as it appears to be, that raises the question of when, or indeed if, the Government will reach their target.</p>
	<p pid=".470.1/5">The latest pension credit progress report, which I obtained from the Vote Office, shows that some 2,700 pensioner households in my constituency benefit from the pension credit. However, a written parliamentary answer that I received last year from the Under-Secretary of State for Work and Pensions, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/872" name="Maria Eagle">the hon. Member for Liverpool, Garston (Maria Eagle)</phrase>, said that more than 1,400 people in Edinburgh, West were already benefiting from the minimum income guarantee. They would simply be transferred over to the guarantee element of the pension credit, so the figure for new pensioners in my constituency to benefit stands at about 1,300.</p>
	<p pid=".470.1/6">According to another parliamentary answer that I received from the DWP that uses the number of winter fuel payments as a guide, there are some 86,250 pensioner households across the six Edinburgh parliamentary constituencies. The Department admitted before introducing pension credit that it expected approximately 40 per cent. of pensioner households in Scotland to be eligible for it. For Edinburgh, that would mean about 34,500 households, but the latest progress report shows that only 18,148 pensioner households in the capital are claiming the credit&mdash;53 per cent of those eligible.</p>
	<p pid=".470.1/7">To the Government's credit, they have worked hard to promote the availability of pension credit before and since its introduction last year. Although I have taken issue with the Government over the emphasis on means-testing, I genuinely wanted to see the credit work and for eligible constituents to get the money that they deserve. As a result, I contacted each household in my constituency twice through newsletters about the credit, providing basic details and making it clear that any person who wanted further information or an application pack could contact my constituency office. I am glad to say that many pensioners did just that, and I put on record my thanks to those working in the Pension Service in Scotland who helped me with that campaign. I know that the Minister will agree that the considerable contribution made by those working in the Pension Service has been much appreciated by constituents. I have always found the team in Scotland to be helpful, friendly, accessible and professional in their work.</p>
	<p pid=".470.1/8">None the less, despite the promotions, the advertising, the work of the Department for Work and Pensions and the Pension Service, the home visits and the roadshows, many pensioners eligible for pension credit still do not claim it. That presents a new problem for the Minister. We are no longer talking about people being unaware of the existence of the credit&mdash;although I accept that some still are&mdash;but about people who know about it and are making a conscious decision not to make a claim for some reason.</p>
	<p pid=".470.1/9">During my local take-up campaign, I received a number of letters from pensioners who found the process of applying for the means-tested benefit complicated and degrading. One constituent from Drylaw in Edinburgh wrote to tell me how she felt &quot;stripped of all dignity&quot; by the questions asked and had decided not to proceed with her application. Another constituent from Queensferry told me that she did not want to</p>
	<p pid=".470.1/10" class="indent">&quot;go through hoops for the sake of a few extra pounds a week.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".470.1/11">I have lost count of the number of times I have heard older people say something like, &quot;I have never had to claim benefits in my life and I am not going to start now&quot;, or, &quot;I have gone through my entire working life without asking for help, and I'm not going to ask the Government for help.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".470.1/12">The fact is that we are talking about a proud section of society. Last Sunday, I was fortunate enough to attend two Remembrance day events in my constituency, in Corstorphine and Davidson's Mains. The immense pride that older people rightfully feel on such occasions illustrates the honour and dignity that they too should be granted. It is no wonder that so many of them do not want to go, as they describe it, &quot;cap in hand&quot; to the Government. They feel that the process is degrading and no amount of information will convince them otherwise. That shows one underlying problem with the Government's mass means-testing of pensioners&mdash;as a policy it is neither desirable nor effective.</p>
	<p pid=".470.1/13">My party and I believe that the only guaranteed way of getting more money to the poorest pensioners is by increasing the wholly inadequate basic state pension. The Minister will be well aware of the Liberal Democrats' pensions package, even if some members of his party have chosen deliberately to misrepresent it. He will know that pensioner poverty is particularly acute among women, because of the rules on national insurance contributions. Just a few days ago, the TUC pointed out that 70 per cent. of female pensioners are getting less than the full basic state pension, compared with just 15 per cent. of men. A system that assumes that a woman does not need a pension if she has a husband is grossly outdated.</p>
	<p pid=".470.1/14">The so-called citizen's pension, which my party proposes, is the kind of basic reform that the UK pension system needs, because it would be linked to residency and uprated in line with earnings. The citizen's pension would make an enormous contribution to alleviating pensioner poverty, especially among women. An extra &pound;100 a month for over-75s would lift 1 million people out of means-testing overnight.</p>
	<p pid=".470.1/15">There are a few other issues that I would like to touch on and I hope that the Minister will find time to comment on them, too. Another major problem facing pensioners in my constituency is the cost of council tax. Nationally, pensioner incomes have risen, in percentage terms, by less than half the increase in council tax bills. In Edinburgh, the average council tax bill has risen by 22 per cent. in four years. The &pound;100 offered to older pensioners in my constituency was welcome, but it ignores the underlying root of the problem. Also, because it was targeted at older pensioners, it left no help for many younger pensioners who are struggling to make ends meet because of their council tax bill. Council tax remains one of the most regressive and unfair taxes. It hits disproportionately those on fixed incomes and low incomes, including pensioners. The result has been that pensioners in my constituency are spending a huge chunk of their pension on council tax; that is money that they should be spending on heating their homes and on food for their meals. Just as with pension credit, too many pensioners&mdash;almost a third&mdash;are not claiming the council tax benefits to which they are entitled. Estimates given to me by Help the Aged suggest that some &pound;2.5 billion worth of benefits, including council tax benefit, is going unclaimed by pensioners.</p>
	<p pid=".470.1/16">Thankfully, in Scotland, the Scottish Executive is undertaking a review into local government finance, and the Liberal Democrats will argue strongly for council tax to be abolished and for a new, fairer, local income tax to be introduced. The system would be based on income, not property values. Thousands of pensioners in my constituency and throughout Scotland would benefit. As fairness would be built into the system, we would also remove the need for council tax benefit and resolve the take-up problems.</p>
	<p pid=".470.1/17">Turning to poverty among disabled pensioners, the Minister will be aware of the strong and widespread feeling among Members about the discrimination in relation to disability benefits. Early-day motion 953, which concerns the Mobilise campaign to allow over-65s to claim disability living allowance, now stands out as one of the most popular EDMs this Session. Almost 250 MPs from all parties have backed it. The main support for the Mobilise campaign has come about because of the in-built injustice that it seeks to end. Surely it cannot be right that under-65s are entitled to help with their mobility costs while the under-65s are not? The allowance of &pound;41 a week would go a long way in helping elderly people who suffer from mobility problems and who have to use their pension to pay for help. Such a move would also have other positive effects. DLA acts as a gateway allowance; entitlement to it also means access to other benefits, such as the Motability scheme and exemption from car tax. The 20 charities that formed the Mobilise campaign have done a power of work on raising awareness of the issue, both inside and outside Parliament. I hope that, at some point, the Minister will confirm that their work has not been in vain, and that changes to the rules will be introduced as soon as possible.</p>
	<p pid=".470.1/18">I remember when the Prime Minister promised to learn from what he described as a mistake&mdash;the 75p increase in the state pension, which many pensioners found insulting. That was one of the big mistakes of Labour's first term, and one of the big mistakes of their second term has been the abolition of pension books. Although that has not added to pensioner poverty, it has added to the general anger and frustration felt by many pensioners. It comes down to the attitude of the Government&mdash;an attitude that has led to their setting a target to end child poverty by 2020, but setting no such target and making no such commitment for older people. That attitude has fostered feelings of injustice and unfairness among the pensioners whom I represent. After all their contributions to society, they are only asking for what is fair. The Government should offer no less.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.473.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1316" speakername="Malcolm Wicks" speakeroffice="The Minister for Pensions"  colnum="473"  time="016:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h05.htm#41117h05_spnew1">
	<p pid=".473.0/1">I thank <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/716" name="John Barrett">the hon. Member for Edinburgh, West (John Barrett)</phrase> for the way in which he approached the debate. We will not agree on everything, but I would like to thank him for his tribute to our local Pension Service. It is the first time that we in these countries have had a dedicated Pension Service, and its work at local level is quite outstanding. It is particularly helpful when it can link up with a local Member of Parliament. I am pleased with the way in which the hon. Gentleman is approaching that work in his constituency.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/2">Whatever the difference between us about policies, such as pension credit, it is our duty as Members of Parliament to play our role in ensuring that all our constituents claim their entitlements. I thank the hon. Gentleman for his approach.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/3">I am hoping that, in the next day or two, the Pensions Bill will become the Pensions Act, although there are still some discussions to be held about it. It would bring much-needed security in the future to those people with final salary pension schemes ending the scandal whereby, when a company goes bust and a scheme does not have enough money, pension rights are, in fact, not rights. We are making sure that the pension promise will be kept in the future.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/4">The hon. Gentleman referred briefly to the Pensions Commission. We will consider its recommendations when they are published in the commission's second report next year and examine some of the fundamental issues about which any Government need to decide.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/5">Understandably, the hon. Gentleman spoke much about the situation facing today's pensioners. It was certainly the case that, when the Government came to power in 1997, one of the great challenges facing us was pensioner poverty. Under the previous Government's income support system, a single pensioner was being asked to live on an income as low as &pound;69 a week. Moreover, under income support, any extra money that the pensioner had, such as savings or a small works pension, was deducted pound for pound from the person's entitlement to income support. Poverty was certainly blighting the lives of many of our senior citizens in our countries. That is why we focused not all but much of the additional money that we can spend on pensioners.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/6">I accept that there is always the argument that we should be spending more, but we will be spending &pound;10 billion a year more on pensioners in 2004&ndash;05 than was spent under the old system. Of that &pound;10 billion, about half&mdash;nearly &pound;5 billion&mdash;is going to the poorest one third of pensioners. The hon. Gentleman talked about means-testing but, whether or not he agrees with our approach, we are proud of the fact that, through such measures as pension credit, we are enabling many additional resources to go to the poorest. Indeed, average pensioner households are receiving &pound;1,350 more a year&mdash;&pound;26 a week&mdash;while the poorest third receives &pound;1,800 a year more, which is about &pound;35 a week. It goes directly into the pockets and the purses of the poorest pensioners. That is important.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/7">I do not want this to be a single-issue debate, but I feel obliged to make several points about pension credit. We have moved away from the intrusive, punitive means test of the past that put many people off taking up what was rightfully theirs. In the past, taking up entitlements meant perhaps a visit to an uninviting social security office and the daunting prospect of filling out a 40-page claim form. As the hon. Gentleman and I acknowledged, we have established a dedicated Pension Service that is tailored to our customers' needs, with a simple free phone application process that includes a local service in the community, which works jointly with our partners in the statutory and voluntary sectors, to provide not only pension credit but housing benefit, council tax benefit and other social care entitlements.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/8">Members need not take my word for it, although I am sure the hon. Gentleman would want to: a recent survey undertaken by our partners, Age Concern, found that about 70 per cent. of people who had applied for pension credit considered that the application process was easy, while 85 per cent. said that they would recommend it to someone else. Pension credit is designed to provide extra money to those pensioners with modest savings for their retirement. Before it was introduced, many people who had managed to save a little were often left no better off than people who had not saved at all. That is the importance of the savings element of pension credit.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/9">In Edinburgh, West, the hon. Gentleman's constituency, the average pension credit is just over &pound;38 a week. I am pleased that, on the latest count, 3,206 individuals in his constituency are receiving pension credit. That extra money enables many of our older citizens to lead more independent and dignified lives&mdash;which they deserve and which we would wish for them.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/10">One group that benefits from pension credit is women pensioners. There has been an uneven distribution of caring responsibilities. For example, many of the hon. Gentleman's older constituents&mdash;those in their 80s&mdash;might have brought up a number of children. They may also have been responsible as the main carer for elderly relatives within the extended family. As a result, they would have had less time to pursue a career and therefore less access to a decent occupational pension scheme. As the hon. Gentleman remarked, such women were less likely to have a full national insurance contribution record and therefore less likely to have a full basic state pension. That gender issue will need to be addressed in future, but we must also address it now. It is no coincidence that two-thirds of people getting pension credit are women&mdash;partly because they are older and partly because of the other caring responsibilities that I mentioned.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/11">It is not only pension credit that can make the difference: for the first time, about 2 million pensioner households now quality for more help with council tax and/or housing benefit. The number qualifying for those benefits has increased because pension credit recipients can now claim those benefits.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/12">On the issue of council tax benefit, which the hon. Gentleman highlighted, I should note also that, as part of the winter fuel payment, an extra &pound;100 will be paid to those households in which one or more members are over the age of 70. It is being paid this year only in order to take a bit of the sting out of the council tax increases&mdash;increases that concern us all.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/13">I recognise that the take-up of council tax benefit has often been appalling. It has been a grey area, not a highlighted benefit. We are trying to change that, working with local authorities in Scotland and across England and Wales. The winter fuel payments that are now going to our constituents include a special leaflet about council tax benefit, urging people who think that they might be eligible to apply. They must apply to the local authority, which is very important.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/14">I now turn specifically to the situation in Scotland&mdash;indeed, the majority of Members here this afternoon represent Scottish seats. As at the end of September, more than 273,000 pensioner households had already taken up their entitlement to pension credit, and that number is growing. As I said, by the end of September more than 2,700 households&mdash;about 3,206 individuals&mdash;in Edinburgh, West will receive pension credit. We believe that there should be a simple income test. The forms are shorter, home visits can be made and people can visit the local surgery.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/15">I have one good news story about the local service. Staff recently visited a couple in Edinburgh, West to help them with a pension credit application. Although the couple were in receipt of a state pension and had been awarded attendance allowance, they had not yet applied for the pension credit. As a result of our approach, they are now receiving more than &pound;49 a week, with a backdated payment of more than &pound;1,300. That is just one example of the difference that pension credit can make to pensioners across our countries. The backdating is important because anyone claiming pension credit can now have it backdated for 12 months, so people could receive considerable lump sums.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/16">We are determined to strengthen our joint working arrangements in Scotland, in order to reach more pensioners who have yet to take up pension credit. That is why the Pension Service in Scotland is working in partnership with the health and care group and the older people's unit within the Scottish Executive. Our approach is not limited to the poorest pensioners alone. It was vital that we got more money to them as quickly as possible. That is what pension credit is all about.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/17">In response to the question of non-take-up, I have always acknowledged that there are both advantages and disadvantages to any pension strategy. The advantage of pension credit, which is income tested, is that by definition it is designed for the poorest, and we have an especial duty to reach the poorest. The challenge is always to maximise the take-up, but I am never sure that hon. Members are right when they say that we should simply do away with means-testing. It is a difficult issue.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/18">As Minister for Pensions, my aspiration is that more people in the younger cohorts should be enabled to retire on incomes based on a combination of state pensions and state second pensions or occupational pensions that put them significantly above the means-tested level. That has to be our long-term aspiration. However, we have a group of people already retired who are poor&mdash;often women and often the older elderly. Would it really be right to say to such an 80-year-old constituent, jogging along on &pound;60 or &pound;70 a week when we came into power, that we will give them the same pension increase as someone with a big investment income or an occupational pension, who is earning &pound;50,000 a year in retirement?</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/19">Should we treat everyone the same? It would be simpler administratively and there would not be a take-up problem, but would it be fair and just? That is the question, and that is why we believe that, in the short to medium term, pension credit is the right approach to righting the injustice that many of those constituents face during their lives. They have done the right thing in bringing up their children and caring for elderly relatives, but then they pay the pension penalty: they do not get the full basic state pension but they have not accrued rights to occupational pensions. Pension credit is designed to help that group. It is controversial, but I am convinced that it is the right strategy and that we all need to put a lot of effort into boosting take-up.</p>
	<p pid=".473.0/20">That is our strategy. We are doing what we can for all pensioners by raising the basic state pension, always at least in line with prices and often more. There are winter fuel payments, which, we should remember, are now worth &pound;300 for our constituents over 80 and &pound;200 for the over-60s. They take a lot of the sting out of the arrival of the electricity and gas bill, and I am proud of that.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.477.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/716" speakername="John Barrett" colnum="477"  time="016:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h05.htm#41117h05_spnew2">
	<p pid=".477.0/1">Before the Minister finishes, will he address the issue of disabled pensioners?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.477.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1316" speakername="Malcolm Wicks" colnum="477"  time="016:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h05.htm#41117h05_spnew3">
	<p pid=".477.1/1">I will reflect on the hon. Gentleman's thoughtful speech, and I will write to him on any points that I cannot cover now. I shall also bring his remarks to the attention of the Under-Secretary of State for Work and Pensions, my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/872" name="Maria Eagle">the Member for Liverpool, Garston (Maria Eagle)</phrase>, who has responsibility for disability issues.</p>
	<p pid=".477.1/2">We have in place a range of disability benefits and, through social work departments in Scotland and social services departments in England, measures to try to help people with disabilities. We always want to do more&mdash; the Disability Discrimination Act 1995 is an indication of our intent in that regard. However, we hope that the disability benefits and the carer's allowance will provide ways of tackling some of the financial hardship faced by both the person with the disability and their carer. I will reflect on the hon. Gentleman's remarks, and my ministerial colleague may write to him if I have missed any points.</p>
	<p pid=".477.1/3">I hope that I have addressed many, if not all, the issues that the hon. Gentleman raised. I am pleased that, on this busy day, we have managed to fit in such an important debate. I congratulate him on securing it and on the measured way in which he has approached the subject.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2004-11-17.478.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1086" speakername="John McWilliam" colnum="478"  time="016:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/vo041117/halltext/41117h05.htm#41117h05_spnew4">
	<p pid=".478.0/1">I thank the hon. Members for Edinburgh, West (John Barrett) and for Greenock and Inverclyde (David Cairns) and the Minister for their assistance in achieving a proper Adjournment debate on the one day in the year on which it is almost impossible to do so. The test of the elasticity of the relatively new Standing Orders was interesting for me in a technical sense.</p>
	<p pid=".478.0/2" class="italic">Question put and agreed to.</p>
	<p pid=".478.0/3" class="indent">Adjourned accordingly at six minutes to Five o'clock.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

