<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.251.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="251"  time="unknown" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0001.htm#08060495000008">
	[Mr. Peter Atkinson in the Chair]
	 &mdash; 
	Pleural Plaques
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.251.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="251"  time="unknown" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0001.htm#08060495000001">
	<p pid="a.251.1/1"><i>Motion made, and Question proposed</i>, That the sitting be now adjourned.&mdash;[Mr. Watts.]</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.251.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1386" speakername="Michael Clapham" colnum="251"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0001.htm#08060495000455">
	<p pid="a.251.2/1">This is the second Adjournment debate on pleural plaques since the Law Lords made their judgment on <phrase class="date" code="2008-10-17">17 October</phrase>. In between those occasions there have been meetings with Ministers and a number of questions have been asked. I make no apology for that, because this is an enormously important issue to ordinary working people. It is nine months since that judgment was made, but it appears that there has been little movement. We want to see movement.</p>
	<p pid="a.251.2/2">Pleural plaques are a clear indicator of asbestos exposure and compensation has previously been paid in respect of claims over the past 25 years. The Law Lords' decision ended the practice of paying compensation and left thousands of people bewildered and confused about the likelihood of their ever obtaining compensation in future for a condition that they contracted through no fault of their own and, in most cases, because of negligent exposure.</p>
	<p pid="a.251.2/3">I shall read a letter I received, as chair of the all-party group on occupational safety and health and its asbestos sub-group, from Mr. Rudd, who is probably the leading expert in the country on asbestos. He is a consultant at Barts and head of its mesothelioma research centre. He was also involved as the expert witness in the House of Lords case. His letter, in my view, clears up many of the fallacies connected with pleural plaques. I shall move from that to explore some of the issues that he raises.</p>
	<p pid="a.251.2/4">Mr. Rudd says:</p>
	<p pid="a.251.2/5" class="indent">&quot;I understand there is to be a debate concerning pleural plaques. I should like to draw the attention of Members of Parliament to some essential points.</p>
	<p pid="a.251.2/6" class="indent">1. Pleural plaques are a pathological change in the membrane which surrounds the lung, caused by inhalation of asbestos fibres.</p>
	<p pid="a.251.2/7" class="indent">2. The plaques themselves usually do not cause symptoms although they may cause discomfort, pain, breathlessness in exceptional cases when they are very extensive.</p>
	<p pid="a.251.2/8" class="indent">3. Pleural plaques are detected on chest x-ray in less than 1% of the general population and when they are present enquiry almost always reveals a history of asbestos exposure.</p>
	<p pid="a.251.2/9" class="indent">4. People with pleural plaques are at risk of developing diffuse pleural thickening causing breathlessness, asbestosis of the lungs causing breathlessness, lung cancer which is usually fatal and mesothelioma, a cancer which can occur in the lining of the chest cavity or in the lining of the abdominal cavity which is almost invariably fatal, usually within 12 to 18 months of the first symptoms.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.251.2/10">Last year there were 2,000 diagnoses of mesothelioma cancer, which is the third fastest-growing in the UK. Mr. Rudd continues:</p>
	<p pid="a.251.2/11" class="indent">&quot;5. People with pleural plaques who have been heavily exposed to asbestos at work have a risk of mesothelioma more than one thousand times greater than the general population.</p>
	<p pid="a.251.2/12" class="indent">6. People with pleural plaques commonly experience considerable anxiety about the risk of mesothelioma and other serious asbestos diseases. Despite reassurance offered by doctors that the condition is harmless often they know of former work colleagues who have gone on to die of mesothelioma after being diagnosed with pleural plaques. For many the anxiety is ever present. Every ache or pain or feeling of shortness of breath renews the fear that this may be the onset of mesothelioma. The anxiety is real for all and for some has a serious adverse effect on quality of life.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.251.2/13">Mr. Rudd's letter dispels a number of fallacies, some of which I shall mention. For example, he says that pleural plaques are a pathological change&mdash;in other words, a disorder caused by pollution of the body through the inhalation of asbestos fibre, which can arise only as a result of exposure to asbestos. He says that pleural plaques are symptomless but can cause discomfort. People who come to my constituency surgery suffering from pleural plaques and breathlessness contend, as victims, that the breathlessness has come on as a result of their pleural plaques.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.252.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1473" speakername="David Howarth" colnum="252"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0001.htm#08060495000456">
	<p pid="a.252.0/1">I congratulate the hon. Gentleman on securing this second debate on the subject. However, will he confirm that the House of Lords decision does not affect people who have symptoms such as breathlessness that they can show were caused by pleural plaques? It is important that we reassure people that if they are ill, their rights have not been taken away.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.252.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1386" speakername="Michael Clapham" colnum="252"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0001.htm#08060495000457">
	<p pid="a.252.1/1">The hon. Gentleman will be aware that the House of Lords decision referred to the fact that people may be able to sue under contract law in cases where they have the condition. I am told by lawyers who have looked at this matter that there is no possibility of a case succeeding at contract. I agree that a worsening of the symptoms&mdash;for example, where diffuse pleural thickening is found&mdash;is a compensatable condition. In addition to compensation being pursued at common law, people may receive payment of an industrial injury disablement benefit where there is pleural thickening. I take the hon. Gentleman's point on board. However, it is important to show the Minister and her colleagues that there is a great deal of concern, because although the consultant says that pleural plaques are symptomless, he mentions that they can cause great discomfort. People come to my surgery and I meet people at trade union conferences. I attended the Union of Construction, Allied Trades and Technicians conference only three weeks ago and met a number of people who contend that their condition of breathlessness is the result of pleural plaques.</p>
	<p pid="a.252.1/2">I want to mention the background of one judge who dissented and had greater empathy, as that is an important factor in understanding why the judgment was made. I also want to draw attention to the hypocrisy of the insurance industry.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.252.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1744" speakername="Ian Gibson" colnum="252"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0001.htm#08060495000458">
	<p pid="a.252.2/1">Before my hon. Friend moves on to talk about judges, I should like to put on record that in respect of bowel cancer there was a phenomenon called polyps, some of which turned out, after years of research, to be early cancers. Perhaps, if we did the research and investigation, we would find that some pleural plaques might, because of other instances, turn into cancers. There is no evidence either way, so we need more research in that field, too.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.253.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1386" speakername="Michael Clapham" colnum="253"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0001.htm#08060495000459">
	<p pid="a.253.0/1">I am grateful for my hon. Friend's intervention. The TUC holds that, in addition to mesothelioma, some 4,000 people die from cancer after exposure to asbestos and it contends that that is clearly the result of the asbestos exposure, although there is not the same evidence to substantiate that point as there is, for example, in respect of mesothelioma cancer.</p>
	<p pid="a.253.0/2">The consultant said that, on investigation, chest X-rays show that less than 1 per cent. of the population are found to be suffering from pleural plaques. In other words, he dispels the view expressed by civil servants that pleural plaques occur generally within the population. That is not true. Pleural plaques occur only as a result of asbestos exposure and the country's leading medical expert has clearly made that point. X-ray evidence shows that people with pleural plaques have been exposed to asbestos and it is not a condition found in the general population.</p>
	<p pid="a.253.0/3">Roughly a third of people occupationally exposed to asbestos develop calcified pleural plaques after 30 years. After 20 years of exposure, 15 to 20 per cent. of people develop calcified pleural plaques. Again, that is clearly an indication that the body has been polluted and that there is an intensity of pleural plaques. One can well understand why people contend that their pleural plaques have caused breathlessness. As my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1744" name="Ian Gibson">the Member for Norwich, North (Dr. Gibson)</phrase> said, more research might show whether when pleural plaques intensify, the condition relates to breathlessness.</p>
	<p pid="a.253.0/4">We know that pleural plaques show a physical change in the lining of the lung in a person who has been exposed to asbestos&mdash;either occupationally and environmentally&mdash;and suffered the penetration of asbestos fibres. Mr. Rudd points out that people with pleural plaques commonly experience anxiety about the risk of mesothelioma and other serious diseases. As I said, I went to the UCATT conference a couple of weeks ago and talked to men with pleural plaques who work in the construction industry. This is what I was told.</p>
	<p pid="a.253.0/5">John Scott, a UCATT official from the north-east who has been diagnosed with pleural plaques, said:</p>
	<p pid="a.253.0/6" class="indent">&quot;For people like me the clock is ticking faster than it is for others. I try to be positive but in my heart of hearts it is always at the back of my mind.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.253.0/7">In other words, although he tries to take an optimistic view of life, he is brought back to reality by the knowledge at the back of his mind that he has pleural plaques and may develop mesothelioma cancer.</p>
	<p pid="a.253.0/8">Tony O'Brien, a UCATT worker from London, was diagnosed with pleural plaques three years ago. He has been exposed to asbestos since he was 15 years old when he started an apprenticeship in the construction industry. He said:</p>
	<p pid="a.253.0/9" class="indent">&quot;The most important thing is the recognition of the damage that has been done to you that didn't need to be done.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.253.0/10">In other words, the damage was clearly caused by negligence. It is a grievance that a person who has been negligently exposed to asbestos, which has caused a physiological change, is unable to make a compensation claim unless his condition worsens to the extent that he is fully disabled. I say that because when one sees someone who suffers from diffuse pleural thickening, they are often gasping for breath and cannot walk uphill. They are limited in their mobility and suffer from a worsening condition that causes a great deal of disability.</p>
	<p pid="a.253.0/11">The Law Lords' decision means that a person with pleural plaques is unable to claim compensation unless the condition worsens. That is despite the fact that, as Tony O'Brien says, he knows he was negligently exposed and would not be suffering from the condition if his employer had taken more care, yet he cannot sue for compensation until his condition worsens.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.254.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1427" speakername="David Anderson" colnum="254"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0001.htm#08060495000460">
	<p pid="a.254.0/1">Not only would Tony know, but his employer would know too, and that is where the real negligence lies. This has not gone on in ignorance but while employers knew that they were using a substance that was poisoning their work force.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.254.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1386" speakername="Michael Clapham" colnum="254"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0001.htm#08060495000461">
	<p pid="a.254.1/1">I thank my hon. Friend for that intervention. It is true that those men were negligently exposed. Part of the grievance is that men who were exposed from the age of 15 in the same way as Tony O'Brien are now unable to pursue compensation. The grievance is made worse because we know that until the House of Lords decision, compensation had been paid in such cases for 25 years. Those men carry a grievance and I say to the Minister that they feel they have been badly let down.</p>
	<p pid="a.254.1/2">The decision was made nine months ago, as the Minister knows because in July 2006 she played an important part in reversing the Barker judgment. The decision in that case was made in the House of Lords in May 2006 and by June the legislation to reverse it was on the statute book. However, there has been no movement on the matter after nine months, despite the concern caused among workmen who have been exposed to asbestos.</p>
	<p pid="a.254.1/3">As my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1427" name="David Anderson">the Member for Blaydon (Mr. Anderson)</phrase> said, it is clearly wrong that an employer should be able to evade their responsibility. The Minister should seriously consider that and think about overturning the Law Lords' decision through legislation. As I said, it is nine months since that decision was made. People like Tony O'Brien and John Scott have every right to be concerned because the fact that the ruling stands is a green light to other employers to take risks in future with people's health when using dangerous chemical or other substances at work. That is an important aspect of the judgment because employers will see that the employer in this asbestos case&mdash;pleural plaques&mdash;has been able to get away with it and does not have to pay compensation.</p>
	<p pid="a.254.1/4">There are 274,000 businesses in the UK construction industry. It is a fragmented industry and the bulk of employers are small companies. Those companies will think that the decision allows them to get away with exposing their work force to asbestos. It is also a green light to small companies in other industries, so we need to be seen to make swift progress on the matter.</p>
	<p pid="a.254.1/5">As I said, the Law Lords indicated that they had sympathy for the plight of the victims. It was suggested that some of the victims might sue for breach of contract. Lawyers have advised me that such cases would not succeed. I have always believed that there has been a failure to empathise in this case, and one can see that when considering the make-up of the judges. The dissenting judge, Lady Justice Janet Smith, comes from an altogether different background. She was a housewife for 10 years before she decided to study law, which she did through a correspondence course. When she became a barrister, she worked in Manchester for 20 years and represented occupational industrial disease cases and personal injury cases generally.</p>
	<p pid="a.254.1/6">It was Justice Janet Smith who dissented in the case; she made the point that she thought that the men should be paid compensation. Her experience sets her apart from her colleagues. She was closer to the victims. She understood them; she knew the background that they came from and the industries that they worked in, and that led to her decision that compensation should be paid. Even in the High Court, Mr. Justice Holland accepted that the men had been negligently exposed to asbestos and that they should be paid compensation for their pleural plaques. I therefore urge the Minister to take up with her colleagues the need to move speedily to ensure that the men can claim compensation.</p>
	<p pid="a.254.1/7">The Minister has to be aware that what we are debating is one of a series of attacks on asbestos victims by the insurance industry. We have already mentioned the Barker case. I have the transcript of an interesting interview that took place on Radio 4 on the day of the Law Lords' decision: <phrase class="date" code="2007-10-17">17 October 2007</phrase>. In that interview, the representative of the insurance industry, Mr. Nick Starling, said, &quot;We&quot;&mdash;the insurance industry&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.254.1/8" class="indent">&quot;are absolutely committed to making sure that people who are affected by the deadly effects of asbestos, mesothelioma, asbestosis and so forth get their compensation quickly.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.254.1/9">However, when we juxtapose that statement with the action of the insurance industry yesterday in launching a test case on the trigger issue, it is shown to be pure hypocrisy. I understand that there will be a nine-week hearing in the court and the case will most probably finish up in the House of Lords. If the insurance industry is successful in the trigger case, it will be able to escape liability completely. The insurance industry comes back time and again, like a jackal, to tackle the issue of occupational disease caused by asbestos. It is therefore important that the Minister takes a stand.</p>
	<p pid="a.254.1/10">The problem for the victim in such a situation is that there may be no other insurer to pay their claim. We shall see whether the insurance industry succeeds with the trigger case, which is really about deciding which insurance company should pay compensation and whether the tumour was caused when the fibre was first inhaled or whether the point at which the insurance industry should take things up is when the tumour develops, which may be 40 years afterwards. By that time, there may not be an insurer that can be traced and the company may not be in business, so if the insurance industry is successful, it could escape liability altogether. The case clearly shows hypocrisy on the part of the insurance industry: on one hand, it says that it wants to pay fair compensation, but on the other hand it is coming back time after time, like a jackal, to try to ensure that it can dispose of liability altogether in asbestos cases.</p>
	<p pid="a.254.1/11">I understand that a consultation exercise will be launched in the next couple of weeks, but I strongly suggest to the Minister, even at this eleventh hour, that she does the following things. She has to emphasise to her colleagues the need to reverse the Law Lords' decision. That is the best and cleanest way forward. Legislation could be framed to say that any permanent, irreversible structural change to the lung or lining of the lung diagnosed during a person's lifetime as pleural plaques, pleural thickening or asbestosis caused by negligent exposure to asbestos shall amount to actionable damage and be compensatable and this shall include any action for such damage that has been struck out or discontinued since <phrase class="date" code="2007-10-17">17 October 2007</phrase>. If we had legislation based on that principle, we could return to the situation that prevailed before the Law Lords' decision, which would be fairer for everybody concerned.</p>
	<p pid="a.254.1/12">The Minister might also consider insisting that the insurers use their considerable savings from the pleural plaques judgment. She may be aware of the suggestion that they made savings of &pound;1.4 billion as a result of the judgment. She might like to insist that the insurers set up a fund for claimants who, through no fault of their own, cannot identify an insurer and whose employer has gone out of business. That would ensure that people caught in that situation could claim compensation from the fund. The Minister might want to raise that with the insurance industry.</p>
	<p pid="a.254.1/13">If there is to be a consultation, I hope that the Minister has thought about the long delay that there has been&mdash;it is nine months since the decision&mdash;and will make it the shortest period of consultation possible. If we have to wait six months before we can start considering the options, people will feel that we have failed. It is important that we show people that we want to restore a fair compensation system.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.256.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1761" speakername="Linda Gilroy" colnum="256"  time="009:56:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0001.htm#08060495000462">
	<p pid="a.256.0/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1386" name="Michael Clapham">the Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone (Mr. Clapham)</phrase> on securing the debate, which is timely. He has led much of the work on this issue. I think that I am right in saying that he was involved in initiating the sub-committee of the all-party group on occupational safety and health, which deals with these matters and keeps them before us. I say to hon. Members who have not yet picked up a copy of the debate pack provided by the House of Commons Library that he has also done us a great service by prompting the production of that pack, because for those of us who have continuously to explain to constituents where the problem stemmed from, it sets out clearly how we have come to this situation, which needs to be changed.</p>
	<p pid="a.256.0/2">My hon. Friend spoke very clearly about how this condition comes from exposure to asbestos at work and how people who are exposed at work to asbestos are 1,000 times more likely than others to develop this condition. My constituency contains the Devonport dockyard, which sadly makes the area a hotspot for deaths arising from asbestos-related diseases. As my hon. Friend mentioned, one third of people develop disease from the pleural plaque condition that turns into a cancer within a 30-year period and 20 per cent. within 20 years. I think that those were the figures that he cited.</p>
	<p pid="a.256.0/3">In Plymouth, we have had 250 deaths in the past 15 years. In 1968, in the early days following people's exposure at work, the number of deaths was as low as 153, but now it is 2,000 a year and it will probably peak at about 2,500 over the next 10 years. We are not talking just about individuals; there are also families whose anxiety is raised&mdash;probably 7,000 to 10,000, if one third go on to develop the condition. Given that some of those families' worries do not translate into death from a cancer-related disease arising from pleural plaques, the number of people affected is much greater than such figures suggest.</p>
	<p pid="a.256.0/4">I pay tribute to everybody who supports people in this campaign and in dealing with those anxieties. I am thinking of groups such as that in my constituency, which was set up by the family of Roger Lowe, who was a dockyard electrical fitter. He lost his battle against the disease in 2005. His family, and particularly his daughter Jackie, who is an articulate spokesperson, have raised these issues. They want to ensure that people can make the best of things. If the disease becomes a cancer, I think I am right to say that people have about 18 months from that point until death. One reason that that gives rise to anxiety for those who have pleural plaques is that they wish to be prepared&mdash;to make those last months as good as possible and to find out about the various support services available.</p>
	<p pid="a.256.0/5">We should also pay tribute to the trade unions that are backing the campaign. The Union of Construction, Allied Trades and Technicians has already been mentioned, but I know that the Public and Commercial Services Union, Unite and GMB are also actively backing the campaign in my constituency.</p>
	<p pid="a.256.0/6">In May, we had an interesting seminar, but great concern was expressed about the time that it will take to sort out the House of Lords ruling. My hon. Friend the Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone has put before us a straightforward and clear way for that to take place. For all those who are worrying about these things, the sooner we sort them out the better. My constituents feel let down.</p>
	<p pid="a.256.0/7">We should consider how many hon. Members have raised the matter in questions, signed early-day motions and have campaigns running in their local constituencies. My hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1744" name="Ian Gibson">the Member for Norwich, North (Dr. Gibson)</phrase> runs an open surgery campaign in his local paper, as the <i>Evening Herald</i> does for Plymouth. The Norwich <i>Evening News</i> runs what it calls the &quot;Dust of Death&quot; campaign.</p>
	<p pid="a.256.0/8">I hope that we will hear shortly from my hon. Friend the Minister of a way ahead. We have heard that there will be consultation, but I hope that it will not be overly complicated and lengthy. The suggestion of my hon. Friend the Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone has the merit of being straightforward; it has great clarity and may prove to be a possible outcome. Once again, I thank him for giving us this timely opportunity to debate the matter. It reminds us what the issue means to our constituents. I hope that we will hear of some progress from the Minister.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.257.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1427" speakername="David Anderson" colnum="257"  time="010:02:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0002.htm#08060495000463">
	<p pid="a.257.0/1">I thank my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1386" name="Michael Clapham">the Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone (Mr. Clapham)</phrase> for initiating the debate. I also thank the Minister; as was mentioned earlier, she has a good track record in trying to address such issues&mdash;and certainly in helping to overturn the Barker ruling. That was most welcome to those who sadly came together to campaign about the problems of exposure to asbestos, a problem that has happened too frequently for well over a century.</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/2">I thank my hon. Friend the Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone for producing the letter from Mr. Rudd. It dispels many myths that have grown up around the subject debate; I shall return to it later. First, however, I want to ask how we got to this state.</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/3">As I said earlier, we have had 25 years of people having the right to compensation, which no one seemed to think was out of order or too expensive&mdash;except, of course, the employers and their insurers. I have no doubt that the lawyers in the Chamber and those outside will explain in great detail why it was the right thing to do. I am no lawyer, and I do not pretend to be one, but I have some simple questions, which will show that there has been negligence.</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/4">First and foremost, did people suffer? There is no doubt that they did&mdash;thousands, perhaps tens of thousands or even hundreds of thousands suffered over the years. Did the employers know that people were suffering? Yes, they did. Did they know that the substance being used was poisonous? Yes, they did; they have known since 1892, when asbestos was declared to be a poisonous substance; and they have known since 1965, when they were told not to use it any more. However, people are still suffering.</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/5">Did employers do anything to alleviate the problem? To an extent, yes they did. Was it enough? Clearly, it was not. Were they liable? If we answered yes to the previous questions, I do not see how we can give any other answer than yes to that last question. Were they negligent? Clearly, they were. Were they criminally negligent? To my mind, they were.</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/6">It is clear that the people who are pushing this are the insurance lobby. Having pushed it this far, they are already gearing up to challenge what might be a way to resolve the matter. We are led to believe that the Scottish Parliament will try to address the legal situation in Scotland, making changes to the law that will allow people in Scotland to challenge the House of Lords ruling.</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/7">However, I have been advised that the insurance lobby is already talking of going for a judicial review. They are thinking of using the European human rights legislation&mdash;if it was not so serious, it would be funny. They speak of challenging the very remit of the Scottish Parliament&mdash;whether it has the constitutional authority to challenge a House of Lords ruling.</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/8">I would be very interested to hear the Minister answer those points about the position of the Scottish Parliament. Does she, and do the Government, support the attempts by the Scottish Parliament to take action to resolve the matter for Scottish people? If possible, will she help the Scottish Parliament to progress the matter despite the influence and the interference of the insurance lobby?</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/9">It is clear, as we heard from my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1761" name="Linda Gilroy">the Member for Plymouth, Sutton (Linda Gilroy)</phrase>, that Ministers have seriously considered the matter. We have had a number of meetings since the matter was first raised, culminating a month ago with a meeting with the Prime Minister. The Prime Minister was very sympathetic to the case being put forward, but some of the advice that he might have been offered gives me cause for concern.</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/10">At that meeting, we were told by an adviser that as many as one person in five could be suffering with pleural plaques. I guess that that is about 12.5 million people; if we have to consider the needs of that many people, it is a very serious situation. I asked the adviser if he could provide me with more information. I am still waiting for it. Much more important, however, is the advice that we were given by Mr. Rudd, who is an expert in these matters. He says clearly that less than 1 per cent. of the general population have the problem, and that for nearly all of them it was the result of a history of exposure to asbestos. That is the key: although it is a big issue, it is nothing like as big as we are led to believe by the Prime Minister's adviser.</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/11">The other thing that worries me&mdash;it was brought out in the previous debate on this subject in this Chamber&mdash;is that some in the industry and some doctors say that it is nothing to worry about. They say that the real problem is people worrying about being ill, and that if people did not know that they had pleural plaques they would not worry and therefore would not be ill. However, if Mr. Rudd is correct, people who have been exposed to asbestos at work have a more than 1,000 times greater risk of contracting mesothelioma than the general population. Those people are right to be worried. We in this Chamber should be aware of that issue, and try seriously to put it right.</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/12">The last sentence of Mr. Rudd's letter gives another reason why people should be looked after properly. He says,</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/13" class="indent">&quot;This anxiety is real for all, and for some it has had a serious adverse effect on their quality of life.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/14">If that is not an issue that should be addressed by the House, what is?</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/15">Like my hon. Friend the Member for Plymouth, Sutton, I work closely with a group involved in the mesothelioma campaign&mdash;the Mick Knighton Mesothelioma Research Fund in the north-east of England. The campaign is run mainly by widows of relatively young men who died in the prime of life. They support each other and raise funds to push forward research. It is clear that they should not have to do this, but they have no alternative. They believe that the only way to make the issue somehow bearable is to try to resolve it for themselves and their families.</p>
	<p pid="a.257.0/16">This is about real people. My hon. Friend the Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone mentioned John Scott, who is a UCATT official in the north-east of England. I had the great privilege of working with him for many years on Newcastle city council. He has spent a lifetime standing up for other people who work in some of the most dangerous occupations in the country in the building and construction industry. He is the sort of person that I came into Parliament to stand up for. If John Scott has pleural plaques, he should be looked after, as should people like him. We should do that now. Will the Minister listen carefully to what is being said today? The consultation period is welcome, but it needs to be short, precise and effective. We need action in the House: if the law needs changing, we should go ahead and do it.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.259.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2007" speakername="Jim Sheridan" colnum="259"  time="010:10:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0002.htm#08060495000464">
	<p pid="a.259.0/1">I add my thanks to my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1386" name="Michael Clapham">the Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone (Mr. Clapham)</phrase> for securing the debate. The issue will not go away until or unless we get some sort of satisfactory conclusion on behalf of our constituents who suffer from that terrible disease.</p>
	<p pid="a.259.0/2">I shall be brief, but I will not dilute in any way the importance of the debate. I am not only anxious to hear what the Minister has to say and to allow her ample time to speak, but to hear what the Opposition parties say. To date, they have been extremely helpful and supportive in the campaign to get justice for those who suffer from pleural plaques. I also thank my hon. Friend the Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone for bringing forward new evidence this morning, and I hope that the Minister reflects on it and responds accordingly.</p>
	<p pid="a.259.0/3">The debate on pleural plaques has been well rehearsed in this Chamber and throughout the country. To my mind, there is no tangible evidence to prevent the Government from introducing legislation that will compensate those workers who, through no fault of their own, have contracted the disease.</p>
	<p pid="a.259.0/4">Insurance companies and their legal conspirators play a role in the drama. From day one, insurance companies have set out to block and obstruct the legislation that provided workers with decent compensation, which prompts the question why, after 25 or 30 years, the matter has gone back to the House of Lords. The only reason I can think of is that the insurance companies are trying to cut costs and save money by denying people compensation.</p>
	<p pid="a.259.0/5">To digress briefly, there was a similar example of such practice under Scots law not so long ago. It used to be that when people died of mesothelioma, their claim died with them, so we saw the unedifying spectacle of insurance companies engaging medical practitioners to assess, across the courtroom, how long a claimant had to live. The companies would then find some sort of technicality to put the case back, hoping that the claimant would die and their claim with them. I mention that to give the Minister and the Government a flavour of the kind of people with whom we are dealing in the insurance industry: they may have sharp suits, but they also have sharp practices. Fortunately, under Scots law, the trade unions, to their credit, fought and won the case, so when someone dies, their family can claim compensation.</p>
	<p pid="a.259.0/6">My hon. Friend the Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone mentioned the previous debate on the matter and the branch of the GMB in London&mdash;only one branch&mdash;in which at least 12 people per year contracted pleural plaques. A significant number of those people went on to die of mesothelioma. That is one branch, as I said, so extrapolating that number throughout the UK would give us an idea of the seriousness of the problem. If the same number of cattle were affected by a disease, the <i>Daily Mail</i> and others would argue that compensation should be at the top of the list, and that it should be a priority for the Government to compensate the farmers whose cattle had died. What is the difference between cattle and human beings?</p>
	<p pid="a.259.0/7">There is an international dimension to the matter. The trade unions and the Government have worked to regulate the use of asbestos in the country, but producers have now moved to third-world countries. There is evidence that people in such countries are suffering from the same disease that people in this country suffered from some years ago. That producers of asbestos move from this country to exploit workers in developing countries is a problem. There is a moral case for this country to lead the way and say, &quot;If you poison and exploit people in third-world countries, you should suffer the same consequences as you would here.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.259.0/8">There is hope that the Scottish Parliament will introduce legislation to deal with the problem. I have said this before and I shall say it again: I sincerely hope that it brings forward legislation to overturn the ridiculous decision by the Law Lords. I still live in Scotland, and I have watched the performance of the current of the Administration there, so I have some doubts that they will deliver, given that they have delivered on very few of their promises to date. I wish them the best, but I sincerely hope that the UK Government is not standing back waiting for the Scottish Parliament to legislate. Like my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1427" name="David Anderson">the Member for Blaydon (Mr. Anderson)</phrase>, I want to know what discussion, if any, the Minister or the Ministry of Justice has had with the Scottish Parliament on the issue and what progress has been made.</p>
	<p pid="a.259.0/9">I have a high level of respect for the Minister&mdash;she is a progressive thinker and a fighter for workers' rights&mdash;but, in the previous debate on the matter, she said that she had a duty to consult other Departments. Will she detail which Departments she has consulted and tell us what their position is? What assistance can those of us who are campaigning for legislation to be introduced offer to bring about a satisfactory conclusion?</p>
	<p pid="a.259.0/10">I am at a loss, as are people outside the Westminster bubble, as to why we need yet more consultation. We have had consultation since October last year. Perhaps people have not been listening, but do we need further consultation? If so, how long will it take? People are anxious about where we are going with those consultations. Telling them that we need another three or six months' consultation on the matter suggests that we are kicking it into the long grass. I sincerely hope that that is not the case.</p>
	<p pid="a.259.0/11">Like others, I was extremely heartened when the Prime Minister appeared at the Scottish trade union Conference and said that the Government are working toward solving the problem of pleural plaques and that they will bring forward legislation in the near future&mdash;he reiterated that at the Scottish Labour party conference. The Prime Minister is a man of integrity. He has said clearly that we want to be on the side of hard-working families and to introduce fairness. To my mind, there is nothing more fair than saying to the workers of this country, &quot;If you contract a disease outwith your control, those responsible will be held accountable.&quot;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.261.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1473" speakername="David Howarth" colnum="261"  time="010:19:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0002.htm#08060495000465">
	<p pid="a.261.0/1">I repeat my congratulations to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1386" name="Michael Clapham">the hon. Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone (Mr. Clapham)</phrase> on securing the second debate on pleural plaques in six months. The fact that he has done so illustrates the importance of this subject.</p>
	<p pid="a.261.0/2">Although I do not want to take up hon. Members' time by repeating what I said in our earlier debate, I stand by what I said then. In particular, I want to mention a point that I raised in that debate, because it is important and has not come up today. Possibly the worst result in the House of Lords cases was that in the Grieves <i>v.</i> Everard case. Unlike those in all the other cases, Mr. Grieves had a recognised psychiatric illness as a result of what had happened to him. People with such illnesses are legally in a very different position from those who suffer simply from anxiety. It is incomprehensible that Mr. Grieves was denied compensation, and I urge the Government to review, in its entirety, the law on psychiatric damage in such cases and, indeed, in all cases.</p>
	<p pid="a.261.0/3">As the hon. Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone has said, we currently have two ways forward, and he described both. One is to reverse the legal result in the House of Lords cases, which has also been suggested in Scotland. The other is to ensure that there is a proper fund from which people can claim if they eventually suffer from the serious diseases associated with asbestos&mdash;mesothelioma and asbestosis.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.262.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1737" speakername="Henry Bellingham" colnum="262"  time="010:19:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0002.htm#08060495000466">
	<p pid="a.262.0/1">The hon. Gentleman is making an interesting point. He has mentioned pleural plaques sufferers going on to develop serious symptoms, but some sufferers will obviously develop less serious ones. Beyond mere stress and anxiety, they may develop physical symptoms that are not life-threatening. Surely, they should also be able to claim from the fund that he proposes.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.262.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1473" speakername="David Howarth" colnum="262"  time="010:19:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0002.htm#08060495000467">
	<p pid="a.262.1/1">That is possible, but it needs to be said that people with symptoms of illness&mdash;breathlessness and general physical problems&mdash;are allowed to claim under the existing law. The House of Lords did not say that they could not, and it is a misunderstanding of what the Lords said&mdash;this is causing anxiety in various communities&mdash;to think otherwise. Such people are not excluded.</p>
	<p pid="a.262.1/2">Let me return to the two solutions. I understand why the Government are having difficulty with the first one&mdash;the reversal of the law in the House of Lords case&mdash;and I will explain why I think that they are right to think that there are difficulties. Indeed, the fact that there are such difficulties is probably why there has been little progress in Scotland, despite the fact that the Scottish Justice Minister announced almost immediately that the Scottish Parliament would reverse the judgment. Those difficulties with the first suggestion are, however, no excuse for not getting on with the second one, which provides a practical way forward. I therefore want to hear the Minister's view not only on the first suggestion from the hon. Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone, but on the second one.</p>
	<p pid="a.262.1/3">Why is it understandable that the Government should hesitate to go forward with the hon. Gentleman's first suggestion and reverse the judgment? All the bad reasons for hesitating have to do with the insurance industry, but there is one good reason for hesitating, and it relates to the question of how such a statute would leave people who were in similar positions, because they still could not sue. There is the question of fairness towards other sorts of claimant.</p>
	<p pid="a.262.1/4">Let me give two examples. What about people who have received blood transfusions that might be tainted with HIV or hepatitis? They have a higher risk than the rest of the population of developing AIDS or hepatitis, and they will be very anxious about that. They are therefore in a similar position to people with pleural plaques, but they would not be allowed to sue under the hon. Gentleman's suggestion, because it would apply only to those with pleural plaques.</p>
	<p pid="a.262.1/5">The second example, which raises an even more serious problem, relates to people who were exposed to large amounts of asbestos, but who have not developed plaques.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.263.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1386" speakername="Michael Clapham" colnum="263"  time="010:19:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0003.htm#08060495000468">
	<p pid="a.263.0/1">As yet.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.263.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1473" speakername="David Howarth" colnum="263"  time="010:19:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0003.htm#08060495000469">
	<p pid="a.263.1/1">As yet. Such people may not, however, develop plaques before they develop mesothelioma. The problem is that those people, who are in exactly the same position in terms of the risk that they face, would not benefit from the hon. Gentleman's suggestion. There is a question of fairness across these various groups of possible claimant, which is a problem.</p>
	<p pid="a.263.1/2">As the letter from the consultant expert mentioned by the hon. Gentleman stated, having pleural plaques does not in itself cause an infirmity&mdash;it might, and if it does, the right to sue will still remain&mdash;but simply marks the fact someone has been exposed to asbestos. At the same time, many people who do not develop plaques, but who have been exposed to asbestos, are at exactly the same risk of developing mesothelioma or asbestosis and should, therefore, be treated in the same way as those who have developed pleural plaques.</p>
	<p pid="a.263.1/3">Hon. Members have already discussed why cases came to the House of Lords when they did. The House of Lords decided that it was not possible in general to sue for the future risk of contracting a disease and that people had to wait until something bad happened to them before they could sue&mdash;that was the ruling in the case of Gregg <i>v. </i>Scott in 2005. As a consequence, it became almost inevitable that the pleural plaques cases would go the way they did.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.263.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2007" speakername="Jim Sheridan" colnum="263"  time="010:19:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0003.htm#08060495000470">
	<p pid="a.263.2/1">I am closely following what the hon. Gentleman is saying. My point is that the House of Lords did not wake up one morning and say, &quot;Let's deny compensation to pleural plaques sufferers.&quot; What happened was a direct result of the insurance companies' challenge.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.263.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1473" speakername="David Howarth" colnum="263"  time="010:19:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0003.htm#08060495000471">
	<p pid="a.263.3/1">I fully accept that the situation has come about because the insurance industry took advantage of the new legal situation, but the insurance industry did not create that situation. The situation was created in a different context&mdash;that of medical cases&mdash;and related to the general point about whether someone was allowed to sue for risks that had not yet arisen. There is a gigantic legal debate about that general question, which has not yet been resolved.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.263.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1761" speakername="Linda Gilroy" colnum="263"  time="010:19:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0003.htm#08060495000472">
	<p pid="a.263.4/1">I, too, am following closely what the hon. Gentleman is saying, because a number of people have deployed these arguments. In addition to the point made by my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2007" name="Jim Sheridan">the Member for Paisley and Renfrewshire, North (Jim Sheridan)</phrase>, there is the fact that the conditions that we are talking about were compensated to a modest extent for 20 years&mdash;we are talking about sums of &pound;5,000 to &pound;10,000. Does the hon. Gentleman not think that that makes this situation somewhat different and explains why our constituents feel that it is so unfair?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.263.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1473" speakername="David Howarth" colnum="263"  time="010:19:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0003.htm#08060495000473">
	<p pid="a.263.5/1">I understand the feeling of the hon. Lady's constituents. My point is simply that it was thought before the Gregg <i>v.</i> Scott case that it might be possible to sue for risk on its own. That is an unresolved issue in the law, which goes back to a House of Lords case called Hotson <i>v.</i> East Berkshire relating to medical negligence. When the Gregg case was decided, however, it became clear that people could not sue for future risks.</p>
	<p pid="a.263.5/2">The question whether people should be able to sue for future risks is a difficult one. Let us say that there are 100 people and that there is a 5 per cent. chance that some of them will develop a disease or condition. If people were allowed to sue for future risk, one would give each of those 100 people 5 per cent. of the future damages to which they would be entitled were they to get the full disease. The problem with that is that 95 of them would turn out to be overcompensated, because they would get 5 per cent. compensation even though they did not get the final disease, while five of them would not get compensation for the whole seriousness of the condition. We might then say, &quot;Let us give the 5 per cent. full compensation, but still give the 95 per cent. 5 per cent&quot;, but the defendants would complain that they were paying out almost double the compensation than if they had simply compensated people with the disease.</p>
	<p pid="a.263.5/3">That is a big unresolved problem with the law, and the consequences of changing the whole law are not yet worked through. It is not clear that it would be a good idea. However, if only the bit concerning pleural plaques is changed, the result is the anomaly of how to deal with people in exactly the same position&mdash;including people exposed to asbestos&mdash;who would benefit if the whole law were changed, but not from the suggestion of the hon. Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.264.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1386" speakername="Michael Clapham" colnum="264"  time="010:19:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0003.htm#08060495000474">
	<p pid="a.264.0/1">The reality prior to the House of Lords decision was that when a man was found to have pleural plaques and received compensation the insurance industry would approach him to ask whether he was prepared to accept a full and final settlement or an interim payment. Such individuals were put in an invidious position, which my hon. Friend the Minister has removed as a result of her work on the Child Maintenance and Other Payments Bill. The payments with respect to mesothelioma will address that situation. The overlapping of different statutes has created a betterment. It seems to me&mdash;the hon. Gentleman admits this&mdash;that the law cannot deal with every problem. Yet the solution that I have put to the Minister would reverse the situation and at least make things better, although not in every case because some cases would be missed.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.264.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1473" speakername="David Howarth" colnum="264"  time="010:19:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0003.htm#08060495000475">
	<p pid="a.264.1/1">I accept the hon. Gentleman's point that there would be an improvement for some cases by following that course of action. The question then is whether it would be right to follow it for all cases. I have spent too much time in my remarks understanding the Government's difficulties, and I do not want to understand them any more, but I recognise that they have a responsibility to the whole range of possible claimants under tort law.</p>
	<p pid="a.264.1/2">I have only a couple of minutes left, and I want to spend them agreeing with the second of the suggestions made by the hon. Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone, which is crucial. The real problem now is that a large number of people are potential claimants with respect to serious disease at some point in the future. When they develop those diseases, they can claim, but what happens when we get to that point and find that the company has gone out of existence, because it is insolvent, or, worse, that as in the Cape cases, which hon. Members will remember, there has been some corporate engineering, so the only bit of the company that is liable is a bit that does not have any money? Those are the possibilities against which the Government must act.</p>
	<p pid="a.264.1/3">There are two points to make: first, the law must require some sort of contingent liability fund to be set up, either directly by the defendant companies, or through the insurance industry; and secondly, we must make sure that future victims will be allowed to claim directly against the fund, and not be told that they can claim only against insolvent companies, and that there is no point. Progress can be made on both those points now, without a vast amount of thought about the consequences for fairness in the rest of the law. That is why I fully support the hon. Gentleman's second suggestion and urge the Minister to think about that suggestion separately from his first.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.265.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1737" speakername="Henry Bellingham" colnum="265"  time="010:34:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0003.htm#08060495000476">
	<p pid="a.265.0/1">I, too, congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1386" name="Michael Clapham">the hon. Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone (Mr. Clapham)</phrase>. He made a good and telling contribution on <phrase class="date" code="2008-01-23">23 January</phrase>, but there was not enough time in that debate for every participant to make a long speech. He presented his case very well, with passion and sincerity. It was most heartfelt.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/2">The issue as a whole affects not only the industrial heartlands of the country, but almost every constituency. Indeed, a significant number of my constituents in North-West Norfolk, which is hardly one of our great industrial heartlands, suffer from pleural plaques problems. They are either retired people or people who have worked in the construction, lagging or other industries. It was interesting to hear the speech of <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1761" name="Linda Gilroy">the hon. Member for Plymouth, Sutton (Linda Gilroy)</phrase>, and to learn about her experience and expertise in connection with shipbuilding and related industries in her constituency.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/3">An aspect of the debate that has struck me is the remarkable success of campaigners on behalf of employees exposed to asbestos, dust and related problems. The history of the issue encompasses the Pneumoconiosis etc. (Workers' Compensation) Act 1979, the action taken to assist mesothelioma sufferers, the Compensation Act 2006, which stipulated that negligent companies had to be jointly and severally liable, and part 4 of the Child Maintenance and Other Payments Bill, which the hon. Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone mentioned. There have also been changes to the civil procedure rules and a practice direction to ensure a uniform fast-track system for all mesothelioma cases. Significant progress can be seen if one looks across the whole spectrum.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/4">Before the House of Lords ruling the law was based mainly on the 1980 case of Patterson <i>v.</i> Ministry of Defence, because a key finding in that case was the theory of aggregation: although the mere existence of pleural plaques could not give rise to a claim, when it was aggregated with the risk of anxiety the situation changed, and a claim could be mounted. The result was that most of the cases were settled and, as the hon. Member for Plymouth, Sutton said a moment ago, most were settled at a fairly modest level. The average settlement was at about the &pound;5,000 mark. Some claims were settled for less, at about &pound;2,000, and some for slightly more, up to about &pound;10,000; large amounts of money were not involved. However, for a pensioner or pensioner couple who had worked hard all their lives for probably pretty mediocre wages and who were suffering great stress and anxiety, such sums, although not exactly life-changing, could make the difference between worry about the future and the ability to afford a holiday, perhaps, or a few other things to cheer up their lives. That is why the difference to those families was significant.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/5">The status quo ante was perfectly satisfactory, because those modest awards were being paid. The cost to the insurance industry was significant, but I do not think that a single insurance company experienced a reduction in profits or in bonuses paid to directors, or significantly increased the costs to other policy holders. The figure of roughly &pound;1 billion has been mentioned, but we should not forget that the problem is a finite one, because the unfortunate truth is that many of the pensioners, retired employees and pensioner couples are now quite old. The context in which we are discussing the matter is one of greatly improved health and safety at work so the problem will eventually go away, but there is an immediate crisis for the affected families.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/6">It is a great pity that the House of Lords took the decision it did in Johnston <i>v.</i> NEI International Combustion, Rothwell <i>v.</i> Chemical and Insulating Company and the related cases, although I can understand why it did so. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1473" name="David Howarth">The hon. Member for Cambridge (David Howarth)</phrase>, who among other things is obviously an outstanding law lecturer&mdash;in fact, if I had spent less time in the pub when I was at Cambridge, and more time attending lectures by people like him, I might have got a better degree&mdash;explained in detail why the decision did not surprise him, and why it was in line with a growing and developing trend in tort case law. He mentioned the case of Gregg <i>v.</i> Scott.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/7">One of the aspects of the House of Lords decision that interested me was the amount of medical evidence that is now on the record. In our debate in January, a number of hon. Members quoted medical experts. On one hand, medical experts Professor Mark Britton and Professor Tony Newman-Taylor, pre-eminent chest physicians and world-renowned experts on lung disease, confirmed that pleural plaques were not prevalent in the general male population and were an indicator of asbestos exposure. In other words, one cannot develop pleural plaques passively or as a result of smoking or other activities. They were quite adamant in their advice on the House of Lords case.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/8">On the other hand, the House of Lords quoted other medical experts, including Dr. John Moore-Gillon, then president of the British Lung Foundation, and Dr. Robin Rudd. Dr. Rudd, a leading consultant, was fairly adamant in his advice to the House of Lords that pleural plaques in themselves did not necessarily lead to any malignant problems or asbestosis, but in the letter quoted by the hon. Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone, he clarified his views and put forward a very different argument. I find that interesting. I hope that the Minister will call in Dr. Rudd and have a discussion with him to find out exactly why his view is changing. It leads me to suggest that medical opinion is divided. A wider inquiry is needed. Surely she should consider setting up a royal commission, or at least tasking the Industrial Injuries Advisory Council to investigate the issue, to pull together all the medical evidence, get the experts in and see whether there is any consensus between the two sides. It certainly looks as though consensus is more likely, in light of what Dr. Robin Rudd has been saying recently.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/9">The data are fragmented, as a number of Members pointed out. I am sympathetic to the idea of a medical register, but I note that the Association of British Insurers is against it and said in its briefing to Members:</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/10" class="indent">&quot;We know that some have called for a new database to record the details of people with pleural plaques. The ABI rejects this proposal. It would not benefit people with plaques, and may cause anxiety&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/11">However, it is essential to have those data.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/12">The hon. Member for Cambridge suggested setting up a fund. The insurance industry has made the point that a pleural plaques sufferer who goes on to develop more serious symptoms or mesothelioma can sue. On the other hand, for someone who is ill and has a limited life expectancy to have to go through all the anxiety and stress of a case is completely unreasonable. That is why I am attracted by the idea that a fund could be set up to pay immediate compensation to anyone with pleural plaques who has developed a physical illness as a result.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/13">I urge the insurance industry to move quickly to use some of the roughly &pound;1 billion that it is saving to set up a fund. Why cannot the Minister join the insurance industry in helping to set it up? The official Opposition would certainly support her if she could persuade her Treasury colleagues to come forward with some money to help pump-prime a fund, on condition that the insurance industry puts up a majority of the money. Will she consider that idea carefully?</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/14">Will the Minister also consider exactly what the cost of legislation would be? I entirely accept the points made by the hon. Member for Cambridge: to introduce legislation to overturn the House of Lords decision could indeed lead to conflicts of interest and have significant implications for other types of tort. He mentioned blood transfusion victims; I am thinking, too, of people who have been subjected to toxic fumes, and other people subjected to various nuisances and torts who have not yet developed serious symptoms.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/15">On the other hand, I do not think that it is beyond the wit of the intelligent lawyers in the Ministry of Justice to come up with a tightly-framed Bill targeted exactly at pleural plaques victims that would not lead to any precedents being set. If the Minister can move forward on that basis, the Conservatives would be sympathetic, and would help and support her, but will she tell us what such legislation would cost? We need to know where we stand and how many victims are out there. We need a proper register, and we need to know exactly what it would cost the Treasury.</p>
	<p pid="a.265.0/16">I understand fully that the Minister's budget is tight, but the debates today and on <phrase class="date" code="2008-01-23">23 January</phrase> have shown the level of feeling in the country. That feeling has been articulated by hon. Members from all parties. People feel very let down. They feel betrayed by what has happened. They do not understand all the legal nuances and the arguments that have been put back and forth. They do not understand what the insurance companies have been saying. What they do know is that a situation that could have given them some slight relief has been taken away, and they look to the Government to come up with solutions. The Conservatives will certainly support the Minister in any action that she takes.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.268.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1682" speakername="Bridget Prentice" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Justice"  colnum="268"  time="010:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0003.htm#08060495000477">
	<p pid="a.268.0/1">I, too, congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1386" name="Michael Clapham">the Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone (Mr. Clapham)</phrase> on securing the second debate on pleural plaques in six months. As <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1737" name="Henry Bellingham">the hon. Member for North-West Norfolk (Mr. Bellingham)</phrase> said, my hon. Friend spoke persuasively in January, as did my other hon. Friends, and he has done so again today. He has spoken persuasively, cogently, powerfully and passionately about an issue that clearly raises great concerns among many of our constituents. We covered many of the same issues in the previous debate, but some issues were raised today that I want to consider a bit more. If I may, I will talk through some of the things that have happened in the past six months and then respond, as far as I can, to some of the particular issues raised today.</p>
	<p pid="a.268.0/2">It is important to put on record again the fact that both the Ministry of Justice and the Government as a whole are absolutely committed to helping people who have been exposed to asbestos, as we have demonstrated in the initiatives that have been mentioned. The Compensation Act 2006 gives people who have contracted mesothelioma the opportunity to get their compensation more quickly, and the new practice direction for mesothelioma claims, which came into effect in April, will ensure that claims are resolved quickly and interim payments are made at the earliest opportunity.</p>
	<p pid="a.268.0/3">As my hon. Friend said, the Child Maintenance and Other Payments Bill will provide up-front financial support for mesothelioma sufferers who were not eligible before, including those who were exposed as a result of contact with a relative, for example by washing their clothes. He kindly gave me credit for the measure, although I do not deserve it, as my colleagues at the Department for Work and Pensions took through the provisions. However, it shows the Government's commitment across Departments to giving people suffering from a particularly horrible disease some security in the last few months of their lives.</p>
	<p pid="a.268.0/4">The previous debate was secured by my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2007" name="Jim Sheridan">the Member for Paisley and Renfrewshire, North (Jim Sheridan)</phrase>. I told him at the time that I would continue to hold discussions with hon. Members about the effects of the House of Lords decision to see whether there was a way for us to help and support people with pleural plaques. My right hon. Friend the Justice Secretary and I have indeed had further discussions with a variety of interested parties: colleagues, trade unions, the insurance industry and others. As the Prime Minister said in March in response to my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1658" name="Stephen Hepburn">the Member for Jarrow (Mr. Hepburn)</phrase>, the consultation work will take place soon. I apologise to my hon. Friends for the fact that the consultation paper has not been published. I shall return to that point in a moment.</p>
	<p pid="a.268.0/5">We take the problem of pleural plaques very seriously. The description given by <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1473" name="David Howarth">the hon. Member for Cambridge (David Howarth)</phrase>&mdash;he mentioned figures of 5 and 95 per cent.&mdash;demonstrated the complexities of the problems involved and explains why we have taken far longer to come up with a plan for pleural plaques than for mesothelioma, which was a much more straightforward case. Fortunately, at the time, the Compensation Act 2006 was going through the House, which allowed me to introduce an amendment to deal with it. Nevertheless, we have been actively exploring options on how to help those who have been exposed to asbestos and who have developed pleural plaques, which clearly is not the same condition as mesothelioma.</p>
	<p pid="a.268.0/6">The House of Lords judgment raised very complex issues. I take the point made by my hon. Friend the Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone about Lady Justice Smith and the 2:1 judgment of the Court of Appeal in favour of the insurance industry. The House of Lords judgment was unanimous&mdash;I shall return later to the point that my hon. Friend made about psychiatric illness&mdash;and based on the fundamental principles of the law of negligence. We must be responsibly mindful of the complexity of the issues and the strength of the Law Lords' findings.</p>
	<p pid="a.268.0/7">I do not want to raise hopes unnecessarily. This is an incredibly complicated area, which the hon. Member for Cambridge articulated far better than I can, owing to his legal background and understanding of the issues. We have been carefully considering all possible options, and the consultation paper being prepared as I speak will deal in detail with the legal background, the available medical evidence and the advantages and disadvantages of suggestions made in response to the House of Lords judgment. We hope to publish that consultation paper by the middle of this month. The intention is that the consultation will run for 12 weeks, as is the case with most Government consultations, so that everyone with an interest can respond fully. We aim to publish our response before the Queen's Speech in November.</p>
	<p pid="a.268.0/8">I take on board what my hon. Friends have said&mdash;that much of the information is available now and that views have already been well expressed&mdash;so I shall consider whether it is appropriate to reduce the consultation period. However, I cannot say that we will definitely reduce it, because, as the hon. Member for North-West Norfolk explained, it is important to collate and review all the medical evidence, and we are in discussion with colleagues about whether it would be appropriate to ask the Industrial Injuries Advisory Council to do that. That is particularly important given the evidence provided by Dr. Robin Rudd, to which my hon. Friend the Member for Barnsley, West and Penistone referred.</p>
	<p pid="a.268.0/9">Dr. Rudd was one of the medical experts on whom the House of Lords clearly relied in its judgment, and at the time, no one dissented from the evidence put forward. I take on board what my hon. Friend said about Dr. Rudd and whether it would be appropriate to ask him to speak to me and the Ministry of Justice directly, or whether we should encourage him to give further evidence to, for example, the Industrial Injuries Advisory Council. I would also be interested in whether the chief medical officer would be prepared to reconsider the evidence. In making an assessment at the end of the consultation, it would be helpful to hear those objective, independent views.</p>
	<p pid="a.268.0/10">As hon. Members have said, pleural plaques are evidence only of exposure to asbestos, as was made clear in the House of Lords judgment, and opinions differ over how many people then develop serious asbestos-related diseases, such as mesothelioma.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.270.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2007" speakername="Jim Sheridan" colnum="270"  time="010:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0004.htm#08060495000478">
	<p pid="a.270.0/1">Will the Minister mention the situation in Scotland?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.270.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1682" speakername="Bridget Prentice" colnum="270"  time="010:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0004.htm#08060495000479">
	<p pid="a.270.1/1">I certainly shall. I shall leave the evidence, which I think is clear. We have been in discussion with officials in Scotland, but nothing clear has emerged. I suspect that my hon. Friend's analysis of the Scottish Executive was accurate, and I would be most interested to hear whether they have made any progress since the declaratory statement that they made some time ago&mdash;there has been a deafening silence ever since.</p>
	<p pid="a.270.1/2">As I said, I shall reconsider the consultation period. The consultation will be objective, and all options will be put forward, and I hope that everyone will respond.</p>
	<p pid="a.270.1/3">Issues relating to psychiatric illnesses were covered in the 2007 consultation. It is of course possible to claim damages when a recognised psychiatric illness is exposed. I accept the point made about the very particular House of Lords decision, which we might want to consider in more detail before returning with some suggestions.</p>
	<p pid="a.270.1/4">This has been a very important and excellent debate and will help to move things forward. As I said, the consultation period will begin very soon, and I hope that as a result my hon. Friends will see serious action from the Government, who are committed to helping people with pleural plaques and asbestos-related diseases.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.271.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="271"  time="010:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0004.htm#08060495000002">
	Supermarkets
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.271.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1645" speakername="Barry Sheerman" colnum="271"  time="010:59:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0004.htm#08060495000480">
	<p pid="a.271.1/1">It is pleasure to serve under your chairmanship, Mr. Atkinson, and to initiate this debate. I did not realise that I would be awarded one in the middle of my Select Committee proceedings. It is an unusual time for me to have to leave my Committee, but it is a pleasure to be here and to introduce a debate on an issue close to my heart.</p>
	<p pid="a.271.1/2">Many years ago, before coming into politics, I was a university lecturer. When I worked for a living as an academic, I lived in a community where I became very interested in co-operatives&mdash;not the normal, retail co-operatives that everyone thinks about, but individual co-operatives of owner-workers who owned their businesses and operated them. It became quite a hobby of mine and I initiated a great deal of work in the field. I was keen on that sort of industrial enterprise, because the notion of people owning their own enterprise and investing and employing people in the local community always attracted me. My relationship with the broader co-operative movement as time went on and I became more active in politics is on record.</p>
	<p pid="a.271.1/3">Today's debate, however, is on a subject that I care deeply about: the diversity and sustainability of local communities. The community that I represent, and which most colleagues from all parts of the House would want to represent, is a diverse and sustainable community that boasts its liveability. We all have an idea of what that means. I was trying to work out what I aspire to for my town and my constituency. In a sense, perhaps, it involves harking back to the past, but there are still many towns with a thriving mix of independent shops&mdash;butchers, fishmongers, newsagents, pubs, bookshops, greengrocers and family-owned general stores. Most of us, if we have a community where that exists, are pretty happy about it. Increasingly, however, we see the enormous power of supermarkets to move into towns and cities and take over their retailing.</p>
	<p pid="a.271.1/4">I shall describe the situation in this country. Some 75 per cent. of the market in food is dominated by four retailers. The four big supermarkets dominate the food industry in this country, which has implications in terms of supply&mdash;where they get it&mdash;and in terms of their enormous power over British farmers, consumers and, I have to say, elected local authorities. Once one has dealt with a great supermarket that wants to expand into one's town or constituency, one realises the sophistication of the process and the efficiency of those organisations. Nothing I say today is to denigrate the efficiency of the great supermarkets; in fact, one real problem is that they, of all our industries, are absolutely world-class. They absolutely know what they are about. When one of those supermarkets decides that it is going to be the dominant retail player in one's area, it moves in a way that would bring credit to any military operation anywhere in the world. They are the finest, and one can understand how they work.</p>
	<p pid="a.271.1/5">I want to use the debate to dispel a myth: that co-operative retailing started in a place in Lancashire called Rochdale. Everyone claims that the first co-op shop opened in 1844 in Toad lane, but actually, we in Huddersfield had a number of co-operative shops well before that date. A man called Thomas Firth, from Huddersfield, could only go around the country talking to people about the wonders of the co-operative commonwealth if a hall accommodating 1,000 could be found. He is buried in Trinity church in the centre of Huddersfield. In those days of the co-operative commonwealth, it was believed that one owned the shops in one's community. In Huddersfield, it was said that there were more than 100 co-operatives. If one stood on the top of Castle hill, one could see 100 communities with their own co-operative shops.</p>
	<p pid="a.271.1/6">I do not want to go back to a golden age, but I do worry, because when one looks at a town, one wonders where the wealth is going. Mr. Atkinson, you and I have known each other for a long time, and people accept that I am not known as the most left-wing member of the parliamentary Labour party, but when we get down to the fundamentals, we have to ask: what happens to the wealth of our communities?</p>
	<p pid="a.271.1/7">Going back 100 or 50 years, towns such as Huddersfield had many more local businesses. Huddersfield is often used by television and radio people because it is the average town in England. If one looks at us in a triangle, we are two thirds of the way up the centre of England, halfway across the M62 between Leeds on one side and Liverpool on the other, we have the average number of migrants, and our education and skills performance is average rather than awful or excellent. Many people do programmes about Huddersfield being the average town, but that average town has changed dramatically over the years that I have been its Member of Parliament.</p>
	<p pid="a.271.1/8">Gone are the days when ICI employed 6,000 people, and David Brown, Brook Motors and a range of manufacturing companies employed most people. Today, the largest employer in my constituency is the university of Huddersfield. In the local authority area of Kirklees, health and education are the biggest employers in terms of numbers, but in Huddersfield, it is the university. The beauty of, and my great luck in, having a university in Huddersfield, is partly down to a former Member, Harold Wilson, who was born and brought up in Huddersfield. He did the town one enormous favour: he gave polytechnic status to what is now the university of Huddersfield. It has grown into a university that employs 6,000 staff, has 25,000 students and was voted the new university of the year last year. It is a vibrant and important part of our community. Indeed, its chancellor, Patrick Stewart, the well-known Shakespearean actor, who is also from Huddersfield, celebrates the fact that the university brings more wealth into the town and keeps it in the community.</p>
	<p pid="a.271.1/9">On the one hand, there is a history of co-operation and small co-operatives keeping business in the community; and on the other, the university also plays that role. But I want to compare that with what the big supermarkets do. We have all the big four supermarkets in Huddersfield, and as we know, in this country, &pound;1 in every &pound;7 is spent in Tesco. That is true of my constituency, and if we add to that statistic Sainsbury's, Asda and Morrisons, we can imagine just how much money is spent in all the supermarkets. Most managers in those stores have on average about &pound;5,000 to give back to the local community directly&mdash;a bit to charities, local efforts and so on. I have often presented computers for schools for Tesco, but I have done so always in the knowledge that Tesco is not giving vast amounts of money to schools, but promoting its own products. The coupons and vouchers are not given away; they are a percentage of the money that is spent in the store.</p>
	<p pid="a.271.1/10">There is a real problem with the power of supermarkets in our communities, because most of the money that is spent drains straight out of the community and straight out of the town. It goes on wonderful salaries for the leading members of the corporation. Sir Terence Leahy earns &pound;20 million a year with share options, and Dame Lucy Neville-Rolfe&mdash;they all have knighthoods or are dames&mdash;is on &pound;2 million a year. I understand that they are very well remunerated indeed, but not their employees, most of whom are employed part-time. Their average salary is about &pound;11,500 a year. They are not wonderful salaries. Sir Terence Leahy earns 415 times more than the average Tesco employee.</p>
	<p pid="a.271.1/11">What worries me about that is the effect on the community. The community does not benefit from any reinvestment in its town or even in its region. In Yorkshire, we have 10 major campaigns against Tesco developing mega-stores in or around&mdash;usually outside&mdash;the main shopping areas of towns. We have a particular problem in Huddersfield. As I said, when one comes up against Tesco, it is like meeting a fine military operation. First, the small Tesco shops open up on every entrance and roadway into a town. They have different names depending on their size. The smaller stores are the Metros and the very large ones are Tesco Extras. Even a small community such as Dalton, which is in the heart of my constituency, has a Tesco in Long lane, one in Broad lane and a one-stop-shop in Mold Green. Just around the corner, a 24-hour shop has opened, which gives an enormous percentage of retailing to Tesco. At the moment, the worry is that a massive Tesco Extra will open.</p>
	<p pid="a.271.1/12">Many people believe that Tesco Extra is just another food shop. They say, &quot;Why are you so concerned about another Tesco? It is just another big supermarket.&quot; However, that is not the case; it is a department store. Between 50 and 60 per cent. of the goods sold in a Tesco Extra will not be food. They will be white goods, cookers, televisions, hi-fi systems, clothes and anything that a household needs. In other words, everything anyone else sells in Huddersfield will be sold in Tesco Extra.</p>
	<p pid="a.271.1/13">The new store is not to be built in the centre of the town. We have a ring road around Huddersfield. Over many years, I have been part of an organisation that encourages people to invest in the town centre. In order to get anchor tenants in our lovely Kingsgate shopping centre, we have had to beg, and wine and dine potential investors. We have been successful in pushing Huddersfield up the list of desired shopping destinations in Yorkshire. We have said, &quot;Come into Huddersfield. Invest in Huddersfield and we will look after you by giving you good sites and all the rest and you will add to the lustre of our retail effort.&quot; The present application is for a site outside the town centre. The store will take up to 100,000 visitors a week, and it will be outside the town centre, so they will not be walking past the other shops&mdash;the little shops.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.273.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1742" speakername="Brian Binley" colnum="273"  time="010:59:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0004.htm#08060495000481">
	<p pid="a.273.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1645" name="Barry Sheerman">the hon. Member for Huddersfield (Mr. Sheerman)</phrase> on securing the debate. I thoroughly support the main thrust of his argument. I am concerned, however, with the robustness and health of town centres and the fact that independent retailers, which are so vital to their well-being, have been driven out. We cannot stop the march of supermarkets. In fact, I use them myself, and I am sure that everyone in this Chamber does. They have provided a massive service to the people of this country. However, we should encourage them to develop a code of practice, help to start small businesses and do something about loss leaders. I wonder whether the hon. Gentleman will address those points quickly, because they are the ones that count.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.274.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1645" speakername="Barry Sheerman" colnum="274"  time="010:59:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0004.htm#08060495000482">
	<p pid="a.274.0/1">I was just coming to those points, but I wanted to get this description quite clear. When a large retailer&mdash;I cite Tesco because it applies to my constituency&mdash;comes into an area, they have enormous power and experience. However, I wonder whether officers in small local authorities&mdash;or even substantial ones such as my own&mdash;are experienced enough to deal on an equal basis with a massive company that has made planning applications and built up stores in many other places. Also, I have worries about local democracy and the planning process. In my own patch, there is a strategic agreement between Tesco and the local authority that is secret; it is commercially sensitive. There is no way of knowing what the deal is between the organisation and Kirklees council, which is a Conservative-controlled council supported by Liberal Democrats&mdash;I am not trying to make a political point. The fact is it is a secret agreement. While this secret agreement exists, people are applying for planning permissions within the town.</p>
	<p pid="a.274.0/2">The Queensgate centre, which is favoured by the local authority, is in the town centre. The extension to the Kingsgate centre, which is not favoured by the local authority, is also in the centre of town. At the same time as decisions are being democratically made on those issues, the local authority is already in bed with, or closely associated with, a supermarket that is going to make an application for a different site outside the town centre. One might say, &quot;What a wonderful deal for Huddersfield because they are going to build a supermarket on the site of a couple of 1970s blocks of flats and the Huddersfield leisure centre.&quot; We are told that we will get a new leisure centre. Perhaps we will, but the deal is highly suspect.</p>
	<p pid="a.274.0/3">An organisation comes along and asks for planning permission&mdash;under section 106 or whatever&mdash;and they get it. Not only is there a secret agreement between the local authority and the supermarket, but there is also an inducement, in the form of a leisure centre, to get that planning permission. I am very dubious about that sort of agreement, especially as there is a perfectly good store in the town centre and Tesco will get planning permission for a whole area of the town that will include a new hotel and residential properties. There will be a bit of social housing in that, but overall the deal looks extremely favourable to Tesco.</p>
	<p pid="a.274.0/4">Over the past 11 years, the Government have failed to recognise the real power of monopoly in retailing. I have seen the power of monopoly in many areas of retailing; it is not just about supermarkets. Supermarkets are a particularly sensitive issue because of their impact on the versatility, sustainability and diversity of our towns and cities. We can see that shrinking all the time with international global brands replacing local businesses. It happened in Cambridge. I believe that the local authority has given planning permission to Tesco in a beautiful part of Cambridge. I know that many people campaigned against it. This monopoly of supermarkets has grown in a stealthy way. The Government have been remiss in the way that they have reacted. When the Office of Fair Trading referred the grocery market to the Competition Commission, the commission said:</p>
	<p pid="a.274.0/5" class="indent">&quot;The retail sector will be less innovative due to lack of independent businesses that evolve through natural competitive pressure. Needs of people in local areas will not be met due to a loss in locally immersed businesses. Access to affordable healthy food will deteriorate. Regular social contact will be lost for certain members of the community, thereby entrenching social exclusion. Citizens will become less devolved from the decision making process surrounding planning policy in the areas in which they live, due to the growing dominance of large retailers over local Governments and councils.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.274.0/6">I raised this debate today for the best of reasons. First, my constituency, my town and my community is under threat from an unwelcome expansion of one major retailer that already has a dominant position in the town. Secondly, unless the Labour Government wake up to the fact that such a monopoly dominates the lives of the individuals in this country, we will be seen as not having stood up for their rights. The amount of power that such companies have is no longer acceptable. We know what has happened in the past in the United States: monopolies have been taken on and broken up. We have a positive power to do something in this country, but we have not used it. Most of the mechanisms that we used have been limp-wristed.</p>
	<p pid="a.274.0/7">I call on the Government to wake up to the fact that one of the big issues in the next two elections will be the power of individuals in communities to stand up to the power of those remote people. They are global companies. Money from our towns not only flows into the salaries of the boards of directors, but to institutions well beyond our communities and this country. There is something fundamentally wrong with British society when the Government do nothing to temper or curb the power of monopoly. Monopolies need to be taken on&mdash;even the former Conservative Government saw the power of the brewing chains' monopoly in public houses, and powerful action was taken by Lord Young. The United States took on the big energy companies and forced them to break up. At the moment, we cannot even take on one of the most pernicious monopolies&mdash;BAA&mdash;which provides the rotten service in so many airports that we must all put up with. It is time the Government realised the power of monopolies and how vulnerable communities and individuals are, and did something about the problem.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.275.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1936" speakername="Patrick McFadden" speakeroffice="The Minister for Employment Relations and Postal Affairs"  colnum="275"  time="011:21:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0004.htm#08060495000483">
	<p pid="a.275.0/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1645" name="Barry Sheerman">the Member for Huddersfield (Mr. Sheerman)</phrase> on securing this debate. The Under-Secretary of State for Business, Enterprise and Regulatory Reform, my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1619" name="Gareth Thomas">the Member for Harrow, West (Mr. Thomas)</phrase>, who has responsibility for consumer affairs, is out of the country on Government business today, but I shall do my best to respond to the important points raised by my hon. Friend the Member for Huddersfield.</p>
	<p pid="a.275.0/2">Supermarkets are an important part of life in our country. We all have them in or near our constituencies&mdash;I have a Morrisons, an Aldi, a Lidl, a small Tesco and a large Waitrose in mine. My hon. Friend talked about supermarkets' work in communities and I believe that they do good work. In my constituency, Tesco has given money to a pensioners link line and Waitrose does good work with the Graiseley primary school. It is important, as my hon. Friend stressed, that such businesses are good citizens.</p>
	<p pid="a.275.0/3">My hon. Friend raised many issues about his own constituency, Tesco and the plans that are under discussion. I am sure he will understand if I do not comment on the detail, given that the proposals are likely to be subject to the planning process; indeed, he would not want me to do so. If an application is made along the lines that he described, the local authority might have to refer it to my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government, so it would be wise not to get drawn too much into the pros and cons of the issue now, lest it prejudice any future decision.</p>
	<p pid="a.275.0/4">My hon. Friend's description of monopoly power reminded me a little of a film we all watch at Christmas&mdash;&quot;It's a Wonderful Life&quot;, starring James Stewart. I cannot remember the name of the character who, in effect, owns the town&mdash;perhaps other hon. Members know&mdash;but I was reminded of him when my hon. Friend described the effect that a monopoly or near-monopoly influence can have on an area.</p>
	<p pid="a.275.0/5">As a society, we probably have dual views on supermarkets' power and small shops. Supermarkets have brought us huge advances in convenience: price, even if there are some issues with that, and choice, because we can choose from thousands of retail lines within one store. However, we also like small shops. We might like to do our major fortnightly or monthly shop in a big supermarket, but in between we like to buy bread at the local bakery or go to the butcher and the small grocer. I am not sure that we should always see the issue in terms of conflict, although I suspect that I might if I were a small retailer. As a society, however, we want both the choice that the big supermarkets represent and probably also the choice represented by small shops in specific cases.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.276.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1742" speakername="Brian Binley" colnum="276"  time="011:21:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0004.htm#08060495000484">
	<p pid="a.276.0/1">Is there not much more that we can do with the supermarkets collectively on issues such as the code of practice on a self-regulating basis? There is a real need, as has been mentioned. Are the Government thinking in those terms?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.276.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1936" speakername="Patrick McFadden" colnum="276"  time="011:21:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0004.htm#08060495000485">
	<p pid="a.276.1/1">As my hon. Friend the Member for Huddersfield said, a structure involving the Competition Commission, the Office of Fair Trading and so on ensures that markets operate properly.</p>
	<p pid="a.276.1/2">My hon. Friend was right to say that the four or five biggest supermarkets wield considerable power. The eight largest retailers account for about 85 per cent. of total grocery sales, with the four largest accounting for about two thirds. Collectively, that is big power.</p>
	<p pid="a.276.1/3">There have been some inquiries into supermarkets, and the Competition Commission report, to which my hon. Friend referred, explored some of the issues just a few months ago. It found that the grocery market in general was delivering a good deal for consumers, but it identified two areas of concern. The first is that several grocery retailers have such a strong position in local markets that it could lead to a poorer retail offer to the consumer, and my hon. Friend touched on that point eloquently. The second area of concern related to the transfer of excessive risk and unexpected costs to suppliers&mdash;the relationship between supermarkets and suppliers is, of course, critical&mdash;through practices that the commission believes adversely impact on investment and innovation.</p>
	<p pid="a.276.1/4">What are the remedies for the concerns that have been highlighted? The commission has proposed several, including restrictive covenants and exclusivity arrangements on land sites, which it has the power to implement. Large grocery retailers will be required to notify the Office of Fair Trading of all acquisitions of large grocery stores. In addition, the commission has recommended to the Government that a competition test be adopted and that the OFT act as a statutory consultee in the process. On the supply chain, the commission will establish the grocery supply chain code of practice.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.277.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1645" speakername="Barry Sheerman" colnum="277"  time="011:21:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000486">
	<p pid="a.277.0/1">I know what the Competition Commission said, but what I want to know is what the Government will do about the monopoly&mdash;the Minister admitted that large retailers account for more than 80 per cent. of the market, which is a monopoly. What are the Government going to do to break up that monopoly? Why can we not start taxing supermarkets so that the tax can flow back into communities to regenerate them? He has not answered that question. All that wealth is going out of communities. What are we going to do to put it back in?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.278.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1936" speakername="Patrick McFadden" colnum="278"  time="011:21:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000487">
	<p pid="a.278.0/1">I am not sure that I accept some of what my hon. Friend has just said. Supermarkets, of course, pay tax&mdash;they are major businesses and they pay tax. Whether we are talking about a monopoly is also something to be debated. I said that we were talking about big power, and it is big power when four or five chains are in the position that they are. Whether that is a monopoly, however, is subject to debate. Nor do I accept that all the wealth goes out of the community. We are talking about major employers, which employ hundreds of thousands of people. My hon. Friend says that the wages are low&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.278.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1645" speakername="Barry Sheerman" colnum="278"  time="011:21:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000488">
	<p pid="a.278.1/1">They are.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.278.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1936" speakername="Patrick McFadden" colnum="278"  time="011:21:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000489">
	<p pid="a.278.2/1">Actually, those jobs often offer paid leave, contributory occupational pensions and benefits that are quite attractive to employees, as well as flexible hours. I do not think that the picture on employment is entirely bleak.</p>
	<p pid="a.278.2/2">There will always be contested views on this issue. As a society, we want the small shops with their character and we want the convenience of the large supermarkets&mdash;we want both. Whatever the regime, I suspect that that will remain the case.</p>
	<p pid="a.278.2/3">11.30 am</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.279.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="279"  time="011:21:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000003">
	<p pid="a.279.0/1" class="italic">Sitting suspended.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.279.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="279"  time="011:21:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000003">
	Post Office Closures (Mid-Wales)
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.279.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1444" speakername="Roger Williams" colnum="279"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000490">
	<p pid="a.279.2/1">It is always a joy to serve under your chairmanship, Mr. Atkinson, although I wish I had a more joyful subject to debate. I have called for this debate many times over the past months but, unfortunately, I have not been able to achieve it. This is a little bit late in the day in respect of the consultation on post office closures in mid-Wales. We anticipate an announcement next week. Some news has broken already, and I may mention that in passing during my contribution.</p>
	<p pid="a.279.2/2">My hon. Friends the Members for Ceredigion (Mark Williams) and for Montgomeryshire (Lembit &Ouml;pik) also feel strongly about this issue. I am aware that other announcements have now taken place in Wales regarding post office closures, so other hon. Members from Wales may wish to be involved in this debate.</p>
	<p pid="a.279.2/3">The previous programme of planned post office closures, which related to urban areas, was titled &quot;Post Office reinvention&quot;, which was a misnomer if ever I heard one. As far as the Post Office is concerned, an urban area is defined as an area with more than 10,000 people in one settlement or contiguous settlements. Such is the rural nature of my constituency that only three out of the 56 post offices then open were considered urban and were caught up in the reinvention programme. Those were all in the Ystradgunlais area, which is an old coal-mining community in my constituency that has suffered in respect of its economy and its ability to generate employment ever since the mines closed. That area should have been looked after a little bit better. In the end, we saved one of those post offices, but the one that was closed was probably the one that should have stayed open, because it was in the most deprived area. So when we approached the next planned closure programme, we did not really have much confidence that, if we opposed the closure of post offices in our area, the ones that were closed would have the least impact on our communities.</p>
	<p pid="a.279.2/4">The consultation exercise in 2006 took place prior to the current closure programme. However, it was difficult to engage in that consultation, because people had to read a relatively thick consultation document and then fill in a pro forma to address the issues raised in that document. A number of people felt that they could not engage in that process. Despite the fact that there were only about 160 responses to the formal consultation in Wales, 40 of those came from my constituency, where I set about ensuring that the people whom I represent made the most of the opportunity. We also submitted 220 responses to our own consultation document, which was easier to complete, with the formal consultation. People were concerned about the criteria for post offices in rural areas. Some 95 per cent. of people living in those areas should be within three miles of a post office, but that means that 5 per cent. of people, whatever their age or capacity to access post offices, could live more than three miles away from one.</p>
	<p pid="a.279.2/5">In my most pessimistic frame of mind, I looked at the relatively large centres of population in my constituency&mdash;Llandrindod Wells, with about 5,000 people, and Brecon, with about 8,000&mdash;and noticed that a post office in one of those places, with about eight others, might meet the 95 per cent. criterion. My most pessimistic view then was that we were in for a wholesale closure of post offices. Our contribution to that consultation made little or no difference, because the closure programme went ahead as set out in the consultation document. It seems to me that our representations had no particular effect.</p>
	<p pid="a.279.2/6">The announcement of the post office closures in mid-Wales under the current closure programme was made on <phrase class="date" code="2008-03-11">11 March 2008</phrase>. By that time, we had been running a campaign to alert people to the possibility of post office closures and distributing postcards to people to be filled in and returned to us so that we could pass them on to the Prime Minister himself in No. 10 Downing street. By <phrase class="date" code="2008-03-11">11 March 2008</phrase>, we had received 2,500 postcard responses. To date, we have received 3,500 postcards from a constituency population of about 50,000. So hon. Members can see the concern and affection. Affection is an emotional term rather than an economic one, but that is how people feel about their local post offices and the contribution that they make to local communities. Furthermore, the postcard campaign required action on the part of my constituents. In many campaigns, people just have to press a button on the web page, hit the &quot;send&quot; button or sign a petition. Petitions are valuable, but with our campaign people had to buy a stamp, stick it on the postcard and send the postcard to me. So people responded actively.</p>
	<p pid="a.279.2/7">The public consultation has now closed and the Post Office is currently reviewing the submissions that it received. Probably all the postmasters and postmistresses involved in the process have now been informed of the outcome, but unfortunately some have broken cover and revealed it. That makes it difficult for other postmasters and postmistresses who have kept the confidence, because if their customers ask what the outcome of the consultation is, they will be in a difficult, embarrassing situation. I regret the process that has taken place.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.280.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1720" speakername="Lembit pik" colnum="280"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000491">
	<p pid="a.280.0/1">Does my hon. Friend recall that something similar happened at an earlier stage in the consultation process? That makes it difficult for those of us who respect those confidences, which must be respected, to do our jobs properly. Does he agree that it is time that some sanction was imposed on people who make it virtually impossible for us to conduct our business simply because of their selfish desire to spread confidential information prior to an embargo being lifted?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.280.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1444" speakername="Roger Williams" colnum="280"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000492">
	<p pid="a.280.1/1">It certainly makes it difficult for us as representatives of the area, if we do not know what is happening and others do.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.280.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1495" speakername="Cheryl Gillan" colnum="280"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000493">
	<p pid="a.280.2/1">I congratulate the hon. Gentleman on securing this debate. He knows that this issue concerns us all, no matter where our constituencies are in the country. It has been brought to my attention that certain post offices know already that they have been reprieved. I did not think that information was embargoed, because my office managed to obtain it quite readily. Will he tell us when the information is embargoed until, because I was proposing to congratulate one of the post offices in his constituency that will remain open? I do not want to contribute to breaking an embargo, but I thought the information was freely available in some instances.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.281.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1444" speakername="Roger Williams" colnum="281"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000494">
	<p pid="a.281.0/1">I contacted the Post Office yesterday, when probably the same information that has come to the attention of the hon. Lady was brought to my attention. The Post Office told me that it had contacted the postmasters and postmistresses whose businesses were under review earlier this week and informed them of the outcome. Members of Parliament and Assembly Members who represent affected areas will be officially informed on Friday, and the public statement is to be made next Tuesday. I shall not make a big fuss about the embargo, but it makes the business today a bit more difficult.</p>
	<p pid="a.281.0/2">Once the Post Office has considered the representations and submissions, the final announcement will be made about those post offices that will be kept open, those that will close and those that will host an outreach service in the form of a mobile service&mdash;in other words, a postal van will be in the area for a few hours each week in place of the post office that previously served the area. Some post offices will provide a hosted service, which involves providing the services of a post office in alternative premises, such as a pub, a community centre or a shop.</p>
	<p pid="a.281.0/3">In the third round of Welsh closures, six post offices were earmarked for closure in Brecon and Radnorshire. It is proposed that out of a total of 54 post offices that are still open, eight should switch to an outreach service. Out of those eight post offices, it is proposed that five should become mobile services and the other three should become hosted services. The five post offices that have been targeted for mobile services will receive a collective post office service of 26 hours a week, and the three listed for hosted services will have a post office service of just eight hours a week.</p>
	<p pid="a.281.0/4">Two post offices are listed for closure in Brecon, which means a town with a population of roughly 8,000 people will have just one post office. It is also proposed that two post offices in Llandrindod should close, which, again, will mean a town of more than 5,000 people will have just one post office. One post office is earmarked for closure in Evenjobb&mdash;a remote village near Presteigne&mdash;and we now have information that that closure has been confirmed. Another proposed closure would affect Cwmgiedd, a small village community in Ystradgynlais. In total, 14 post offices will be affected in my constituency. I would like to mention each one, but because of the time and because I can see other hon. Members want to make a contribution, I will keep this as short as I can.</p>
	<p pid="a.281.0/5">Both Llanfaes and Pendre post offices in Brecon are open 46 hours a week and have a large number of customers who are over 65 years old and who suffer from limiting life-term illnesses. The nearest alternative post office is not far away, but it is situated amid hilly terrain on which it is difficult to walk. The existing branch in the middle of Brecon is crowded, and it is estimated that a minimum of 500 additional customers will now have to use that post office. I often use it, and during the middle of day I have queued for upwards of a quarter of an hour or 20 minutes to be served. Another 500 customers will be directed to that post office, if the closures take place. The people who use both Llanfaes and Brecon post offices have put in substantial submissions to keep them open, and we wait to hear the outcome.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.282.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1495" speakername="Cheryl Gillan" colnum="282"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000495">
	<p pid="a.282.0/1">I confirm what the hon. Gentleman has said. When I went to Llanfeas to meet Karen Weale, a continuous stream of people queued up to use the post office, and there was not a spare minute in the day. Similarly, when I met Jay Vakil in Pendre, the post office was in constant use. Losing either or both of those post offices would be a disaster for the local community.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.282.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1635" speakername="Peter Atkinson" colnum="282"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000496">
	<p pid="a.282.1/1">Order. May I ask the hon. Lady to address the Chair, because the <i>Hansard </i>reporters cannot easily pick up her comments?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.282.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1444" speakername="Roger Williams" colnum="282"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000497">
	<p pid="a.282.2/1">I thank the hon. Lady for her comments. It is good that this is not just the subjective opinion of the local Member of Parliament, but that it has been validated by other distinguished hon. Members.</p>
	<p pid="a.282.2/2">I shall now turn to the two post offices in Llandrindod earmarked for closure, both of which are open for 46 hours a week. Although the alternative branch is not far away, it is not situated in the easiest terrain for less able people&mdash;it is about a 25-minute walk and there are no regular buses. The additional 300 to 400 customer sessions that would have to be served by the remaining post office would put great pressure on that facility.</p>
	<p pid="a.282.2/3">The good news is that we understand that the Tremont road post office has been saved. I can safely say that because it is on the front page of <i>The Brecon and Radnor Express</i> today&mdash;a fine organ in my constituency that keeps the public aware of what is going on. I can also see representatives from the <i>County Times </i>sitting at the back today, which is a fine organisation too. I am pleased that Tremont post office has stayed open. It is run by an energetic couple who also run a good shop. I am pleased that such a facility will be available at that end of Llandrindod Wells. I pay particular credit to the community that lives in that area and uses the facilities that the post office provides. It is not the richest community in my constituency, and its needs are great. That community responded to the consultation and to my postcard campaign&mdash;huge quantities of postcards were sent back to me. That campaign alerted the community to the seriousness of the proposals, and as such we have had lots of responses. We now wonder whether Ridgebourne will remain open in Llandrindod Wells. Sadly, Evenjobb has received notice that it will close.</p>
	<p pid="a.282.2/4">A number of other post offices have also received huge support, including Erwood and Llyswen in the Wyre valley. We have had two fantastic public meetings to drum up support for those post offices. Indeed, the ability of people to get to other facilities to obtain cash is limited, and the public transport system is not of the highest order. The proposal to have a mobile service has not been received well by the local people. Indeed, Erwood is in a dangerous position on a trunk road in the middle of a village. The situation in relation to Erwood is entirely unacceptable.</p>
	<p pid="a.282.2/5">In Llyswen, the proposal is to place the mobile facility outside the shop where the post office is sited. I cannot understand the logic of that. If the post office closes, the likelihood that the shop will be put under economic pressure greatly increases. The synergy between the shop and the post office is what keeps many villages going and provides the services that people desperately need.</p>
	<p pid="a.282.2/6">Gladestry has been offered a service for two hours a week in the village hall. The postmaster there wants to retire, and although the village is not entirely happy with the situation, it is more accepting than some places. However, it is a very remote area. I was present when the Post Office unveiled a cash machine in Llanbister post office not long ago. We thought that that was a good news story, but it was not entirely so.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.283.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1495" speakername="Cheryl Gillan" colnum="283"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000498">
	<p pid="a.283.0/1">If we look at the post offices where an outreach service has been proposed, we see that some services are for nine hours, some for four hours and some for two hours. The irony of the van spending nine hours outside the shop where the post office used to be is not lost on me or anyone else. Does the hon. Gentleman know how those hours were arrived at? Also, what consultation of the local community has been conducted? Presumably, when the service is for only two hours, it will be on a certain day of the week, which may not be convenient for some of the residents who normally use the post office service.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.283.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1444" speakername="Roger Williams" colnum="283"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000499">
	<p pid="a.283.1/1">The hon. Lady has raised another point. During the consultation, I asked how it was decided which villages would receive a mobile service and for how long and which would receive a hosted or a partner service. There was a considerable amount of sucking of teeth and stroking of chins at that point. I put it to those people that probably the defining factor was trying to get the maximum use out of the mobile facility, not what was best for or would have been most appreciated by that community.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.283.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1469" speakername="Hywel Williams" colnum="283"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000500">
	<p pid="a.283.2/1">There are not only consequences in terms of convenience for local users, but consequences for the people providing the service in the van. During the trial run in my constituency, the person supplying the two hours a week in various communities found that he could not make a business out of the hours that he was granted.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.283.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1469" speakername="Hywel Williams" colnum="283"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000501">
	<p pid="a.283.3/1">My hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1489" name="Mark Williams">the Member for Ceredigion (Mark Williams)</phrase> may be able to refer to a similar experience.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.283.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1489" speakername="Mark Williams" colnum="283"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000502">
	<p pid="a.283.4/1" class="italic"> rose&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.283.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1489" speakername="Mark Williams" colnum="283"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0005.htm#08060495000503">
	<p pid="a.283.5/1">I will resist giving way, because I want to get on and because other hon. Members want to speak. This is a long and sorry tale, but I will try not to take up too much time. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1495" name="Cheryl Gillan">The hon. Member for Chesham and Amersham (Mrs. Gillan)</phrase> has raised an important point that I will consider in relation to Llanwrtyd Wells, which claims to be the smallest town in the UK. It was the location of the composition of &quot;Sosban Fach&quot;, a song that is often sung at rugby internationals, and it is the site of the man versus horse race. Many enterprising things are going on Llanwrtyd Wells, but there is a proposal to close the post office, which residents see as an affront to their status as a town. The lady in question wants to retire&mdash;one problem is that some postmasters and postmistresses want to retire.</p>
	<p pid="a.283.5/2">The proposal to substitute for the post office a mobile service for nine hours is unacceptable for a number of reasons. A minor one is that the suggested site is a very steep car park. It gets icy during the winter and it would be dangerous for pensioners and older people to access. If the post office has to close&mdash;my wish is that it will not close&mdash;it would be much better for the service to be hosted by an existing facility in Llanwrtyd, such as a shop or the tourist information centre, which is no longer run by Powys county council but by a private operation. If the post office, or what is to be substituted for the post office, were in one of those facilities, those facilities would be more likely to remain open. We sincerely hope that the conclusion is a hosted or partner service rather than a mobile service.</p>
	<p pid="a.283.5/3">I have talked about Llyswen and Erwood. Merthyr Cynog will have a mobile service, and Pantydwr will have a hosted service. For a rural area such as mine, the number of closures could create real difficulties in relation to village life and the sustainability of rural communities. A 2005 Postcomm survey suggested that 91 per cent. of people believe that post offices play an important role in their community. An article in <i>The</i><i>Daily Telegraph </i>in March 2008 estimated that half of the 2,500 post offices earmarked for closure double up as village shops. The post office is often the last shop in the village, in which case the closure of the post office rings the death knell for the shop as well.</p>
	<p pid="a.283.5/4">Although our campaign to keep those village post offices is drawing to a close, the next campaign is already beginning, because we see it as a real challenge to keep open the post office network that will remain after the closures that might take place. I call on the Minister to ensure that the Post Office has the ability to advertise the services that it provides. At some of our post offices, postmasters have posted handwritten signs outside their post offices to show that they still issue car tax discs. Surely we can have a system to inform people that the Post Office has not withdrawn from that service, as it has had to withdraw, unfortunately, from the television licence service.</p>
	<p pid="a.283.5/5">For example, I run a small business, a farm, and every week I have to write a PAYE&mdash;pay-as-you-earn&mdash;cheque for my employees. I used to send it to some anonymous office in Shipley, from whence I received no further communication as to whether it had arrived or not. Now I realise that I can deal with that at a post office and get a receipt, so I have a record. We need to alert the public to the fact that such facilities are available in post offices, in which case we will stand a chance of keeping some of them open.</p>
	<p pid="a.283.5/6">This is a sad day for mid-Wales, for Brecon and Radnorshire and particularly for the elderly. I am told&mdash;I do not know whether this is true&mdash;that the total saving in relation to the closure programme for the 2,500 post offices is &pound;48 million. It is an awful lot of grief and worry for people not only in Brecon and Radnorshire but throughout the country for a &pound;48 million saving. I do not know whether the process, which must have been costly in terms of staff and time, justifies that.</p>
	<p pid="a.283.5/7">You have been generous with me, Mr. Atkinson, as other hon. Members have, but what I have said needed saying. The Government seem to have given up on rural communities and rural Wales, and it is vital that the remaining post offices in mid-Wales continue to operate and that we do not face further closures in the future.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.284.0" speakerid="unknown" error="No match" speakername="Several hon. Members" colnum="284"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0006.htm#08060495000504">
	<p pid="a.284.0/1" class="italic">rose&mdash;</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.284.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1635" speakername="Peter Atkinson" colnum="284"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0006.htm#08060495000505">
	<p pid="a.284.1/1">Order. Before I call the next speaker, may I remind hon. Members of the time? We have just over half an hour for Back-Bench contributions, so to allow everyone to speak, I urge hon. Members to be reasonably brief. I call Hywel Williams.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.285.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1469" speakername="Hywel Williams" colnum="285"  time="014:58:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0006.htm#08060495000506">
	<p pid="a.285.0/1">Thank you, Mr. Atkinson; I will take your injunction to heart. I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1444" name="Roger Williams">the hon. Member for Brecon and Radnorshire (Mr. Williams)</phrase> on securing the debate. It is an important, if slightly unglamorous, debate, covering the bread-and-butter issues that constituency MPs deal with every day. Clearly, such a debate cannot compete with the glamour of the debate in the main Chamber, as not a single member of the Welsh parliamentary Labour party is here. Presumably, those hon. Members are in the main Chamber, vying with one another to contribute to the debate on volunteering&mdash;or possibly not. However, this is an important issue, pertinent not only to mid-Wales but to all of rural Wales.</p>
	<p pid="a.285.0/2">The point that the hon. Member for Brecon and Radnorshire made about rurality being defined in terms of populations of under 10,000 people is very important for my constituency. Not a single town in the constituency of Caernarfon has a population of more than 10,000, so I assume that all of my constituency is defined as rural, which would come as a surprise to some of the town dwellers.</p>
	<p pid="a.285.0/3">Rural Wales faces a profound challenge. I will mention only in passing such challenges as the Government's decision to grant greater tax relief in relation to capital gains on holiday homes. That will have a strong effect on that market. The Joseph Rowntree Foundation report published just today on housing in Wales shows that there are 18,000 empty houses, while at the same time homelessness in rural Wales is up sharply. Houses in rural Wales typically cost five time average earnings. That is a truly shocking scenario. The challenge to life in rural Wales is clearly substantial, and it will become more substantial&mdash;the situation is even more dangerous&mdash;because of the Post Office proposals. They not only affect post offices in mid-Wales, but will extend to north Wales as a result of the consultation that is under way, which I understand will report at the end of July.</p>
	<p pid="a.285.0/4">I shall not go through all the arguments. They are fairly familiar, as such debates are held regularly in this Chamber&mdash;indeed, I have contributed to a number of them. However, it is worth quickly restating some points. For instance, rural sub-post offices are focal points for the community; they pay pensions and benefits and provide all kinds of vital services&mdash;not only shopping, but basic information and social contact for local people. Some of those services are not commercial; some are. The commercial ones might not be viable without the post office element, such as the one at Llyswen referred to by the hon. Member for Brecon and Radnorshire.</p>
	<p pid="a.285.0/5">In my constituency, we have a sub-post office that is clustered with a couple of other shops. I believe that those shops depend on each other to attract custom; without the post office, there would be a serious threat to the viability of the other shops that crowd into that parade, which is in a nice area in the north of Caernarfon. It is not only post offices that are under threat; their closure will also affect newsagents, small grocery stores and so on. The area will be less attractive for shoppers. Closing the post office can have a domino effect on other local shops. We should also be aware of the multiplier effect, which has been mentioned a number of times, as people who claim a benefit or draw money from the local post office tend to spend it locally. That pound circulates more widely and has a much more beneficial effect on the local economy.</p>
	<p pid="a.285.0/6">Between March 2001 and December 2007 in Wales, 258 post offices closed, many of them in rural areas in mid and north Wales. That is about 19 per cent., or nearly one in five. As I said, a consultation is taking place in north Wales and we expect a number of post offices to be closed. Some of them, I suppose reasonably, will close because people will want to retire and put their business up for sale, but I am sure that some will be closed in the teeth of local opposition. I hope that the Minister will assure us that the Post Office will listen to local opinion when the consultation is held in north Wales.</p>
	<p pid="a.285.0/7">As I said in an intervention on the hon. Member for Brecon and Radnorshire, mobile post office vans have been introduced in my constituency, which is in a particularly rural part of the Lleyn peninsula. That, of course, has led to diminished hours. It also raises specific questions about the business model. The provider of the van found that he could not make a business of driving the 50 or 60 miles while ensuring that someone minded the shop at home. At the same time, although some people accepted a service every two or three hours, some found it insufficient.</p>
	<p pid="a.285.0/8">Given the geography of rural Wales&mdash;and the deeply rural areas of England and the north of Scotland&mdash;the post office could be miles away. As the hon. Member for Brecon and Radnorshire said, the standard is three miles. However, 5 per cent. of people might be as far as six miles away from the post office. In rural areas where public transport, if there is any, might be scarce, travelling such a distance could be a challenge.</p>
	<p pid="a.285.0/9">We are all aware that there is a green aspect. In areas such as Powys, which is represented by the hon. Member for Brecon and Radnorshire, it is not surprising that car ownership is at its highest&mdash;and incomes are at their lowest. Car ownership is sometimes seen as a measure of prosperity, but in Powys the car is a necessity. I am sure that the hon. Gentleman will agree that many families own one, two or even three cars in order to ensure that life in rural areas is viable. Cars are not a costly luxury, but a costly necessity. For such families, the withdrawal of the post office will be a further disincentive to live in rural areas.</p>
	<p pid="a.285.0/10">Rural poverty is also an issue. Without doubt, lack of access to good services is a major component of poverty. That is recognised in the index used by the Welsh Assembly Government to measure deprivation and poverty. Remoteness is another factor. The closure proposals will exacerbate rural poverty on such measures.</p>
	<p pid="a.285.0/11">One might think that some of those bad effects could be countered by the introduction of new technology and that people could perhaps use services online. I draw the House's attention to a report published yesterday, which shows that in rural areas broadband access is not easy to obtain because of what are called not-spots, although BT claims that only 1 per cent. of Wales has not-spots. None the less, I seem to have many of them in my constituency. For example, one cannot receive broadband in the village of Rhiwlas but gallingly one can see Caernarfon and Bangor on the coast from there as it is high on the side of the hill. One can see areas where people have not only good access to shops but broadband.</p>
	<p pid="a.285.0/12">We may have not-spots, but significantly yesterday's report also noted that broadband speeds in Wales are about half those in London. I have no technical expertise in these matters, but I believe that as a result it is more difficult to use broadband for all kinds of services, not least receiving television pictures&mdash;but that is another matter. Such things have a significant effect on the viability of living in rural areas. Local businesses in my constituency that use the post office and might use broadband instead will have to think again, because of the difficulties of working online.</p>
	<p pid="a.285.0/13">The rural-urban split is deepening, as life in much of Wales becomes more and more unsustainable. The Government's policy should be to ameliorate that divide, not deepen it, as a perhaps unintended consequence of that deliberate and unwelcome policy.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.287.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1506" speakername="David Jones" colnum="287"  time="015:07:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0006.htm#08060495000507">
	<p pid="a.287.0/1">I am aware of the shortness of time, Mr. Atkinson, so I shall be brief.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.0/2">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1444" name="Roger Williams">the hon. Member for Brecon and Radnorshire (Mr. Williams)</phrase> on securing this important debate. I also have a good word for the Minister. Of all the poisoned chalices on offer in Westminster, he seems to have drawn the most unpalatable. It is a credit to him that over the past few months he has been at one debate after another attempting to defend the indefensible. I remember the mauling that he suffered in March in an Opposition day debate on the subject. It must be difficult for him to undertake his present role. Nevertheless, I believe that the hon. Member for Brecon and Radnorshire was right to invite the Minister to come here again this afternoon to take another mauling from Welsh Members.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.0/3">The hon. Member for Brecon and Radnorshire has already mentioned the particular difficulties caused by the remoteness of his community. Mid-Wales is a part of the country that I know only too well. My wife comes from mid-Wales, and I can certainly attest to the area's remoteness. I sometimes wonder how I ever found her; but find her I did. In many respects, the hon. Gentleman's constituency resembles mine. It is one of scattered villages, many separated by hills and rivers. That is where the Government's access criteria fail. The three-mile radius is meaningless when one considers the topography of mid and north Wales. One cannot travel as the crow flies there. The damage being done to communities in the rural parts of Wales by the closure programme, as <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1469" name="Hywel Williams">the hon. Member for Caernarfon (Hywel Williams)</phrase> pointed out, is significant.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.0/4">Very often, the post office is literally the only business in the village, let alone the only shop. There are villages in my constituency, as I am sure there are in the constituency of the hon. Member for Brecon and Radnorshire, where the post office is also the shop, and it might also be a small guest house. As a composite, such a business is viable, but if one element is taken out, it becomes unviable. I regret to say that that is precisely what will happen in mid and north Wales and in other rural parts of Wales when the closure programme is completed.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.0/5">Rural life in Wales is becoming increasingly difficult. We have seen school closure programmes, the effect of high fuel prices and now the effect of the Government's disgraceful tinkering with vehicle excise duty. It is becoming almost impossible to live a civilised life in rural parts of Wales, and the post office closure programme is doing deep social damage to the fabric of life.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.0/6">When the Government tabled their successful amendment to the Opposition day motion, it was interesting that they recognised</p>
	<p pid="a.287.0/7" class="indent">&quot;the vital social and economic role of post offices, in particular in rural and deprived urban communities&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.287.0/8">If they really do recognise the vital role of post offices, why are they presiding over such a draconian closure programme?</p>
	<p pid="a.287.0/9">For many people in mid-Wales and other parts of Wales, the post office closure programme will simply be the last straw. Businesses will close across Wales, and the heart will be taken out of village communities, which will ultimately die. It is sad that the Government are presiding over this programme with apparent equanimity, seemingly oblivious to the social effects that they are inflicting on people in scattered rural communities. It is probably too late for the Government to think again, but I would like the Minister to reflect on the damage that has been done and possibly even to consider apologising for it to the people of Wales.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.288.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1489" speakername="Mark Williams" colnum="288"  time="015:12:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0006.htm#08060495000508">
	<p pid="a.288.0/1">It is a pleasure to serve under your chairmanship, Mr. Atkinson. I, too, am grateful to my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1444" name="Roger Williams">the Member for Brecon and Radnorshire (Mr. Williams)</phrase> for raising this important issue. The front pages of the <i>Cambrian News</i> and the Cardigan <i>Tivy-side Advertiser</i> in my constituency have yet to break any news, so I am a little in the dark as to where we are going on the issue. As Members, we wait with expectation for the announcement on Friday, as well as for the public announcement next Tuesday.</p>
	<p pid="a.288.0/2">Like <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1506" name="David Jones">the hon. Member for Clwyd, West (Mr. Jones)</phrase>, I am in a reflective mood and I shall comment first on the consultation process. In all fairness, it has been a very thorough affair in my constituency. There have been a huge number of submissions to the Post Office about the changes to services in the 14 communities concerned. The Post Office management have shown willingness&mdash;although they were slightly reluctant on one occasion&mdash;to come and listen to local people's concerns. We have had public meetings, and about 1,200 people listened to the Post Office's case, as well as the alternative case that some of us put.</p>
	<p pid="a.288.0/3">The sad reality, however, is that on more than one occasion the tone from the Post Office has been that it is a done deal and there is little opportunity to influence the course of events. That perception was not helped when the Post Office seemed to prejudge the outcome of the consultation. To give just one small example, the post office in Talybont, which is threatened with closure, had its parcel collection scheme removed because of the uncertainty about the post office's future. That may seem very small in the big picture, but it is a big issue for the community's small businesses.</p>
	<p pid="a.288.0/4">We have used the opportunity of the consultation to clarify many of the Post Office's misconceptions about the reality on the ground. I still question how thoroughly the Post Office consultation team drew up its proposals, because they ranged from completely inappropriate locations for proposed mobile services&mdash;sometimes in very unsafe locations&mdash;to discussion of public transport services that simply did not exist or whose operating times did not tally with the opening hours of the recommended alternative branches. As other hon. Members have suggested, the proposals also referred to alternative branches that could, ironically, never cope with the increased custom, even if people were in a position to move from branch to branch.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.289.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1495" speakername="Cheryl Gillan" colnum="289"  time="015:12:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0006.htm#08060495000509">
	<p pid="a.289.0/1">Has the hon. Gentleman had any help from Postwatch in Ceredigion? Will he comment on what is happening with Postwatch? How will it be affected if it goes into a consumer council?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.289.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1489" speakername="Mark Williams" colnum="289"  time="015:12:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0006.htm#08060495000510">
	<p pid="a.289.1/1">I worry about Postwatch, and the hon. Lady is right to mention it. Postwatch's role in the process has been minimal, and I am very concerned about it. In some instances, Postwatch did not even come to our large consultation meetings, which is a real worry. In their many submissions, my constituents were quite wise to that fact.</p>
	<p pid="a.289.1/2">We cannot overstate the significance of practical issues such as access to services and the lack of public transport. I represent a large county with 147 villages and hamlets, where rurality really does mean something. Ceredigion has 7,000 small businesses, which is more than any other constituency in the United Kingdom, let alone Wales. We are talking, therefore, not only about business opportunities for the person who undertakes the mobile van service, but about the great inconvenience to a large number of our small businesses, which are the backbone of the rural economy, and to the farming community. Another threatened post office, in the community of Pontsian, serves a large ward and 64 farming families. Again, small businesses will not easily be able to fit in with the van's limited hours.</p>
	<p pid="a.289.1/3">I shall cite one more example to highlight the vagaries of public transport. The now infamous village of Llanddewi Brefi&mdash;it is a wonderful community&mdash;has a post office with an accompanying village shop. It has been asserted that when the van is not there, people will be able to access services in Tregaron&mdash;another delightful town in the south of Ceredigion. However, even if people had the good fortune to catch the bus to Tregaron, which is five miles away, they would either have to undertake all their business in 33 minutes flat so that they could catch the bus home, or they would have to wait two hours for the next service&mdash;and that is a pretty good service, compared with other public services in my constituency. The alternative would be to hire a taxi for the return journey, which would involve a &pound;12 fare.</p>
	<p pid="a.289.1/4">Sadly, as my hon. Friend the Member for Brecon and Radnorshire said, we are looking ahead to the next campaign. Like the hon. Member for Clwyd, I shall reflect on the criteria set out by the Government. We were told at the numerous public meetings that the Post Office was the agent of the Government and of Government decision making, and that the criteria are a Government responsibility. However, there has been a complete lack of recognition of rural deprivation. Ninety-nine per cent. of the total population in deprived urban areas across the UK are to be within one mile of the nearest post office branch, but the same recognition has not been afforded to rural areas.</p>
	<p pid="a.289.1/5">Ceredigion and the constituency of <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1469" name="Hywel Williams">the hon. Member for Caernarfon (Hywel Williams)</phrase> fall into the EU convergence funding&mdash;formerly objective 1&mdash;area for a very good reason. As he said, the National Assembly, through its communities first programme, has also recognised that they are areas of acute rural deprivation. Europe has recognised that, the Welsh Assembly Government have recognised it, but the Westminster Government seem not to recognise it in this instance. There is a widely held perception that the communities of west Wales, which are scattered and isolated, are being left to wither on the vine.</p>
	<p pid="a.289.1/6">Over and above its initial criteria, the Post Office has said that it would consider the impact on local economies, but I seriously question how much weighting it has given to that critical factor. In many communities in Ceredigion&mdash;Talybont, Llanilar, Llangeitho, Llanddewi Brefi and Pontsian&mdash;the post office is integrally linked to the village shop: if one goes, the other will go too. I remain very concerned about the future viability of those businesses. I cite again the verdict of the Select Committee on Business, Enterprise and Regulatory Reform, which I realise the Minister heard yesterday in the debate on post office closures in East Devon. The Committee said that</p>
	<p pid="a.289.1/7" class="indent">&quot;there should be a presumption against closing a Post Office where this is the last shop in the village or in a deprived urban area&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.289.1/8">We cannot overstate the significance of the post office in rural life. It is the last community social business in those communities. When the village school has gone and the chapel is boarded up the post office is the last thing left. Sometimes I think that we and the Government have been debating completely different cases; the social role of post offices has been neglected.</p>
	<p pid="a.289.1/9">I know that the Minister is well versed in the many anecdotes that he has been and will be subjected to in past and coming months, but people such as Heulwen Astley, the postmistress in Talybont, and Ann Mayes-Davies in Pontsian, have served their communities very well, and, if given the opportunity, will continue to do so in future. The majority of postmasters and postmistresses I have spoken to in the affected areas are keen to carry on their businesses and do not want to join the exodus that others have talked about. They want their businesses to thrive, and they want support. I should have thought that if the Post Office was sincere about supporting those retail businesses it would at the very least have offered them an outreach facility. My hon. Friend the Member for Brecon and Radnorshire cited the example of the van parked outside the shop. Pontsian post office near Llandysul is a case in point. If the proposal proceeds, the van will be located outside that shop. What an insult to the years of service that the postmistress has given. Giving her the chance to have the outreach facility in the shop would at least guarantee footfall across the threshold.</p>
	<p pid="a.289.1/10">I am conscious of the time, so I will be quick, but I want to ask the Minister the extent of his discussions, and the Post Office's, with the National Assembly Government, in the light of the announcement in January of the recommencement next year of the post office development fund, which did good work in its previous life. Another threatened post office in Ceredigion, Devil's Bridge, was one of those that benefited from the development fund. The branch received many accolades from the Post Office itself. Edryd and Jane Jenkins, the owners, have done a huge amount of community work, which has been acknowledged by the Post Office. They pioneered a service there with the Dyfed-Powys police, yet it seems that when the National Assembly starts its work next year, even in the communities first areas that it has defined itself, the post offices will already have gone.</p>
	<p pid="a.289.1/11">Business has been taken from the Post Office over many years, such as the loss of TV licences. There is a continuing fear about the future of the Post Office card account. I hope that, as other hon. Members have said, notwithstanding the economics of the issue and the work that needs to be done to publicise future post office services and encourage people to use them, the Government will at least acknowledge the essential social role of post offices. The irony is that at a time when the Post Office is being branded &quot;the people's Post Office&quot;, in Wales, practically and theoretically, it seems far removed from people's everyday lives.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.291.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1720" speakername="Lembit pik" colnum="291"  time="015:23:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0007.htm#08060495000511">
	<p pid="a.291.0/1">I, too, congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1444" name="Roger Williams">the Member for Brecon and Radnorshire (Mr. Williams)</phrase> on bringing this important issue to the fore once again. I ask myself to what end he has done that. To what extent are the Government genuinely willing to listen to the feedback that he, I and so many other Members of Parliament have tried to bring to their attention? Let us recognise that while the Post Office has indeed conducted a consultation its hands have been tied by the political judgment of the Government to go ahead and demand the closure of 2,500 post offices. I understand that in total more than 5,000 post offices have shut since 1997. That is a lamentable record when one considers the value of post offices to the communities that have lost them.</p>
	<p pid="a.291.0/2">In advance of the comments of <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1495" name="Cheryl Gillan">the hon. Member for Chesham and Amersham (Mrs. Gillan)</phrase> for the Conservatives, and in response to the comments of <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1506" name="David Jones">the hon. Member for Clwyd, West (Mr. Jones)</phrase>, we have evidence about what happens when post offices shut. Communities shut down too. They become dormitories for larger local conurbations. Sadly, more than 4,000 post offices were shut under the reign of the Conservatives, so we need not look too far back to see the damage that has been done. I ask the hon. Lady, if she is minded to do so, to tell us what assurances we have that a future Conservative Government would perform any better than the present Government. I judge people on reaction and results, and unfortunately I do not think that the Conservatives performed significantly better at preserving our post office network than the current Government.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.291.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1495" speakername="Cheryl Gillan" colnum="291"  time="015:23:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0007.htm#08060495000512">
	<p pid="a.291.1/1">It may have escaped the hon. Gentleman's notice that under the last Conservative Government the Post Office actually made a profit.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.291.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1720" speakername="Lembit pik" colnum="291"  time="015:23:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0007.htm#08060495000513">
	<p pid="a.291.2/1">Yet still the Conservatives closed post offices. That makes the position even more incongruous than I believed.</p>
	<p pid="a.291.2/2">The criteria for considering which post offices to shut have been described as numerous, but money is obviously the core consideration. The Government and the Post Office say that they have been required to make a profit and that what is happening is the only way they can do it. Actually, the Government could make a different political judgment instead of dogmatically requiring the closure of post offices; if, rather than taking away the ability of post offices and sub-postmasters to offer facilities, they positively widened that access, we would not be in the mess that we are in. The irony is that television licensing, which was taken away from the Post Office, costs more now than it did under the Post Office.</p>
	<p pid="a.291.2/3">With an ageing population and high rural house prices the problem is even worse in rural areas such as mine. Several post offices have been and continue to be under threat in my constituency, including those at Llanbrynmair, a small settlement with no convenient local alternative; Carno, a village with the capacity to grow substantially; Trefeglwys, which has a successful shop, and where others, including the community, are interested in taking on the post office facility; Garth Owen, the only other post office in Newtown, which has a population of about 11,000; Sarn, where there is a small outlet of many years' standing; Castle Caereinion, which has a cherished and well used post office under the auspices of Michael Rogers; Berriew, which is an idyllic village with many tourists and a Spar shop that is very keen to take on the facility; and Abermule, perhaps the greatest concern of all, where Pauline and Peter Albrecht have worked their guts out to make their shop successful and their sub-post office an important local service. All those post offices are under threat because of the mandate that has come from the centre.</p>
	<p pid="a.291.2/4">It is all very well for the Government to adopt the approach of pretending that there is no alternative. If they gave post offices more opportunity to provide wider services, profits would be forthcoming. In addition, the Government seem to be ignoring what is happening in the oil market at the moment. With diesel at &pound;1.30 a litre in my area, my constituents are all too aware of the additional cost of travelling to other post offices in lieu of those that are to be closed. Let us not pretend that what is happening is cheap. If Castle Caereinion post office were to shut it would cost at least &pound;2 to post a letter, taking into account the cost of the fuel to travel to the next nearest post office, at Llanfair Caereinion.</p>
	<p pid="a.291.2/5">What about the environmental consequences? The Government talk about wanting to be environmentally responsible, yet in the same breath they announce the decimation of rural services, so that people are forced to travel further than ever before for such facilities. The Government also seem to ignore the fact that post offices are not just a business service; they are a social service. Nothing in the accountancy-led decision that has been made seems to reflect the social importance of post office facilities to constituencies such as Montgomeryshire and those of my hon. Friends who are here today.</p>
	<p pid="a.291.2/6">The strength of feeling can be garnered not just by word of mouth from the population but from the well organised and coherent campaigns that have been run by so many people in the affected communities. I pay tribute to the <i>County Times</i>, which has done more than any other paper in my constituency to highlight the issue and consistently to portray, with a fact-based approach, how important local people consider post offices to be. Furthermore, the paper employs the finest photographer and some of the finest reporters anywhere in the land.</p>
	<p pid="a.291.2/7">In conclusion, I have some questions for the Minister. Why are the Government unwilling to make a surcharge, to ensure that the private competitors of the Royal Mail do not have to pay towards the universal service obligation? What is the justification for continuing with the ludicrous access headroom discount, which means that the Post Office has to discount its competitors? Why could that money not be used to cross-subsidise the post office network? We could also look again at the price of stamps. What assurance can the Minister give us that the consultation process, in which all of us have meticulously participated, has the capacity to make any positive difference?</p>
	<p pid="a.291.2/8">Like many others, I have acted in good faith. I have worked with the Post Office, Postwatch and Ministers to get the Government to think again. Forthcoming announcements will give a clear indication as to whether the Government and the Post Office value the consultation and whether the social value of post offices has been taken into consideration. If there is wholesale closure of rural post offices, they will also tell us that the Government know the price of everything and the value of nothing.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.293.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1445" speakername="Sarah Teather" colnum="293"  time="015:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0007.htm#08060495000514">
	<p pid="a.293.0/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1444" name="Roger Williams">the Member for Brecon and Radnorshire (Mr. Williams)</phrase> on securing this debate. He said that today is a sad day for the people of Wales, as indeed it is, because they have learned that they are going to lose yet more post offices. He spoke about the impact, particularly on his most vulnerable constituents, and the idiocy of closing a post office, losing the shop, and putting a mobile post office immediately outside. That defies common sense. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1506" name="David Jones">The hon. Member for Clwyd, West (Mr. Jones)</phrase> and my hon. Friends the Members for Ceredigion (Mark Williams) and for Brecon and Radnorshire have also discussed whether the access criteria take into account the pressures of rural areas.</p>
	<p pid="a.293.0/2">I welcome the Minister once again to his usual place. We debate this issue at least once a week&mdash;indeed, I have seen him debate it with individual hon. Members much more frequently than that. I am sure that he realises the extent of the anger among hon. Members, including those on the Government side, about the decision to close 2,500 post offices in addition to the 4,000 that closed in previous Government programmes, and the 3,500 post offices that were closed by the Conservatives when they were in power.</p>
	<p pid="a.293.0/3">There is huge frustration that the Government simply do not recognise the social value of the post office. All hon. Members who have spoken, including my hon. Friends the Members for Ceredigion and for Brecon and Radnorshire, have mentioned the frustration of the consultation process. The former spoke about the sense that the proposals were a done deal and that once they were put forward, nothing could be done to fix the problem. Many other hon. Members in previous debates expressed the frustration that my constituents feel, because, even if they managed to save one post office, they would be told by Post Office Ltd that a nearby office would be closed.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.294.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1444" speakername="Roger Williams" colnum="294"  time="015:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0007.htm#08060495000515">
	<p pid="a.294.0/1">I did not cover that point in my contribution. We managed to save a post office in my constituency, but we wait with baited breath to find out whether another has been identified for closure, which would mean going through the whole six-week consultation process again.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.294.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1445" speakername="Sarah Teather" colnum="294"  time="015:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0007.htm#08060495000516">
	<p pid="a.294.1/1">Absolutely&mdash;it is invidious to expect local people to make such a choice. People will always campaign for their local post office, and they understand that the closure of a post office could have a huge impact on a neighbouring area. Six weeks is not long enough to put together any kind of sensible rescue package. Many communities, perhaps working with the local authority or businesses, want to put together a rescue package to ensure that a post office continues to be viable, but six weeks is not long enough to do that. It is as if we are simply going through the motions. By law, the Government must consult, but they are not terribly interested in what local people think about the impact of closures.</p>
	<p pid="a.294.1/2">London is a different kind of area&mdash;it is urban rather than rural&mdash;but we in Brent have just found out that another six post offices are due to close, so I sympathise with the frustration that hon. Members feel. Only 60 per cent. of post offices that were open in 1997 remain. A number of hon. Members spoke about queues. I have seen a change in people's behaviour even before post offices close, and the queues are already unmanageable at neighbouring post offices.</p>
	<p pid="a.294.1/3">All hon. Members who have spoken mentioned the impact on local shops. That is especially relevant in villages, where the post office might be the only shop, but it is also relevant in urban areas where, often, post offices reside in small parades of shops. If the post office is lost, the shop often goes with it. Because of the lack of footfall to neighbouring shops, the whole parade of shops in the area could be lost.</p>
	<p pid="a.294.1/4">A post office has an important economic role to play in surrounding areas&mdash;<phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1469" name="Hywel Williams">the hon. Member for Caernarfon (Hywel Williams)</phrase> and my hon. Friend the Member for Ceredigion made that point well. A number of reports have attempted to quantify their value. The New Economics Foundation, for example, has said that the cost to an urban area's economy of losing a post office is around &pound;277,000, which impacts on VAT received by the Government. Sometimes, the Government do not benefit greatly from their own cuts. In rural areas, it has been estimated that for every &pound;1 of subsidy, there is something between a &pound;2 and &pound;4 pound benefit to the local economy.</p>
	<p pid="a.294.1/5">Mobile post offices are simply inadequate to replace an original post office&mdash;they will not replace local shops that are lost.</p>
	<p pid="a.294.1/6">A number of hon. Members spoke about the small amount of money&mdash;&pound;45 million&mdash;that the Government will save from the process. Given the amount of grief they get and the impact on the rural economy, I am sure that the Minister, sitting in his place yet again, wonders whether it is really worth it and whether, in the long run, it will cost the Government more money. I know that he will hate my raising this, but that sum is in stark contrast to the figures published by Royal Mail that show that Adam Crozier gained more than &pound;3 million in bonuses, benefits and salaries. The Minister has an answer to that point, because he knows that I make it all the time.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.295.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1936" speakername="Patrick McFadden" speakeroffice="The Minister for Employment Relations and Postal Affairs"  colnum="295"  time="015:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0007.htm#08060495000517">
	<p pid="a.295.0/1">I appreciate that my time to speak is coming. I assure the hon. Lady that I do not hate her raising anything&mdash;before today's debate, I simply said that our exchanges are sometimes predictable.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.295.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1445" speakername="Sarah Teather" colnum="295"  time="015:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0007.htm#08060495000518">
	<p pid="a.295.1/1">Of course, there is a way to fix that: the Government could change their mind, so that we do not have to go through this little game once a week, in which we all have a go at the Minister for closing our local post offices. If he simply changed his mind and stopped closing our post offices, we would not need to go through this little ritual. It is in the Minister's hands, but I shall endeavour to be unique in contributing to these debates. We make some of our points repeatedly, because he does not appear to be able to hear us.</p>
	<p pid="a.295.1/2">Many hon. Members spoke of the sense that losing the local post office would mean losing everything in the area. My hon. Friend the Member for Ceredigion has spoken passionately about the many things that his rural area will lose and the fact that the post office is the last thing standing. I assure him that the same is true in urban areas. We have lost police stations, and job and health centres. There is a sense that everything is going and that facilities that offer opportunities for people to deal face to face with one another are being closed.</p>
	<p pid="a.295.1/3">The Business and Enterprise Committee report raised the spectre of further closures, because the Post Office refuses to state the lower limit on the number of post offices for a viable network. I am especially anxious about that. Only 7,500 post offices are required to meet the Government's access criteria, and the Government simply do not have a long-term plan for the sustainability of the network. The whole point of the closure programme, supposedly, is to drive the footfall into the remaining post offices to make them viable, but that does not stand up, and it has not been demonstrated by experience or any sensible audit of the available evidence. When post offices close, people tend to change their behaviour and stop using post offices, because it is more difficult to get to them&mdash;people might have to drive or take several buses, as my hon. Friends have mentioned, so it becomes impossible.</p>
	<p pid="a.295.1/4">In my remaining minutes, I shall suggest what the Government might do. I hope that they will consider separating the Post Office from Royal Mail, which would give the Post Office an opportunity to work with competitors. There are many possibilities for post offices to work as parcel depots, for instance, where people can pick up parcels delivered not just by Royal Mail but by its competitors. That might improve the network's financial viability.</p>
	<p pid="a.295.1/5">We need a dramatic increase in investment, including a lump sum, to allow the network to modernise so that it can compete on the high street. In particular, the Crown post office network is haemorrhaging money and urgently needs modernisation. Post offices desperately need a source of revenue. There is uncertainty about the Post Office card account, but I hope that the Government will consider making the Post Office the cornerstone of a new universal service obligation to provide bank accounts, either through the Post Office or by working collaboratively with banks. There are many opportunities that the Government could take to ensure that the post office network is viable, but I suspect that they will not take them and that we will simply hear again, &quot;The Government have to do this in order to save money.&quot; That would be a shame.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.296.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1495" speakername="Cheryl Gillan" colnum="296"  time="015:40:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0007.htm#08060495000519">
	<p pid="a.296.0/1">I, too, congratulate all hon. Members who have participated in this debate. I also welcome the Minister to his place. This debate is a little desperate&mdash;indeed, the Minister looks a little desperate himself, if he does not mind my saying so. He had the sympathy of my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1506" name="David Jones">the Member for Clwyd, West (Mr. Jones)</phrase>, and he has mine as well, because I know that he will have heard much of this before. However, whereas I am temporarily deaf in my left ear and hope to recover in due course, the Minister and the Labour Government appear to be permanently deaf on the matter of post offices. No matter how many representations are made or debates are held, or how many times we try to repeat the will of the people to this Government, they insist on blanking the wishes of the people in our communities, not least in Wales.</p>
	<p pid="a.296.0/2">I suppose that I ought to declare an interest. My husband, when he was a senior official in the Department of Trade and Industry, was responsible for the Post Office&mdash;indeed, it was under him that it made a profit&mdash;and my sister-in-law was a sub-postmistress. I am not unfamiliar with what went on in post offices. Although the Liberal Democrats like to complain about the number of post offices closed under the Conservatives, I assure them that it pales into insignificance when we study the record of this Labour Government, who are closing post offices faster than any other Government in history at a rate of almost 10 a week since 1997. With the announcement about the 2,500 post offices, the network will continue to be decimated. By the time of the next election, we estimate that a third of the entire post office network will have been closed down.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.296.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1720" speakername="Lembit pik" colnum="296"  time="015:40:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0007.htm#08060495000520">
	<p pid="a.296.1/1">Will the hon. Lady give way?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.296.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1495" speakername="Cheryl Gillan" colnum="296"  time="015:40:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0007.htm#08060495000521">
	<p pid="a.296.2/1">No, I do not have enough time. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1445" name="Sarah Teather">The hon. Member for Brent, East (Sarah Teather)</phrase> almost ate into my time.</p>
	<p pid="a.296.2/2">The Government's target for closures arbitrary, illogical and does not take into account whether a post office marked for closure is profitable. As <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1444" name="Roger Williams">the hon. Member for Brecon and Radnorshire (Mr. Williams)</phrase> has said, communities will be pitted against each other, not least because of the dog-eat-dog closure programme under which, if one community campaigns successfully against a closure, a neighbouring branch will be shut down.</p>
	<p pid="a.296.2/3">I hope that the Minister will address the anomaly in the announcement and its timetabling, because it is appalling that there are doubts about how such announcements are made. For example, I was delighted to learn that the Tremont road post office in Llandrindod Wells will not close, and that Margaret Hodges, the postmistress, will continue to serve the community there, but that is in contrast with Ridgebourne, run by Mr. and Mrs. Yeo, whose fate is yet unknown. The salvation of the neighbouring post office puts the Yeos under more pressure.</p>
	<p pid="a.296.2/4">Hon. Members' points about the vulnerable in our society such as the elderly and disabled who will be disadvantaged by the closures were all validly made, but I have another point to add. In my travels around post offices in Wales, I came across one post office that is located down the road from a women's refuge. The women there visit the post office regularly. It is one of the safest routes that they can walk. It is an outlet and allows them regular contact with people in the community. Some of those women are the most abused in our society. Removing their local post office will remove a facility that is very valuable to them, and they will have a great deal of difficulty making their voices heard. When I was in Penarth with some disabled post office users, I was alarmed to hear what would happen to their quality of life. At the moment, they can travel down the road to collect their post and carry out their own business at the post office, which would be denied them if that post office were to close. There is fear and anxiety. It is obvious that the Government have no long-term vision for the post office network.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.297.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1720" speakername="Lembit pik" colnum="297"  time="015:40:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0008.htm#08060495000522">
	<p pid="a.297.0/1">Will the hon. Lady give way?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.297.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1495" speakername="Cheryl Gillan" colnum="297"  time="015:40:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0008.htm#08060495000523">
	<p pid="a.297.1/1">I have no intention of giving way. I do not have enough time.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.297.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1720" speakername="Lembit pik" colnum="297"  time="015:40:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0008.htm#08060495000524">
	<p pid="a.297.2/1">On a point of order, Mr. Atkinson. We all gave way. I had seven minutes, and the hon. Lady insisted on intervening. I know that I cannot force her to give way, but it seems the height of disrespect for her not to give way at least once.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.297.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1635" speakername="Peter Atkinson" colnum="297"  time="015:40:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0008.htm#08060495000525">
	<p pid="a.297.3/1">That is not a matter for the Chair. If the hon. Lady says that she will not give way, she will not give way.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.297.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1495" speakername="Cheryl Gillan" colnum="297"  time="015:40:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0008.htm#08060495000526">
	<p pid="a.297.4/1">Thank you, Mr. Atkinson. We certainly recognise the fantastic service provided by postmasters and sub-postmasters in local communities, which came through in some hon. Members' contributions. However, what I did not hear from any of the Liberal Democrat Members or the Plaid Cymru Member was a concerted plan for post office action.</p>
	<p pid="a.297.4/2">As the Minister knows, in response to increasing fears about significant post office closures, the Conservatives published a post office action plan last year. For the sake of symmetry, I shall repeat it, which will give the Minister an opportunity in responding to update me on the Government's views. First, on freeing up sub-postmasters, we would certainly allow sub-postmasters to provide a greater range of products and services, including private mail services. The network's long-term future will be best secured if the post office is opened up to new markets and new customers. We want to use post offices as a sort of government GP surgery. We could investigate a scheme in which people with concerns involving a range of government services could use their local post office as a kind of government GP.</p>
	<p pid="a.297.4/3">Will the Minister update me on what has been happening with the Welsh Assembly Government? The &quot;One Wales&quot; document said that the Government would</p>
	<p pid="a.297.4/4" class="indent">&quot;reinstate and refocus the Post Office Development Fund&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.297.4/5">Will he confirm whether that has happened? Also, what has been happening as far as the small business rate relief scheme is concerned for post offices in Wales?</p>
	<p pid="a.297.4/6">We campaigned on the Post Office card account. We called repeatedly for the Government to review the decision to abolish the POCA, and we were delighted that they responded to our arguments and changed their mind, but we also propose to encourage council counters, which would encourage local councils to see what services they could provide through their post offices and whether they could use the post office network in their area to engage better with local residents.</p>
	<p pid="a.297.4/7">Services should be more widely available in the community. Indeed, one of the post offices I visited, in the constituency of the hon. Member for Brecon and Radnorshire, was providing fishing licences for a father and son. That was an excellent additional service. When I visited Pendre, I spoke to Jay Vakil, and in Llanfaes I met Karen Weale with our excellent candidate for Brecon and Radnorshire, Suzy Davies, who has been doing a tremendous amount of work on the issue. She started many of the petitions in the area. I became aware of the pressure from the community to keep those post offices open, as I said when the hon. Member for Montgomeryshire so kindly let me intervene.</p>
	<p pid="a.297.4/8">The post office closures have worrying implications for Wales. Will the Minister comment on the New Economics Foundation study showing that when post offices close in a community, it has an impact on the local economy, and that a single post office closure could result in the loss of &pound;270,000 to that local economy? The foundation also worked out that every &pound;10 earned by a post office generates &pound;16.20 in income in the local economy. He will know that our economy in Wales is fragile, to say the least, in rural areas. What work has he done on that effect of the closures that the hon. Member for Brecon and Radnorshire has brought to our attention?</p>
	<p pid="a.297.4/9">Despite all the protests by Members of Parliament and members of the community, the Government appear not to have responded. I point out to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1720" name="Lembit pik">the hon. Member for Montgomeryshire (Lembit &Ouml;pik)</phrase> that no Welsh Labour MPs are present in this debate. When we proposed to halt the closure programme, 22 Welsh Labour MPs voted against our motion; the only one to stick with us was <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1733" name="Paul Flynn">the hon. Member for Newport, West (Paul Flynn)</phrase>, on which he should be congratulated. I believe that the Government are doing Wales and the rest of the country a great disservice. They are not listening to the people. I hope that the Minister will not turn out the standard response that he has been turning out in these debates over the past weeks, months and years, and that this time he will really listen to the people of Wales.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.298.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1936" speakername="Patrick McFadden" speakeroffice="The Minister for Employment Relations and Postal Affairs"  colnum="298"  time="015:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0008.htm#08060495000527">
	<p pid="a.298.0/1">As is customary, I begin by congratulating <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1444" name="Roger Williams">the hon. Member for Brecon and Radnorshire (Mr. Williams)</phrase> on securing this debate. As a number of hon. Members have commented, post office closures have been debated a number of times, and in some ways there might not be much new to say. However, he certainly spoke with great passion about his constituency.</p>
	<p pid="a.298.0/2">Today's debate reminds me in some ways of the one that we had a couple of months ago on post office closures in the highlands and islands, some of the characteristics of which I suspect that mid-Wales shares: it is geographically large and sparsely populated. It has 166 post offices serving about 200,000 people. Of those post offices, 13 are scheduled for closure, which is actually a lower proportion than the average across the country, partly in recognition of some of those characteristics, about which all three of the mid-Wales Members spoke.</p>
	<p pid="a.298.0/3">The hon. Gentleman made some points about the release of information. The Post Office is trying to inform people, such as MPs and sub-postmasters, before decisions are made public, but there is an element of trust in that. If it did not do that and simply released all of the information on one day without telling anyone, I think that people would complain about a lack of advance information.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.299.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1444" speakername="Roger Williams" colnum="299"  time="015:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0008.htm#08060495000528">
	<p pid="a.299.0/1">My complaint was not with the Post Office, which has proceeded perfectly properly, but that the information broke in my constituency before I was informed. I do not put the blame on the Post Office.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.299.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1936" speakername="Patrick McFadden" colnum="299"  time="015:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0008.htm#08060495000529">
	<p pid="a.299.1/1">I understand. I was saying that the Post Office tries to inform people, such as MPs and sub-postmasters, before information enters the public domain. Difficulties can result if someone else&mdash;we do not know who&mdash;releases that information, but I suspect that, if the Post Office were to stop informing such people in advance, the effect would be even worse, because people would simply read about it in the newspapers.</p>
	<p pid="a.299.1/2">Understandably, hon. Members talk about the strength of feeling about, and opposition to, the closures in their constituencies. No one likes their post office to close, even if they do not use it very much. Hon. Members might object, but quite often I have to point out the reasons for some of the closures and set out some of the challenges that face the Post Office. Over the past hour or so, we have not heard a great deal about that. The Post Office's difficulties are being driven by three significant factors. The first factor is life-style change, the biggest example of which is how we receive money. Nowadays, people are used to receiving their salaries directly into their bank accounts, which is reflected as people retire. We might think of the post office as the outlet of choice for almost all pensioners when picking up their pensions, but that is no longer the case. Eight out of 10 have their pensions paid directly into their bank account, and the younger a pensioner is, the more likely that is to be the case&mdash;the figure is nine out of 10 among new retirees. That is one example of how things are changing for the Post Office.</p>
	<p pid="a.299.1/3">The second factor is technology. The past decade has witnessed a complete revolution in the way that people communicate with one another. That technological change has also affected the way that we pay bills and carry out transactions. An example is car tax online, which is a service that did not even exist a year ago. Last year, 500,000 people used it every month, and that figure is now 1 million&mdash;1 million people no longer visiting their post offices to tax their cars. What should the Government do about that? Should we deny the availability of that service? I do not believe so. The difficult truth is that, far from being ahead of the curve on technology and the way that people live, I believe that the Government are probably behind it. The public are probably ahead of the politicians. That will inevitably have an impact on the number of people who use the Post Office.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.300.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1444" speakername="Roger Williams" colnum="300"  time="015:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0008.htm#08060495000530">
	<p pid="a.300.0/1">One way in which the Minister could help is by ensuring that post offices can check the insurance of a car being taxed, without the customer bringing the cover note with them. That way there would be a level playing field.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.300.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1936" speakername="Patrick McFadden" colnum="300"  time="015:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0008.htm#08060495000531">
	<p pid="a.300.1/1">Those who use the online service like the idea that the databases are joined up behind the scenes, but I do not want to be drawn into too much detail on that, because I have very little time.</p>
	<p pid="a.300.1/2">The third factor is competition. Other networks now provide some services traditionally provided by the Post Office. Reference was made to the television licence, the contract for which was lost to another network, as a result of a decision taken by the BBC, not the Government. That illustrates the environment in which the Post Office is working.</p>
	<p pid="a.300.1/3">A number of Members made a general point about the Government giving up on rural areas and ignoring the social side of post offices. Nothing could be further from the truth. The Government are in the middle of putting in place support for the post office network of some &pound;1.7 billion in the years running up to 2011, which will enable thousands of post office branches that would otherwise be under threat from the kind of changes that I have talked about&mdash;in technology, lifestyle and competition&mdash;to stay open. I understand that it is difficult for communities when faced with a post office closure, but it is also important to recognise the size and extent of Government support for the post office network. That &pound;1.7 billion demonstrates that the Government are doing anything but giving up on rural areas and the social side of post offices. Some of the individual post offices mentioned today have fewer than 100 customers a week and some of them have fewer than 50. In those post offices, the subsidy per transaction is between &pound;8 and &pound;17. That is the extent of the support for some rural post offices.</p>
	<p pid="a.300.1/4">On future business, of course the Post Office card account is out to tender. A decision will be made by the Department for Work and Pensions later this year. Legally, we must put that decision out to tender; we cannot simply give that business to the Post Office. It is in a strong position to bid, but let us see how it turns out. I do not believe that the future can involve turning back the clock on the lifestyle changes about which I spoke. I do not believe that any of us will be collecting our state pension from post offices, but there are new possibilities, one of which involves the provision of identity management information&mdash;passports, driving licences and, possibly in the future, identity cards. So when hon. Members say, &quot;Let's give more work to the Post Office,&quot; we should point out that neither the Conservatives nor the Liberal Democrats would even create the possibility for the Post Office to gain access to that line of work. It would have to bid for that work, but it could represent an important line of business, yet every Member who spoke today represents a party that opposes even that possibility. I hope that we can consider that when saying that the Government should give the Post Office more business.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.301.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="301"  time="015:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0008.htm#08060495000004">
	Wiltshire Police Helicopter
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.301.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1803" speakername="Robert Key" colnum="301"  time="016:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0008.htm#08060495000532">
	<p pid="a.301.1/1">May I say what a pleasure it is to sit under your chairmanship, Mr. Atkinson, and welcome my right hon. and learned Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1537" name="Michael Ancram">the Member for Devizes (Mr. Ancram)</phrase> and my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1926" name="James Gray">the Member for North Wiltshire (Mr. Gray)</phrase>? They have been fighting this campaign along with me and other Members with Wiltshire constituencies. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1866" name="Anne Snelgrove">The hon. Member for South Swindon (Anne Snelgrove)</phrase> has sent her apologies. She has been called away elsewhere on business, but she, too, has pledged her support for the Wiltshire police helicopter.</p>
	<p pid="a.301.1/2">The reason for the debate is that the Wiltshire police helicopter was one of the very first in the country and is still one of only two that provide a joint air ambulance service. It is important to put on record just how busy the helicopter is. Back in 1990, when it came into operation as part of the air operations unit of Wiltshire constabulary, no one could have had any idea how important it would become to the county's policing. It provides 19 hours' cover per day, 365 days a year, and it is on call for those missing hours between 3 am and 8 am as requested.</p>
	<p pid="a.301.1/3">Over the past three years, the helicopter has flown 3,693 sorties, and it has been involved in finding 53 vulnerable missing persons, sufferers from Alzheimer's and similar dementia cases. It has been involved in the arrests of 506 people, the location of 60 vehicles, the recovery of property to the value of &pound;275,000 and, most significantly, in taking 906 seriously injured patients to hospital. That is a remarkable record for a helicopter that operates on a budget of &pound;1.6 million a year.</p>
	<p pid="a.301.1/4">The funding is divided into three sources. The public finance grant, which comes from the Home Office, is &pound;405,000 a year. The Great Western ambulance service pays 30 per cent. of the cost of the first 500 flying hours and 25 per cent. of the cost of any further hours, and that budget provision works out at about &pound;326,000 a year. Wiltshire police fund the balance of &pound;911,000. All that funding excludes the cost of the paramedics, who are provided by the Great Western ambulance service. The paramedics provide an observer role for the helicopter when it is flying, and without them Wiltshire police would incur extra costs.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.301.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1537" speakername="Michael Ancram" colnum="301"  time="016:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0008.htm#08060495000533">
	<p pid="a.301.2/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend on securing the debate. Is it not true that the equation he has just set out&mdash;the three sources of funding&mdash;has made the ambulance and police facility totally viable, and that if it is broken, it is likely that neither service will be available to our constituents?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.301.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1803" speakername="Robert Key" colnum="301"  time="016:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0008.htm#08060495000534">
	<p pid="a.301.3/1">Emphatically yes. My right hon. and learned Friend is wholly right, and part of the magic of the Wiltshire solution to the problem is that it involves the community. The air ambulance side of the facility is provided by a charitable trust, but more on that later.</p>
	<p pid="a.301.3/2">The helicopter is manned by three individuals. The pilot is provided under a private finance initiative and employed by a company called Police Aviation Services. The first observer role is provided by a police officer who is trained in air support, and police observers are trained and competent to carry out limited health care, too. The second observer role is provided by a paramedic who is fully trained to supply health care at the incident if necessary. Both police and ambulance observers are trained to national police observer standards.</p>
	<p pid="a.301.3/3">As I said, the helicopter is provided by a PFI contract with Police Aviation Services. As the contract is for the provision of an operationally ready helicopter, the risk of breakdowns, non-availability and so on is passed to the provider, rather than held by the public sector as is usually the case with police helicopters.</p>
	<p pid="a.301.3/4">Negotiations to extend the contract, which comes to its close at the end of this year, are taking place with Police Aviation Services, but there are still problems about short-term extensions because the camera equipment support contract is also about to terminate. Over the 10 years of the contract, technology has advanced and initial quotations to replace the equipment stand at about &pound;800,000. Short-term extensions are therefore economically unviable, but discussions continue.</p>
	<p pid="a.301.3/5">That sounds fine, but the Wiltshire public&mdash;our constituents&mdash;are very worried about a number of aspects. I shall not go into the relationship between the charitable trusts and the Great Western ambulance service, although that concern has been drawn to the attention of the charity commissioners. I am concerned about the impact on Wiltshire policing, which is why I decided to ask a Home Office Minister to respond to the debate. The Wiltshire police authority is very keen to renew the arrangement with the Great Western ambulance service for a further five years, and the authority wants the joint service to continue if at all possible. The position of the ambulance service, however, is a bit more enigmatic, and in a letter dated <phrase class="date" code="2008-05-12">12 May</phrase> the chief executive explains why the service is involved in a long-term review of the situation. He simply says:</p>
	<p pid="a.301.3/6" class="indent">&quot;There are therefore no 'firm' plans at this stage.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.301.3/7">That might be good for the Great Western ambulance service, but it is very bad news for the police service.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.302.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1922" speakername="Andrew Murrison" colnum="302"  time="016:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0008.htm#08060495000535">
	<p pid="a.302.0/1">It was not as if the Great Western ambulance service did not know about the renewal. Does my hon. Friend not think it remarkable that Great Western has taken this long to crack on with its review? The review is its problem; it should not become the police's.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.302.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1803" speakername="Robert Key" colnum="302"  time="016:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0008.htm#08060495000536">
	<p pid="a.302.1/1">I am very glad that my hon. Friend from west Wiltshire has joined us for the debate, because he has been a doughty fighter for his constituents, who, if anything, are rather more rural than even mine and depend even more on the joint service. He is wholly right. The problem has not just suddenly sprung up and hit everyone; it has been predictable for 10 years. Now, however, the situation has been thrown into confusion, not least because only two days ago, on <phrase class="date" code="2008-06-02">2 June</phrase>, the Great Western ambulance service issued a press release announcing the start of its new air ambulance service, which will become &quot;operational this week&quot;. The problem is that it leaves Wiltshire in the same position as before. The announcement is fine for people in Avon and in Gloucestershire. It is good news for them, except that unlike the police helicopter, the air ambulance cannot fly 24 hours a day. It can fly only in daylight hours, which means that in winter it will fly for only seven or eight hours a day, unlike the Wiltshire service, which one can fly all the time. The Civil Aviation Authority is also changing the rules governing the public use of helicopters, which further complicates the equation.</p>
	<p pid="a.302.1/2">We are fortunate that the Minister is present today, because she has in a very short time acquired a great deal of expertise in the matter. On <phrase class="date" code="2008-05-13">13 May</phrase>, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1839" name="Frank Cook">the hon. Member for Stockton, North (Frank Cook)</phrase> initiated a debate in this Chamber about the problems that people have been having in the north-east&mdash;in Northumberland, with which you will be familiar, Mr. Atkinson, as the Member for Hexham. What the Minister said then is, to a large extent, applicable to what is going on in Wiltshire now. She mentioned that</p>
	<p pid="a.302.1/3" class="indent">&quot;the Civil Aviation Authority amended the air navigation order to increase compliancy requirements for public transport at night.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.302.1/4">But she also talked of</p>
	<p pid="a.302.1/5" class="indent">&quot;the existence of a national strategy underpinning police air operations, which dates back to January 1993.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.302.1/6">That is extremely important. She pointed out that</p>
	<p pid="a.302.1/7" class="indent">&quot;the Government allocate specific capital funding of &pound;5 million a year to support aviation.&quot;&mdash;[<phrase class="offrep" id="westminhall/2008-05-13.387"><i>Official Report, Westminster Hall</i>, 13 May 2008; Vol. 475, c. 387-388WH</phrase>.]</p>
	<p pid="a.302.1/8">She also said that the funding, which includes a 40 per cent. contribution by the Home Office, was agreed with the Association of County Councils many years ago.</p>
	<p pid="a.302.1/9">I should be grateful if the Minister could please update us on the Association of Chief Police Officers' review of police air operations in England and Wales. We know that the group is working with the National Policing Improvement Agency and with the police, and I hope that they are on to Wiltshire's case, because it is very important to our constituents. The ACPO review will establish what the forces and the public need, which is air support, and what the policing priorities are. Recommendations will flow from that, but will the Minister tell us when we will get them?</p>
	<p pid="a.302.1/10">I understand that there might be some short-term financial alleviation to allow equipment to be procured. That might be relevant for the Wiltshire police helicopter, which needs new equipment worth some &pound;800,000. There is a round of Home Office funding worth &pound;5 million, but the lid to that particular pot will be closed at the end of December. How will that help the Wiltshire situation?</p>
	<p pid="a.302.1/11">What is unique about the Wiltshire police helicopter is the fact that it has joint funding, with charitable funding for the air ambulance side. That is hugely important. I find myself quite torn. It is very important for the community to feel that they are stakeholders in this project. The air ambulance belongs to the people of Wiltshire; they have raised the money. The &pound;1.3 million in the kitty of the charitable trust is Wiltshire money and we hope that the air ambulance will continue to be used in Wiltshire. There is tremendous commitment to the service from our constituents. It is feared that if the air ambulance side of the operation comes to an end, the police helicopter will no longer be viable and will have to cease its service by the end of the year, which would be tragic.</p>
	<p pid="a.302.1/12">Therefore, while I welcome the charitable contributions to the air ambulance side, I do not think that it is the right solution. No doubt the reviews will consider that matter. It is not right in this day and age to be wondering whether we can afford a police helicopter. Police helicopters and air ambulances are not a luxury, and they are no longer a novelty. They were 10 years ago. In the 19th century, the police constable and village bobby would not have shared their pedal cycle with the district nurse; in the 21st century, the police helicopter should not have to be shared between the crime busters and the trauma clinicians on whom we all rely.</p>
	<p pid="a.302.1/13">This significant issue has not been aired publicly in a satisfactory way. Far too much is going on behind closed doors. The lips of all the employees involved are sealed. There is suspicion among the ambulance crews because they feel that the air ambulance does not go out when it should. However, that is for perfectly sound operational reasons based on the professionalism and experience of the air support unit located in the constituency of my right hon. and learned Friend the Member for Devizes. That problem will get worse and run into the buffers unless the Minister can help us. She cannot solve the problems of the air ambulance as such, but I hope that it will concentrate her mind to know that if we do not crack this problem, and if her colleagues in the Department of Health do not rap someone over the knuckles, we will lose a very important component of policing in Wiltshire.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.304.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1515" speakername="Geoffrey Clifton-Brown" colnum="304"  time="016:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0009.htm#08060495000537">
	<p pid="a.304.0/1">I am sorry to intrude into the debate of my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1803" name="Robert Key">the Member for Salisbury (Robert Key)</phrase>. Gloucestershire shares the ambulance helicopter with Wiltshire but has no police helicopter. Does he not agree that a comprehensive solution needs to be found to benefit the three counties&mdash;Wiltshire, Avon and Gloucestershire&mdash;involved in the air ambulance?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.304.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1803" speakername="Robert Key" colnum="304"  time="016:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0009.htm#08060495000538">
	<p pid="a.304.1/1">From my hon. Friend's point of view, he is entirely right. From Wiltshire's point of view, he is entirely wrong. We should not have such a problem. In the 21st century, we should have a comprehensive national approach. The national health service, for which the Minister is not responsible, should not need to approach charities to fund air ambulances when they are proving so cost-effective. The clinicians and consultants of the Hampshire and Isle of Wight helicopter service are adamant that air ambulances should be part of standard national health service provision. We need a national plan for that and for the police helicopter. I hope that the Minister will tell us that one is coming soon so that we can reassure our constituents.</p>
	<p pid="a.304.1/2">This is an all-party matter. The Labour Members representing Swindon are as keen and as worried about this as we are. I hope that we can find some resolution because this problem will escalate if we do not deal with it quickly. I am sure that the Minister, with her swiftly acquired expertise, will be able to address the problem in a way that will allay the fears of our constituents, many of whom have benefited from the air ambulance and the police helicopter.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.304.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1605" speakername="Meg Hillier" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for the Home Department"  colnum="304"  time="016:15:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0009.htm#08060495000539">
	<p pid="a.304.2/1">It is a pleasure to serve under your chairmanship for the first time, Mr. Atkinson. I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1803" name="Robert Key">the hon. Member for Salisbury (Robert Key)</phrase> on securing this debate.</p>
	<p pid="a.304.2/2">The point about the interest in the service has been well made both by the presence of four other hon. Members and by the support of others who were not able to be here today. I recognise the concerns that the hon. Gentleman raised about the future funding arrangements of the combined police and air ambulance operation. The unit provides police air support and helicopter emergency medical services to the people of Wiltshire. Significantly, the helicopter has been provided under a private finance initiative and is based at the Devizes headquarters of the Wiltshire constabulary. The PFI contract has been going for a long time. By working with its local ambulance service and co-locating some of its services, Wiltshire has been one of the most forward thinking police authorities. Perhaps other parts of the country could learn from such an operation. The contract has been running for nearly 10 years and is due for renewal from December this year.</p>
	<p pid="a.304.2/3">Contract negotiations are currently ongoing. The Great Western ambulance service has asked for an extension to the contract while it carries out a review of the area's clinical need for helicopter services. I understand that the police are pressing for a further five-year contract. As the hon. Gentleman said, the two parties are still in negotiation over that point.</p>
	<p pid="a.304.2/4">As the hon. Gentleman appreciates, there are limits to the Home Office's reach in such areas. As he quite helpfully pointed out, I do not have responsibility for the national health service; I have plenty of other things on my plate. There are important issues about the autonomy of local police and ambulance authorities. It is not the role of the Home Office to direct, at a close local level, individual operational decisions. It is for Wiltshire constabulary, the police authority, neighbouring police forces and the air ambulance charities to determine their own operational needs. It is important to recognise that the Government do not run everything from Whitehall. We do not have any locus in this area and neither do the Department of Health or the National Policing Improvement Agency, for which I have some responsibility.</p>
	<p pid="a.304.2/5">From the Home Office perspective, police helicopter operations are very important. They have been used to target criminal activity and have improved safety on dangerous vehicle pursuits. In this instance, in which the aircraft is shared, we have seen benefits to the public, which is what we all, as Members of Parliament, are most interested in. The vital role of delivering emergency care to people across south-west England has proved an effective and faster way of getting people to hospital and supporting inter-hospital transfers.</p>
	<p pid="a.304.2/6">The hon. Gentleman mentioned the amount of money that has been raised by the public. Clearly, the service has had enormous support from the public. People have been dipping into their pockets to pay for it. They also support the work that has been done by the medical and trauma teams. I am grateful for the work done by both the police and the helicopter emergency medical service, which is carried out on a 24/7 basis. The teams work long hours, which is very impressive.</p>
	<p pid="a.304.2/7">It was interesting and instructive to learn&mdash;from the review that the hon. Gentleman mentioned&mdash;that Wiltshire and Sussex are the only two counties with a joint operation. We should consider that model for the future. In a moment, I will touch on what is happening with the review, as the hon. Gentleman asked. There are clearly financial benefits to linking services, which enables the air ambulance to operate at night because of the capacity of the police helicopter and the equipment therein.</p>
	<p pid="a.304.2/8">The current national air support strategy for the police has served police services since 1993, but there has been no meaningful review for 14 years. It is a mark of the differences and changes over the years that in 1993 only 16 forces nationally had any form of air support, but today 39 of 43 forces have direct access to aircraft, with 34 helicopters and four fixed-wing planes available to the police nationally, although procured on the basis of local demands and resources.</p>
	<p pid="a.304.2/9">The hon. Gentleman mentioned the funding provided by the Home Office, in the funding round that we are approaching at the moment, with a capital pot of &pound;5 million available for part-funding the capital purchase of helicopters. Because the Wiltshire helicopter was purchased under a private finance initiative arrangement, the aircraft belongs to Police Aviation Services, as the hon. Gentleman mentioned. We cannot put Home Office investment into an asset that belongs to that organisation rather than the police. That limits the opportunities to look at that pot of money.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.306.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1803" speakername="Robert Key" colnum="306"  time="016:15:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0009.htm#08060495000540">
	<p pid="a.306.0/1">Is that fund applicable to equipment in the helicopter that is purchased specially for the use of the air ambulance service and the police service?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.306.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1605" speakername="Meg Hillier" colnum="306"  time="016:15:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0009.htm#08060495000541">
	<p pid="a.306.1/1">I think not, because of the ownership of the helicopter, but I will write to the hon. Gentleman in detail and clarify the matter. Perhaps we can have a dialogue about exactly which bits of equipment he is talking about to ensure that we get things straight. I would not want to commit myself on the technical detail of bits of equipment that I do not know anything about.</p>
	<p pid="a.306.1/2">What is going on in Wiltshire is an example of what we should be looking at for the 21st century. Wiltshire is setting the agenda. The work being done by the Association of Chief Police Officers in its air operations working group and the fundamental review, which the hon. Gentleman talked about and which I mentioned on <phrase class="date" code="2008-04-13">13 April</phrase> in respect of police air operations in England and Wales, will provide a framework for what we envisage and hope for in the next 10 years and will be updatable as necessary. We are making progress on that.</p>
	<p pid="a.306.1/3">The draft report is currently with Chief Constable Hogan-Howe and the first meeting to discuss it will be tomorrow morning at about 9 am, so I cannot tell the hon. Gentleman exactly where we are with that, because we are a day ahead of ourselves&mdash;if only we had had this debate tomorrow afternoon. The aim is that the chief officers council will see the proposals in or around July, although I cannot predict a precise time. I am happy to keep in contact with the hon. Gentleman and ensure that he is made aware of progress.</p>
	<p pid="a.306.1/4">The review will consider all issues to do with where a helicopter is based and co-operation options. It will be down to ACPO to finalise the detail. I hope that it will note good practice where it works, take those lessons and apply them more widely. That is a matter for the review. Whatever the recommendations of the review, decisions need to be made locally, as an operational matter, between the local force and air ambulance service.</p>
	<p pid="a.306.1/5">I am sure that hon. Members agree that the Home Office's and the Government's commitment to policing is demonstrated by the fact that we have increased the police grant by more than 60 per cent., or &pound;3.7 billion, between 1997 and 2010-11. Funding is allocated chiefly through the police formula grant to allow police forces and authorities the flexibility to determine their local priorities, which we have already mentioned.</p>
	<p pid="a.306.1/6">The ACPO air operations working group provides national co-ordination and support to police air operations and the review will be helpful in that respect. Chief Constable Bernard Hogan-Howe, who is leading the review and leads on police air operations overall, is able to lend the group's support to any forces to overcome any difficulties. If the hon. Gentleman has not already made contact with Chief Constable Hogan-Howe, he may wish to do so to see if he can use his weight, along with my words today, in support of a solution to the issue.</p>
	<p pid="a.306.1/7">The hon. Gentleman has used his influence effectively and no one in Wiltshire can be in any doubt about his commitment, and the commitment of the public, to the joint service. There is an opportunity for him to contact Chief Constable Hogan-Howe. I will make sure that I answer the point about funding issues in writing and I will also keep him up to date on progress on the review programme, so that&mdash;I hope&mdash;by July we will have the results.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.307.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1537" speakername="Michael Ancram" colnum="307"  time="016:15:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0009.htm#08060495000542">
	<p pid="a.307.0/1">One aspect of the use of the helicopter that should be put on the record is that the A4, which is in my constituency, is a straight road and is good for speeding motorcycles&mdash;if I can put it that way. Motorcycles often go at speeds that are impossible to police by car and the police helicopter has been an effective way of policing them. If the helicopter goes, it could be very damaging.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.307.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1605" speakername="Meg Hillier" colnum="307"  time="016:15:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0009.htm#08060495000543">
	<p pid="a.307.1/1">The right hon. and learned Gentleman raises an important point. The issue of police chases and how the helicopter can help to prevent accidents is important. I cannot quote the figures off the top of my head, but the statistics for motorcycle safety are immense. When a police car chases somebody on a motorcycle, the temptation to go faster is no doubt huge. I, and the Home Office, see the benefit of police helicopters.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.307.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1926" speakername="James Gray" colnum="307"  time="016:15:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0009.htm#08060495000544">
	<p pid="a.307.2/1">I had not intended to intervene, but we have some time left so I hope the Minister does not mind me doing so. I have listened carefully to the technicalities of what she has so far discussed and, as far as I am aware, she has not reiterated the fundamental importance of a police helicopter for the county of Wiltshire, which is a large rural county with access problems caused by road structures. In light of the intervention of my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1515" name="Geoffrey Clifton-Brown">the Member for Cotswold (Mr. Clifton-Brown)</phrase>, will she take this opportunity to reiterate to the House that the Government believe it is important that we in the county of Wiltshire&mdash; and the county of Wiltshire alone&mdash;should have the use of a police helicopter for the foreseeable future?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.308.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1605" speakername="Meg Hillier" colnum="308"  time="016:15:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0009.htm#08060495000545">
	<p pid="a.308.0/1">I am aware that in different local areas there have been discussions about the benefits of sharing helicopters across areas. I recognise that Wiltshire's size and the fact that it is a largely rural area means that it would certainly benefit from a helicopter, but it is up to the local police authorities and chief constables to determine local needs. As I have said, the public in Wiltshire clearly support the project&mdash;not just in principle but in financial terms.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.308.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1926" speakername="James Gray" colnum="308"  time="016:15:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0009.htm#08060495000546">
	<p pid="a.308.1/1">I quite understand that the Minister is saying it is a matter for the chief constable. If the chief constable of Wiltshire were to conclude that it is clear that we must have a police helicopter for Wiltshire alone and that the helicopter should not be used outside the borders of the county of Wiltshire, would Her Majesty's Government support the chief constable in that conclusion?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.308.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1605" speakername="Meg Hillier" colnum="308"  time="016:15:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0009.htm#08060495000547">
	<p pid="a.308.2/1">It would be open to the chief constable, as it is already, to fund the helicopter, to apply at different times to the Home Office for support if a new helicopter needed to be procured at any point and to apply for a share of the capital funding that the Home Office puts into new helicopter equipment. However, it would still be a matter for police authorities and chief constables locally to determine whether it might sometimes be beneficial to stray slightly over the Wiltshire border and engage in joint work across two police authority areas. That would be a matter for local determination.</p>
	<p pid="a.308.2/2">There seems to be a well established tradition in Wiltshire that there is not just a long-established police helicopter, but long-established and far-sighted co-operation between services, which has served the people of Wiltshire well. That record speaks for itself. It is important that we allow local policing priorities to determine the matter. I am sure that the hon. Gentleman would object if I were to come in from the Home Office and direct local police authorities and chief constables to do something that he might interpret as not so beneficial to his area. It is important that local chief constables and police authorities make those decisions. I have no doubt that hon. Members in the Chamber and elsewhere will use their influence to shape those decisions, as this debate has effectively done.</p>
	<p pid="a.308.2/3">The service is an example of far-sighted, good practice. There are issues under negotiation that are not the direct locus of the Home Office or the Department of Health. Points on the matter have been well made and anyone involved in the discussions will be clear about the support of hon. Members for the continuance of co-operation between the health emergency helicopter and the police helicopter.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.309.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="309"  time="016:15:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0009.htm#08060495000005">
	Shrewsbury Sixth Form College
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.309.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1817" speakername="Daniel Kawczynski" colnum="309"  time="016:29:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0009.htm#08060495000548">
	<p pid="a.309.1/1">This is a subject that I feel passionately about. The college is a major centre for learning in my constituency, and during the next 15 minutes I have a tremendous opportunity to share some of our experiences of co-location with the Minister and to ask for clarification on certain elements of Government policy.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/2">I start by stating my admiration for the teachers, lecturers and staff of the sixth-form college, who do a tremendous job&mdash;I am always in awe of what they achieve. The Minister will know of the tremendous results of the college's pupils. That is primarily down to the professionalism and hard work not only of the teaching staff but of the assistants, management and everyone involved. That is not the problem.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/3">There is no doubt that sixth-form colleges need investment. I was taken around the sixth-form college by Mr. Robert Bland, one of the governors, and I was shown the dilapidated state of some of the rooms. I have no doubt that both colleges in Shrewsbury&mdash;the sixth-form college and Shrewsbury college of art and technology&mdash;need significant investment.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/4">Funding comes from the Learning and Skills Council. The LSC will allow a community such as mine to apply for funding for only one project at a time, and there is no alternative to that. In our case, the principals have decided to go ahead with a co-location proposal to scrap the Shrewsbury sixth-form college in the town centre and co-locate that college with another&mdash;Shrewsbury college of art and technology&mdash;in London road.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/5">That is the proposal, and the LSC has told our community that it can have &pound;30 million if we co-locate both colleges on London road, which the principals of both colleges want. However, there is no alternative for the community; there is no alternative for me; there is no alternative for the council; and there is no alternative for the thousands of my constituents who object to co-location in London road, which is in a highly residential area of Shrewsbury.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/6">If the proposal does not secure planning permission, the governing bodies will have to go back to the drawing board. It is much better always to have a back-up plan when trying to secure such an investment, rather than putting all one's eggs in one basket&mdash;co-location or nothing&mdash;and then having to go back to the drawing board and start discussions all over again.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/7">I disagree with co-location on London road, because it is a highly residential part of the community and it will pull the students away from the town centre, where they have become are an integral part of its life and character. My hair is going grey as a result of the controversy; over the last year, I have had to grapple with this issue more than any other. There is huge dissatisfaction among the teachers at the sixth-form college, who are not convinced by the educational case for co-location.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/8">My first question to the Minister is this. What is Government policy on co-location? Is it something that the Government want? Do they want to see colleges co-locating? Is there an educational case for co-location? Ninety-three per cent. of the teachers at the sixth-form college have written to me stating that they do not want co-location. They want independence; they want to be able to carry on as they have done for generations past and make a tremendous success of it. What is Government policy on co-location?</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/9">I want to share with the Minister the problems that the community has had in that regard. For the benefit of this debate, I shall mention the three most important people involved in the project. I shall read statements from a Shrewsbury resident who is a parent of three school-age children, a governor who was forced to resign from the sixth-form college over the issue and a lecturer at the sixth-form college.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/10">The parent states that</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/11" class="indent">&quot;the professional bodies the Highways Agency and the Commission for Architecture and the Built Environment have issued numerous and wide-ranging criticisms of the co-location plans (HA issued a TR110 directing that planning permission not be granted until all the HA's concerns have been addressed and CABE rated the plan's environmental strategies as 'poor', the lowest possible rating).&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/12">I was so concerned about the views of the Highways Agency that I held a public meeting, attended by more than 150 members of the public. The agency has stated on record that it has serious concerns about the prospect of the co-location going ahead in London road, because that would have major ramifications for the A5 and Emstrey island, for which it is responsible. Do the Government share my concerns? I ask the Minister for a guarantee that such a project cannot go ahead as long as the Highways Agency continues to have those professional concerns.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/13">The parent goes on to say:</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/14" class="indent">&quot;Despite all this, the principals continue to attempt to force their project through. At times there has been scant regard for free speech and democracy (SSFC Code of Conduct issued Nov 07 prohibiting staff from speaking to the media without the Principal's permission), and undue pressure has been brought to bear on individuals, including yourself, (you'll remember the co-location meeting minutes of late Jan 08 which said 'MP will be placed under pressure at appropriate points to curb his random tendencies').&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/15">Those are the minutes of the meeting of the governors of the sixth-form college. They were leaked and given to my office. I am extremely concerned that the governors and principal of the sixth-form college have tried to stifle debate among teachers at the college who object to the proposals.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/16">I come now to the governor of the college who was forced to resign, for whom I have great admiration, Mr. David Holmes, who is head of civil engineering for a major British company. He was forced to resign because he objected to the proposals. He had the temerity to write to my borough council and say that he did not think that the plans were right and that, as a resident, he wanted to voice his concerns. He said that he very much hoped that planning permission would not be given for the project to go ahead. He made the mistake of saying in his letter of objection to the council that he was a governor of the college, and he was forced to resign. Is the Minister happy for governors of colleges to be forced to resign if they object to planning applications?</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/17">Mr. Holmes says:</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/18" class="indent">&quot;I was requested to resign by Philip Morris (clerk) and he told me that this was as a result of a meeting between Bill Dowell&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/19">the principal&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/20" class="indent">&quot;and Robert Bland (chair). I assumed that this had been with broad support of other governors but I subsequently learned that they had not been consulted at all. This is another example of the unassailable power base of the principal&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/21">Mr. Holmes says:</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/22" class="indent">&quot;There are 16 governors...2 are elected by parents, 2 by staff, 2 by students and 2 are councillors and so have some accountability through the ballot box. This means that 50 per cent. are not elected in any fashion.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/23">I am very concerned about that. What plans does the Minister have to make governors of important learning institutions, such as that sixth-form college, more accountable to the people whom they purport to represent, such as students, teachers, the MP and the local community? It is of great concern to me that so many of the governors are appointed rather than being directly elected to their posts.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/24">Mr. Holmes says:</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/25" class="indent">&quot;There is no means of holding the governors to account in any meaningful fashion. They do not answer to a single electorate. Parents, for example, can only elect 2 out of 16, a very small proportion&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/26">He says that the principal told him that there were &quot;high levels of accountability&quot;. He says:</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/27" class="indent">&quot;When I asked him who could hold the governors to account he could only come up with the LSC&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/28">Of course the principal says that the governors can be held to account by people going to the LSC, but if someone goes to the LSC, it says, &quot;No, we can't hold the governors to account. You have to go to the governors.&quot; That is ludicrous. It allows the whole governing body to be totally unaccountable.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/29">Mr. Holmes goes on to say:</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/30" class="indent">&quot;The introductory documentation (emailed to you on <phrase class="date" code="2008-05-13">13 May</phrase>) for a person seeking to be an elected parent governor is now intimidating and virtually demands a person who is willing to accept and support all governor decisions without question. Dissent and debate do not appear encouraged. This stifles any fresh thinking.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/31">I am trying to speak in a non-partisan way. I would like clarification from the Minister on those points. I am deeply concerned about the lack of accountability in the governors and the principal, and the fact that everything is somehow falling through that lack of accountability.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/32">Many of the teachers at the sixth-form college feel extremely intimidated if they say anything against the proposals. I have had some 14 meetings with teachers from the college. They have come to see me here at the House of Commons, and I have gone to see them. They are desperately concerned about what is happening. One of the lecturers&mdash;of course, I will not reveal her name&mdash;put the following questions directly to the Minister:</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/33" class="indent">&quot;Staff at SSFC met with Bill Rammell in summer of 2007&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/34">a meeting that I organised for them&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/35" class="indent">&quot;who advised them to continue talking to their governors. This was not facilitated by governors and ultimately led to staff passing an overwhelming vote of no confidence in their governors.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/36" class="indent">In the light of advice from John Denham's office that staff should speak to their governors following an overwhelming vote of no confidence in them, what is the response to the fact that these same governors have now refused to engage in direct communication with staff on urgent and pressing issues?&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/37">The Department has told teachers that they must go and speak to the governors if they have a concern, but the governors have made it quite clear that they are not prepared to talk to the teachers.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/38" class="indent">&quot;Those staff who feel compelled to voice their opinions have been and continue to be threatened by disciplinary action; is it acceptable that this situation exists and how does this best serve the interests of democracy?&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/39">We all came into politics for different reasons. I came into politics because of an insatiable belief and interest in democracy, and I will stand up for the interests of every constituent of mine and their right to object to things that affect their daily or professional life in any way they like without threat of intimidation. I am extremely concerned that the trade unions representing those lecturers have not done more to make the management of the college realise that they cannot treat professional lecturers in that way. If we are to make co-location a success, those lecturers are the most vital ingredient.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/40">The lecturer concluded:</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/41" class="indent">&quot;Why, if the college is so committed to this project on the overwhelming grounds of the 'educational case', have the directors been unable to convince the college staff of the validity of their educational case?&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/42">Those are the points that have been made, and I shall conclude with a few brief remarks. I feel strongly that we need investment for our two colleges in Shrewsbury, but I hope that the Minister will tell me a few facts about the future of the LSC. I have had run-ins on the issue with the LSC chief executive, who came to see me at the House to discuss my concerns. I know that the LSC will be reformed; perhaps the Minister can tell me something about that. I am greatly concerned that Government are giving such autonomy and power to quangos such as the LSC, which make decisions from very far away without knowing the problems of the geography of places such as Shrewsbury, the feelings of my community&mdash;the community is overwhelmingly opposed to the move&mdash;or the principals, lecturers, teachers, parents and staff, who are also overwhelmingly opposed to co-location. I need an assurance that the Minister will take a personal interest in all the professional problems that the teachers have experienced.</p>
	<p pid="a.309.1/43">My final plea is given everything that I have said, will he at least consider meeting teachers at the sixth-form college to hear their concerns at first hand, because they can put their case far better than me? I could also arrange for them to visit the House of Commons. Furthermore, will he take on board my concerns about the way in which the LSC has put my community in a straitjacket by saying, &quot;You can have &pound;30 million, if you co-locate your colleges in London road, or you have to go back to the drawing board.&quot;? That is not acceptable. My constituents and I want funding and investment for both colleges at their existing, separate sites.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.312.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1882" speakername="David Lammy" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Innovation, Universities and Skills"  colnum="312"  time="016:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0010.htm#08060495000549">
	<p pid="a.312.0/1">I thank <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1817" name="Daniel Kawczynski">the hon. Member for Shrewsbury and Atcham (Daniel Kawczynski)</phrase> for raising this issue and for the close interest that he of course takes in the future of Shrewsbury sixth form college. As he indicated, he has raised the issue on a number of occasions, and has met my hon. Friend the Minister for Lifelong Learning, Further and Higher Education. The hon. Gentleman has also held a number of meetings&mdash;14, I think&mdash;in his constituency and has written to the Department for Innovation, Universities and Skills on a number of occasions. We have been willing and keen to continue to discuss what are very local issues in his part of the world.</p>
	<p pid="a.312.0/2">We both ultimately have the same aim: to secure the best possible educational provision for the young people of Shrewsbury and the surrounding area. Shrewsbury sixth form college is a good college, according to the latest Ofsted report published in May. However, it recommends that the college should</p>
	<p pid="a.312.0/3" class="indent">&quot;address unsatisfactory aspects of accommodation and social space&quot;,</p>
	<p pid="a.312.0/4">which was also recommended in its previous Ofsted report, in 2004, prompting the college to look at options for redevelopment. The Government are undertaking a massive capital investment programme to ensure that colleges such as the one in Shrewsbury have world-class buildings and facilities. Hundreds of thousands of learners in communities throughout England have benefited from colleges taking up the opportunity given by our investment. The planned capital investment in the Shrewsbury colleges will total approximately &pound;65 million, to provide fantastic resources for the young people in the area.</p>
	<p pid="a.312.0/5">In 1997, there was no dedicated capital budget for further education colleges. Over the past 10 years, the Government have invested more than &pound;2 billion ensuring that learners have access to the state of the art buildings and facilities that are essential if we are to meet the skills needs of local communities and young people. As set out in our capital strategy document, &quot;Building Colleges for the Future&quot;, a further &pound;2.3 billion will be invested in the estate over the next three years. That investment will benefit generations of learners to come, meet the skills needs of employers and act as a catalyst for community regeneration.</p>
	<p pid="a.312.0/6">Capital investment plays a crucial role in the Government's implementation of their priorities for young people and adults, as set out in the 14 to 19 reform programme and our response to the Leitch review of skills in England. Capital grants for sixth form colleges are managed by the Learning and Skills Council. Following machinery of Government changes, we announced our intention to bring sixth form colleges within the scope of the &quot;Building Schools for the Future&quot; strategy document, from 2010-11, so that they can be part of the area-wide entitlement to 14 to 19 provision. We will ensure that our capital investment coheres to support sixth form colleges in the new system.</p>
	<p pid="a.312.0/7">Modernisation of the college estate is not just about bricks and mortar. It is about creating the best possible learning environments accessible to all learners, and ensuring that young people are excited by learning so that they stay on in education and training. It is about delivering greater specialisation, so that businesses have access to a wider range of industry-specific skills development opportunities for their current and future employees, and about creating community-owned facilities that meet local needs and that can provide an important kick-start for local regeneration. Ensuring that such facilities are accessible to those who most need them is obviously critical, and it is absolutely necessary if we are to maximise the public benefit of the investment that we are making.</p>
	<p pid="a.312.0/8">Our investment will result in cutting-edge facilities and ensure that our work force have the skills that they need to succeed in a rapidly changing world. The Learning and Skills Council will expect all contractors that access public funding to have in place a formal training plan that maximises access to apprenticeships and work-based learning and training opportunities.</p>
	<p pid="a.312.0/9">Although we are making significant progress towards modernising our further education estate, we must not do so at the expense of the environment. We will require all new projects to meet the highest building standards for sustainable design and we have a taskforce in place to advise on how to ensure that by 2016 all new buildings will be zero carbon&mdash;two years ahead of the Government target for public sector buildings that was announced in the Budget.</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.314.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1817" speakername="Daniel Kawczynski" colnum="314"  time="016:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0010.htm#08060495000550">
	<p pid="a.314.0/1">I am following keenly what the Minister is saying about the environment, but it would be bad for the environment to co-locate colleges outside the town centre, where they would not be close to the railway station. We will have to provide many new buses to transport students from the railway station to a co-located site on the periphery of Shrewsbury. That is not joined-up government. With all respect, I am pleased that the Government are offering vital investment for co-location, but why co-locate? Why can the colleges not have money for their existing separate sites?</p>
</speech>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-04a.314.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1882" speakername="David Lammy" colnum="314"  time="016:45:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080604/halltext/80604h0010.htm#08060495000551">
	<p pid="a.314.1/1">I was about to come to that point. The Government's capital investment programme is providing Shrewsbury sixth form college with the opportunity to redevelop its estate to ensure that learners have the best possible facilities in which to learn.</p>
	<p pid="a.314.1/2">The educational and business cases for co-location are strong. Sharing facilities at the new site will allow learners to access world-class facilities and a broader curriculum offer than they could by staying on the current site. The plans have the support of the local strategic 14 to 19 partnership for education and training, the local education authority and the local learning and skills council. The building design has been developed so that colleges retain their separate identities. They will share the building but have separate governance and management. Separate teaching and learning areas will exist for each college. The premises costs will decrease substantially owing to the modern, efficient design of the new campus.</p>
	<p pid="a.314.1/3">The hon. Gentleman asked about local decision making and the accountability of governors. I should make it clear that the redevelopment of the college is ultimately a matter for local decision and for the governing body of the college as an independent institution. Such autonomy is important if we are to have a strong further education sector that can shape its own future in response to the needs of learners and employers. It would be wrong and inappropriate for a Minister to intervene directly&mdash;I am actually prohibited from doing so by legislation.</p>
	<p pid="a.314.1/4">To respond specifically to the hon. Gentleman's points about the governing body, we must remember that the decisions of a governing body are corporate decisions. From the correspondence between the hon. Gentleman and the Department, it is clear that the parent governor who resigned because of his opposition to the proposals was aware of the corporate nature of the decision-making process. Having decided to oppose publicly the decision to relocate the college, which he was entitled to do, it is understandable that the corporation felt that his position as a parent governor was untenable. The governor could not be forced to resign outside the corporation's procedures, but I understand that he was asked to resign and did so.</p>
	<p pid="a.314.1/5">Governing bodies do important work. The governance of Shrewsbury sixth form college is regarded by Ofsted as a key strength. Independent inspectors found that the college had a strong governing body. My Department has an ongoing programme of work with the sector and the Association of Colleges to ensure that governance arrangements for all further education colleges are strong and that governing bodies are accountable to the communities they serve.</p>
	<p pid="a.314.1/6">On the process for capital applications, it is crucial that any investment plans by colleges underpin their core mission of providing high-quality learning opportunities while responding to the diversity of their local communities. That means that a college must engage with all sections of the community when starting to plan any redevelopment project, to take into account the needs of the population it serves.</p>
	<p pid="a.314.1/7">In order to be considered for public funding support, colleges are required by the Learning and Skills Council to demonstrate that their proposals will serve the educational needs of people in their local area. It is certainly not a policy of the Government or the LSC actively to encourage co-location. Indeed, the Government's plans for transforming education for 14 to 19-year-olds include a rich choice of learning opportunities.</p>
	<p pid="a.314.1/8">The LSC expects a college to put forward the strongest educational case for a capital project based on a comprehensive options appraisal and a feasibility study. It would not make sense for the LSC to make a decision for the governing body about which of its options is the most appropriate. Once the college has submitted its capital proposal to the LSC, it has to go through a robust, multi-stage process in which the educational and business cases are scrutinised. Listening to the views of those who will be affected by the proposals is an important part of that process and is required before planning permission can be granted. We are in that stage now.</p>
	<p pid="a.314.1/9">Looking in more detail at the situation for Shrewsbury sixth form college, in 2004, the LSC commissioned a review of infrastructure in the area, which concluded that a significant amount of Shrewsbury sixth form college's accommodation was no longer fit for purpose and that the estates do not lend themselves to the kind of flexibility needed for the modern curriculum encapsulated in the Government's 14 to 19 reforms.</p>
	<p pid="a.314.1/10">I understand that the site has many listed buildings. Much of the Shrewsbury sixth form college estate is subject to planning restrictions, and large areas of both Shrewsbury sixth form college and Shrewsbury college of arts and technology cannot be made compliant with the Disability Discrimination Acts. Shrewsbury sixth form college and Shrewsbury college of arts and technology commissioned separate property strategies in 2004 to inform them how best to address the issues. The property strategies examined a number of alternatives, including redevelopment of the existing college sites, relocation to alternative sites and co-location of both colleges on a single site.</p>
	<p pid="a.314.1/11">After carefully weighing up the pros and cons of each option, the college governing body decided on co-location, because it presents the best opportunities for the college's future development. Towards the end of 2006, the development of the project was put on hold due to objections to relocation of the sixth form college from the town centre raised by the hon. Gentleman and a number of the sixth form college staff. A review of the project was then undertaken, in which all known or current town centre sites for co-location were re-examined and reconsidered in some detail. In view of the aspirations of the educational case and the existing estate issues, continuing on the present site and other alternatives were ruled out. Addressing the objections raised regarding the potential loss of the sixth form college's distinctiveness and the impact on the town centre and transport has been built into the project execution plan, which is now being implemented.</p>
	<p pid="a.314.1/12">I understand why the hon. Gentleman does not want to lose the college in his town centre, but after a lot of weighing up of the options, it has been decided to co-locate. In essence, the colleges will remain separate, but it is in the interests of young people in the area that co-location should go forward. That is the determination of the LSC and the governing bodies of the two organisations. The hon. Gentleman dissents from that, and he is entitled to do so, but it would be wrong for the Government to step in, to take sides and disrupt a local process, despite the understandable anxiety caused by changes in local circumstances.</p>
	<p pid="a.314.1/13" class="italic">It being Five o'clock, the motion for the Adjournment of the sitting lapsed, without Question put.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

