<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.437.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.437.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.437.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.437.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.437.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.437.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.437.2" nospeaker="true" colnum="437"  time="unknown" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h01.htm#50406h01_head1">
	<p pid=".437.2/1"><i>Motion made, and Question proposed</i>, That the sitting be now adjourned.&mdash;[<i>Mr. Jim Murphy</i>.]</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.437.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.437.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.437.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.437.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.437.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1271" speakername="David Taylor" colnum="437"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h01.htm#50406h01_spnew1">
	<p pid=".437.4/1">I do not want to anticipate the hon. Gentleman, but I wonder whether he would include in that list of examples the steady stream of families that return money that they are pretty certain they are not entitled to, only to be reassured that it is part of their entitlement&mdash;and then, to their chagrin, they are landed with an overpayment assessment at the end of the year. Such circumstances are pretty difficult to understand.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.438.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.438.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.439.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.439.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.439.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.439.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.439.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1280" speakername="John Thurso" colnum="439"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h01.htm#50406h01_spnew4">
	<p pid=".439.1/1">I agree with the hon. Gentleman. One of the things that strikes me most when comparing the social security system with the tax credit system is that in each case the social security system has a proper appeal procedure, ending in an almost judicial process, whereas there is no such process in the credit system. Each decision is entirely down to the choice of the particular official dealing with the case. It would be much more helpful if there were at least a proper set of guidelines or, at best, a formal system.</p>
	<p pid=".439.1/2">I asked the Minister another question. The Paymaster General referred to &quot;a small number of people&quot;, but what is a small number? If my case work is anything to go by, the number may be small to the Treasury, but not to those who are affected by it&mdash;in fact, the issue is the biggest in my case work. I have to deal with the full range of issues, right across the spectrum, as, I am sure, does every hon. Member. However, tax credits has more files than any other item. Why are the details not being kept? I have experience of being a non-executive director of a plc and if we behaved like that, we would be brought to book by the authorities, because we would be required to keep such details and information. At the very least, we would be lambasted by a consumer organisation, and no doubt the Government or this place would be seeking to legislate.</p>
	<p pid=".439.1/3">I shall refer to the three cases that I have chosen as examples. I shall not use the names of the constituents, because I have not had an opportunity to ask them about that, and it would not be fair to use their precise names. However, I am in correspondence with the Paymaster General in connection with all three cases, and would be happy to give the Minister the names afterwards if he so wished. I was going to call the cases Mr. and Mrs. S, and so forth, until I discovered that the first two surnames both began with S, so instead I shall refer to them as case A, and so on. I also thought of referring to them as Mr. and Mrs. Caithness, Mr. and Mrs. Sutherland, and Mr. and Mrs. Easter Ross, but I shall stick with case A.</p>
	<p pid=".439.1/4">In 2003, the husband was in work. The wife notified the Inland Revenue of her return to work following the birth of their baby. Both their P60s, and seven payslips for the two of them, were handed in to the Inland Revenue office. The wife's earnings were recorded but, unbeknown to the couple, the husband's earnings were deleted. The couple took on a new housing commitment: they bought a house, and took on a mortgage based on their income as calculated in light of the award. They did not enter into that commitment lightly, and it is not something that they could get out of lightly.</p>
	<p pid=".439.1/5">In 2004, the couple were told by the Inland Revenue that there had been an overpayment of &pound;2,444. The Revenue admits the error, but the Paymaster General told me in a letter of <phrase class="date" code="2005-03-10">10 March</phrase> that the Inland Revenue did not think that it was reasonable for the couple to believe that their award was correct when only one income was shown on the form. I have here the actual form from which it is supposed they should reasonably have deduced that there was a mistake. It has the wife's name quite clearly on one side, and underneath it says that she works 16 hours a week. The husband's name is underneath, and the form says that he works 40 hours a week. Under &quot;total income&quot; they have given the correct total for the two of them.</p>
	<p pid=".439.1/6">The form asks the couple to tell the Revenue if their annual income gets above a certain amount&mdash;and a figure of &pound;7,560 is given opposite the section filled in by &quot;Mrs. Sutherland&quot;&mdash;as they may receive too much tax credit and may be asked to pay back the amount awarded. There is nothing in the form or in its layout to suggest that that figure refers to the combined total of the two incomes, which is stated on the form and which is, in fact, correct. The couple were, in my view, reasonably entitled to feel that they had been given a correct award. As I said, they took on a mortgage as a result of that reward, and are now in severe difficulties in attempting to deal with the situation that has come about. I do not believe that the ordinary literate and numerate man or woman on the street can reasonably be expected to find their way around a system with that degree of complexity.</p>
	<p pid=".439.1/7">The second case is of a husband who was made redundant in 2003. He informed all the relevant authorities, and he received jobseeker's allowance and a tax credit award. In May 2004, he started a new job, and all the authorities were informed of the change of circumstances. A steady flow of letters arrived from the Inland Revenue&mdash;in fact, he received seven in one day. He came to a clinic that I held in a village hall near where he lives, and produced a paper bag, from which he tipped a phenomenal pile of papers. I thought that I had problems filling out and dealing with my own tax demand, but when I saw the sheer complexity of his case, I thought to myself, &quot;One would really need to employ an accountant to go through all of that.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".439.1/8">The situation went on from there. It culminated, on <phrase class="date" code="2004-09-21">21 September 2004</phrase>, with the couple receiving a demand for repayment of a child tax credit of &pound;2,248.71 and of a working tax credit of &pound;1,528.99. In a subsequent telephone call to the Inland Revenue, the couple were informed that the overpayment now stood at some &pound;3,800&mdash;nearly &pound;4,000&mdash;for the one tax credit, and at &pound;2,300 for the other. Again, the Paymaster General has received details of this case. The couple are still awaiting a full explanation and clarification of their position. Between <phrase class="date" code="2005-02-05">5 February</phrase> and <phrase class="date" code="2005-02-07">7 February</phrase> this year, the couple received a further nine different award notices from the Inland Revenue, and on <phrase class="date" code="2005-02-26">26 February</phrase> a further eight award notices were received. If the test is one of reasonableness, is it really reasonable that a constituent should be expected to deal with that volume of paperwork coming through their letterbox?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.441.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.441.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.441.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.441.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.441.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.441.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.442.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.442.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.442.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1280" speakername="John Thurso" colnum="442"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h01.htm#50406h01_spnew8">
	<p pid=".442.0/1">My hon. Friend has again put his finger on the button. Before I come to the third case, I should like to refer to what the ombudsman said to the Public Administration Committee on <phrase class="date" code="2004-12-02">2 December 2004</phrase>:</p>
	<p pid=".442.0/2" class="indent">&quot;If you have six different award notices and you have no real idea which of those, if any, is right, having a debate about whether you reasonably believed that that was the right figure is not helpful in those circumstances.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".442.0/3">There is a wide opinion, shared on both sides of the House and among professionals, that there is a very real problem that has to be dealt with.</p>
	<p pid=".442.0/4">I shall touch on the third case. It involves a couple, one of whom has knowledge of the tax credit calculations through his employment; he works in a citizen's advice office. At the end of November and the beginning of December 2003, he started to telephone the tax credit office to say that he believed that an error had been made in the calculation. No adjustment was made.</p>
	<p pid=".442.0/5">On <phrase class="date" code="2004-01-12">12 January 2004</phrase>, he confirmed in writing to the tax credit office his belief that the calculation had been wrongly made. He was particularly concerned not to build up overpayment, and he made five subsequent telephone calls. In the first, he was told that the case would be looked at. In the second, he was told not to worry, that the matter would be sorted out in April and that the Inland Revenue would treat it as a loan. In the third call, he asked whether he could repay by cheque, but was told that there was no facility to enable him to do that. The official responding to the fourth call said that there was no knowledge of any difficulties with the case at all. During his fifth call, made in April 2004, he was told by the Inland Revenue that it would now update its records.</p>
	<p pid=".442.0/6">It finally transpired that a zero had been mistakenly left off his recorded earnings. In August last year, the Revenue admitted that error, but informed my constituent that it did not think it reasonable for him to believe that his award was correct. In fact, he had spent five months asking the Revenue to check the calculation. Last month, he received notice of a new award and, at the same time, a demand for an overpayment of &pound;4,779.29.</p>
	<p pid=".442.0/7">I have given only three examples, but I suspect that all of them could be replicated in the casework of other Members here. The examples that I have given represent only the tip of the iceberg of what I have in my office; some 25 or 30 other cases are currently under way, and they have three things in common. First, the claimants did everything by the book. Secondly, the error, whether human or computer, was with the Revenue and thirdly, the resulting stress and hardship has achieved the diametric opposite of the intention of the policy.</p>
	<p pid=".442.0/8">The Minister might wish to tell me how many of my constituents have benefited from the policy; I am happy to accept that and will not dispute it. He can, if he wants to, blame it all on the claimants. However, because I suspect that he is in politics for pretty much the same reason that I am&mdash;to help those who need it most&mdash;he could accept that there is a real problem causing genuine hardship for a small but significant number of our citizens, and could use the power of his office to deal with it.</p>
	<p pid=".442.0/9">The test is reasonableness. Is it reasonable to award desperate and hard-up families life-giving succour one day, only brusquely to withdraw it at a later stage&mdash;so increasing their difficulties&mdash;all through administrative incompetence? Is it reasonable to issue forms so complex that trained accountants and the Revenue's own staff have difficulty dealing with them, and is it reasonable to operate a system with a fault level that would not be tolerated in any other organisation? I would say no to all three of those questions; it is not reasonable.</p>
	<p pid=".442.0/10">I end with the case of a young mother who was so desperate because of the circumstances that she found herself in that my office staff feared for her life. Finally, in desperation, they phoned the officials involved to say that that was their belief. The hotline responded magnificently; emergency aid was given and all was well in that case. However, I wonder how long it will be before somebody in such desperate circumstances does resort to desperate measures. I hope that the Minister, having heard the cases that I have described and the examples given by other hon. Members, will realise that the problem may be small, but it is very significant for those whom it affects. Please will he think about what can be done to put right the appalling problem of overpayments and seriously consider waiving the payments in those cases in which the fault is clearly not on the part of the claimant, but has arisen from an error in the system, be it human or computer.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.443.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.443.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.444.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.444.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.444.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1271" speakername="David Taylor" colnum="444"  time="009:58:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h01.htm#50406h01_spnew10">
	<p pid=".444.0/1">Does my hon. Friend agree, as I do, with <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1280" name="John Thurso">the hon. Member for Caithness, Sutherland and Easter Ross (John Thurso)</phrase> that the staff who support the MPs' hotline are top quality people with good communication skills who deal with these issues in an accurate way? Is it not a pity that those characteristics are not more widely shared among the operational staff in the Inland Revenue?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.444.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.444.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.444.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1003" speakername="Kevan Jones" colnum="444"  time="009:58:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h01.htm#50406h01_spnew11">
	<p pid=".444.1/1">I do, but it is sad that constituents have to come to their MPs to get an answer to these problems. When they ring the Inland Revenue they do not get the same service as we get, which is not right. They should be able to get answers to their questions and be dealt with properly. I shall give examples of people who are still waiting for replies to letters several months down the line.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/2">The hotline has been useful, but both the Inland Revenue and the Department are not very good at replying to Members' letters about these cases. It makes it difficult for MPs because, as the hon. Member for Caithness, Sutherland and Easter Ross said a few minutes ago, we are dealing with people who want help. They cannot wait for two or three weeks. I have an abhorrence of debt, which is shared by most people in working-class communities. It is wrong that such people, through no fault of their own, end up thinking that they owe the system money. I shall make a suggestion in a minute: the Minister might find it controversial, but it needs to be considered.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/3">I want to focus on four cases, which touch on similar issues to those raised by the hon. Member for Caithness, Sutherland and Easter Ross. I also want to describe how these people have been treated by the system before my office became involved. The first case is that of Mark McGough and Victoria Kerry of Catchgate. They contacted me in December 2004 when their payments suddenly stopped without explanation. They contacted the tax credit office, which told them that it was because there had been an overpayment. On further inspection the tax credit office explained that the overpayment had occurred because the calculation assumed that Mr. McGough and Miss Kerry had no income. That was totally incorrect, as they were both in work.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/4">Their award notice clearly stated their correct income and so they assumed that the tax credit that they were receiving was correct. The information on that form was used by the tax credit office to calculate their tax credit. A mistake was made by the Inland Revenue and my constituents were not responsible for the overpayment. It could be argued that they should have raised the matter. But how could they? The notice they received was correct and stated their correct income.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/5">I am pursuing this case because I believe that in such cases the money should be written off. My constituents were in no position to suggest that their payments were incorrect. The people who I have been dealing with are simple, hard-working and honest individuals. They have been honest with the Inland Revenue in terms of providing information. They have not tried to manipulate or hoodwink the system. They have been open and honest and have got into these situations through no fault of their own.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/6">The second case is that of Mr. and Mrs. Hall of West Pelton. They have had a difficult time with the tax credit office. They originally contacted me in July 2004. They had received numerous conflicting claim notices, which led on two or three occasions to the withdrawal of credits with no explanation. I asked the tax credit office to investigate and in August I received a reply, stating that everything had been resolved, and that the Halls would receive regular payments from then on. However, there was no explanation of the mistaken stopping of the other payments. All that was said was that&mdash;I hate this explanation, as I did when I was in local government&mdash;the system had a failure in it. That is not acceptable. I want to know the reasons for the payments being stopped, and I think that the people concerned deserve to know them.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/7">That state of affairs continued until December and January, when the Halls suddenly received an overpayment notice, although they had been receiving regular payments for the previous six months. The tax credit office appears confused about how that happened. It is another instance in which Mr. and Mrs. Hall have been entirely honest and up-front, and have provided the system with all the relevant information, but have been given no explanation for the overpayment. That is another matter that I am still pursuing by letter, although I have yet to receive a reply.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/8">The next case that I want to mention concerns Miss Julie Simm, of Perkinsville in my constituency, who contacted me to say that the tax credit office said that she had been overpaid. She had supplied all the correct information about her income and her partner's income, and therefore could not understand why she had been told that an overpayment had been made. Again, the cause was error on the part of the tax credit office.The remarkable thing about the case is that, before Miss Simms received the notice, she realised that she was being overpaid and contacted the tax credit office to inform it of that. Nothing was done; it took 42 days to reduce the payments, so an overpayment was accrued.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/9">I wrote to the Paymaster General on <phrase class="date" code="2005-01-19">19 January</phrase> and received a reply last week, which is, I think, unacceptable. Her letter really just supported the system, stating, in effect&mdash;this is the traditional response from the tax credit office&mdash;&quot;Yes, we did make a mistake, but you should have noticed it, so it is not now our fault.&quot; Well, my constituent recognised the mistake and told the tax credit office, which did nothing about it.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/10">She thus accrued an overpayment, whereas if the office had acted when she contacted it she would not have done. I do not think that she should have to pay the overpayment, just because of the inefficiency of that office. I have written to my hon. Friend the Economic Secretary and look forward to a reply&mdash;which I doubt will arrive this side of the election, but may possibly come later in the year.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/11">The next case I want to mention concerns Mr. and Mrs. Armstrong, of the Gardens, Chester-le-Street, and it is another extraordinary one. The couple have been honest with the Inland Revenue; they received their regular payments, and realised that in one month they received two payments. They contacted the tax office and said that they thought that they had been paid twice. Mrs. Armstrong was told that the two payments were correct, because of an underpayment earlier in the year owing to the birth of their fourth child.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/12">Mrs. Armstrong accepted that explanation and used the money in good faith as part of the family budget, as, I think, anyone else would in the circumstances. Subsequently, the tax credit office contacted the couple to say that there had been an error and, therefore, an overpayment. It had sent an overpayment notice, telling them to pay the money back. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/765" name="John Burnett">The hon. Member for Torridge and West Devon (Mr. Burnett)</phrase> raised the issue of professional advice; Mr. and Mrs. Armstrong obtained such advice from Hazel Tindale of Book Keeping Services Ltd., who acted on their behalf. She wrote on <phrase class="date" code="2004-08-20">20 August 2004</phrase> and, lo and behold, is still waiting for a reply to her letter. So the Inland Revenue still ignores individuals, even when they contact professional services.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/13">The Armstrongs appealed, but their appeal was rejected because, as the tax credit office said in its letter,</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/14" class="indent">&quot;We have decided that the overpayment was not due to a mistake on our part&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/15">That is unacceptable, particularly as the tax credit office admitted to the Armstrongs in the same letter that they were paid twice. Clearly this was the tax credit office's mistake. Mrs. Armstrong told the tax credit office that she believed that she was not entitled to the money, so I do not know how it can reject her appeal.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/16">I wrote to the Inland Revenue in October 2004 and again received a letter in December&mdash;two months later&mdash;from Barrie Rushton, the assistant director of customer relations at the tax credit office, who promised to have the case reviewed. However, the overpayments team refused to review the case when he referred it to them, reiterating the point that was made earlier.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/17">Despite several phone calls from my office to the MPs' hotline to try to secure a review of the case, the tax credit office continues to say that the overpayment is the Armstrongs' responsibility, and continues to reduce their monthly payments to recoup the money. As I said, the Armstrongs did everything in their power to tell the Inland Revenue that they thought that they had been overpaid, so I repeat that the money should simply be written off in such cases.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/18">I said at the beginning that I am proud of the tax credit. I suppose that I am because it has genuinely helped many poor and hard-working families in my constituency. These cases discredit the system, even if they are in the minority, although I have lost count of the number of cases that I have in my office. I strongly suggest to my hon. Friend the Minister that we write off the money in cases where people have been totally honest and up front and have given all the information to the Inland Revenue that it requires. Overpayments have been made through no fault of their own. If we do not write this money off for these people, they will have the hardship of having their monthly incomes substantially reduced to recoup the overpayments.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/19">As I said, these people have already suffered a great deal of heartache and frustration. They have had to ring the Inland Revenue constantly and have sometimes had to employ people to do that on their behalf, but they have got nowhere and have simply been sent around the system. It always makes me angry when one gets sent round the system time and time again.</p>
	<p pid=".444.1/20">I urge the Minister to resolve these issues, otherwise a flagship policy will be dented and people will continue to suffer hardships through no fault of their own.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.447.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.447.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.447.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.447.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.447.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1058" speakername="Peter Luff" colnum="447"  time="010:13:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h01.htm#50406h01_spnew13">
	<p pid=".447.1/1">I have consulted my right hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1344" name="George Young">the Member for North-West Hampshire (Sir George Young)</phrase>, and I believe that only two Back-Bencher speeches remain to be made. We have agreed how much time he needs, so I hope that I comply with his requests and his needs.</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/2">I genuinely wish to congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1280" name="John Thurso">the hon. Member for Caithness, Sutherland and Easter Ross (John Thurso)</phrase> on securing this important debate and on the manner in which he introduced it. I express my appreciation for the remarks of <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1003" name="Kevan Jones">the hon. Member for North Durham (Mr. Jones)</phrase>. This is a matter of pressing importance to far too many hard-working, decent and honest families.</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/3">My wife is my constituency secretary, and hardly a day seems to go by without a telephone call from another family in desperate circumstances. It is interesting to note that so many of these cases are dealt with on the telephone because their sheer complexity is overwhelming. They would overwhelm me; I cannot cope with my tax return, and I certainly could not cope with the working families tax credit if it got into the sorts of difficulties that my constituents have so often experienced. It also takes a considerable amount of time to sort out these difficulties.</p>
	<p pid=".447.1/4">I do not know what the problem is, but I am more sceptical about the whole tax credit system than the hon. Member for North Durham. I am not sure whether the problem lies in inadequate systems, particularly in information technology, or in the poor training of staff. It has been suggested that it might simply be because the Inland Revenue is better at taking money from people than giving it away, and that it is &quot;a culture thing&quot;. That is quite a plausible explanation. Could it be that personal lifestyles are too complex to enable such a system to function at all? We have had problems like this in the past: there was a disability issue in my first Parliament&mdash;1992 to 1997&mdash;when I was overwhelmed by complaints about the way in which that system worked, but that could be sorted out because disability can be measured relatively objectively. We also wrestled to get the Child Support Agency right. The problem is that the sheer complexity of people's lifestyles cannot comply with carefully written statutory instruments, Government guidelines and codes of conduct.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.447.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.447.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.447.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.447.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.447.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1058" speakername="Peter Luff" colnum="447"  time="010:13:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h01.htm#50406h01_spnew15">
	<p pid=".447.3/1">As it happens, most of the cases that I wish to raise&mdash;coincidentally, like the past two speakers I also have four cases to discuss, if there is time&mdash;arise from simple maladministration by the Inland Revenue. I was very disappointed that the document, &quot;Tax credits: reforming financial support for families&quot;, which was published at the time of the Budget, appears to make no mention of the problems associated with the implementation of tax credits. It is a Panglossian document. Tax credits may have benefited many families, but they have brought nothing but heartache in these four cases.</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/2">In the first case, that of Julie Brown, there has been a phantom overpayment. She has not received an overpayment but the computer thinks that she has. The result is that she received no money at Christmas or Easter. It is an absolute scandal for the poor woman. We have spent so much time trying to sort out her case, but she is at her wits' end. We are told that another emergency payment has been sent to her, but she had not received it this morning. There is also the problem that emergency payments have to be repaid, which will further confuse the system. I desperately fear for the future of Julie Brown's case. We shall chase it up in three week's time. We have been advised to do so then because no giros can be issued for the next two weeks: apparently the computer is busy issuing new schedules of payment for the next tax year, so there is no prospect of any money for Julie Brown.</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/3">Although many members of the hotline staff are excellent, and tribute has been paid to them, we sometimes find it difficult to persuade some of them that they are dealing with real human beings who are in desperate financial circumstances. I am not surprised, as they must be a bit battle weary by now with all the cases that they have to handle&mdash;we all get case hardened&mdash;but one of them suggested that Mrs. Brown should go to the Worcester tax office to sort things out. She does not have the money to go to the Worcester tax office. She survived Easter with a &pound;10 note kept for emergencies, just in case. She could buy nothing else: no petrol, no bus fares and no train fares. It shows how out of touch some of those people are that someone should suggest that she should travel from her town to Worcester to try to get her justice, which she deserves. She has received no overpayment, but the computer still thinks that she has.</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/4">The next case that I want to raise is that of Mrs. Georgina Gadd, who has received an overpayment because of an unrecorded change of circumstances, which the Gadds desperately tried to tell the Inland Revenue about. In view of the time, I shall not weary the Chamber with the details of her case, but she has kept meticulous records since February 2003, when she first applied for tax credits. She quickly became aware that there was a mistake and on <phrase class="date" code="2003-06-25">25 June 2003</phrase> she called the Inland Revenue and expressed her greatest concern that she was receiving payments to which she was not entitled. Her notes state:</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/5" class="indent">&quot;I was then reassured that the payments I was receiving were correct and that I was fully entitled to the working tax credit. I was even told that quite a few people had contacted them thinking that the payments were too much but that it was a very good tax award for families with young children. I was told to expect a further tax form in the next few days.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/6">So a PR spin was put on what Mrs. Gadd knew was an overpayment. I have the details here: there was a succession of telephone calls, letters and formal complaints running through to <phrase class="date" code="2005-01-15">15 January 2005</phrase>. Mrs. Gadd's notes state that around that date she received a telephone call from the Inland Revenue apologising that she had not yet received a reply to a letter from September and that it was trying to sort out the complaint. The issue is to do with the nature of her husband's employment and earnings. The Inland Revenue also told her, &quot;Why don't you get in touch with your MP? If you get your MP involved, you might actually get it sorted out.&quot; That is why she wrote to me. In a letter to me she said&mdash;and I think that she is right:</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/7" class="indent">&quot;It would appear to me that the Inland Revenue are delaying replying to my letters and even ignoring some of my letters which enclosed bank statements&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/8">proving that she has spent the overpayment&mdash;</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/9" class="indent">&quot;until they have recouped the &pound;1000 overpayment despite the fact that according to their own code of practice, which they have admittedly failed to meet, and which I have proved to have made substantial effort to ensure that they held the correct information, they should look into waiving some if not all of this overpayment&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/10">That is the point that I want to make to the Minister. These people, who have striven to be honest with the Inland Revenue, deserve an amnesty. Mrs. Gadd points out that she has had no tax credit since June 2003. That is devastating for a family with one wage earner, a small baby and a two-year-old child.</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/11">A letter from another constituent arrived this morning. It is on a topical subject, but I do not have permission to name its author, so I will not do so. She is a single mother earning &pound;14,500 a year and she has two children, one at university and the other at sixth-form college. She is struggling to keep them in education, but she hopes to send her second child to university shortly. She has pointed out time and again that she is paying too much, and she wants to know how much she is overpaying so she can accurately budget for that, but the Inland Revenue will not tell her. Her letter states:</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/12" class="indent">&quot;I did receive a reply saying I would hear in 6 to 8 weeks, then a further letter telling me that the amount I was receiving was right, but I know fine well it's not because they still had all my details wrong and had me working for the NHS on &pound;10,384 which I was three years ago. I despair.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/13" class="indent">However, I have been onto them again after 4 hours of trying today, to be advised that their computer is not working correctly and that, although on every occasion I have advised them of my change in circumstances, my old details are stuck in their system and that the computer is not accepting my new details, so until the computer is fixed I will still be getting a payment of &pound;267 per month which I know is too much for one child. I am very worried about all this&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/14">Her letter concludes:</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/15" class="indent">&quot;I do hope you can help me. I am very worried about all this and could cry with frustration&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/16">I bet she could. She has tried in every way to get information from the Inland Revenue, and none of them has succeeded.</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/17">We have talked about cases of overpayment&mdash;a phantom overpayment, and two actual overpayments&mdash;where people have behaved with absolute honesty and integrity, and been determined to sort things out, but where they have not received the level of service from the Inland Revenue that they are entitled to expect. However, it is also important to remember that some people are not getting the money to which they are entitled. A constituency case of mine involving Sheila Christian Brookes highlights that we have worked hard on that, too. Many interventions and telephone calls have been made, and it was shown that she was owed substantial arrears:</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/18" class="indent">&quot;We were told on <phrase class="date" code="2005-03-10">10 March</phrase> that a giro was sent that day for &pound;1,577.31, and another for &pound;131.04&quot;,</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/19">but the cheques never arrived. Apparently, they were returned to the tax office for unknown reasons, and</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/20" class="indent">&quot;they can't try to re-issue the cheque as the computer is working on the new schedule of payments for the next two weeks and then there will be a backlog of cheques waiting to go out . . . and the Hotline assistant asks if we can remember to chase her again after two weeks!&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/21">What kind of level of service is that?</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/22">Although I am more sceptical about the whole tax credit system than the hon. Member for North Durham, I entirely agree that for many families it is working well and brings great benefits. However, I am desperately worried; these are four random cases, one of which happens to be in today's post. Along with civil service pensions, it is undoubtedly the biggest issue in my telephone call log&mdash;although not in my postbag as, typically, these cases are not made in writing. We must have a better system.</p>
	<p pid=".447.3/23">The Minister must not just boast about the families that are benefiting&mdash;although I am happy for him to do that, as an election is coming up, after all. He must also explain how the Inland Revenue will improve its systems, so that the decent, hard-working families that have been referred to today get the justice and the money to which we all believe they are entitled.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.450.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.450.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.451.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.451.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.453.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.453.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.453.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.453.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.453.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.453.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.453.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.453.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.453.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.453.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.456.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.456.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.456.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/949" speakername="John Healey" speakeroffice="The Economic Secretary to the Treasury"  colnum="456"  time="010:46:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h01.htm#50406h01_spmin0">
	<p pid=".456.0/1">I genuinely congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1280" name="John Thurso">the hon. Member for Caithness, Sutherland and Easter Ross (John Thurso)</phrase> on securing this debate and on the way in which he has consistently pursued questions on the tax credit system and problems, including overpayment, faced by his constituents. He introduced the debate in a measured way and set out genuine concerns about the administration of the system. I appreciate the tribute that he paid to those in the Inland Revenue who work on the MPs' hotline. I will pass his comments to them and know that they will be welcome, because those people try their best to help all hon. Members to sort out the problems that arise with our constituents.</p>
	<p pid=".456.0/2">I appreciate also the comments made by <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/765" name="John Burnett">the hon. Member for Torridge and West Devon (Mr. Burnett)</phrase> on the same subject. I pay tribute to his contribution to the proceedings of the House over the past eight years. I am sorry to see him go and will miss the debates that we have. I will also miss the combination of fair-mindedness and well-informed criticism that he always brings to bear on the scrutiny of the work of the Government and the Treasury.</p>
	<p pid=".456.0/3">As my right hon. Friend the Paymaster General has said consistently to all hon. Members who have contributed to this debate, I invite all of them, if they have not already done so, to let me have the specific details of the cases that they have raised this morning. I do not want to pick up on individual cases, but will respond to some of the points that have been made this morning.</p>
	<p pid=".456.0/4">On the point made by the hon. Member for Caithness, Sutherland and Easter Ross, cheques will be accepted by the Inland Revenue in cases of overpayment. In the very early months there were a few cases where that was not taking place, but that is not so now.</p>
	<p pid=".456.0/5">I say to my hon. Member for North Durham (Mr. Jones) that, in general terms, where a claimant is concerned that their payments are wrong and they are reassured by the tax credit office that they are correct, any subsequent overpayment should be remitted. We will go back and check such cases&mdash;we are doing so&mdash;including checking the tapes from telephone conversations that such claimants had with the Inland Revenue. Where claimants have been wrongly advised that their award is correct, I would expect any overpayment to be waived.</p>
	<p pid=".456.0/6">In respect of the point made by <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1058" name="Peter Luff">the hon. Member for Mid-Worcestershire (Mr. Luff)</phrase>, the Inland Revenue computer is being updated at the moment, as it normally is at the end of the financial year. However, payments can still be made.</p>
	<p pid=".456.0/7">It may help <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1344" name="George Young">the right hon. Member for North-West Hampshire (Sir George Young)</phrase> if I say that the Inland Revenue is simplifying the ways in which it handles claims regarding disputes on overpayments. I will say a little bit more about the new measures that are being put in place. In general, however, I say to all hon. Members, including the hon. Member for Mid-Worcestershire, that if they will give me specific case details that have not already been submitted to my right hon. Friend the Paymaster General, I shall ensure that they are carefully examined,, and undertake to check the progress that is being made.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.457.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.457.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.457.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.457.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.457.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.457.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.457.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.457.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.460.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.460.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.460.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.460.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.461.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.461.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.461.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.461.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.463.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.463.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.463.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1029" speakername="Stephen Ladyman" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Health"  colnum="463"  time="011:10:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h02.htm#50406h02_spmin0">
	<p pid=".463.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/787" name="William Cash">the hon. Member for Stone (Mr. Cash)</phrase> on taking up this issue on behalf of his constituent, and express my great sadness on hearing the details of the case. I hope that he will pass on my sincere condolences to Benjamin Moston's family. This must be a very sad time for them and I am sure that they are devastated by what has happened, as the hon. Gentleman has said.</p>
	<p pid=".463.0/2">The incident has had a profound effect on the Staffordshire Ambulance Service NHS trust, which provides the out-of-hours service in the area. The chief executive of the trust has been to see Benjamin's parents; he has formally apologised on behalf of the local NHS and offered his personal condolences. The trust has been the highest performing ambulance trust in the country for many years, but we&mdash;and it&mdash;must recognise the importance of learning from such events.</p>
	<p pid=".463.0/3">The staff of the trust are hardworking and diligent, but they would be the first to say that they owe it to Benjamin and his family to use this experience to do even better in the future and, if it emerges that their performance was less than optimal on this occasion, to do everything in their power never to let the same thing happen again. But I stress the &quot;if&quot;; the only way to find out whether their performance was less than optimal is to carry out an inquiry and face the issues honestly, and such an inquiry has not yet been carried out. Until it is, we should not speculate about where fault may lie but should stick to discussing the facts as we know them. It would be inappropriate for me to discuss the details of Benjamin's illness at this time, but I can tell hon. Members what I know of the events following his parents' call to the out-of-hours service. What I am about to say is based on what I have been told by Shropshire and Staffordshire strategic health authority and, of course, it is subject to review in the inquiry that I will talk about later.</p>
	<p pid=".463.0/4">I am told that the call from Benjamin's parents to the    out-of-hours service, at 6.08 pm on <phrase class="date" code="2005-02-13">Sunday 13 February</phrase>, was handled by a paramedic call handler who made a clinical decision, based on the information available, that Benjamin should have a home visit within an hour of the end of the call, which was at 6.21 pm. That is covered in the ambulance service trust's internal investigation report, and it would not be appropriate for me to comment on that decision at this time. At 7.01 pm, Benjamin's parents, worried that Benjamin's condition had deteriorated, made an emergency 999 call, and a community paramedic officer was dispatched to the Mostons' home at 7.02 pm. The parents made a further emergency call at 7.18 pm to ask where the ambulance was. The paramedic arrived at about the same time as that second emergency call.</p>
	<p pid=".463.0/5">On arriving at the scene, the paramedic found that Benjamin was in cardio-respiratory arrest and requested that an ambulance be sent as quickly as possible. The ambulance was mobilised at 7.27 pm and arrived at 7.34 pm. The ambulance trust's doctor arrived at 7.35    pm. At 7.45 pm, Benjamin was taken to Staffordshire general hospital; he arrived at 8.08 pm. Sadly, as we know, he did not survive.</p>
	<p pid=".463.0/6">I should point out that a coroner's inquest into Benjamin's death has been launched and is currently adjourned. It would not be appropriate for me to comment on what its findings might be. However, I can reassure the hon. Gentleman and Benjamin's family that the local health community has taken this incident very seriously and absolutely understands the need to look into the matter with a view to avoiding similar incidents.</p>
	<p pid=".463.0/7">The hon. Gentleman will be aware that the ambulance trust immediately launched an internal inquiry into the circumstances surrounding the incident. The initial findings of the inquiry and the detailed action plan drawn up as a result have already been shared with the family. The investigation report will be tabled at the ambulance trust's risk and clinical governance committee, which reports to the trust board. The detailed action plan is already being implemented by the trust. The plan addresses areas such as staff training and the introduction of dual paging/SMS texting and clinical policies.</p>
	<p pid=".463.0/8">I can advise the hon. Gentleman that on <phrase class="date" code="2005-04-01">1 April</phrase> the trust moved to a single computer-aided dispatch system, which allows better control of the interface between the out-of-hours service and the emergency ambulance system. The strategic health authority, which is responsible for monitoring and improving the quality of health care in the area, has also commissioned an independent inquiry into the incident to determine any contributing factors and to recommend any actions that should be taken to prevent a similar occurrence.</p>
	<p pid=".463.0/9">The inquiry is being undertaken by Dr. Matthew Cooke, accident and emergency consultant at the Heart of England NHS foundation trust&mdash;formerly the Birmingham Heartlands and Solihull Hospitals NHS trust&mdash;and national A and E medical advisor, and Dr. Richard Fairhurst, medical director of Lancashire Ambulance Service NHS trust.</p>
	<p pid=".463.0/10">The inquiry is in two parts. The first will look at the out-of-hours service, which, although it is provided by Staffordshire Ambulance Service NHS trust, is in fact the responsibility of South Western Staffordshire primary care trust. The second will look at the response of the emergency ambulance service. It would not be appropriate for me to pre-empt the findings of the review, and the results will be presented to the boards of the PCT and ambulance trust in due course.</p>
	<p pid=".463.0/11">Both the ambulance trust and the PCT will respond to any further recommendations that come out of the inquiry. I am also requesting a copy of the report so that any wider issues to do with either out-of-hours or emergency services can be considered, and any lessons that can be applied nationally can be disseminated.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.465.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.465.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.465.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.465.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.465.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1029" speakername="Stephen Ladyman" colnum="465"  time="011:10:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h02.htm#50406h02_spnew2">
	<p pid=".465.1/1">Yes, I am happy to commit to that. If on receiving the report there are still outstanding questions, and those directly involved and in positions of authority&mdash;including the Minister who holds the appropriate portfolio after the election&mdash;believe that questions may still be unanswered, clearly we will have to commit to further inquiries. It may well be that the hon. Gentleman, if he is returned after <phrase class="date" code="2005-05-05">5 May</phrase>, will want to seek another Adjournment debate to discuss the matter in the Chamber. If I am still Minister after <phrase class="date" code="2005-05-05">5 May</phrase>, I will certainly be happy to meet him to discuss the findings of the report and how matters should best be moved forward, after we have the results of the inquiry.</p>
	<p pid=".465.1/2">I hope that the hon. Gentleman would agree that there is no cover-up and no lack of willingness on behalf of the trust, the local health authorities and the NHS to learn from events. In due course everyone will know exactly what happened and how such tragedies can best be avoided in the future.</p>
	<p pid=".465.1/3">The hon. Gentleman mentioned the policy on ambulance service and response. He and his constituents should be aware that there is substantial progress and high performance in their area. He mentioned the various categories of response; the NHS plan has an objective to improve ambulance response times so that 75 per cent. of 999 calls to life-threatening emergencies&mdash;the category A responses that he referred to&mdash;are responded to within eight minutes. The latest information for 2003&ndash;04 shows that 75.7 per cent. of category A calls in England resulted in an emergency response arriving at the scene of the incident within eight minutes, which was slightly up from the previous year's figure of 74.6 per cent. In Staffordshire, 86.6 per cent. of category A calls received a response within eight minutes in 2003&ndash;04.</p>
	<p pid=".465.1/4">Other emergency calls, category B and C calls, should receive a response within 19 minutes 95 per cent. of the time in rural areas such as Staffordshire.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.466.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.466.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.466.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.466.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.466.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.466.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.466.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/787" speakername="William Cash" colnum="466"  time="011:10:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h02.htm#50406h02_spnew5">
	<p pid=".466.2/1">Will the Minister take note of the allegations that I mentioned, which, as I stated, I cannot verify? In light of the fact that they appear to be related to what is going on before the Birmingham employment tribunal, which is a responsible tribunal, I hope that he will take note of the situation and consider also the allegation about deliberate reductions in emergency care resources. I am not in a position to verify that allegation either, but if there is a connection between the incident and the allegations, I am sure that the Minister will want to look into it.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.466.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.466.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.466.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.466.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.466.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/787" speakername="William Cash" colnum="466"  time="011:10:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h02.htm#50406h02_spnew7">
	<p pid=".466.4/1">Just to wind up, as it were, I am extremely glad to hear the Minister say that in light of the information made available to him and, indirectly, to me and other people in appropriate positions of responsibility, he will have a public inquiry should the circumstances warrant it. That is an important first step. We look forward to receiving the information that comes from the inquiries that have been set up.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.467.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.467.0" matchtype="multiplecover"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.467.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.467.1" matchtype="multiplecover"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.467.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1029" speakername="Stephen Ladyman" colnum="467"  time="011:10:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h02.htm#50406h02_spnew8">
	<p pid=".467.0/1">I very much hope that it will not be necessary to have any further inquiries because we get all the answers that we need from the inquiries that have been set up. I look forward to being in a position to discuss these issues with the hon. Gentleman after the events of the next four weeks.</p>
	<p pid=".467.0/2" class="italic">Sitting suspended until Two o'clock.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.468.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.468.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.468.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.468.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.468.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/836" speakername="Claire Curtis-Thomas" colnum="468"  time="014:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h03.htm#50406h03_spnew0">
	<p pid=".468.1/1">As a member of the Select Committee on Home Affairs, I regularly meet people who work in the criminal justice system, and I am pleased to have secured this debate because everyone I have spoken to in the probation service and the Prison Service has told me of their deep concerns about the structure and implementation of the National Offender Management Service.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/2">The concerns that I shall raise are similar to those discussed by my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1271" name="David Taylor">the Member for North-West Leicestershire (David Taylor)</phrase> and others in an Adjournment debate on <phrase class="date" code="2005-03-16">16 March</phrase>, but they were not adequately addressed because of time constraints, and I hope to receive more satisfying answers today.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/3">The aims of NOMS are laudable. How can anybody argue with the NOMS vision? We are told that it will:</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/4" class="indent">&quot;Implement the orders of the courts and supervise offenders and those remanded in custody in such a way as to protect the public . . . Provide a range of effective interventions and services that are designed to reduce reoffending . . . Give offenders the opportunity to lead law abiding, productive and healthy lives . . . Work in a way that treats offenders fairly and with decency.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/5">Protection of the public, a reduction in reoffending and the rehabilitation of offenders&mdash;I cannot argue with any of that.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/6">Similarly, discontent and decreasing morale among staff seem strange when one realises that there is fairly widespread acceptance of the objective of taking some responsibility for what happens to offenders once the court sentences them to different kinds of punishment.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/7">Everybody applauds the sentiments of NOMS, but people are concerned about the organisational structure that is proposed to implement it. The current division of responsibilities between the Prison Service, the probation service and others leads to inefficient and disruptive services, as I have seen for myself during my visits to prisons and probation boards.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/8">Nor are the existing arrangements conducive to providing services that promote offenders' rehabilitation and reduce their reoffending. No single organisation is ultimately responsible for the offender, which means that there is no clear ownership of the front line for reducing reoffending. Clear ownership is the goal that we all want to achieve, and the promotion of a single, integrated, seamless service that provides end-to-end management for offenders, whether they are sentenced to custodial or community punishment, therefore enjoys widespread acceptance and my support. The challenge, however, lies in how to achieve such integration to maximise the gains and minimise the risks involved&mdash;and the current risks are exceptional.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/9">To explain the increasing concern felt by myself and others, it is important to put the introduction of NOMS in context. The decision to merge correctional services resulted from the review of those services led by Patrick Carter. The Carter report &quot;Managing Offenders, Reducing Crime&quot; found that although the Prison Service and the national probation service had achieved improvements,</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/10" class="indent">&quot;access to services such as drug treatment and education depends more on whether an offender is sent to prison or probation, rather than their individual needs&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/11">So remedial support and action are based more or less on postcode prescription.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/12">NOMS has been identified as a way of remedying that. It came into existence five months after the Carter report had recommended its establishment and the Government had agreed to it in &quot;Reducing Crime&mdash;Changing Lives&quot;. That was far too quick and meant that the Government's consultation strategy was patchy and ineffective and did not reassure people in the probation service that they had a voice or that their concerns would be heard.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/13">The Probation Boards Association vented its frustration in February 2004, when it explained that one of its initial reactions to the Government's agreement to introduce NOMS was</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/14" class="indent">&quot;dismay that the Home Office appears to have taken far-reaching decisions without public or parliamentary scrutiny and consternation that those matters which have yet to be decided are offered only for 'comment or suggestion'&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/15">Discussion with members of the probation service has provided me with a full picture of the Government's consultation strategy, and it makes that frustration perfectly understandable. In some cases, there was no consultation, and where it did exist, it involved sending just a few scant letters; there did not seem to be much of a coherent rationale behind them.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/16">On <phrase class="date" code="2004-05-07">7 May 2004</phrase>, under cover of a letter from Martin Narey, the Home Office issued information containing organisational and design proposals for consultation with probation boards and other interested parties. The overwhelming response to that consultation was critical of the brevity of the information that accompanied the proposals and the lack of any reference to local arrangements.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/17">On <phrase class="date" code="2004-07-20">20 July 2004</phrase> the Minister withdrew the proposals and made various comments about how he saw the future of the National Offender Management Service. After that, it became increasingly difficult for the probation service and others, including me, to obtain meaningful information from anyone with any authority in the Home Office about the way forward for NOMS during the latter part of 2004.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/18">It would appear that no clear proposals were forthcoming and no responses were available to the myriad questions that were being asked. The Probation Boards Association, representing probation boards throughout England and Wales, became so frustrated that I understand it wrote to the Minister in January 2005 expressing its view on the lack of progress and the paucity of information.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/19">Whether those and other concerns were the trigger to action is not known, but a brief flurry of information followed, issued by the Home Office and containing various descriptions of a NOMS end-state diagram, NOMS design work and suggestions for service level agreements to be drawn up to guide the relations, including operational and budgetary matters, between probation boards and regional offender managers who had been appointed in the latter part of 2004.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/20">I know that the probation service is concerned that, despite a number of negative responses to the consultation, the end state of NOMS is no different in essence from the proposed system that was withdrawn by the Home Office in July 2004, following consultation. That lack of transparency on the part of the Government has been self-defeating. As is mentioned in the summary of responses from the consultation exercise, there is support for NOMS in general. Much of the resulting unease and discord stems from people's disappointment that they were not fully consulted and their concerns not acted on, as well as general confusion about the lack of forthcoming answers&mdash;confusion which, as I said earlier, I fully understand.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/21">I think that the Government would like to argue that the lack of a detailed blueprint gives key stakeholders the chance to influence the shape of NOMS at a crucial stage of its development. However, from what I have just related it is plain that that is not happening. Views are sought, but, it appears, not translated into any operational procedure or design. As a result, the view of the National Association of Probation Officers is that support for the concept of NOMS is now virtually non-existent, with key stakeholders, including the trade unions, among those who do not support it.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/22">There is a feeling that NOMS, as currently constructed, will not work. The Home Affairs Committee, of which, as I have said, I am a member, criticised the lack of consultation in our report on the rehabilitation of prisoners. The report states:</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/23" class="indent">&quot;We welcome in principle the introduction of the National Offender Management Service, although we regret the lack of prior consultation and the failure to publish a comprehensive business case. These failures have undoubtedly created unnecessary difficulties in developing NOMS. We welcome recent signs that the Government has recognised these problems. A more collaborative approach with those working in the Prison and Probation Services will produce effective change more swiftly.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/24">I should like to be thoroughly convinced that there will now be more thorough consultation.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/25">I noticed that the Under-Secretary of State for the Home Department, my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/917" name="Paul Goggins">the Member for Wythenshawe and Sale, East (Paul Goggins)</phrase>, referred to the possibility of a new stakeholder forum during the previous Adjournment debate. I should like more information on that, as well as details of the outcome of the meetings so far of the NOMS joint consultative council. I am glad that my hon. Friend seems to have taken on board the fact that the initial lack of consultation and the speed of introduction have led to low morale among staff affected by NOMS. The object of inspiring commitment in staff has obviously not been achieved. I truly believe that unless stakeholders are consulted and their views taken on board, NOMS will not achieve its aims. Therefore, it is immensely important that the stakeholder forum should come into being and that the council should be used to maximum effect.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/26">On <phrase class="date" code="2004-01-06">6 January 2004</phrase> the then Home Secretary, my right hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/739" name="David Blunkett">the Member for Sheffield, Brightside (Mr. Blunkett)</phrase>, explained how the Government envisaged the service being provided at regional level. He said:</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/27" class="indent">&quot;We believe that the task of integrating the management of offenders is best achieved at regional and local level&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/28">I emphasise the word &quot;local&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/29" class="indent">&quot;where effective links can be forged and joined-up strategies developed. Those will include working with complementary services, including health, education, housing and employment.&quot;&mdash;[<phrase class="offrep" id="debates/2004-01-06.172"><i>Official Report, House of Commons,</i> 6 January 2004; Vol. 416, c. 172</phrase>.]</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/30">However, local arrangements were omitted from the development of the organisational structures, and, subsequently, more than 90 per cent. of the boards either suggested alternative sub-regional structures or felt that the current 42 areas, or something similar, should be retained. None of the union responses was in favour of the regional structure. Most felt that the 42 areas, or something like that, should be retained.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/31">One of my worries is the sheer size of each regional offender region. Liz Hill, the regional offender manager for my area is responsible for the north-west, while Carol Bernard is the ROM for the whole of Wales. ROMs will have major responsibility. By 2006&ndash;07, they will be responsible for holding the budget for probation and prisons in their regions, commissioning services for prisons and local probation boards, holding both prison and probation areas to account for their performance, improving performance by developing contestability and allowing alternative service providers to compete for work so that regions obtain the best value for money in managing offenders.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/32">I do not understand how such a task can be managed at regional level. My area will include not only Merseyside, but Cheshire, Lancashire, Manchester and Cumbria, each with wide-ranging and varied offending problems. I fear that the regional structure will lead simply to increased bureaucracy, not better local results. What works in Bootle does not necessarily work in Crosby, and we must not lose sight of that in the re-organisation. I wish to receive reassurance that ROMs will work to make a strong, local focus possible within a regional structure, or else the structure will fail. As much commissioning as possible should be carried out locally rather than regionally to make delivery of contracts as relevant as possible to local people, their local problems and local issues.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/33">Following consultation, the Government decided to retain the current structure of the probation service only for the time being. The fact that regional offender managers are working with the 42 existing local boards seems to be an example of the Government's improved stance towards consultation, and I firmly welcome it. I was initially pleased by my hon. Friend the Minister's response in July 2004 to concerns about the move to a regional structure. He seems to have acted on consultation responses that included reservations about regionalisation, especially the replacement of probation boards populated by members of the local community with regional boards, which, it was thought, would disrupt links and reduce local accountability. The focus was to be end-to-end management of offenders and contestability, which also gave cause for concern.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/34">As well as the retention of probation boards, my hon. Friend explained that individual offender management would work at local level because it understands the importance of links at local level. I am keen to see how that will transpire in organisational reality. I am also aware that he emphasised that it was not a good idea to move to new regional boards for several reasons. However, regardless of his comments, it seems that NOMS is moving towards a more regional structure so, despite concerns expressed about such a move, plans have been postponed, not changed. Given that my hon. Friend the Minister still intends to move towards a regional structure and to replace the probation boards, those real worries have not been addressed.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/35">Such a change will be driven centrally and result in a lack of local accountability, and I want local accountability. I do not want to undermine the good multi-agency work that is happening in my constituency and throughout Merseyside. Will my hon. Friend clarify whether NOMS will move towards a more regional structure and, if so, what will it look like? If regionalism is the goal, the Government need to assure parliamentarians and key stakeholders that that will make improvements to what already exists.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/36">I should also like more information about the role and the powers of local offender managers. I am concerned that the Prison Service seems to have opted out of NOMS and, thus, that offender managers will not be able to affect the programmes in prison as they will have no authority over prison governors. Will my hon. Friend expand on the role and responsibilities of offender managers and explain how much influence they will have over the management of offenders in prison? I should be grateful if he told me whether he intends to remove local probation boards because it is important that they have power and resources to make links at local level. I, for one, am much in favour of local probation boards.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/37">Community involvement was seen to be an important feature of NOMS, as are restorative justice measures. On that, one charity said:</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/38" class="indent">&quot;we support measures to treat civil renewal as a matter of building confidence, resilience and social capital so that crime can be reduced and lower level nuisances can be dealt with by civil and social measures, including restorative measures, without recourse to the criminal justice process.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/39">I say amen to that. I fear that the move to regionalisation could damage those links with the local community, and we must retain them.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/40">I am not necessarily opposed to the inclusion of a regional tier; there is definitely a place for a regional section within the proposals, for strategic purposes alone. However, the form of regionalism that NOMS seems to be moving towards would undermine the strengths of the current system, particularly the criminal justice partnerships that have been established in all our communities and are beginning to work well.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/41">The criminal justice system has been moving towards a partnership approach to tackling crime and disorder since the introduction of the Crime and Disorder Act 1998, in recognition of the fact that organisations and individuals can achieve more if they work together than if they work in isolation. The 1998 Act places a joint responsibility on local authorities and police to formulate and implement strategies to reduce crime and disorder in their area. They must do that in co-operation with a large number of organisations from the statutory, private and voluntary sectors. They must also consult the local community about their proposals.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/42">Partnership groups make decisions on the setting of local priorities, targets, strategies and resources, and most have established a series of working groups to assess that process. Those working groups bring particular expertise to bear on a specific issue and make recommendations. Membership of the working groups will vary according to the issues that they address. They may contain a wider range of agencies than those represented in partnership groups, including agencies such as Victim Support and neighbourhood watch schemes. Vitally, they also involve members of the local community. Members of our local community are currently involved in criminal justice partnerships, which address problems caused by criminals operating locally. They are keen to ensure that such offenders are involved in restorative justice programmes that they have access to and have a voice in, and we cannot afford to lose that.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/43">The probation boards operating in each of the 42 probation areas have boundaries that are contiguous with constabulary and court boundaries. That has encouraged the growth of local partnerships between a range of agencies and service providers covering the same area, from crime reduction and disorder partnerships and the local criminal justice boards to primary care trusts and local authorities. We are currently in a utopia of coterminous authorities, and we wreck that at our peril. The Carter report vision is for the continuation of such partnerships, and it highlights the need for improving shared information. I totally agree with that direction, as do the people I have spoken to and the responses I have seen in the summary of responses to the consultation.</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/44">My local probation service is outstanding; through my experiences with it, I am aware of the good practice that emerges through collaboration&mdash;it has taken great pains to demonstrate that to me on more than one occasion. There is a lot of support for increasing the use of partnerships, although concerns have been raised about how that might happen in practice. In general, organisations appeared to be keen to work with each other, and to develop the work that has been done in recent years. The Probation Boards Association said that it would</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/45" class="indent">&quot;welcome the increased use of the voluntary/not-for-profit sector in dealing with the needs of offenders and communities. These partnerships not only add to the capacity of probation boards to deliver services but play an important part in community engagement and awareness-raising.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".468.1/46">The second part of &quot;National Offender Management Service&mdash;Next Steps&quot; summarises the response to the second consultation, which focused on the preferred organisational design of the new service. Despite the support that there is for increased partnership working, many respondents made it clear that they felt that there was no need for radical structural changes, and that the required changes in delivery could be brought about without so much upheaval to staff&mdash;staff who have been involved in the process of change for many years. That process is not conducive to good, efficient working, or the improvement of morale.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.473.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.473.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.474.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.474.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.474.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.474.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.474.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.474.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.474.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/836" speakername="Claire Curtis-Thomas" colnum="474"  time="014:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h03.htm#50406h03_spnew4">
	<p pid=".474.2/1">NOMS, the probation service and prisons are not on many parliamentarians' list of hot topics, but they are certainly on mine. A discrete number of colleagues in the House are interested in this matter, and we will not let it rest. We know that there are significant consequences to changing the probation and prison services. I want to ensure that any changes deliver a better service, and I will not stop until I have seen evidence of that and probation boards tell me that what is going to happen is better. Those people have the experience, and I am not going to argue with them because that experience has been gained over a long period, as my hon. Friend the Member for North-West Leicestershire just said.</p>
	<p pid=".474.2/2">Many respondents to the consultation pointed out that existing local relationships, both formal and informal, were important in ensuring successful management. As I said earlier, and as I intend to repeat, I want local people working with the crime and disorder partnerships, the probation boards, the youth offender teams and the youth justice boards to ensure that there is local accountability. That matters immensely to me.</p>
	<p pid=".474.2/3">One of the strongest messages coming from the consultation was concern about regional rather than local delivery structures. Numerous respondents pointed out how integral local structures and partnerships were to criminal justice services, and it was felt that the NOMS design would reduce that. The NOMS design does nothing to enhance those organisations that were set up as a result of the Crime and Disorder Act 1998 and runs counter to many of the measures introduced under that Act that focused on local involvement and local agency working.</p>
	<p pid=".474.2/4">Local arrangements supported by local people are necessary to ensure that work with offenders can be carried out effectively and in partnership with the range of other agencies which provide services to offenders. Furthermore, co-operation between locally managed probation services, the police and courts has been vital to crime reduction and the running of youth justice teams, which have been enabled by coterminous boundaries.</p>
	<p pid=".474.2/5">I am extremely impressed with the work on Merseyside through multi-agency public protection arrangements, and there are currently interagency arrangements to tackle serious crime. Those arrangements bring together all the relevant agencies and organisations to share information on the minority of offenders who cause the most concern&mdash;that is, sexual or violent offenders.</p>
	<p pid=".474.2/6">Until the mid to late 1990s, joined-up work was patchy. Agencies tended to work in isolation and guard their information on offenders, often managed in isolated pockets of time. That would mean one agency closing a file, with another opening a new one. Now, there is file sharing, and things are much better. A different approach prevails, and we have seen good examples of it in Liverpool. One of the basic principles of sharing such information is illustrated by the Liverpool intensive supervision monitoring scheme, whereby the police and probation officers have access to each others' computer files. Three levels of seriousness have been introduced to assist the process. Level 3 is the most serious and is reserved for the critical few who pose a risk to the community that requires input from a range of agencies. Senior managers come together locally to allocate significant resources to manage such individuals.</p>
	<p pid=".474.2/7">The scheme has been successful, as the 2003&ndash;04 statistics indicate. Some 67 individuals were subject to a level 3 multi-agency protection panel, and only two were subsequently charged with a new serious offence. In areas such as Bootle, that meant a massive reduction in some drug-related crime; and by massive I mean 80 per cent. The agents involved in the exercise&mdash;they are involved to this day&mdash;say that that is the result of multi-agency working and local solutions to local problems.</p>
	<p pid=".474.2/8">It is worth giving a real example. AA, who is just 20, has been in trouble with the law all his life and is serving a long prison sentence for violent muggings on trains. He has a history of psychological problems, made worse by drink and drug abuse. He has completed his intensive offending behaviour programme, acquired some educational qualifications during his prison sentence and faced up to the effects of his behaviour on his victims. He will soon be released on licence to complete his prison sentence under supervision in the community, which I applaud.</p>
	<p pid=".474.2/9">A MAPPA meeting will therefore be called to ensure that all the supervision arrangements are in place, to monitor his progress. At such meetings, all agencies share information, assess the risk and agree actions to be taken by the various agency representatives. In AA's case, the agencies involved will work together, as they understand that although good use is being made of custody time, he must be supported in the community.</p>
	<p pid=".474.2/10">Merseyside has formed a strategic management board made up of the relevant senior agency representatives, as well as the prison and probation services and the police. The board includes representatives of Support After Murder and Manslaughter&mdash;SAMM&mdash;the director of social services, the area manager of the St. Helens youth offending team and the deputy director of nursing for Mersey Care NHS Trust, to name but a few. Those people will be lost the regional structure, but we cannot afford to lose them. They must stay in place.</p>
	<p pid=".474.2/11">The head of St. Helens youth offending services has found that the work has informed his involvement with the strategic management board and feels that it has helped his understanding of issues involving victims of crime and the wider community. Where is there a place for such people in the current organisational structures for ROMs? I cannot see it. Does that mean that their role disappears, or does it mean that they are pulled into the centre of NOMS, a long way from Merseyside and the problems that my constituents experience.</p>
	<p pid=".474.2/12">Carol Chalmers, who is the chief executive of victim support and witness services in Merseyside, also welcomes her part in the multi-agency partnership. She says that</p>
	<p pid=".474.2/13" class="indent">&quot;research has shown that a collaborative approach in addressing the issues surrounding serious offenders is essential to prevent re-offending re-occurring . . . public protection is dependant upon thorough co-ordination by all the key agencies.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".474.2/14">I have laboured the point about localisation of the structure long enough and should turn to contestability. The Minister wants to place contestability at the heart of NOMS to ensure the best services. In an interview with <i>NOMS Update</i> magazine in January, Christine Knott explained that ROMs were already forging links with the key people in their regions and would quickly begin working to separate offender management from interventions. That will mean that existing providers will compete with private and voluntary sector providers to supply interventions in the community, thus leading to secrecy rather than information sharing. If agencies have to compete for work, they will develop their own strategies and ways of preparing and pricing programmes. There will not be the sharing of best practice between providers that we have now. I have seen that kind of sharing in action; providers say, &quot;What is working with you? This is working with us.&quot; If they all have to contract for work, there will be no sharing of good practice. People will keep good practice to themselves in the hope that they can win further contracts, and I am deeply opposed to that.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.476.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.476.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.477.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.477.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.477.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/836" speakername="Claire Curtis-Thomas" colnum="477"  time="014:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h03.htm#50406h03_spnew6">
	<p pid=".477.0/1">I agree absolutely; that is my experience. We have seen repeated examples of that when we have privatised a service. Privatisation may provide a service at less cost, but that does not mean it is more effective. We cannot overestimate the sophistication of the programmes developed to address the criminal habits of some individuals. The programmes have to be specifically tailored for each individual at great expense to the taxpayers. That is as a result of the criminals' action in the first place. The result is further expense to try to curtail and manage their behaviour in future. Experts currently put these programmes together, and they work.</p>
	<p pid=".477.0/2">A regional structure will incur greater costs, and those will have to be shared by each of the probation services, so we will get increasing costs and supervision. I want to know how that translates to the bottom line in terms of improved delivery. Quite frankly, I do not want any more managers in the system; I want more people out on the streets doing work with offenders.</p>
	<p pid=".477.0/3">Many probation staff feel clearly threatened by the proposal to split the purchaser-provider functions, as do the trade unions. Nearly 60 per cent. of union responses were strongly against the proposal. One union said that the split would</p>
	<p pid=".477.0/4" class="indent">&quot;run counter to Patrick Carter's original aim of 'breaking down the silos of the services' and will have a negative impact on staff and on the recruitment of staff, as well as on the principles of the service.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".477.0/5">The move towards contestability seems to go against the principle suggested in the Carter report. The proposals appear not to provide any structural integration of the probation and prison services; rather, they keep them separate and signal the intention of splitting the probation service in two.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.477.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.477.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.477.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.477.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.477.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/836" speakername="Claire Curtis-Thomas" colnum="477"  time="014:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h03.htm#50406h03_spnew8">
	<p pid=".477.2/1">Yes, I am aware of that. A member of my staff is currently with some of the probation boards and services across the UK, and I asked about some of those services. I know that some are shaping up to be put out, but I did not realise some of them had gone out.</p>
	<p pid=".477.2/2">As hon. Members know, I am prolific in asking parliamentary questions, having asked nearly 2,000. I give the Minister good notice of the fact that I shall be putting pen to paper, and I will expect to find out exactly what is what in this area. That will be good news for the Minister for after the next election, one hopes.</p>
	<p pid=".477.2/3">I want to bring my remarks to a close. I apologise for the length of my speech, but I wanted to put these matters, which I feel so strongly about, on the record. I am accountable to the people I serve in my constituency, and I am proud to be so. This is an essential part of my job. Many of us do not like to think of prisoners coming back into the community and reoffending. I have been trying my damnedest to limit that eventuality in my community. That is why I have such a great interest in the subject, and I do not intend to relinquish that interest.</p>
	<p pid=".477.2/4">In a press statement, the National Association of Probation Officers said:</p>
	<p pid=".477.2/5" class="indent">&quot;The purpose of the National Offender Management Service, which is established in today's Bill, is to dismantle the Probation Service and introduce privatisation in order to drive down costs. This will be done through reducing terms and conditions of staff.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".477.2/6">That is not necessarily the case. However, the statement went on:</p>
	<p pid=".477.2/7" class="indent">&quot;This is unlikely to reduce re-offending and, indeed, could actually lead to an increase in crime, because quantity not quality will become the main principle.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".477.2/8">It is not the cost but the value that matters. There is therefore a belief that NOMS will cause disruption in the service while failing in its aim to reduce reoffending.</p>
	<p pid=".477.2/9">As I have mentioned, one of the most effective methods of working in the probation service of late has been the multi-agency approach. I argued that that would be undermined if the boundaries of the probation service were changed. It will be more difficult to maintain links as their focuses will vary. However, multi-agency working, which we have been moving towards, faces a greater threat from the decision to move towards contestability through the separation of purchaser and provider functions. As one commentator noted:</p>
	<p pid=".477.2/10" class="indent">&quot;There is a risk that this approach could be counterproductive if NOMS is to succeed in delivering end-to-end management of offenders that will rely upon co-operation between service providers from all sectors.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".477.2/11">There is much evidence to support the view that dislocating the work of offender management and interventions would adversely affect the provision of an integrated, coherent and effective service to offenders.</p>
	<p pid=".477.2/12">I have said enough. My primary concern is that the NOMS service will be managed regionally. The dimension of locality seems to be missing. I have looked at the organisational structures&mdash;I am something of an expert in those&mdash;and cannot find anything that suggests that local providers will be able to determine what best suits local needs. That is what is crucial. Moreover, our probation boards are populated by local people who are accountable to local people and take great pride in the work that they do. We must not prejudice the involvement of local people in the action of the probation boards&mdash;that is also crucial.</p>
	<p pid=".477.2/13">I am implacably opposed to contestability. At the moment it is about reducing cost and not necessarily about improving the effectiveness of services. We cannot do that. We must continue with the good work established with a number of agencies since the Crime and Disorder Act 1998 was introduced, which is commendable. We have worked hard to involve local people in the management of local offenders, and we have to continue to do that. I cannot see NOMS, as constituted, enabling that process of local accountability one jot. I look forward to the reassuring words that I hope to get from my hon. Friend the Minister at the end of the debate, which will address not only my concerns but those of my hon. Friend the Member for North-West Leicestershire and of <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/914" name="Cheryl Gillan">the hon. Member for Chesham and Amersham (Mrs. Gillan)</phrase>, as expressed in recent debates. We must have overt and coherent answers to our concerns. If we do not, I have a long and interesting record of writing parliamentary questions about the matter.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.479.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.479.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.481.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.481.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.481.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.481.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.481.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.481.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.481.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/914" speakername="Cheryl Gillan" colnum="481"  time="014:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h03.htm#50406h03_spnew12">
	<p pid=".481.2/1">There is a huge element of d&eacute;j&agrave; vu about our debate, but   I am delighted that <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/836" name="Claire Curtis-Thomas">the hon. Member for Crosby (Mrs. Curtis-Thomas)</phrase> has given us another opportunity to beard the Minister in this den of Westminster Hall. I hope that he will be left with a lot more time to answer today's debate, as we have a lot more questions and many are hanging over from previous debates.</p>
	<p pid=".481.2/2">I congratulate the hon. Member for Crosby on her introduction to the debate. I understand that the Minister is married to a lady from Crosby. I hope that that will soften him up for his replies to the debate&mdash;and I hope that the hon. Lady will have more success in getting replies out of the Minister than did other Members did in this Chamber on previous occasions.</p>
	<p pid=".481.2/3">I identify strongly with the story told by <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1136" name="Mark Oaten">the hon. Member for Winchester (Mr. Oaten)</phrase>. Unfortunately, the Liberal Democrats do not have much continuity in dealing with the subject; <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/785" name="Alistair Carmichael">the hon. Member for Orkney and Shetland (Mr. Carmichael)</phrase> was speaking on prisons in the previous Westminster Hall debate. It would be nice to see consistency, with the same people following the subject through.</p>
	<p pid=".481.2/4">I, too, have spoken to many prisoners and discovered that the way in which they are prepared for release is so inadequate that they would rather stay inside. Recidivism is one thing, but it borders on the ridiculous that people can be so frightened of re-entering society that they would prefer to lose their liberty. That is when probation officers and prison officers come to the fore. They are the very people, the experts, needed to deliver a reduction in reoffending and to help ex-prisoners to take a proper role in society&mdash;a role in which they can contribute by working and paying tax rather than being a net drain on society. We all share that view.</p>
	<p pid=".481.2/5">To a certain extent, the Carter principles, the rebalancing of sentencing and a greater congruence between the work of the Prison Service and the probation service to help reduce reoffending and to protect the public is something to which we all subscribe. I have no doubt about that. Nevertheless, however pleasant, charming and helpful the Minister is, I am afraid that we seem to be descending into a quagmire. People do not know what is going on, and communications are exceedingly poor.</p>
	<p pid=".481.2/6">I understand that a group or cluster of prisons has already been put out to competition under the National Offender Management Service, but the Bill has gone nowhere. I was today handed a letter in reply to the debate that was instigated the other day by <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1271" name="David Taylor">the hon. Member for North-West Leicestershire (David Taylor)</phrase>. That letter confirms that the first competition has gone ahead, but the points that I raised on the Bill were not dealt with, other than the Minister stating:</p>
	<p pid=".481.2/7" class="indent">&quot;It is regrettable that the Parliamentary timetable has not allowed for this Bill to be progressed more swiftly; however, I confirm that I have no intention of withdrawing the Bill this Session.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".481.2/8">That was allegedly written on <phrase class="date" code="2005-03-24">24 March</phrase>; yet on <phrase class="date" code="2005-04-06">6 April</phrase>, today, the Bill has little likelihood of success. I hope that the Minister is not going to pick a horse on the Grand National on Saturday; I am not sure that I would trust his judgment. It was an open secret: everyone knew that the Bill would go nowhere&mdash;everyone except the Minister, who seemed always to stand up for it. I have heard rumours that the Bill will be redrafted&mdash;I am sure it will&mdash;yet NOMS is rolling on apace without legislative scrutiny, and the Minister has not consulted those involved in the work or Members of the House. Despite that, the change affects every constituency.</p>
	<p pid=".481.2/9">The business plan is not an impressive document. It is one of the thinnest business plans that I have seen for a long time. I, too, know about business and management. The business plan runs to five pages. The corporate plan is a little longer, but several of its pages show pictures of the members of the NOMS executive board. I thought that legislation had to be scrutinised by the House before the changes took place, but the plan mentions April 2005. I am not sure when it was prepared, but it must have been obvious that the Bill would not be introduced or debated. We question how it was introduced and how it is being managed by the Home Office. I have no doubt that there is general confusion and chaos, and that communications are poor.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.483.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.483.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.483.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.483.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.483.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/914" speakername="Cheryl Gillan" colnum="483"  time="014:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h03.htm#50406h03_spnew14">
	<p pid=".483.1/1">It is hard to glean much detail from it, but it has just appeared on the Home Office website and one must ask to whom it has been sent because the chief probation officers have not received it yet. I am not sure what the distribution process is for information, but while we are talking about communications from the Home Office, I note that NOMS officials have acknowledged that communications have been poor. I understand that the NOMS updates that are circulated to all staff have also dried up. Will the Minister confirm that NOMS updates have not been issued to staff recently and that they have been left in the dark on a permanent basis at a time of unprecedented change? Goodness only knows. I used to work for Arthur Young when it merged with Ernst and Whinney, and became Ernst and Young, and we had daily communications. In a major upheaval in a major organisation, the staff must be spoken to, informed and consulted, not kept in the dark. At a time such as this, during a general election, the updates should not be allowed to dry up.</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/2">I question the way in which the whole process is being managed. Our prison and probation services are not running along nicely. Indeed, they are in crisis in many areas: we still have gross overcrowding in some areas; the prison system is 24 per cent. overcrowded, as confirmed by Anne Owers; and there are at least two self-inflicted deaths a week. Last year, prison staff had to resuscitate 228 prisoners&mdash;that is 228 lives that were saved by the people who are not being consulted about the way in which their jobs are being changed&mdash;and there were almost 18,000 incidents of self-harm in our prisons. We are talking about the most vulnerable people in our society, who are at the mercy of the state, and about the people who provide this service to our society.</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/3">There are still many questions, and I am disappointed in the response so far as this should not be a contentious matter. Members of the Labour, Conservative and Liberal Democrat parties have pressed the Minister for an answer, but answers came there none. There is silence on so much about the way in which NOMS has been put forward.</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/4">Throughout this process, I have been briefed by the unions and their representatives, and I have been pleased to do business with them as they have conducted themselves in a first-class fashion. They have sought not to make political mileage but to get their organisations' voices heard by the Labour Government. I am grateful for the fair way in which they have briefed me.</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/5">The National Association of Probation Officers believes that there are still huge gaps and unanswered questions, and that the vision that the Minister has so often articulated about the statement of purpose for the Prison Service and the aims of the probation service is silent on the objective of rehabilitating those who have offended. It is an alarming indictment that it is silent on core values and principles. It is silent on achieving diversity and treating people with humanity, and on supporting the staff. Believe me, the staff do not feel supported. It is silent on the principles of openness and transparency, on the need for problem-solving approaches and on the need for an approach based on partnership and collaboration. That is a fundamental criticism of the process, which is reflected in the way in which the hon. Member for Crosby introduced the debate.</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/6">I do not want to speak for too long, as I want to leave the Minister plenty of time to respond, but I am worried. My having covered this brief for the past year and having spoken to so many people, it is natural that documents should be sent to me from time to time, and I need some explanation from the Minister about some of them.</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/7">There is no doubt that this is a time of unprecedented change with the major sentencing reforms in the Criminal Justice Act 2003 being introduced this week, on <phrase class="date" code="2005-04-04">4 April</phrase>. The challenges from the changes to the courts and the criminal justice service, particularly the probation service, are great, and our services need stability and support if they are to achieve the aims that the Minister and the Home Office have set out for them. However, at the same time, we have NOMS going on.</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/8">The business plan for the national probation service is obviously assessed internally within the Home Office. I have been passed something called annex C which is a summary risk register for 2005&ndash;06. I think that I understand the document, but I would like the Minister to answer some questions about it.</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/9">The risk register takes a couple of headings from the circular and identifies the likelihood of the risk taking place and what the impact would be of certain happenings. The first heading is:</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/10" class="indent">&quot;Contributing to the building of an excellent National Offender Management Service with the separation of Offender Management from Interventions: During 2005&ndash;06 areas will be expected to reorganise themselves to establish a clear operational division between offender management and interventions.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/11">The risks and risk descriptions are then laid out, accompanied by a traffic-light system. One obviously, therefore, looks at the ones marked in red. I find there that there is a medium likelihood, with a high impact, and a risk rating assessment which is right up the register, that a</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/12" class="indent">&quot;lack of programme and programme management for NOMS implementation leads to uncertainty resulting in drop in performance and organisational effectiveness&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/13">of the prison and probation service. That sounds pretty serious. I would like to know what the Minister thinks a medium risk with a high impact is. Also considered to be of medium risk is</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/14" class="indent">&quot;insufficient priority to establishment of new interventions organisation results in non-viable interventions capacity.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/15">Likewise, a medium risk is given to</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/16" class="indent">&quot;inadequate workforce planning to meet challenges of new CJA/Offender Manager development results in loss of confidence by sentencers.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/17">All those risks fall into the red area.</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/18">The next heading is:</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/19" class="indent">&quot;Working purposefully with other criminal justice agencies to protect the public from harm.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/20">I really want some answers from the Minister today on that area. Various risks have been identified, with their likelihood of the risk taking place and the impact. The first is</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/21" class="indent">&quot;industrial action/work to rule leading to disruption of service delivery.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/22">Apparently the Home Office considers that to be a medium risk. However, there is also considered to be a high risk of a</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/23" class="indent">&quot;loss of key skills resulting in inadequate supervision of dangerous offenders&quot;,</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/24">of which the impact would also be high. That is rated outside the traffic-light system: it goes to black.</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/25">Another area considered to be of very high risk and very high impact is described as follows:</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/26" class="indent">&quot;Failure to obtain GSI accreditation results in reduced cross-CJS collaboration leading to failure to deliver benefits of joined up for CJS.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/27">I understand that that is a total failure of communications by e-mail; it does not work. There is considered to be a very high likelihood of it happening, and a very high risk.</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/28">We are talking about a system for managing offenders. They are vulnerable people and people who, if they are not properly contained, looked after, managed and seen through the process&mdash;as the Minister likes to call it&mdash;of offender management, may put other people at risk. If this document says that even the basic communication system is not going to work, I am worried. Will the Minister comment on that?</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/29">There is also considered to be a high risk of</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/30" class="indent">&quot;inadequate supervision of cases leading to high profile media attention and unmanageable policy making.&quot;</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/31">The impact of that would also be very high. Again, that is put in a black box, so it is outside the traffic-light system&mdash;it is right at the top of the risk rating.</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/32">If all that is the case, everything that has ever been said by the Opposition on this area is coming home to roost; the prison and probation service have been tipped into a position in which risks are being run. The Minister should take the 25 minutes available not only to respond to the points raised by the hon. Member for Crosby, but to talk us through those risk assessments. I am sure that they will be easy for him to dismiss. He said, &quot;Well it might happen; that is how we look at the risks&quot;. However, we deserve an answer from the Minister, even this close to a general election, when the ratings against the risk factors that I have identified in the debate are &quot;very high&quot;.</p>
	<p pid=".483.1/33">Our prison and probation services are very good. I am proud of them, and they deserve first-class treatment for the first-class job that they try to do. As I said, they do not deserve the current chaos and uncertainty, and I look to the Minister to answer today and not to write to me before the election.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.486.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.486.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.486.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.486.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.486.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.486.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.487.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.487.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.487.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.487.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.487.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.487.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.487.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.487.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.487.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.487.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.487.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.487.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.488.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.488.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.488.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.488.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.488.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.488.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.488.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.488.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.489.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.489.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.490.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.490.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.490.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.490.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.490.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.490.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.490.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.490.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.490.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.490.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.491.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.491.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.491.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.491.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.491.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.491.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.492.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.492.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.492.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.492.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.492.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.492.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.492.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.492.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.492.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.492.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.492.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/914" speakername="Cheryl Gillan" colnum="492"  time="015:05:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmhansrd/cm050406/halltext/50406h03.htm#50406h03_spnew40">
	<p pid=".492.4/1">On a point of order, Mr. Deputy Speaker. Can you advise me how I can ask the Minister to respond, outside this debate, to the serious points I have made about the risk register? In light of the fact that this Parliament is about to be dissolved, would it be in order for him to have to write to Members who have taken part in this debate within 24 hours?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.492.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.492.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.493.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.493.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.493.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.493.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.494.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.494.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.494.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.494.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.498.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.498.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.502.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.502.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.502.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.502.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.505.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.505.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.507.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.507.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.507.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.507.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06.510.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2005-04-06a.510.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

