<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.185.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.185.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.185.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.185.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.185.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.185.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.186.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.186.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.186.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.186.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.186.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.186.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.186.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.186.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.186.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.186.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.186.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.186.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.187.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.187.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.187.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.187.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.189.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.189.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.190.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.190.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.190.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.190.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.190.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.190.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.190.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.190.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.191.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.191.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.191.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.191.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.192.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.192.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.192.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.192.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.193.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.193.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.193.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.193.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.193.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.193.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.193.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.193.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.193.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.193.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.193.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.193.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.194.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.194.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.194.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.194.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.194.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.194.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.194.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1736" speakername="Norman Lamb" colnum="194"  time="010:06:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080115/halltext/80115h0002.htm#08011594000637">
	<p pid="a.194.2/1">Absolutely.</p>
	<p pid="a.194.2/2">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1885" name="Vincent Cable">the Member for Twickenham (Dr. Cable)</phrase> on securing this debate and on raising again an issue of fundamental importance. He has a track record on this matter. He mentioned that he secured a ten-minute Bill right at the start of his time in this place, demonstrating a commitment to a Cinderella part of a Cinderella service that does not secure nearly enough attention from the public or from politicians of any party.</p>
	<p pid="a.194.2/3">My hon. Friend presented a powerful case with regard to the facility in his area, Marble Lodge, which serves his constituency and that of my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1783" name="Susan Kramer">the Member for Richmond Park (Susan Kramer)</phrase>. It is extraordinary that, having gone through a full consultation process just 18 months ago and reaching the conclusion that the facility should continue to play a valuable part in local health services, a completely contradictory decision was taken only a short period afterwards. There is, inevitably, concern that the decision was driven more by cost saving than by quality.</p>
	<p pid="a.194.2/4">I pay tribute to the organisations that fight tirelessly to keep such issues in the public mind, including Age Concern, Help the Aged, the Alzheimer's Society and Mind. They operate in a difficult area and are constantly in touch with the Minister, who has the same view about the role that they play. Their work is of fundamental importance in securing improvements to services that are so vital in a civilised society.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.194.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.194.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.194.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.194.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.194.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1736" speakername="Norman Lamb" colnum="194"  time="010:06:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080115/halltext/80115h0002.htm#08011594000639">
	<p pid="a.194.4/1">I am grateful to the hon. Gentleman for raising that issue, which I was going to cover. I understand that there is clear evidence of discrimination, not because the Government want that, but because of the way in which the system has ended up operating in too many parts of the country. The Royal College of Psychiatrists has done a lot of work to highlight key concerns.</p>
	<p pid="a.194.4/2">I acknowledge the Minister's commitment to improving the quality of the service. My hon. Friend the Member for Twickenham referred to a speech that the Minister made last summer, and I acknowledge his role in seeking to improve service provision. I do not intend to make a knocking, party political contribution; I want to raise issues of genuine concern, which mirror what my hon. Friend said. I hope that the Minister will accept my comments in that light.</p>
	<p pid="a.194.4/3">I acknowledge that there have been significant improvements in funding. We supported the increased investment in the health service, which has clearly benefited mental health services in many parts of the country. None the less, increased investment in funding for mental health has lagged behind. I appreciate that it depends partly on how that is measured, but it has lagged behind investment in some other parts of the health service, and that should be acknowledged and addressed, particularly because, as my hon. Friend said, it is self-evidently a growing problem. It looks as though it will be the greatest challenge to face us in funding health care and social care.</p>
	<p pid="a.194.4/4">The disparity in funding was highlighted in the autumn pre-Budget report; on the same page there was reference to a 4 per cent. increase in funding for the health service, but to an increase of only 1 per cent. for social care. Support services&mdash;the infrastructure for support&mdash;for elderly, mentally ill people depend not only on funding support within the health service, but on social care support. In many parts of the country, social care is drifting into a state of crisis. The Library's helpful debate pack refers to a report about the situation in Lincolnshire, where social care is pretty dismal, and crisis management is ineffective in partnership with other organisations such as the NHS. We must never neglect the problems of social care within the health service.</p>
	<p pid="a.194.4/5">As well as funding increases lagging behind other areas of the health service, the drift into deficit has had an impact on many organisations within the NHS where the political imperative is to get them out of deficit. The Select Committee on Health highlighted the extent to which mental health services around the country have been disproportionately affected by cutbacks.</p>
	<p pid="a.194.4/6">My hon. Friend the Member for Richmond Park talked about distortions based on accounting principles, but I have been told by people working in the NHS that there is another distortion. With payment by results in the acute sector and the impact of targets to reduce waiting times&mdash;a worthy ambition&mdash;there is a tendency for money to be channelled disproportionately into acute treatment to meet the stringent waiting-time targets. Because payment by results does not operate within mental health, there is less money in the pot for primary care trusts to enter contractual arrangements with mental health trusts for the funding of mental health services, so PCTs ask the mental health trust to negotiate a reduction in the contract or in what it hopes to provide for mental health service funding. That seems to have happened in many parts of the country and, in turn, puts pressure on trusts' mental health services.</p>
	<p pid="a.194.4/7">I shall talk about the impact of the pressures on mental health services as a result of funding challenges. The Royal College of Psychiatrists provided a helpful briefing for the debate, and highlighted two issues. It said that old people's mental health services are among the most innovative person-centred community services in the country. My hon. Friend the Member for Twickenham used the same terms as the Royal College of Psychiatrists when he referred to services being cynically dismantled. The RCP also raised concerns about age discrimination.</p>
	<p pid="a.194.4/8">I shall deal first with the assertion that specialist services for elderly, mentally ill people are being cynically dismantled. The royal college said that primary care trusts throughout the country seem to be transferring the care of older people with mental health problems to general psychiatric services. Age Concern has also raised specific concerns about that. Part of the justification for transferring specialist services for elderly, mentally ill people to general psychiatric services is to end age discrimination by providing the same service for all ages. The paradox is that dismantling specialist services for elderly people increases age discrimination, as the services provided are not appropriate, suitable or sufficiently specialist for the particular needs of elderly people with mental health problems.</p>
	<p pid="a.194.4/9">That can happen in a countrywide health service, and I am not blaming the Government for masterminding the drive to apply general psychiatric services to everyone, and thus being responsible for an increase in age discrimination, but I urge the Minister to address what seems to be happening, and the concerns of many specialists and charitable organisations in the field.</p>
	<p pid="a.194.4/10">The Royal College of Psychiatrists fears that we will end up with a second-rate service for elderly people with mental health problems, that we will lose specialisms because we will not have people with training in that area of mental health and that the end result will be an inferior service for those with mental health problems in their older years. The royal college draws attention to the fact that the national service framework for mental health has introduced the targeted commission of new services. It refers specifically to early psychosis, assertive outreach, and crisis resolution home treatment teams and says that the &pound;300 million investment in those new services broadly excludes older people, so again the services are discriminatory. I am sure that will be as much a concern for the Minister as it is for us. The RCP also says that the &pound;1.65 billion cash increase for adult mental health services over four years excludes older people.</p>
	<p pid="a.194.4/11">I am sure we all agree that access to services must be based on individual need, and not on the age that someone happens to be. There are some good, innovative pilots in the country. East Sussex has a particular commitment to ensure that services are suitable for each individual, and that must be the objective we all seek to achieve.</p>
	<p pid="a.194.4/12">I want to comment briefly on the role of acute care, to which <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1791" name="Jeremy Wright">the hon. Member for Rugby and Kenilworth (Jeremy Wright)</phrase> referred. He seems to have disappeared.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.196.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.196.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.197.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.197.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.197.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.197.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.201.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.201.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.201.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1467" speakername="Ivan Lewis" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Health"  colnum="201"  time="010:38:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080115/halltext/80115h0003.htm#08011594000643">
	<p pid="a.201.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1885" name="Vincent Cable">the hon. Member for Twickenham (Dr. Cable)</phrase> on securing the debate and on setting its tone. We have had a high-quality discussion, free of the usual party politics and, as <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1736" name="Norman Lamb">the hon. Member for North Norfolk (Norman Lamb)</phrase> said, we have been addressing one of the great public policy challenges that faces our society and all political parties and it is the responsibility of Government. May I also say to the hon. Member for Twickenham that the way he talked about his own experience with his mum was very moving? We should remember that the situation that we are discussing is reflected in an increasing number of families throughout the country. It does the body politic good that occasionally we talk in the language of our own families and life experiences, which shows that we are not as out of touch as sometimes politicians of all colours are accused of being.</p>
	<p pid="a.201.0/2">As the hon. Member for North Norfolk said, this issue is one of the great challenges that our society faces. I refer to the fact that we live in a society in which people live longer and, in doing so, have increasingly complex conditions such as dementia. In his recent speech on the NHS, the Prime Minister said that demography was one of the top challenges facing the NHS. That is an important step forward because, often, the debate is solely about social care, but demography is every bit as important. As the hon. Gentleman for Hemel Hempstead (Mike Penning) said, if one goes to an acute hospital, one will see an incredibly high number of older people receiving care. That is a challenge for the social care system, but, equally, it is a challenge for the NHS and, arguably, for all public services. If the demography of our society is changing, the future development of all kinds of public policy will have to reflect it.</p>
	<p pid="a.201.0/3">People's expectations are very different now. The vast majority of people wish to remain in their own homes rather than enter institutionalised care. That does not mean that there is no need for specialist, high-quality residential nursing units&mdash;there is, and there always will be&mdash;but the reality is that the vast majority of people, given the choice, would wish to stay in their own homes. The baby boomer generation&mdash;I shall not fit any particular Member into any particular generation&mdash;have much higher expectations of care than our grandparents' generation, both in terms of the quality of care and of the level of personalisation.</p>
	<p pid="a.201.0/4">As I have said before, I intend to bring dementia out of the shadows. For too long, individual families have struggled and battled with dementia, but public policy has almost been in denial about it, instead focusing on the generic needs of older people without recognising that dementia brings with it particular issues. Anybody who has seen the powerful and shocking documentary in which Barbara Pointon allowed the filming of her husband Malcolm's deterioration could not help but understand the power of the condition for the individual and the family member. I am delighted that I have got to know Barbara recently and that she is playing an active role in the development of our national dementia strategy, and in the Department's work with carers.</p>
	<p pid="a.201.0/5">I have also focused on making the case for putting the dignity of older people at the heart of our care services, and I shall continue to provide leadership on that. I do not believe that there are easy solutions or magic wands, or that we can run every hospital, GP surgery and social care service, but providing national leadership that says that dignity at all times must be at the heart of care for older people would begin to make a difference and to get the debate going in every care establishment up and down the country.</p>
	<p pid="a.201.0/6">The hon. Member for Twickenham talked about a number of issues. He was on to something when he put dementia alongside cancer, stroke and heart disease as a condition that challenges the NHS. Dementia should be given a much higher status and reflect the priority that we give to it. He was good enough to say that practice on older people's mental health has improved in the past 10 years, but we are beginning in deficit, because practice is nowhere near as good as it needs to be. However, he said that we have seen advances in the way in which care is provided in the past decade.</p>
	<p pid="a.201.0/7">The hon. Gentleman raised the issue of Marble Lodge in St. John's hospital in his constituency. Quality of life without medication is the ethos of that institution, which provides a calming environment&mdash;&mdash;as he said, an oasis of peace. Those are the qualities, characteristics and attributes that people with dementia and their families in every part of the country would want. However, I must tell him that I cannot instruct local NHS organisations how to do their business. He made a powerful case when he said changes should not be made in advance of the national dementia strategy, without, perhaps, all the evidence on the direction of policy. The people charged with making such difficult decisions&mdash;it is a difficult change to make&mdash;should consider whether it would be appropriate. I should also like to put on record that the national dementia strategy will be published in the autumn, but a consultation document will be presented in June and people will have the opportunity to comment before the final strategy is produced.</p>
	<p pid="a.201.0/8">The hon. Gentleman may want to acknowledge that carers have been involved in the tendering process&mdash;they have had input and oversight. To say that there has been no engagement or consultation in the case he mentioned is not fair, because significant attempts to engage and consult were made. Indeed, the matter was originally referred to the overview and scrutiny committee of his local authority, which chose not to express any reservations about the change. It subsequently had second thoughts and raised its concerns, but to say that there was no consultation is not fair. The hon. Gentleman did not say that there was no consultation, but the hon. Member for Hemel Hempstead spoke of consultation in a derogatory way. Genuine attempts to engage on the issue were made, but because of the unique and special nature of the unit, there is a great deal of emotional attachment to it and a great belief that the clinical care it provides is of the highest possible standard. I would be happy to speak privately to the hon. Member for Twickenham about that particular situation.</p>
	<p pid="a.201.0/9"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1791" name="Jeremy Wright">The hon. Member for Rugby and Kenilworth (Jeremy Wright)</phrase>, who has left the Chamber, does an excellent job as the chairman of the all-party group on dementia, and the group makes an important contribution to the debate.</p>
	<p pid="a.201.0/10">The hon. Member for North Norfolk made a constructive and helpful contribution, and I echo his tributes to Age Concern, Help the Aged, the Alzheimer's Society, Action on Elder Abuse, Mind and, indeed, to carers organisations such as Carers UK, the Princess Royal Trust for Carers, Crossroads, Partners in Policymaking, and the Royal College of Psychiatrists. Those organisations frequently ensure that older people's needs are placed far higher on the political agenda than they would be by constantly pressuring parliamentarians and using the media, and by championing the interests of older people and their families, so I pay tribute to them.</p>
	<p pid="a.201.0/11">The hon. Gentleman talked about funding. We spend large amounts of money, in every community through the NHS and local government, both on social care and on mainstream well-being services through the benefits system, but that is not often not referred to in debates such as this. We spend money, for example, on the disability living allowance, the attendance allowance, housing, and, indeed, we spend money through excellent third and voluntary sector organisations. We need to get to a situation in which we have a joined-up, integrated approach to health and well-being in every local community that shifts us toward early intervention and prevention. We signed the &quot;Putting People First&quot; concordat before Christmas with local government and the NHS. I believe that in the next three years, a radical transformation of the social care system in partnership with the NHS, focused on a shift to early intervention and prevention, and on giving people maximum control and power through personal budgets, universal information and advice to people, including those who fund themselves, is massively important. It would begin to transform well-being services in every community in every part of the country.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.203.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.203.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.203.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.203.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.203.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1467" speakername="Ivan Lewis" colnum="203"  time="010:38:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080115/halltext/80115h0004.htm#08011594000645">
	<p pid="a.203.1/1">I am open to that view, but that is not what I am saying and it is not the Government's position. As the hon. Gentleman knows, we are about to embark on a major, extensive public consultation that will lead to a Green Paper and scope out the scale of the challenge of the future funding of social care and the range of available options. I am not necessarily talking about the need to put all the investment into one organisational framework because, sometimes, tinkering with organisational structure is not the solution. I am saying that those resources should be considered, commissioned and spent in a holistic and integrated way in every community rather than being looked at separately. That is not quite the same as saying that they should all be brought within the same organisational framework. In our view there is not enough money in local communities to ensure that older people, disabled people, those with mental health problems and carers have a much better quality of life. I argue that it is not only about more money, although the demography means that over the next 10, 15 or 20 years we will need more resources just to keep up with demand, but that existing resources could be used in a far more integrated and sensible way.</p>
	<p pid="a.203.1/2">That is why I ask the House to consider the &quot;Putting People First&quot; protocol. It will be followed in the next few days by a letter to every local authority. Local government has signed up with the Government to a radical shake-up of social care services, in partnership with the NHS, in every community over the next three years, beginning in April.</p>
	<p pid="a.203.1/3">The hon. Member for North Norfolk made an important point in respect of acute hospitals, and the opportunity for older people who are admitted to them to have access specialist mental health services.</p>
	<p pid="a.203.1/4">The hon. Member for Hemel Hempstead&mdash;I welcome his unusually non-political contribution&mdash;rightly spoke about the inappropriate medication of older people. He will therefore welcome the significant expansion of psychological therapies over the next three years. At primary care level, people will have far greater access to psychological therapy than ever. That will be as relevant to older people as to those of all other ages.</p>
	<p pid="a.203.1/5">Like the hon. Gentleman, I spent Christmas day visiting the two acute hospitals in the vicinity of my constituency. I felt a sense of awe on meeting the staff, who were giving up their whole of their Christmas time to care for NHS patients in a sensitive and professional way. It demonstrates the power and the uniqueness of our national health service and the staff who work on the front line. Of course, we cannot walk away from the growing number of patients in acute hospitals that have dementia, and Lord Darzi's Next Stage Review of the NHS will give serious consideration to that factor.</p>
	<p pid="a.203.1/6">I could speak about all that the Government have done on these issues over the past 10 years, but much of what we have done is already on the record. In 1999, we introduced an annual carers grant to every local authority, the right for carers to request flexible working and enhanced pension credits for carers&mdash;and we will be doing more. That is why the Prime Minister, my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Health and I spent several hours in Leeds last Friday talking directly to 70 or 80 carers about what they want from the new deal for carers that the Prime Minister will announce later this year. Rather than a new deal for carers being drawn up in offices in Westminster and Whitehall, it will be based on the real, everyday experiences of carers.</p>
	<p pid="a.203.1/7">We will consider respite care, a subject raised by the hon. Member for North Norfolk. There should be greater recognition and valuing of the tremendous contribution made by carers. That contribution will grow with the ageing population. Indeed, people often miss the significant implication for families if ever more people are to stay in their own homes rather than going to institutions. Nor, as the Minister for Schools and Learners, arrives for the next debate, should we forget the plight of young carers. Together we need to do a lot more as we face one of the new challenges to which society is waking up&mdash;that far too many children are spending too great a proportion of their lives caring, inappropriately in my view, for sick or dependent parents. As the hon. Gentleman said, we must address the needs of carers, and we will be doing so in our new deal for carers.</p>
	<p pid="a.203.1/8">The year 2008 will be crucial in facing up in a radical way to the challenges of demographic change. We will produce a national dementia strategy, which will focus on raising awareness of the problem among professionals and citizens, so that we can identify the symptoms at an early stage; the earlier we intervene the better. Appropriate diagnosis and intervention are important. Too often, family members or the older people themselves approach a professional, describe symptoms and are told that they are not suffering from dementia or Alzheimer's, and many are given an inappropriate diagnosis. That is bad, because the earlier we intervene in such circumstances, the better and more effective the treatment and support will be.</p>
	<p pid="a.203.1/9">The final element of the national dementia strategy will be quality specialist care. I agree entirely with those who said that we need specialist expertise, staff training and, when appropriate, specialist services. Simply to say that all older people should receive the same service, as an expression of equality, is a mistake.</p>
	<p pid="a.203.1/10">The national dementia strategy will be produced in the autumn and we will consult on it from June. It will be incredibly important, and I am delighted that the chief executive of the Alzheimer's Society is playing a central role, with recognised leaders in social care and the NHS, in developing the strategy.</p>
	<p pid="a.203.1/11">As I said, extensive consultation will take place this year on the future funding of the social care system, and we will produce a Green Paper later in the year. I want an all-party consensus for change on the funding of long-term care. I hope that politicians will resist the temptation to resort to petty politics. We all know that it is not easy to balance the respective responsibilities of the state and the citizen when considering the scale of demographic change and people's rising expectations. Publication of the Green Paper will be incredibly important.</p>
	<p pid="a.203.1/12">I will be extending my campaign to put dignity for older people at the heart of all care services. We want the subject to be debated on every hospital ward, in every residential and nursing home, and within all domiciliary services, voluntary organisations and local authorities. The question is how to improve dignity for older people in every care setting.</p>
	<p pid="a.203.1/13">We will review the protection regulation system for vulnerable adults. We know that elder abuse is a growing concern. Twenty or 30 years ago, we were beginning to talk openly about the scale of child abuse. With elder abuse, public debate is arguably at a similar stage so we will review the protection regulations later this year.</p>
	<p pid="a.203.1/14">In the spring, the Prime Minister will announce a new deal for carers. With a 10-year plan, we will seek to address the growing number of people who spend a significant proportion of their lives caring for older or disabled relatives; and we as a society and as a Government must do more to recognise, value and support their contribution.</p>
	<p pid="a.203.1/15">Alongside that is the Darzi review of the NHS. Having rebuilt the foundations of the NHS during the past 10 years, the challenge now is to move to a world-class health service, with personalisation at its heart&mdash;one in which people are treated as people and not patients, because individuals and families have distinct needs. As the Prime Minister said recently, we need to harness all our expertise and technology and the most recent medical advances to shift towards early intervention and prevention, moving from a sickness health service to a well-being national health service.</p>
	<p pid="a.203.1/16">The year 2008 is the time for us to consider all approaches to the needs of older people and disabled people, and for the Government to demonstrate their willingness to step up to the plate and tackle the issues head on. I believe that many of them require an all-party consensus, and we will be striving to achieve that whenever possible as those debate become more acute.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.207.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.207.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.207.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.207.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.207.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1432" speakername="Brian Iddon" colnum="207"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080115/halltext/80115h0004.htm#08011594000646">
	<p pid="a.207.1/1">Thank you, Mr. Olner. It is a pleasure to serve this morning under your chairmanship.</p>
	<p pid="a.207.1/2">Unfortunately, this debate has clashed with a seminar on renewable energy that the members of the Innovation, Universities and Skills Committee are now attending at Imperial college. Otherwise there would have been a much greater attendance at this meeting. However, the quality is here and that is what matters.</p>
	<p pid="a.207.1/3">First, I should declare an interest, in that I am a parliamentary adviser to the Royal Society of Chemistry. That is a non-pecuniary interest, which I have registered.</p>
	<p pid="a.207.1/4">My contribution to this debate is not going to be about the supply or quality of science teachers, important as those subjects are, because they have been covered in two Select Committee reports. One was published by the House of Lords in the 2005-06 Session of Parliament and the other was published by the House of Commons in the 2001-02 Session of Parliament.</p>
	<p pid="a.207.1/5">I intend to concentrate on issues that are used to embellish the teaching of science, some of which I have been closely involved in. Many of us, if not most of us, who became scientists in the past would probably agree that, foremost, it was the enthusiasm of the science teacher that attracted us to pursue such a career. Some science teachers can make the sciences, whether it be chemistry, physics, geology, biology or even zoology, sound extremely complicated, if not boring, probably because they do not enjoy teaching the subject or, in some cases, because they do not even understand the basic principles. Of course, the lack of specialist teachers is part of the problem and that situation has got worse in recent years.</p>
	<p pid="a.207.1/6">The worst science teachers make no attempt at all to embellish the curriculum by taking their students out of the classroom, for example to listen to an outside lecture or to visit an outside facility that is trying to make science interesting to students and the general public. They are also reluctant to invite scientists or engineers into their classroom to talk about their experiences and they make minimum effort to run practical classes. Indeed, their sole aim appears to be to cover the curriculum so that their students will achieve the highest grades possible in examinations, even by abandoning many of the practical classes if that should prove necessary.</p>
	<p pid="a.207.1/7">Recent surveys by the Science museum in Kensington and the awarding bodies have shown that hands-on practicals in laboratories and visits and excursions outside school are the most enjoyable aspects of studying the sciences. I am aware of <i>The Times Education Supplement</i> published in October last year that revealed that a third of teachers had cancelled school trips, with cost cited as the problem by 40 per cent. of the teachers surveyed and form-filling cited as the problem by 36 per cent. of the teachers surveyed. However, to be fair to the Government, they have responded to that criticism by publishing a manifesto entitled &quot;Learning Outside the Classroom&quot; and pledging &pound;2.7 million towards encouraging school trips, for which I am extremely grateful, as I am sure are others.</p>
	<p pid="a.207.1/8">I would like to pay a tribute to the 12,000 or more volunteers who take part in the Science and Engineering Ambassadors in Schools, or SEAS, programme, which is organised in partnership with the Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics Network, or STEMNET, as we should now call that organisation; previously, of course, it was called SETNET. Those volunteers are mainly young people who are encouraged by their employers to convey the excitement of their work to secondary school children who might be attracted as a result to pursue a career in science or engineering. Unfortunately, pressures from the Research Assessment Exercise in recent years have reduced the number of younger university academics willing to visit schools.</p>
	<p pid="a.207.1/9">My own interest in science began with an opportunity, at the age of 11, to purchase a rather complicated chemistry set from another boy in my village who had become rather bored with it. It was accompanied by a very old practical textbook. The front porch in our house, which was only used on significant occasions such as funerals, became my laboratory. The absence of a fume cupboard did not deter me from carrying out the experiments, much to the consternation of my parents, I might add.</p>
	<p pid="a.207.1/10">In those days, chemicals and basic glassware, such as round-bottomed and flat-bottomed flasks, retort stands and clamps, beehive shelves and thistle funnels, could be purchased from a chemist's shop, believe it or not. All my purchases were made from Caves the Chemist in Neville street, Southport, the town where I attended secondary school and, later, the technical college.</p>
	<p pid="a.207.1/11">In those educational establishments, my enthusiasm for practical science was fired by two very fine teachers, Mr. Jones and Mr. Crossley. They made full use of the demonstration bench at the front of the class. If they were talking about chlorine, they made chlorine before the very eyes of the students who were watching in fascination. Indeed, whenever they talked about a chemical, the chemical was there on the demonstration bench and many reactions were carried out, with wonderful colour changes, lots of smells and a few flashes and bangs. I must say that watching a teacher perform the thermite reaction was one of the highlights of the chemistry year.</p>
	<p pid="a.207.1/12">I suppose it was those experiments that attracted me to become the first senior demonstrator in organic chemistry at Durham university, at the age of 24. That brought me into contact with the great demonstration lecturers of the day, for example, &quot;Flash Porter&quot;, otherwise known as Professor George Porter of the Royal Institution and the famous B.D. Shaw of Nottingham university, who gave his famous lecture on explosives until he was well into his 90s; he also gave it on television. As a result, for 29 years I presented a demonstration lecture, which was 90 minutes long and called &quot;The Magic of Chemistry&quot;. I presented it at least once a month and many more times during the Christmas period. Indeed, Christmas lectures have been a tradition in many of our towns and cities in this country, especially here in London at the Royal Institution in Albermarle street.</p>
	<p pid="a.207.1/13">I was on the &quot;demo circuit&quot; and came to know some of the &quot;greats&quot; in the business, people such as the Rev. Ron Lancaster, with his &quot;Fireworks&quot; lecture, and Dr. John Salthouse of &quot;Son et Lumiere&quot; fame. Ron, whose son is now a Conservative MP and is today sitting not very far from me, was a chemistry teacher at Kimbolton school in Cambridgeshire and became the only private individual in his day to gain a licence to manufacture fireworks. Kimbolton Fireworks is one of the few remaining manufacturers of fireworks in Britain today, and is well known for its public displays. In &quot;Son et Lumiere&quot;, John Salthouse takes the line of &quot;Look what happens when you mix this with that&quot;; the result, of course, is a flash, a bang or a wallop, and plenty of noise or light, or both. Now, imagine how much more interesting the teaching of science is when you have people such as that around the classroom.</p>
	<p pid="a.207.1/14">Sadly, the classroom and teachers have changed. Of course, the fear of litigation should something go wrong and the health and safety regulations, such as the introduction of the Control of Substances Hazardous to Health&mdash;COSHH&mdash;regulations, have helped to put a damper on some of the more exciting experiences that a student can have in the classroom.. However, teachers very often use those regulations as an excuse. It is still possible to present science in an extremely exciting way, but the teachers are not trained to do it and few take the opportunity to engage themselves in reading the relevant and excellent textbooks on presenting demonstration lectures in the classroom. If they are not confident or able enough to present such lectures themselves, there are many visitors who can do so and they should be invited into the classroom or laboratory to fascinate the students with such demonstrations.</p>
	<p pid="a.207.1/15">It is, of course, important, even mandatory, that risk assessments are carried out on all activities that are undertaken with young people, especially those working in a school laboratory. Learning about the hazards presented by all chemicals and the risks involved in their use is considered now to be a part of chemical education. However, recent statistics available from both local authorities and the Health and Safety Executive show that school science laboratories are one of the safest places in the school in terms of the accidents that may arise from science experiments.</p>
	<p pid="a.207.1/16">In an interesting publication, &quot;Surely That's Banned?&quot;, published by the Royal Society of Chemistry in 2005, the Consortium of Local Education Authorities for the Provision of Science Services, or CLEAPSS, and the Scottish Schools Equipment Centre, or SSERC, detail what is banned in school teaching. In fact, very little is banned, contrary to the perception of a significant number of science teachers. If teachers are unsure about what is banned, they can seek advice from those organisations and their publications, or from the Association of Science Education&mdash;the ASE&mdash;and the learned societies, or consult those societies' publications.</p>
	<p pid="a.207.1/17">Solvents such as benzene, which is a carcinogen, tetrachloromethane and 1,1,1-trichloroethane, which are ozone depleters, are banned, and there are restrictions on the quantity of thorium and uranium salts that can be kept in the laboratory. Not surprisingly, the amount of explosive materials that can either be made or stored in a school laboratory is also restricted.</p>
	<p pid="a.207.1/18">I have been following closely the introduction of the new ways of teaching science in the classroom, and particularly the 21st century science syllabuses, of which there are a number. I recently visited two schools in Bolton&mdash;one in Turton and one in Westhoughton&mdash;that are teaching science using the new syllabuses and I was impressed by the enthusiasm of the two young teachers and the students I observed. I was also impressed by the way in which those teachers had prepared their lessons and I witnessed good use of modern whiteboards, plenty of interactive handouts, a laptop computer in front of every science student and excellent use of the large amount of material that is available on the internet.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.210.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.210.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.210.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.210.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.211.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.211.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.211.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.211.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.211.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1432" speakername="Brian Iddon" colnum="211"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080115/halltext/80115h0005.htm#08011594000650">
	<p pid="a.211.1/1">Indeed. I agree and I shall produce some figures in conclusion to underline what the hon. Gentleman has said.</p>
	<p pid="a.211.1/2">Let me turn now to another aspect of science teaching that has been on the wane in recent decades&mdash;field trips. Unfortunately, initial teacher education does not show fledgling teachers how to exploit the wealth of knowledge in the outside laboratory. I pay tribute to the Field Studies Council for the work that it does in that respect. It not only promotes outdoor education through its publications and lobbying, but walks the talk, too, by running 17 field centres in some outstanding parts of the country, such as Malham Tarn, in north Yorkshire, Brockhole, near Windermere in the Lake district, and Flatford Mill, which was made famous by Constable's painting.</p>
	<p pid="a.211.1/3">I still remember being taken into the countryside by my primary school teachers, who helped me to identify wild flowers, insects, birds, wild animals and trees. For a while, I was the proud owner of a flower press and I had quite a good collection of dried and pressed wild flowers, which I was able to identify.</p>
	<p pid="a.211.1/4">An education officer at the London outdoor education centre has remarked:</p>
	<p pid="a.211.1/5" class="indent">&quot;All we see these days are primary schools. We never see science groups from local secondary schools any more&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.211.1/6">The Government have argued that outdoor education is thriving in our schools, but the FSC's evidence suggests otherwise. More than 96 per cent. of GCSE science pupils will not experience a residential field trip, while nearly half of all A-level biology students will do no field work, with the possible exception of half a day's experience near their school.</p>
	<p pid="a.211.1/7">Last year, the FSC and the ASE jointly published a report on the training of pre-service teachers to support the development of outdoor teaching in secondary science education. The report contains nine recommendations on how to halt the decline in the use of field trips to teach science outdoors and, inter alia, lists the barriers to such teaching, such as the lack of minimum requirements, the failure to recognise the potential of fieldwork, the lack of training among initial teacher education tutors and teacher mentors, the lack of a communication and organisational structure to promote fieldwork, the low status awarded to fieldwork by Ofsted inspectors and, inevitably, the cost of field trips. Let us hope that the new standards set by the Training and Development Agency for Schools will be fully implemented by those responsible for initial teacher education, and that the Malham protocol, a set of minimum standards for teaching science outdoors within ITE, will be adopted by the TDA.</p>
	<p pid="a.211.1/8">In May the Institute of Biology published &quot;Dissection in Schools&quot;, a survey funded by the Association of the British Pharmaceutical Industry. Eighty-five per cent. of the respondents believe that less dissection work has been carried out in schools since 1986, when the new national curriculum and compulsory science at GCSE were introduced. Time pressures because of the current nature of the curriculum, costs, doubt about what activities are permissible, difficulties in acquisition of materials, a shortage of skilled technicians and the need for a resource handbook were commonly cited reasons for that decline. Again, there appear to be problems with ITE. If dissection is not a minimum requirement of the curriculum, it will not be carried out by the teachers.</p>
	<p pid="a.211.1/9">There are, again, incorrect perceptions of health and safety regulations. For example, contrary to a commonly held belief, cheek cell and saliva sampling is permitted, as long as students work only with their own cheek cell and saliva samples, the cotton buds and disposable cups are disposed of appropriately, and the glass slides are sterilised in a chlorine-based disinfectant. The taking of blood samples is not ruled out either, providing that the COSHH regulations are adhered to. Dissections of eyes can be carried out, but there are some rather complicated restrictions. There can be regional differences. Unlike those in the rest of Britain, pupils in Northern Ireland cannot take samples of their own cheek cells, saliva or blood. Dissection was encouraged in only 69 per cent. of the institutions surveyed. Only 17 per cent. of respondents cited dissections as a cause of students being turned off science. There appear to be increasing concerns, too, about animal welfare. The Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs has recently introduced requirements about the disposal of live material, which has caused biology teachers some concern.</p>
	<p pid="a.211.1/10">Dissection is, however, regarded as bringing science to life. It enhances a student's knowledge and understanding, makes it possible to understand the complexity and efficiency of animal anatomy and engenders an appreciation of the fragility of tissues. Students can relate animal anatomy to an understanding of how their own bodies work and dissection improves hand-eye co-ordination. Ethical issues about the use of live animals in research can of course be discussed in the context of dissection.</p>
	<p pid="a.211.1/11">When the Connexions service was established, its staff concentrated, unfortunately, more on those with learning difficulties than on the most able pupils. Consequently, high-quality schools career advice failed to reach many of the most gifted pupils, who were unable to realise the breadth and excitement of the careers that can be pursued with a science, technology, engineering or mathematics background. Regrettably, according to the report of the House of Lords Select Committee on Science and Technology, &quot;Science Teaching in Schools&quot;, few careers advisers have a STEM background. In any case, the sciences are perceived to be difficult by teachers and pupils alike, and schools consequently adopt &quot;softer&quot; options to take their schools high in the league tables, which now seem to determine which schools are good or bad. In &quot;Next Steps&quot;, the Government largely neglected careers advice, and it has now become urgent that they address the deficit in good careers advice for the most able students.</p>
	<p pid="a.211.1/12">By 2014, according to the National Endowment for Science, Technology and the Arts, the demand for science and technology professionals will increase by 20 per cent. compared to an increase in demand for all other occupations of only 4 per cent. That is the point that <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1488" name="Bob Spink">the hon. Member for Castle Point (Bob Spink)</phrase> was making. A recent study of our 15 year-olds' ability by the Programme for International Student Assessment of the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development revealed that British teenagers have slipped 10 places in six years to a lowly 14th place in the world's most prestigious league table charting scientific knowledge among schoolchildren.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.213.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.213.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.213.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.213.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.213.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1432" speakername="Brian Iddon" colnum="213"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080115/halltext/80115h0005.htm#08011594000652">
	<p pid="a.213.1/1">I am glad that the Minister has made that point, because I did not know that, and neither, obviously, did many people who have made the comparison.</p>
	<p pid="a.213.1/2">In <i>The Guardian</i> of <phrase class="date" code="2007-12-03">3 December 2007</phrase>, Dr Richard Pike, who is the chief executive of the Royal Society of Chemistry, said:</p>
	<p pid="a.213.1/3" class="indent">&quot;The dramatic slippage of the UK to the 14th place in the league for science teaching should be seen against the backdrop of numerous, often failed, uncoordinated initiatives, and a reluctance within the whole community to stand back and look at education from a holistic viewpoint&quot;&mdash;</p>
	<p pid="a.213.1/4">which is what I have tried to do this morning.</p>
	<p pid="a.213.1/5">I have tried to highlight the decline in what are regarded as important aspects of science teaching, and give possible reasons for that decline, which I hope that the Minister will address in future planning of science education. There is a lot of goodwill out there, in industry and commerce and in the teaching fraternity, and we need to tap it to the advantage of all those students who show an interest in pursuing a science career. Let us make science teaching exciting again in the classroom, as it once was, in my day.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.214.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.214.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.214.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.214.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.214.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1744" speakername="Ian Gibson" colnum="214"  time="011:26:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080115/halltext/80115h0005.htm#08011594000654">
	<p pid="a.214.1/1">I am delighted to take part in this debate once again. We have pushed this issue half a dozen times, because it is recognised as important, and I shall quote something from the Sainsbury report about why that is. I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1432" name="Brian Iddon">the Member for Bolton, South-East (Dr. Iddon)</phrase> on once more bringing the matter into the arena of debate. We have similar backgrounds, except that I was in Scotland and he was in England. We always get more money in Scotland, for some reason&mdash;or perhaps we use it better; who knows? That is another argument, for another time and place. Nevertheless, Scottish science has produced some excellence, as has English science, and we compete well in the world.</p>
	<p pid="a.214.1/2">Lord David Sainsbury has just produced a document entitled &quot;The Race to the Top: A Review of Government's Science and Innovation Policies&quot;, in which he talks first about the need for a</p>
	<p pid="a.214.1/3" class="indent">&quot;major campaign to enhance the teaching of science and technology&quot;,</p>
	<p pid="a.214.1/4">including raising the number of qualified science teachers, increasing the number of young people studying triple science, improving careers advice, establishing a national science competition and rationalising the many schemes to inspire young people to take up careers in science and engineering. Indeed, although we are worried about the future, there is much going on in different localities, about which I shall say something in a minute.</p>
	<p pid="a.214.1/5">Lord Sainsbury also points out in his review that although it is not clear where in the future the jobs will necessarily come for scientists, there will be many opportunities for UK companies, and therefore there is a need for science education and research. New industries will appear in</p>
	<p pid="a.214.1/6" class="indent">&quot;aerospace, pharmaceuticals, biotechnology, regenerative medicine, telemedicine, nanotechnology, the space industry, intelligent transport systems, new sources of energy, creative industries, computer games, the instrumentation sector, business and financial services, computer services and education.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.214.1/7">That is not a bad challenge for a small island and we play, I think, quite a hard-hitting role in those fields internationally now. We are of course worried about what will happen in the future, as we watch the emerging economies of other countries, such as China, with a university in every street, everyone getting a degree and large numbers of people flooding through. One need only go to Singapore to see scientific excellence being developed. The journey to such developments starts with early school days and continues through university and into the job market, whether the jobs are in research or industry.</p>
	<p pid="a.214.1/8">I want particularly to mention the field of cancer. In the 10 years I have been in the House, that has been a major commitment for me. I have seen how well things have developed through Government support. There is now a cancer reform strategy, which recognises that science is moving on and driving a need for new policies. That is very important. We know that more will happen in that context. For example, personalised medicine will be a key factor in a world in which we target drugs to people to the advantage of their genetics, around which are many issues, such as how drugs are produced and paid for, the reaction of companies, the kind of partnerships that we adopt and how academia and the industry can merge, in which regional development agencies and many other organisations will have a role to play.</p>
	<p pid="a.214.1/9">I am told that in the cancer field&mdash;this comes from anecdotes from a dinner party on Saturday night with consultant oncologists&mdash;many medics now have never seen a tumour. They might see one on a video screen, but they will not see one for real until they are thrust into their oncology work. In many ways I think that that is true across science. Many people no longer learn the kind of hard science that I had to do. I do not want to be too crude&mdash;I must watch my parliamentary language&mdash;but there is nothing like seeing a real heart throbbing, and operating or working on it, to get a feel for handling the job. It is no use just seeing it on the screen and saying, &quot;It will be all right on the night.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.214.1/10">Furthermore, as my hon. Friend said, it is no use students thinking that they know how things work in the world outside without actually seeing it. A generation of young people has been brought up watching Attenborough programmes, which I find fascinating. I watch big cat programmes and am amazed at how lions get chased by creatures that they fancied eating. Those educational relationships are good for young people and allow them to pick up on, and try to understand, the behavioural patterns of animals and plants, which they can reflect on to themselves. That is somewhat anthropomorphic, but is important because it gets them asking questions.</p>
	<p pid="a.214.1/11">Young people are stimulated by all sorts of things at a very early age. We have been talking about how different people are not working together or united, and about various initiatives and publications. I know of a nice book for young people, called &quot;Have a Nice DNA&quot;, by a friend of mine, Professor Balkwill, at Queen Mary's college. I also know of the school garden is pupils' new classroom project, which has helped pupils to build a willow tunnel, research life forms in the pond, and build a bird hide to watch wildlife, giving them first-hand experience of ecology. That project was not set up by a teacher, but by a science technician&mdash;a dying breed. A Committee that I used to chair once looked into patterns in schools on either side of the Scotland-England border and found that, in Scotland, technicians are still valued. They are the backroom people who prepare the experimental classes, ensure that the equipment is available and make noises if it is not. In a way, that also aids young people's education when experimenting in laboratories.</p>
	<p pid="a.214.1/12">I sometimes joke about a school in my area&mdash;Sprowston high school&mdash;that produces good drummers. In fact, one is marrying KT Tunstall, although I doubt if any Member here knows who she is&mdash;</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.216.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.216.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.216.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.216.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.216.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1744" speakername="Ian Gibson" colnum="216"  time="011:26:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080115/halltext/80115h0005.htm#08011594000656">
	<p pid="a.216.1/1">The Minister obviously does.</p>
	<p pid="a.216.1/2">I would much rather that the person marrying her was a scientist than a drummer&mdash;but there we go. It reflects the education in that school; the music department is well run, has all the necessary equipment and attracts young people. The science department could do the same, but its laboratories use those dull brown-topped wooden desks with &quot;Tony loves Cherie&quot; and other such messages scratched on them, because young bored people spend time listening but not really taking anything in.</p>
	<p pid="a.216.1/3">The school garden in Norwich that I mentioned is important and is really developing. One young person said of it:</p>
	<p pid="a.216.1/4" class="indent">&quot;It makes more sense actually seeing and touching things than reading about them in a textbook. We are even going to go to the junior school and help them with their own garden.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.216.1/5">My Committee found the same thing. That is the kind of experimentation that we want.</p>
	<p pid="a.216.1/6">Young people are also fascinated by boiling things and get a kick out of making colours in test tubes, as my hon. Friend the Member for Bolton, South-East said. I had a chemistry set as a child and remember applying to a medical school and saying, &quot;Ever since the days of my first chemistry set, I have been interested in understanding how the world works.&quot; However, that argument did not wash with the great deans of Edinburgh university, where applicants needed parents who went to the right school. But that is another story; hopefully those days are over, but I doubt it.</p>
	<p pid="a.216.1/7">Professor Balkwill is also developing, at Queen Mary's college, an outfit where a cell will be manufactured architecturally so that people can come in off the streets and get involved. I have always wondered why science and art museums do not mix. However, I shall come on to the interaction between science and the arts later. I do not have to tell Members about the fascination with dinosaurs and the Natural History museum, where people can learn what a dinosaur was and discuss, until the cows come home, how and why they died out.</p>
	<p pid="a.216.1/8">I have some other books with me. One is &quot;Why Can't I... Jump up to the Moon?: And Other Questions about Energy&quot;&mdash;perhaps the Minister will tell me why he cannot jump up to the moon&mdash;and another is &quot;Why Can't I... Sleep on a Bed of Bubbles?: And Other Questions about Materials&quot;. They have been written for young people, but do not seem to have got into the classroom to the extent that I think that they should have. I know, too, about an anthology of poetry and artwork around science by children from Rockland St Mary county primary school and Framingham Earl high school, which is just outside Norwich. It is quite brilliant how they developed poems around scientific structures seen down an electron microscope and so on. It is wonderful to see the interest in the questions and the enthusiasm that it generates. That happened because a young woman doing a postdoctoral fellowship at the John Innes centre decided to do it. She is a high-flyer in her research field, but wanted to put something back into the community because she could see that there was a need for it.</p>
	<p pid="a.216.1/9">We often talk about the shortage of teachers, but sometimes we could use people in universities, such as postdoctoral and PhD students, who are the lifeblood of research in this country. I learned that first-hand from Paul Nurse, who is one of our Nobel prize winners. They do all the work; they stimulate ideas, lecture among undergraduates and help them in practicals and so on. We should use that force, until we get the numbers that we need in physics, chemistry and biology. I speak from practical experience. I once went on a course to Murray house in Scotland for three months. I think that I passed, although I was told off for not wearing a tie&mdash;such is rebellion in Scotland. However, instead of teaching religion to a class, when I visited a school, I took the children outside to show them how to take corner and penalty kicks. I do not think that the two of us doing it were sacked, but we were moved on. Nevertheless, many stimulating activities can be undertaken.</p>
	<p pid="a.216.1/10">I shall move on from the enthusiasm in practical school classes to postgraduate and undergraduate students, who to some extent get a rough deal. They cannot always see a career in front of them, because of the limited number of grants, which can be for one or three years, but not for five years. That is changing gradually; bright young people who want to stay in science are being given a career structure, which is necessary in that field.</p>
	<p pid="a.216.1/11">Finally, one of the reasons why those students are giving up is that they cannot do exciting experiments on a Friday afternoon after they have been to the pub&mdash;hopefully not for too long. Nevertheless, they try things out&mdash;&quot;I wonder what would happen if...?&quot;. Science is about asking such questions. To a large extent, that has been taken out of their training. Research assessment exercises now require a safe pair of hands and safe experiments so that they can get the paper out. Much of the paper work is done by postgraduate students&mdash;although their names still appear last, after the senior professor and so on. They are not recognised properly in our society for their value to science education. We could do much more with them. Hopefully, at last, something will happen, because we have been talking about these things for some years. Things are happening in certain places&mdash;I gave a few examples&mdash;but not nationally.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.217.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.217.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.217.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1715" speakername="Mark Lancaster" colnum="217"  time="011:38:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080115/halltext/80115h0006.htm#08011594000657">
	<p pid="a.217.0/1">I intend to make the briefest of contributions. I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1432" name="Brian Iddon">the hon. Member for Bolton, South-East (Dr. Iddon)</phrase> on securing this very valuable debate and pay tribute to him for his lifetime's contribution to the world of science, which was reflected in his speech. I was delighted to be with him when the Royal Society of Chemistry presented him with the president's award for a lifetime's contribution to science. That was very well deserved.</p>
	<p pid="a.217.0/2">I declare an interest as a parliamentary adviser to the Royal Society of Chemistry. When I first came to this House, I thought that I had the honour of being the first Member of Parliament who was also a fireworks maker, which is rather appropriate on the 400th anniversary of Guy Fawkes' execution. However, I then discovered that the hon. Gentleman had beaten me to it; I understand that back in 1997 he dressed up as Guy Fawkes and blew up gunpowder in the Jubilee Room. I am not sure whether the Serjeant at Arms would let me do that, but I certainly intend to try. My plea to the Minister is, simply, let us make science fun again. It is certainly not his fault, but there has been a general decline for various reasons that I shall consider shortly. Science is not as fun as it used to be, and that has to be a crying shame.</p>
	<p pid="a.217.0/3">I am a lucky chap. We have discussed having chemistry sets when we were young, and my set was probably the best in the world. It was a firework factory. One of my earliest memories is as a young lad, peaking over my father's work bench to see him mixing wonderful coloured chemicals, and with a glint in his eye, he would take me with him to blow them up in the garden. We would bury them to see how big a hole we could create. My mother would be absolutely horrified when my father got slightly bored on a Friday afternoon, because he would give me the nod and we would creep out and blow holes in the garden. It was a wonderful way to start.</p>
	<p pid="a.217.0/4">I shall never forget doing Nuffield physics as an A-level student and being able to do practical experiments. Much of my A-level was practical, and that was the joy of Nuffield&mdash;going out into the school fields and firing tennis balls out of 3-in mortar tubes to investigate the optimum firing angle. I was very lucky, because the Lancaster household is a strange one, and all I had to do to get hold of gunpowder was to go the bread bin, where my father used to keep it. I also discovered through that practical process that although 45&deg; was the optimum angle to send one's tennis ball across the fields, it would go just as far if one put it at 60&deg; or 30&deg;. If one put it at 60&deg;, it went much higher and one could dislodge the tiles from the headmaster's roof. If one put it at 30&deg;, one could get it under the trees and bounce it off the windows. Those are the lessons that only practical science can teach us.</p>
	<p pid="a.217.0/5">There are no barriers preventing such experiments in the classroom, although I always remember the advice about pipettes and burettes and not to suck too hard because it might take the enamel off one's teeth, but it is important that we educate people. That is why the Royal Society of Chemistry's publication &quot;Surely that's Banned&quot; is so valuable. I encourage the Minister to try to get it to as broad an audience as possible.</p>
	<p pid="a.217.0/6">There are, however, practical barriers. The hon. Members for Bolton, South-East and for Norwich, North (Dr. Gibson) referred to the importance of having more or better laboratories in schools, and although I recognise that the Minister will probably tell us that the Government's building schools for the future initiative may go some way to address that concern, that better schools programme will not hit my constituency until 2013. He knows that my constituency faces considerable financial challenges already, and I am delighted that he has promised to do something about it. Generally, however, more must be done sooner.</p>
	<p pid="a.217.0/7">I ask the Minister to recognise also that science is a changing subject. It is vital that teachers receive the opportunity constantly to retrain, which is why it is slightly disappointing to discover that science teachers are not entitled to science-related continual professional development. That is another area for the Minister to examine. Indeed, I should tie that issue to the debate last week about equivalent or lower qualifications, about which the Minister knows I feel strongly because of its impact on the Open university. I ask him to talk to his ministerial colleagues and press the point that if the Government pursue the policy of withdrawing ELQ funding, it will have a significant impact on science teaching.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.219.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.219.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.220.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.220.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.223.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.223.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.223.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1389" speakername="Maria Miller" colnum="223"  time="011:59:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080115/halltext/80115h0007.htm#08011594000660">
	<p pid="a.223.0/1">I join other hon. Members in congratulating <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1432" name="Brian Iddon">the hon. Member for Bolton, South-East (Dr. Iddon)</phrase> on securing this important debate. He has contributed greatly to the discussion of science and maths in this place, and we have been privileged today to hear from parliamentarians from all parts of the House, who have brought into Parliament not just their expertise in science but their passion and enthusiasm for the future of science in our schools&mdash;none more so than my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1715" name="Mark Lancaster">the Member for North-East Milton Keynes (Mr. Lancaster)</phrase>. He gave us an exciting insight into his own childhood, including the keeping of gunpowder in the bread bin&mdash;not something that I shall mention to my own son&mdash;and, more importantly, into the practical physics and science experiments that he undertook, such as firing tennis balls at 45&deg; angles to see where they hit and how far they went. I am sure that he took a practical application of that into his career as a bomb disposal expert in the Army, and that his practical science experience came to good use in his military career.</p>
	<p pid="a.223.0/2">The importance of science is not to be underestimated. It is an important part of education, in the same way as history or modern languages, equipping the next generation to think about and deal with some of the most important issues facing the country&mdash;whether biofuels, energy, climate change, genetic modification or mapping the human genome. Those are all science-related issues, and we need young people, whether they are budding scientists or destined for other careers, to appreciate the importance that science has in all our lives.</p>
	<p pid="a.223.0/3">Of course, science also has a vital role in our economy. My constituency, in north Hampshire, has one of the largest centres of employment. The pharmaceutical industry is at the heart of the success of my constituency, so I know at first hand how important science is to local business employers. The Leitch report clearly says that the demand for science and technology professionals will increase by 18 to 30 per cent. between 2004 and 2014&mdash;far higher than for any other occupational group. As my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1488" name="Bob Spink">the Member for Castle Point (Bob Spink)</phrase> has pointed out, we cannot rely on overseas expertise to ensure that business needs are met, because those people can too easily return home, taking their skills with them.</p>
	<p pid="a.223.0/4">The hon. Member for Bolton, South-East focused on the importance of practical science, but the pathway to achieving high-quality practical science in our classrooms has to be through our teaching staff and teaching professionals within our schools. It will be difficult for the Minister to disagree that there is a crisis in science in our schools today. Many hon. Members have stated their concerns about science teaching in our schools and the ability of schools to secure specialist science teachers. We have heard figures on the shortfall in the number of specialist science teachers: only 19 per cent. of science teachers have specialisms in physics, and only 25 per cent. in chemistry. Indeed, one in four schools in the state sector do not have a specialist physics teacher. That is another issue of which I have first-hand experience of problems in my constituency.</p>
	<p pid="a.223.0/5">The failure to attract new science teachers is concerning, particularly given that many science teachers are nearing retirement. We must also make international comparisons. When one considers that 90 per cent. of teachers in China have some sort of science degree, one realises that, in this country, science simply is not as ingrained in the teaching of our young people as it is in our economic competitor countries. It is important for us to examine that issue and to hear from the Minister what he intends to do about it.</p>
	<p pid="a.223.0/6"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1546" name="Annette Brooke">The hon. Member for Mid-Dorset and North Poole (Annette Brooke)</phrase> spoke about the impact that the situation has had on the results achieved in schools, and on GCSE numbers. The number of young people who are able to take three separate sciences is low indeed: just 26 per cent. of comprehensive schools are able to offer the three sciences separately&mdash;clearly as a result of the shortfall in the number of specialist teachers. That has had a knock-on effect on the number of students able to study at A-level and a further knock-on effect on the number studying science at university. There has been a 40 per cent. fall in demand for undergraduate places in physics, and I know from my experience in south-east England that the physics department at the university of Reading, which provided an excellent opportunity for students in my area to study physics close to home, has recently closed.</p>
	<p pid="a.223.0/7">The Royal Society of Chemistry has warned that too many science students need remedial lessons when they arrive at university, which causes significant problems for university teachers. Most sobering of all, it says that 30 per cent. of university physics departments have closed since 1994, and that only 47 out of 125 universities now offer physics places. It is estimated that only six chemistry departments will be left by 2014.</p>
	<p pid="a.223.0/8">What has been the Government's response so far? We should not be surprised that it has been to set a target. The target is that by 2014, 25 per cent. of science teachers will have a physics specialism, and 31 per cent. a chemistry specialism. Those are admirable objectives, and I am sure that the Minister will touch on them in his remarks, but the royal society felt that those targets were somewhat short on detail when they were announced. Indeed, the Institute of Physics did not feel that there was a well-defined strategy in place for achieving the goals that the Government set out. Perhaps we should not be surprised that in the past decade, parliamentary answers obtained by my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1623" name="David Willetts">the Member for Havant (Mr. Willetts)</phrase> have revealed that, year on year, the Government have failed to meet their targets on the recruitment of more science teachers into this area, despite the considerable effort put into golden hellos and bursaries, which simply have not been hitting the targets on improving recruitment or other targets that the Government wanted to achieve.</p>
	<p pid="a.223.0/9">The most concerning statistics of all must be that 40 per cent. of science and maths teachers who qualified in 1999 were not teaching a year later, and that 50 per cent. were not teaching five years later. Those figures come from the royal society. Why are we not retaining the scientists whom we have enticed into the teaching profession? Perhaps the hon. Member for Bolton, South-East hit the nail on the head by making the lion's share of his speech about practical work, which brings science to life, not only for students but for teachers. He talked about his experiences, in his early years, when he got a chemistry set from his friend and undertook his own experiments, thus finding out how exciting science can be for young people. For me, the highlight of biology at school was dissecting a cow's eye, but I hear that, unfortunately, such dissections are not always offered in schools in my area.</p>
	<p pid="a.223.0/10">The practical role of science was highlighted in the House of Lords report as an essential component of effective science teaching. The Lords also picked up on the problem of health and safety inhibiting teaching. Several speakers, including the hon. Members for Mid-Dorset and North Poole and for Bolton, South-East, have discussed the conditions in laboratories. I share the concern of my hon. Friend the Member for North-East Milton Keynes that building schools for the future will not be available to many constituents until five years hence, which will be too late for the work that needs to be undertaken in our science laboratories.</p>
	<p pid="a.223.0/11">Science teachers might feel let down by the Government, because many students do not have basic English and maths when they reach secondary school, and that affects the teaching of science in schools. How does the Minister feel about that? Surely, if children do not have a grasp of basic English and maths, it will be next to impossible for them to access physics, chemistry and biology. Does he not share our concern that that is a fundamental issue and that the Government must start to take it far more seriously?</p>
	<p pid="a.223.0/12">I noted with interest that the Minister picked up on the fact that there have been some discussions on the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development rankings of the UK in science. I am sure that he is not complacent in that area at all, and that he is as concerned as Conservative Members are that, in absolute terms, China&mdash;one of the countries that we must keep in mind as a key competitor in the future&mdash;significantly outperformed the UK on science and maths in 2006. I would appreciate some thoughts from the Minister as to how he will reverse that situation in the coming years.</p>
	<p pid="a.223.0/13">The Opposition want specialist science to be taken seriously by the Government. Too little progress has been made on recruiting and retaining suitably qualified teachers for core academic science subjects. The Government need to share our pledge that all secondary school pupils capable of doing so should be able to do the individual science GCSEs if that is their choice. The hon. Member for Mid-Dorset and North Poole also picked up on that.</p>
	<p pid="a.223.0/14"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1744" name="Ian Gibson">The hon. Member for Norwich, North (Dr. Gibson)</phrase> mentioned the importance of firsthand experience for children in schools, and echoed many of the thoughts of other Members. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1756" name="Evan Harris">The hon. Member for Oxford, West and Abingdon (Dr. Harris)</phrase> discussed the importance of inspirational specialist teachers. There is a great deal of agreement on the issues that face us.</p>
	<p pid="a.223.0/15">Will the Minister pledge that students who wish to study individual sciences will be able to do so? When will the Government be able to meet their recruitment targets and perhaps make up the shortfall of the past decade? The Government's promise in the 2005 general election campaign of &pound;200 million for school science labs has not been delivered, much to the annoyance of some sectors. Given the declining number of science students, how will the Minister guarantee that building schools for the future money will actually be used to improve science labs in schools? What will he do to help more teachers access the regional science learning centres?</p>
	<p pid="a.223.0/16">Last but by no means least, will the Minister undertake a review of science teaching and take up some of the issues that the hon. Member for Bolton, South-East raised, to establish what can be done to enhance the excitement of teaching science in our schools? Science is the lifeblood and one of the most important aspects of the economy and the future of this country.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.226.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.226.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.227.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.227.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.227.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.227.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.230.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.230.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.230.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.230.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.231.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.231.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.232.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.232.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.232.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.232.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.232.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.232.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.232.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.232.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.233.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.233.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.233.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.233.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.233.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1778" speakername="Crispin Blunt" colnum="233"  time="012:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080115/halltext/80115h0008.htm#08011594000671">
	<p pid="a.233.1/1">I am grateful to my hon. Friend, whose intervention refers to my previous comment that the provision of public services in Surrey has proved to be an enormous challenge under the financial settlement that all the institutions in the county have received.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/2">On reflection, the merger between Crawley and Horsham NHS Trust and the East Surrey Healthcare NHS Trust was not a marriage made in heaven. As in many such mergers, reorganisation was required to provide the best services throughout the new trust's two district hospital sites and its other sites, but the principal sites were at Crawley and in east Surrey south of Redhill. The trust's proposals for reorganisation were broadly supported by all local MPs.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/3">The plan presented to Ministers in 1999 was that acute services, including major accident and emergency services and in-patient maternity services, should be co-located at the newer and less constrained East Surrey hospital. The plans were presented to the Department in 1999, but it took a year for approval to be given in June 2000 by the then Minister, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1411" name="Gisela Stuart">the hon. Member for Birmingham, Edgbaston (Ms Stuart)</phrase>. Ministers dictated that a review was to be established to produce recommendations on the long-term provision of secondary health care, including the prospect of a new hospital on another site at Pease Pottage, just outside Crawley, after 2020. That review was to be chaired by Peter Bagnall, and whatever its health merits, its overt political purpose was to address concerns in Crawley about the loss of the local accident and emergency department.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/4">Those conclusions would have meant the transfer of acute services from Crawley to East Surrey hospital. The closing of Crawley hospital's accident and emergency department would inevitably have been unpopular, but the professional consensus was that those changes were necessary, and I recall that <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1519" name="Laura Moffatt">the hon. Member for Crawley (Laura Moffatt)</phrase> was part of the consensus. However, the local papers in Crawley were not convinced and ran a strong campaign against Crawley hospital losing its acute services. In response, Ministers altered the terms of reference of Peter Bagnall's review of future hospital services to consider changes to be made by 2010, holding out the prospect of a new hospital 10 years earlier than previously planned. That was still not enough to placate the residents of Crawley.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/5">The hon. Member for Crawley lobbied the then Secretary of State, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1527" name="Alan Milburn">the right hon. Member for Darlington (Mr. Milburn)</phrase>, to postpone the transfer of services away from Crawley before the 2001 election. Meetings were held and a delegation taken to meet the Secretary of State for Health from which I and other local MPs were excluded. With weeks to go before the likely election in May 2001, which was later postponed to June 2001, the Secretary of State declared a moratorium on the clinical reconfiguration in March. That was despite that clinical configuration having commenced and maternity services having been moved. Paediatrics, ENT and gynaecology, all of which are associated with maternity, were left with twin-site working.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/6">The political nature of the decision was made explicit in a letter dated <phrase class="date" code="2008-02-28">28 February</phrase> from Sir William Wells, who was then chairman of the south-east regional office of the NHS, to the Secretary of State. He said:</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/7" class="indent">&quot;Although in practice there is little direct connection between the outcome of the Review and the need to move emergency services, in the short term this is not understood by the general public and in particular by Laura Moffatt's constituents and as a consequence she has asked whether there could be some moratorium on service moves until such time as the outcome of the review is known.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/8">In a draft statement, Sir William wrote:</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/9" class="indent">&quot;Laura Moffatt has agreed with the Secretary of State that, except on patient safety grounds, no further service reductions will take place at Crawley until the South East Surrey and North West Sussex Review is published in December 2001.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/10">It is indeed a novel departure for a Back-Bench MP and a Secretary of State to thrash out health policy, which will affect hundreds of thousands of people, in the interest of one constituency. I was not consulted, nor was I offered a meeting with Sir William Wells, despite the site of one of the two hospitals concerned being in my constituency; nor were my hon. Friends the Members for East Surrey (Mr. Ainsworth) and for Mole Valley and those with constituencies in the wider area, including my right hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1642" name="Francis Maude">the Member for Horsham (Mr. Maude)</phrase>, invited to agree the postponement with the Secretary of State. Let us not fool ourselves. We all know what was going on in the run-up to the 2001 general election. However, even if we accept that Ministers were entitled to make that decision to address local public concerns, it was a ministerial intervention.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/11">The Bagnall review was finally published in 2002 and turned out to be an expensive diversion. Its initial political purpose was to hold open the prospect of a new hospital, but it was then used as a pretext to delay the closure of Crawley's acute services. The continuation of twin-site working from 2001 came at an appalling cost both financially and in patient care. It cost the trust an estimated &pound;10 million a year. That was not rectified until the end of 2004 or, arguably, September 2006 when Crawley hospital was finally taken off the books of the local hospital trust. The Secretary of State's intervention cost some &pound;40million&mdash;or 1,600 heart transplants, 1,000 liver transplants or 50,000 cataract operations&mdash;which was a substantial majority of the deficit accumulated by the trust. Documents obtained through the Freedom of Information Act 2000 show that the trust believed that clinical safety would be imperilled by that suspension. I am very cautious about making specific links between cases and the moratorium, but coincidentally mortality rates in the borough of Reigate and Banstead rose during the suspension while they fell in Surrey as a whole.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/12">Peter Bagnall's team considered six options and, after an exhaustive process, recommended a new hospital at Pease Pottage. Bagnall's recommendation came with capital cost of &pound;278 million and an annual additional revenue requirement of &pound;42.9 million. His second choice, which was effectively the proposals put to ministers in 1999, envisaged a rise in the running costs of &pound;24.5 million and a capital cost of &pound;105 million. The strategic health authorities were then established by the Government and they immediately instructed health economists to review the Bagnall recommendations. In 2003, the recommendations were confirmed as unaffordable. The trust continued with the burden of a district general hospital that it did not want or need. In 2006, Crawley hospital was transferred to the local primary care trust.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/13">Finally, the board was in a position to do what it had wanted to do all along, which was to operate with one district general hospital. Robin Eve, an excellent non-executive director at the time, has made that clear in public. However, the board was prevented from managing the trust as it wished by the politics of Crawley and ministerial decisions.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/14">Today, we have arrived at Peter Bagnall's option 2, namely single site operation at East Surrey. That was the cheapest option in revenue terms, but it still required, on Bagnall's analysis, an enhancement of &pound;21.5 million in revenue and a capital enhancement of &pound;117 million by 2010. As far as I am aware, that capital expenditure has not been made despite it being the product of Bagnall's detailed review.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/15">Let me return to the management of the hospital after the imposition of the moratorium in 2001. The financial position deteriorated over the next four years until 2005 when the trust was in the worst financial position in the country. The management had undoubtedly been demoralised by the intervention in 2001, but it had the benefit of a talented and experienced chief executive, Ken Cunningham, who had been hand-picked to replace Isabel Gowan, who had herself been removed in 2000 when her accounting to meet Government performance targets had been rather too creative. The Minister will recall that in this period of the management of the health service, deficits were an increasing problem as managers tried to balance the imperative of meeting their performance targets with sustaining a balanced budget. The costs of providing public services in the south-east are well documented and those pressures, overlaid with this ministerial decision, made the trust impossible to manage, and led to the deficit running out of control.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/16">In February 2005, Ken Cunningham and his board agreed to leave, and Robin Eve had to be dismissed. They were replaced by an interim administration from the private sector under Anthony McKeever. His successor, Gary Walker from the private sector, was still dealing with a &pound;20-million-a-year deficit in January 2006, and it had become clear that it was not reasonable to expect the hospital to resolve this deficit alone. That position was shared by his successor, Gail Wannell, who took over in August of that year. By October, the principle cause of the deficit had been removed, as Crawley hospital was placed in the hands of Crawley PCT.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/17">Now, it could be the case that that string of NHS managers were all equally incapable of handling the crisis at the trust, and it could be that the turnaround teams brought in by the then Secretary of State, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1676" name="Patricia Hewitt">the right hon. Member for Leicester, West (Ms Hewitt)</phrase> were stymied by the incompetence or obstruction of the management, but that stretches coincidence too far. Ministerial decisions had caused the crisis, and no manager could balance the performance targets and the budget in those circumstances.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/18">The good news is that the trust is forecast to break even this year. However, there remains a debt of &pound;54.9 million to the Department. I would like the Minister to address that figure when she responds. The interest on this loan is currently costing the trust &pound;2.7 million. The trust's financial managers are also in the position of having to find &pound;2 million-plus every year from their budget to repay the loan, and they have to do that in the knowledge that for every year the loan remains, more money that should be invested in patient care is being used to pay interest.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/19">In seeking this debate, my hope is to ask the Minister to look into the very particular history of the debt incurred by the Surrey and Sussex Healthcare NHS Trust. If she does so, she will see that costly reorganisations were punctuated with costly delays&mdash;for reasons far outside the control of the trust. Ministers could have enabled the reorganisation to begin in 1999, but the Department took a year to consider plans that had taken a year to create. Ministers suspended the reorganisation in progress in 2001. Previous ministerial decisions have contributed directly to the highest deficit in the country. Today's management should satisfy the Minister that the trust is becoming financially sound. The current management are bringing the trust on to a solid financial footing. The financial improvement, however, has come at a price. My constituents and I and my hon. Friends the Members for East Surrey and for Mole Valley are beginning to see a rising tide of concern about the clinical care and performance of the hospital. My impression is that the obsessive concentration on achieving financial goals has taken the current management's eye off the performance goals in a way that runs counter to the position that was developed under Ken Cunningham. That is the area in which I would like the Minister to show real faith in the trust, and to put the needs of patients first.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/20">Without this loan, the trust would be in a position to address the problems in its accident and emergency department that have played such a part in the weak scores ascribed to it by the Healthcare Commission. If the Department writes off this debt, the Trust can at last move on after nearly a decade of instability and uncertainty. The alternative is that my constituents, those of my hon. Friends, and those of the hon. Member for Crawley will continue to be served by a hospital that is paying debts imposed on it by political decisions. I have seen the very debilitating effects of a management being constrained from doing the right thing. The consequences today are that the patients served by this hospital could be enjoying nearly &pound;5 million a year invested in improving services and the prospect of a management delivering further improvements under foundation status. That is quite apart from the &pound;117 million of capital investment that was identified as required by Peter Bagnall in 2002.</p>
	<p pid="a.233.1/21">Timing is everything. This year the health service is in surplus. I urge the Minister to use this opportunity to examine the case and to write off the deficit of this trust, which was imposed in unique and not very creditable circumstances.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.237.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.237.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.237.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.237.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.237.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.237.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.238.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.238.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.238.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.238.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.238.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.238.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.238.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.238.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.239.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.239.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.240.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.240.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.240.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.240.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.242.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.242.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.242.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.242.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.243.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.243.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.246.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.246.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.247.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.247.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.247.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.247.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.248.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.248.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.249.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.249.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.250.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.250.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.250.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.250.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.251.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.251.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.251.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.251.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.251.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.251.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.251.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.251.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.251.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.251.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.251.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.251.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.251.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.251.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.251.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.251.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.251.8" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.251.8" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.251.8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1554" speakername="Ian Pearson" speakeroffice="The Minister for Science and Innovation"  colnum="251"  time="013:46:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080115/halltext/80115h0011.htm#08011594000698">
	<p pid="a.251.8/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1905" name="Edward Vaizey">the hon. Member for Wantage (Mr. Vaizey)</phrase> on securing the debate, and welcome the opportunity to debate the Science and Technology Facilities Council. The STFC deals with some of the key research challenges of our time, and has a growing role in the innovation agenda. Its portfolio of activities is very wide ranging and includes, as the hon. Gentleman said, the Government's shareholding in the Diamond synchrotron at Harwell, which opened last year after being built to time, budget and specification. The STFC participates in major international research projects, such as the large Hadron collider at CERN&mdash;the European organisation for nuclear research&mdash;and funds research in UK universities.</p>
	<p pid="a.251.8/2">Government support for the science base remains strong. We shall be spending almost &pound;6 billion on research by 2010-11, which is made up of the science budget allocation and &pound;2 billion of funding to reach universities in England through the quality-related funding stream of the Higher Education Funding Council for England. We remain second only to the United States in global scientific excellence as measured by citations, and we have a stronger performance across the range of scientific disciplines than most other countries. Of course, we retain our lead over all G8 countries on scientific productivity measures.</p>
	<p pid="a.251.8/3">Many factors have contributed to the growth in UK economic productivity in the past decade, and the science and innovation measures that the Government have introduced, including the highly successful research and development tax credit for industry, and new bodies such as the National Endowment for Science, Technology and the Arts, are making a valuable contribution to science, technology and innovation. In addition, we are funding university knowledge transfer activities to the highest ever level. The higher education innovation fund will rise to &pound;150 million a year by the end of 2010-11, which will help universities further to develop the professional capability to undertake top quality knowledge transfer.</p>
	<p pid="a.251.8/4">The Science and Technology Facilities Council was created on <phrase class="date" code="2007-04-01">1 April 2007</phrase> by merging the former Particle Physics and Astronomy Research Council and the Council for the Central Laboratory of the Research Councils. Any new organisation inevitably experiences a period of transition, and like all research councils the STFC faces challenging decisions to determine its priorities in the light of the resources available to it.</p>
	<p pid="a.251.8/5">To restate the basic facts of the matter, which have all too frequently been incorrectly reported in recent weeks, the STFC's budget will go up over the next three years; it will rise by 13.6 per cent. by the end of the comprehensive spending review period. The hon. Member for Wantage went into some detail on that point. However, he must recognise that there has been an overall increase, amounting to &pound;185 million, and a total budget for the STFC of &pound;1.9 billion. Of the seven research councils, the STFC has the second highest budget. We spend more on it than we do on medical research through the Medical Research Council.</p>
	<p pid="a.251.8/6">The STFC's delivery plan for the three years reflects its assessment of priorities across its activities, allowing it to manage its resources within the budget increases allocated to it. As the Secretary of State for Innovation, Universities and Skills, my right hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1827" name="John Denham">the Member for Southampton, Itchen (Mr. Denham)</phrase> explained to the House last week, the Government are fully committed to the Haldane principle, which protects the autonomy of research councils in deciding what research should be pursued. On occasion, I get the impression that the hon. Member for Wantage has not looked in detail at the STFC's delivery plan, from which I shall quote two short sentences to give a flavour of what I mean. The plan states:</p>
	<p pid="a.251.8/7" class="indent">&quot;The implementation of our strategy will require us to think in new ways about how we focus our investments.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.251.8/8">That is right. The STFC's mission is to promote and deliver world-class science and to achieve a step change in the economic impact that the UK derives from its science through knowledge exchange and the training of skilled people. However, that does not mean that nothing should ever change.</p>
	<p pid="a.251.8/9">The STFC has determined its highest priorities. The delivery plan states:</p>
	<p pid="a.251.8/10" class="indent">&quot;To accommodate the major facilities coming on line and create sufficient financial flexibility to enable us to pursue some existing high priority planned programmes and new opportunities, we will implement a substantial programme of organisational restructuring.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.251.8/11">I accept that point. The STFC is making its own decisions in its delivery plan about its new and highest priorities. We believe that, based on its assessments of the science, and in accordance with the Haldane principle, the STFC should make those decisions.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.253.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.253.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.253.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.253.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.253.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.253.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.253.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.253.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.253.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.253.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.253.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.253.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15a.256.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-01-15b.256.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

