<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.73.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.73.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.73.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.73.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.73.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.73.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.73.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.73.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.73.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.73.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.75.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.75.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.75.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.75.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.75.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.75.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.76.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.76.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.76.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.76.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.76.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.76.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.76.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.76.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.76.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.76.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.77.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.77.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.77.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.77.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.77.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.77.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.77.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.77.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.78.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.78.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.79.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.79.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.79.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.79.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.79.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.79.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.79.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1424" speakername="Joan Humble" colnum="79"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0002.htm#09042266000445">
	<p pid="a.79.2/1">My hon. Friend anticipates the conclusion of my speech, because I shall make exactly that point, and agree with what the commissioner says in her summary of her conclusions.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/2">Dr. Atkins reports that a 2005 survey found that 42 per cent. of servicewomen felt there was a problem with sexual harassment. More than two thirds of women interviewed reported experiencing adverse sexual behaviour ranging from unwelcome comments to criminal assault in the previous year; 15 per cent. reported having a &quot;particularly upsetting experience&quot;. On <phrase class="date" code="2008-02-21">21 February 2008</phrase>, in response to a question at column 859W, the Ministry of Defence reported that only 32 complaints of sexual harassment and eight of sexual discrimination in the armed forces had been received in 2006-07. That is startling evidence that under-reporting is rife. I agree with the commissioner that robust reporting systems should be available to support the complaints process. It is difficult to make decisions about management procedures and future policy without reliable statistical evidence. That should be available from unit level to the highest echelons of the services.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/3">Dr. Atkins draws eight main conclusions and bases her 17 recommendations on them. The Service Complaints Commissioner regards timeliness of handling and communicating complaints as a critical aspect of provision but finds current performance &quot;generally poor&quot;. She makes recommendations on timetable target-setting, use of specialist equality investigation teams and measures to ensure effective communication with the complainant and the person who is complained about.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/4">I should like the Minister to address a point about allegations of bullying. When soldiers are being bullied or perceive that they are at risk they frequently need protection, and that must be prompt. The findings of the Surrey police so-called fifth report into incidents at Deepcut barracks between 1995 and 2002 provide a wealth of information about the internal service culture on the camp at the time. It is well known that the police investigation of the conduct of training instructor Leslie Skinner led to a successful prosecution. However, Surrey policy say that not one of the 13 alleged victims had felt confident enough to access any of the welfare services, confidential information lines, faith-based counsellors or senior officers that should have been able to provide redress.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/5">In my capacity as chair of the all-party group on army deaths, I have been told by concerned parents and groups such as Daniel's Trust that recruits who are being bullied or who fear that they are risk of bullying believe that they have no option but to escape immediate risk by going AWOL. What steps will the Minister take to assure recruits who feel under threat of bullying that their safety can be guaranteed and that action can taken without delay?</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/6">The Service Complaints Commissioner states:</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/7" class="indent">&quot;There is a need for more ownership and proactive management of complaints at the heart of command&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/8">I wish to make two points about that. First, I want to see a culture change in the armed services, and Parliament has a critical role to play in that.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/9">The commissioner finds that too few servicemen and women have the confidence to speak out when treated badly. All service personnel should feel able to voice their concerns if they are victim to bullying, discrimination or harassment. There should be an open and honest environment for everyone. Complainants should not be seen as troublemakers. They should be supported, not shunned. Many feel that making a complaint will impact negatively on their career, and there is evidence that some wait until they leave the services before making a complaint.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/10">The enlightened employer should encourage feedback and protect whistleblowers who act in the public interest. The environment that pertains in the armed services clearly presents a greater challenge for the exercise of that responsibility, but I invite the Minister to join me in asserting that the greater risk of maintaining a culture of silence and complicity requires that solutions are found.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/11">The second point is this: the commissioner should be given greater assistance in developing a flexible approach to what should be regarded as a complaint. Why should the evidence given and the allegations made by the BBC about bullying at Catterick not be given the formal status of a complaint requiring investigation? The commissioner is required to receive communications from a Member of Parliament on behalf of service personnel. Does such a communication constitute a formal complaint? If not, why not? Dr. Atkins refers in her report to receiving letters from Members of Parliament. Will the Minister assure me that he is routinely informed of serious incidents, and that commanding officers are required to ensure that a death in barracks is reported to the commissioner within 24 hours?</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/12">Dr. Atkins concludes that the focus of the service complaints system, which is to provide individual redress, must be broadened to take account of the need to address failure and to learn from it. If mistakes are identified, the system should provide a means by which they can be addressed. Complainants need to be secure in the knowledge that they will be treated seriously and well, and that complaints should result in organisational improvement. There should be evidence to show that once complaints are proved, changes are made. That is similar to the direction taken by the Government in their proposals for coroner law reform. The commissioner makes specific recommendations, but I wonder whether the Minister, when responding to the debate, will find a form of words to endorse the dual purpose approach that she advocates.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/13">The Service Complaints Commissioner reports her wish to promote greater awareness of the existence and role of her office. I understand the difficulty of achieving a satisfactory level of recognition in the first year; the Irish ombudsman found a similar time lag. Although that guarantee of awareness will ultimately show the commissioner's effectiveness in meeting her objectives, I believe we all have a role to play. The Minister should draw up a plan to promote awareness and to ensure that we have parliamentary time to discuss it.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/14">In my role as chair of the all-party group on army deaths, I am keenly aware of the work of bereaved families in trying to prevent the children of others falling victim to the same fate. If those families have confidence in the role of the commissioner, they will willingly promote her services. I bring to the attention of the House an initiative taken by Debra Williams, whose son Gavin was beasted to death at Lucknow barracks in 2006. Debra used her son's story to urge others to work together to prevent future loss of life. Her website&mdash;stopbeastingsinthearmy.com&mdash;provides information and advice for families who think that their children may be at risk. It is important to find a way to give victims a voice in the process of creating greater awareness. The commissioner is already in touch with a number of such groups, but MPs and the Government could provide more help.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/15">The commissioner concludes that there is inconsistency of practice on the handling of complaints across and within the services. She also believes that the lack of expertise in handling complaints is a common cause of failings. Can the Minister confirm that resources will be made available to monitor the system effectively, and to identify priority areas for improvement? Will he agree to review guidance to deal with the confusion caused by the different procedures required for equality and diversity complaints, and complaints about other matters?</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/16">When complaints about bullying and harassment arise in the public domain, the response of the MOD press office is sometimes too defensive. The standard approach of affirming the policy of zero tolerance towards bullying is well meaning but sometimes empty. The implication is that the existence of the policy has eradicated the problem. It would be better if the position was restated as a tri-service commitment to work towards the elimination of bullying and harassment, while ensuring that the Service Complaints Commissioner has been notified.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/17">The commissioner argues that a system of complaints works best if the complaint is about a matter within the scope of command of the armed services, and recommends that the service secretariats should review the handling of complaints that arise outside the scope of the chain of command. Her report concludes that the complaints system is geared to work at the top levels and not at the lowest appropriate level, and it makes specific recommendations in order to address that imbalance. Finally, Dr. Atkins finds that the complaints system is accessible in theory but beset by barriers in practice. That is also the prime concern of bereaved families and those who contact anti-bullying organisations.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/18">The Royal British Legion has been at the forefront of the campaign to give new meaning and substance to the military covenant. I believe that an open and transparent system for investigating complaints, and for making effective redress and institutional response to identified failure, must be at the heart of the Government's support for service personnel.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/19">This is the Service Complaints Commissioner's first report, and she is clearly describing work in progress. In that first year, Dr. Atkins was contacted by 193 people, and I have no doubt that more will come forward this year. Her conclusions and recommendations mark out a method that will establish a workable baseline from which future progress can be gauged and accurately assessed. The commissioner's proposals are carefully constructed as a coherent framework, and I urge the Government to respond to the block of recommendations as a whole.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.2/20">This will not be our last debate on accountability and oversight of the armed services. Failure to address these issues will undermine the ability of Her Majesty's armed services to deliver the effective and efficient service that we need. Oversight is an aspect of good governance that we must get right. We have a responsibility to continue the debate, to learn from experience and take the process forward. I place on the record my thanks to the Service Complaints Commissioner, who has done an excellent job in the role that Parliament gave her. I am sure that we will discuss the nature of that role at greater length as she produces many more reports.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.82.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.82.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.83.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.83.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.83.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1424" speakername="Joan Humble" colnum="83"  time="010:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0002.htm#09042266000447">
	<p pid="a.83.0/1">I am on the record as saying in earlier debates on this matter that the training that our armed services receives is different from that received by someone in civilian life doing a civilian job. Dr. Atkins, when she gave evidence to the Select Committee on her first report, also recognised that point, saying that there is a difference between training in the armed services and training to work in Sainsbury's. I agree with her. She also said that we need a fair complaints system, because otherwise there would just be a moaning system, and we cannot have that. If people have a complaint, it needs to be looked at.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.84.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.84.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.84.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1926" speakername="James Gray" colnum="84"  time="010:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0002.htm#09042266000448">
	<p pid="a.84.0/1">The hon. Lady makes my point very much better than I did, and she is, of course, absolutely right.</p>
	<p pid="a.84.0/2">The second caveat is this: the armed services have always had an extremely good complaints system. In my experience of the armed services&mdash;as chairman of the all-party group on the Army, a former Territorial Army soldier and an MP with quite a large number of servicemen in my constituency&mdash;by and large, the regiment, or RAF Lyneham, which is also in my constituency, go out of their way to address problems as they arise. They do not want these things to happen, and when an allegation of bullying or harassment is made, the families officer in particular goes out of their way to discover the truth. One must also bear in mind that an allegation of bullying or harassment is not necessarily the same thing as bullying or harassment. Very often, an allegation might not hold up under scrutiny. None the less, I accept the commissioner's role, which is a particularly useful one, and I can think of quite a number of constituency cases in which I was glad to have her in the background.</p>
	<p pid="a.84.0/3">I had a slight difficulty, however, with one part of the hon. Lady's contribution. She suggested that the role laid down in the 2006 Act for the commissioner to scrutinise the armed services complaints procedure&mdash;that is really what it says in the Act&mdash;should be extended to a generalised investigation of the circumstances surrounding an otherwise unexplained death of an armed serviceman. Like us all, the hon. Lady is very concerned about the circumstances surrounding the very unfortunate deaths in Deepcut. That was a more or less unique set of circumstances. The original Select Committee report that led to the establishment of the commissioner was particularly concerned about Deepcut.</p>
	<p pid="a.84.0/4">Leaving Deepcut to one side, however, should we accept the principle that the role of the commissioner is to investigate all armed services deaths where no other explanation is known? In a number of cases, that might be sensible&mdash;when a person dies from beasting, in the example that the hon. Lady gave, or when there is an unexplained death in barracks. Such cases might well be worthy of further investigation by the commissioner if there is the suspicion of improper behaviour by the armed services, but I believe&mdash;I am ready to be corrected&mdash;that by far the largest number of armed services deaths are caused by road traffic accidents. In such cases I presume that the commissioner would have no role&mdash;unless the equipment or vehicle was defective, I suppose.</p>
	<p pid="a.84.0/5">That argument could be developed further. I mentioned earlier the tragic deaths of 10 servicemen in a Hercules XV179 in Baghdad in 2004 or 2005. A High Court case is pending. The families are suing the Ministry of Defence, because it did not fit foam suppressant in the wing tank of the Hercules aircraft. That is a matter for the High Court, and we cannot discuss it here. The coroner reviewed the case very carefully and came out heavily against the MOD. However, the notion that the commissioner might act on behalf of those families would seem to cut across the High Court, which is considering the matter, and the coroner, who produced an extremely critical report and said that the MOD was badly at fault. There was a similar case involving a Nimrod. For a third authority&mdash;a lady with no particular back-up or support&mdash;to throw her two pennies' worth into such an extremely complicated and difficult inquiry would be plain wrong.</p>
	<p pid="a.84.0/6">Establishing an independent ombudsman to do precisely what the coroner ought to be doing, merely because the hon. Lady has a number of complaints about the way in which the coronial system works, would seem to be a diversion of effort. The Coroners and Justice Bill is being considered in the other place, where I hope the point about barristers at inquests will be taken into account. There is something to be said for that. Surely, however, if there is something wrong with the way in which families are handled in the coronial system&mdash;I made this point during Second Reading and the Committee stage of the Bill&mdash;that is an argument for improving the coronial system. The notion of introducing a third organisation&mdash;the commissioner&mdash;to make up for perceived deficiencies in the coronial system or regimental chain of command seems administratively complicated.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.85.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.85.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.85.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1720" speakername="Lembit Öpik" colnum="85"  time="010:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0003.htm#09042266000449">
	<p pid="a.85.0/1">The hon. Gentleman apparently fails to understand that the coroner is not a detective. The coroner establishes the cause of death, but that does not mean that the coroner's report can identify why that cause of death occurred. Does he not understand that those of us who believe that young recruits were murdered at Deepcut Army barracks do not expect the coroner to be able to prove that point? That was explained by Nicholas Blake QC, when he called for either the full disclosure of the Devon and Cornwall police report into the Surry police handling of those death, or a full independent public inquiry. Does the hon. Gentleman disagree with Nicholas Blake?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.85.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.85.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.85.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.85.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.85.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.85.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.86.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.86.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.86.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1424" speakername="Joan Humble" colnum="86"  time="010:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0003.htm#09042266000453">
	<p pid="a.86.0/1">The hon. Gentleman misinterprets what I said. I thought that I had clarified my point in answer to his hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1922" name="Andrew Murrison">the Member for Westbury (Dr. Murrison)</phrase>. I am not asking for the commissioner to be a separate investigating body. I am pointing out deficiencies in the existing system, some of which are being addressed through the Coroners and Justice Bill. Questions relating to boards of inquiry and their link in to the coroners' system have not been properly addressed. The Government have already said that the complaints commissioner should be notified of a death; I am simply asking that she be kept informed of the progress of the investigation of that death. Surely the hon. Gentleman agrees with me that if a pattern is emerging across a series of deaths of which the commissioner and the armed forces should be aware, she should report on that? Not all road traffic accidents are the same: some might have a cause of which she and the army should be aware and on which they should act.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.86.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.86.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.86.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.86.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.86.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.86.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.86.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.86.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.86.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1650" speakername="Greg Pope" colnum="86"  time="010:08:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0003.htm#09042266000457">
	<p pid="a.86.4/1">Before I call <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1720" name="Lembit Öpik">the hon. Member for Montgomeryshire (Lembit &Ouml;pik)</phrase>, may I remind hon. Members that it is customary for us to begin the winding up speeches at half-past 10?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.87.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.87.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.87.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1720" speakername="Lembit Öpik" colnum="87"  time="010:24:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0003.htm#09042266000458">
	<p pid="a.87.0/1">I accept and acknowledge your guidance, Mr. Pope.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.0/2">I am standing here because, for about seven years, I have been trying to clarify why Cheryl James, the daughter of my constituents Des and Doreen James, died at Deepcut barracks. I am left in little doubt that she was murdered and that there has been a systemic cover-up of her murder and probably the murder of three other recruits at that Army camp.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.0/3">My frustration with the situation arises from the fact that, at every turn, it seems that the Army and, to an extent, the police have been quite happy to conspire to cover up the circumstances of those deaths. My direct response to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1926" name="James Gray">the hon. Member for North Wiltshire (Mr. Gray)</phrase> is that no coroner would be able to get to the heart of the matter as an independent and effective Service Complaints Commissioner could. He fails to understand that a coroner is not able to exercise the authority to establish whether systemic bullying, or nefarious practices that lead directly to the death of recruits, are going on at an Army barracks. The coroner is simply required to establish the cause of death, and not why the victim suffered those causes. It is for that reason that we need to examine the reach of the powers of the Service Complaints Commissioner, as <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1424" name="Joan Humble">the hon. Member for Blackpool, North and Fleetwood (Mrs. Humble)</phrase> has said.</p>
	<p pid="a.87.0/4">I am astounded that, after all these years, we still have not got full disclosure of the facts pertaining to the Deepcut deaths. The only reason that we have made any progress at all is that we have persisted in trying to expose the murders. I remember the day I was attempting to force the Government to respond to an urgent question regarding the deaths at Deepcut when, lo and behold, the MOD Minister, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1976" name="Adam Ingram">the right hon. Member for East Kilbride, Strathaven and Lesmahagow (Mr. Ingram)</phrase>, decided to make a statement to launch the Nicholas Blake inquiry. Naively I thought that the inquiry would be objective and would lead to progress, but, sadly, it seems to have been as big a sham as the rest of the process. That is why it is necessary that we to look closely at the powers of the Service Complaints Commissioner and decide whether those powers are sufficient to get to the heart of cases such as those at Deepcut. In my last exchange with the Minister, he brushed me off by saying that it was not necessary or appropriate for him to respond in detail to the question that I asked on the Floor of the House. He implied that I was a conspiracy theorist. Well, I am a conspiracy theorist because I believe that there has been a conspiracy to cover up four deaths at Deepcut Army barracks. <i>[</i><i>Interruption.</i><i>]</i></p>
	<p pid="a.87.0/5">The Minister for the Armed Forces is clearly entertained by this, but I can tell him that the parents are not. Des James is one of the most reasonable and circumspect individuals whom I have had the honour to represent. I am sorry to tell the Minister that Des James has no faith in the state's ability to investigate itself when individuals are murdered within state structures. Mr. James recently saw a play at the Tricycle theatre that covered those very points. When the Minister's predecessor was invited to attend the play, he sent a message to Des James that said:</p>
	<p pid="a.87.0/6" class="indent">&quot;I have no wish to see the play because I believe it will not be balanced and will reflect an all too painful analysis.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.87.0/7">In another e-mail, he said that he believed the play would be</p>
	<p pid="a.87.0/8" class="indent">&quot;strong on polemic and weak on objective analysis.&quot;</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.88.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.88.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.88.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.88.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.88.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1720" speakername="Lembit Öpik" colnum="88"  time="010:24:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0003.htm#09042266000460">
	<p pid="a.88.1/1">I can show the Minister the text that was sent to Des James. Is that the sympathy that we can expect from the Government? How on earth is there any consistency between the alleged empathy with the plight of parents who have lost their offspring within the military system that the Minister expresses and comments such as those are sent directly to one of the parents of a deceased child?</p>
	<p pid="a.88.1/2">I have two specific requests to make. Will the Minister tell me whether he is certain that the four who died at Deepcut Army barracks were not murdered? Will he tell us on the record that they were not murdered? Secondly, why on earth is it that, so much time after the Nicholas Blake inquiry, we still have not had an independent public inquiry into those deaths? The Minister will recall that Nicholas Blake said that, if the Devon and Cornwall police report into Surrey police's handling of the deaths at Deepcut Army barracks was not made public, we should have a full, independent public inquiry. That is on the record, but the report has not been published, nor have we had the inquiry. When will the Minister ensure that one or other of those takes place?</p>
	<p pid="a.88.1/3">I have tried time and again to use the Freedom of Information Act 2000 to have the Devon and Cornwall police report released, but it has not been released. It is in the public interest to get the heart of why the four recruits died at Deepcut. Unless the Minister is willing to make progress today, the matter will go to the courts. That will lead to yet another embarrassing series of revelations, when the Government and the Minister could simply put right something that has been very wrong for 14 years.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.88.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.88.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.88.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1539" speakername="Nick Harvey" colnum="88"  time="010:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0003.htm#09042266000461">
	<p pid="a.88.2/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1424" name="Joan Humble">the hon. Member for Blackpool, North and Fleetwood (Mrs. Humble)</phrase> on the way in which she introduced the debate. As she said, this is the first occasion on which we have such a report to debate and the first opportunity to make a judgment on how the new system is performing. She tangled with some difficult and emotive issues in an even-handed and level-headed way and I agreed with a number of the points that she made.</p>
	<p pid="a.88.2/2">The new commissioner has made herself available to Members of the House and everybody else with whom she interacts. She has been very open and I commend her on it. I met her to discuss her work and it is clear that she is setting about her role within the terms laid down by Parliament with determination. She has a clear vision of where she is going. I am impressed by her general approach and encouraged by some of the things that she told me. She said that in some instances, initially, she found some resistance to her involvement in inquiries, and some scepticism and suspicion of her role. However, she said that even in the short time in which she has been in post, there has been a thawing of some of the hostility towards her and a willingness on the part of the armed forces to interact with her, which is welcome.</p>
	<p pid="a.88.2/3">None the less, at this stage, she is only beginning to scratch the surface of the problems, based on the surveys to which the hon. Member for Blackpool, North and Fleetwood referred when she introduced the debate. The experience, impressions and belief of armed service personnel is that the problem is more widespread than the scale of the cases with which the commissioner is dealing would imply. I am not suggesting that all cases ought to end up with the commissioner; it is hoped that the chain of command will be capable of dealing with the lion's share. However, I believe that there is a bigger problem than she has yet begun to tangle with. It is her first year of operation. The 193 cases that she has considered do not constitute a large number, but I expect that when we debate such things in future, the number will have increased.</p>
	<p pid="a.88.2/4">For the first time probably, the debate gives us the opportunity to consider whether we believe that the system that has been created has given adequate power and independence to the commissioner. My party colleagues and I wanted to the commissioner to have a stronger role and preferred the proposal of an ombudsman, which the Defence Committee and others suggested. Nothing so far has given me occasion to change my view that we need an official with greater powers than we have given to the commissioner. I noted with interest some of the proposals that the hon. Member for Blackpool, North and Fleetwood made, particularly her suggestion that the role should be vaguely analogous to that of Her Majesty's chief inspector of prisons and that there should be role for lay visitors. Both proposals are interesting. We must give it time, but I believe that we have not given adequate powers to the commissioner.</p>
	<p pid="a.88.2/5"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1926" name="James Gray">The hon. Member for North Wiltshire (Mr. Gray)</phrase> made an excellent speech in the defence procurement debate on Monday afternoon and I found myself heckling him, in a sympathetic fashion, from a sedentary position. I am rather less in agreement with what he said in this debate. He started off by correctly reminding us that young personnel new to the armed services must learn to accept military discipline. They are going to be put into theatres of war, where complete military discipline is essential to their survival and the successful prosecution of their objectives. It would therefore be no great kindness to young recruits to treat them with kid gloves or to avoid the need for them to accept those harsh realities from the outset. However, precisely because it is their duty to obey the chain of command virtually unquestioningly, it is all the more important that there is a separate, independent avenue to go down if they have a genuine grievance that they do not feel able to raise with the chain of command.</p>
	<p pid="a.88.2/6">I fundamentally disagree with some of the points that the hon. Gentleman made. In particular, I do not agree that allowing a commissioner to have a power of investigation&mdash;at the moment, all she can do is monitor the investigations that the armed forces carry out&mdash;would somehow cut across what other people do. The role of the police is to examine whether the law has been broken and whether there has been any criminality. That is all&mdash;their role does not go beyond that. The coroner's role is to establish the cause of death. Coroners have slightly more latitude than the police to go beyond that. They often look at some of the background, and they may make recommendations, as the hon. Member for Blackpool, North and Fleetwood said, based on what comes to their attention in the course of their inquiries. However, even the coroner's role is limited. Many of aggrieved service personnel and their families want more investigation into the nooks and crannies, beyond that which the police or the coroner have a duty to undertake.</p>
	<p pid="a.88.2/7">I disagree with the hon. Member for North Wiltshire that court action would cut across any investigatory powers given to the commissioner. I would compare the situation with what happens when there is a death or maiming in a hospital. In that case, the police are called in to investigate potential criminality and the coroner looks at the cause of death, but an aggrieved patient or their family might wish to take the matter either to court or to the health service ombudsman. Many ombudsmen exercise their powers only as long as court proceedings are not taking place, but it is perfectly common for them to go over the same ground that the police or a coroner might go over to learn more and to determine whether there has been any systematic failure, as the hon. Member for Blackpool, North and Fleetwood said. I am not persuaded that we will not need to come back in future and extend further powers to the commissioner to create something more akin to an ombudsman.</p>
	<p pid="a.88.2/8">We ask an awful lot of our armed services personnel. The bullying and harassment about which we have heard a lot this morning are undoubtedly unacceptable. I am quite convinced that there are the beginnings of a shift in culture, but there is further to go. Nevertheless, armed forces personnel may wish to raise matters other than bullying and harassment. They might want to raise the inadequacy of their kit, for example, on which one coroner has commented. I should have thought it preferable for people to make complaints before the event rather than looking at things in retrospect.</p>
	<p pid="a.88.2/9">The hon. Member for North Wiltshire said that many people die in road traffic accidents. Some years ago, a constituent of mine was maimed by a collision with a vehicle while on physical training. To this day, he blames the Army for what happened, but he has never had the opportunity to have his case looked at. That was a question not of faulty equipment, but of faulty procedure. There is a lot more to come. The commissioner's reports in future years will give us further opportunity to judge whether we have given the office adequate powers. I am not convinced that we have done so and I believe that we will have to return to the matter in future to extend the commissioner's role or something akin to it.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.90.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.90.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.90.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1922" speakername="Andrew Murrison" colnum="90"  time="010:39:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0003.htm#09042266000462">
	<p pid="a.90.0/1">May I start by declaring my interests in the Register? I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1424" name="Joan Humble">the hon. Member for Blackpool, North and Fleetwood (Mrs. Humble)</phrase> on securing this debate and on the excellent way in which she presented it. It debate has been excellent, but slightly odd in that the meat of the Service Complaints Commissioner's first report has been set to one side as we have debated wider issues relating to Deepcut. However, Deepcut is important, as it underpins the creation of the post.</p>
	<p pid="a.90.0/2">It seems to me that the investigation of Deepcut is not the function of the Service Complaints Commissioner as the post is constituted. However, the prevention of a future Deepcut most certainly is. I welcome the creation of the post, as it will give a level of transparency to our armed forces and assist in changing some unhelpful elements of the culture. Somebody mentioned beasting earlier. I have not been beasted in my service career, but I was training to be a diver in Portsmouth at the time&mdash;many here will remember it&mdash;when an Army soldier died while being beasted on the mud at Portsmouth. Around that time, we started to wonder whether some aspects of the training of young people in our armed forces were appropriate.</p>
	<p pid="a.90.0/3">Since that time, I have been concerned about how professionally those people are managed. Professionalism comes in many guises. It involves the way in which we conduct ourselves on operations, of course, but it also involves things such as how people are trained and how they are looked after and stewarded during the training period. There is no question in my mind but that beasting, although it was certainly part of the service culture at the time, was not what might be called professional, if for no other reason than that it causes mortality and morbidity from time to time. That is in nobody's interests, let alone those of the organisation concerned. Such things need to be addressed, and I believe that the Service Complaints Commissioner might be part of a preventive strategy to ensure that they are less likely to happen.</p>
	<p pid="a.90.0/4">Several hon. Members referred to the Service Complaints Commissioner as independent. We must accept that hers is a sort of independence&mdash;a semi-detached oversight&mdash;as she reports to Ministers and her budget comes from the Ministry of Defence, so we need to be slightly careful about the status that we accord to that office. It is important that we have such people to examine organisations that could be called total or closed, or that have the attributes of such organisations. The armed forces certainly have those attributes, as a number of hon. Members have mentioned.</p>
	<p pid="a.90.0/5">According to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1539" name="Nick Harvey">the hon. Member for North Devon (Nick Harvey)</phrase>, the Service Complaints Commissioner had some concerns about how she was initially received. I must say that it does not come across that way in her report, although I can understand why an organisation such as the armed forces might resist somebody like Dr. Atkins: an inquisitorial new appointment meant to shine light on darkness. However, the more thoughtful elements of the chain of command will probably welcome the Service Complaints Commissioner. That is certainly what I am hearing from those to whom I talk in the armed forces.</p>
	<p pid="a.90.0/6">The Service Complaints Commissioner makes suggestions about how her role might be expanded, but they are pretty subtle. Although the hon. Member for Blackpool, North and Fleetwood eloquently described how the role might be developed over the years, that does not really come across in Dr. Atkins's first report. We will have to see how it evolves as the years go by, but it would be premature at this stage&mdash;she has been doing the job for little more than 12 months&mdash;to suggest that it should be radically overhauled. That would be a little unfair. At this stage, the balance that has been struck is about right. I would like to see how the office copes during the next few years and its subsequent reports. We will have to keep it under review, of course&mdash;we keep everything under review in this place, do we not?&mdash;but it seems to be a pretty good starter for 10. I look forward to the commissioner's contribution as the months and years roll by.</p>
	<p pid="a.90.0/7">Having been ever so nice, I think that it would be wrong of me not to raise one or two slight concerns. The report talks throughout of accountability. The Service Complaints Commissioner says that she accounts publicly to Ministers and Parliament; she says it on page 82 and again on page 15, and it is a thread throughout the whole publication. We could debate how she might be held to account, but it is important that we use language judiciously. I am not aware of any meaningful accounting to Parliament. We are indebted to the hon. Member for Blackpool, North and Fleetwood for securing this debate; otherwise, we would not have had a formal opportunity to discuss the report at all. Some might think that I am being a bit pedantic in making the distinction, but it is important that we consider it.</p>
	<p pid="a.90.0/8">The commissioner found that knowledge of her role was poor. She is being a little harsh on herself. In the evidence that she gives in the annexe, which touches on the most recent service continuous attitude survey, we find that knowledge of how to complain overall is pretty poor within the armed forces. It is not specifically about her role; it is simply that people do not know where to go. Still, a key index for the current year is that she will improve recognition of her office, and I look forward to seeing her achieve that target and reading her report on it in a year's time.</p>
	<p pid="a.90.0/9">The commissioner mentions timeliness in the investigation of complaints, which is important. On a grander scale, we can consider the delayed inquiry into Iraq as evidence for why we should conduct any inquiry or investigation in a timely fashion. As the months and years go by, unfortunately, memories fade and evidence is destroyed. I endorse wholeheartedly and with great feeling her concerns about the lack of timeliness in the investigation of some complaints within the armed forces.</p>
	<p pid="a.90.0/10">Dr. Atkins points out that the complaints should be sorted out at as low a level as possible. It is a pity that she has had to say that, as it is just good management practice to ensure that complaints, concerns and worries are sorted out quickly and at as low a level as possible. I would have thought that that was axiomatic. I hope that the armed forces will consider how current procedures lead to the escalation and formalisation of complaints, which is off-putting to many people, particularly those of relatively junior ranks.</p>
	<p pid="a.90.0/11">To be rather prosaic in the context of many of the remarks made today, the financial position is given briefly in annexe 4. It appears to be fairly summary. It would be nice, for future years, to have an account of superannuation, for example, in the breakdown of costs. We must be accountable for all money these days&mdash;at least, the Minister must&mdash;and it seems odd that things such as salaries should be cited but superannuation should not. Maybe we need to give that a bit of thought.</p>
	<p pid="a.90.0/12">In conclusion, I think that the commissioner will be of particular use to families. I know from my experience that they often find it extremely difficult to approach the chain of command and the usual channels. They feel that such an approach might have an adverse impact on their careers, and there are significant grounds for supposing so. I hope that Dr. Atkins will be able to provide an alternative conduit for many of those concerns and that, as a result, the satisfaction of service families&mdash;on whom we rely as well as servicemen themselves&mdash;will be enhanced and improved. Service families constitute one area where this particular officer will have a particular part to play.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.93.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.93.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.93.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1516" speakername="Bob Ainsworth" speakeroffice="The Minister for the Armed Forces"  colnum="93"  time="010:50:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0004.htm#09042266000463">
	<p pid="a.93.0/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1424" name="Joan Humble">the Member for Blackpool, North and Fleetwood (Mrs. Humble)</phrase> on securing this debate. I am grateful for her long-standing interest and engagement in this issue. She has put a lot of effort into these matters over a long period. I am grateful for the many contributions that have been made to this interesting debate. I will respond to as many of the points as I can in the time that I have.</p>
	<p pid="a.93.0/2">The operational effectiveness of the armed forces depends on mutual trust and respect. It is crucial that our people have confidence in the system that investigates their complaints. That must be prompt and fair, while complementing the command structure that is fundamental to carrying out successful military operations. The Service Complaints Commissioner, Dr. Susan Atkins, provides valuable independent oversight of our system. She is a key component of that system.</p>
	<p pid="a.93.0/3">The Ministry of Defence and the services are wholly committed to the welfare of our people. We welcome the commissioner's first annual report on the fairness, effectiveness and efficiency of the complaints system. It commends the three services on their commitment to tackling all forms of unacceptable behaviour and on ensuring that servicemen and women are treated well. Dr. Atkins has reported that the complaints system is well designed and is working, but there is scope for improvement. I acknowledge and accept that. It is her job to help us to improve the system, but not her job alone. It must be taken seriously by all three services and by the MOD, which is considering the commissioner's report in detail. We expect to provide a formal response in the summer.</p>
	<p pid="a.93.0/4">We are building a good working relationship with the commissioner. The MOD and the services are committed to raising awareness of Dr. Atkins' role among all servicemen and women. The commissioner will issue 40,000 leaflets to armed forces personnel all over the world with the full support of the chain of command. Furthermore, the commissioner continues to visit our people regularly and has the opportunity freely to talk to all ranks.</p>
	<p pid="a.93.0/5">Widening the commissioner's power has been advocated today. The Government committed themselves to the establishment of a Service Complaints Commissioner in their response to the Deepcut review published in June 2006. Provisions had already been proposed in the Armed Forces Bill for an independent external reviewer who would examine the fairness, effectiveness and efficiency of the service complaints system and report to Ministers annually.</p>
	<p pid="a.93.0/6">A big difference between those who advocate an ombudsman and those of us who support the current role is that we do not want the chain of command to be circumvented. We are committed to the chain of command doing the job that we require it to do. Rather than circumvent that, which a different system of complaints such as an ombudsman might do, we want the Service Complaints Commissioner to work with the chain of command and to help it to improve the system and to change the culture that has existed in the armed forces.</p>
	<p pid="a.93.0/7">My hon. Friend the Member for Blackpool, North and Fleetwood asked about the culture, but acknowledged that she was complaining about the culture that existed in Deepcut 10 years ago. It has been acknowledged that that culture was unacceptable and a lot has been done to try to change it over the years. We have set up the complaints commissioner and taken the attitude surveys which show that people are still reluctant to complain to try to change the culture and force those issues out so that we can amend a system that has been unsatisfactory in the past.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.94.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.94.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.94.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.94.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.94.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.94.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.94.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.94.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.95.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.95.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.95.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.95.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.95.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.95.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.95.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.95.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.95.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.95.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.96.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.96.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.96.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.96.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.96.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1777" speakername="Karen Buck" colnum="96"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0004.htm#09042266000473">
	<p pid="a.96.1/1">I am very grateful for this opportunity to discuss extended schools and related issues again. In the past couple of years, the Minister has been more than generous with her time, as I have debated extended schools and have corresponded and discussed with her the delivery of that incredibly important programme. She has sometimes expressed concerns about my approach, so, for the avoidance of doubt, I want to put on record yet again that I come at the subject from the perspective of someone who believes that, along with the Sure Start and children's centres programmes for the under-fives, the extended school approach is one of the most important things that we can do for our children. However, I remain concerned that aspects of delivery, including reliance on co-funding from sources outside her Department, upon which her programme depends, still need further work.</p>
	<p pid="a.96.1/2">I am aware that extended schools and the whole early years programmes have their detractors&mdash;the usual sources, who will use any stick that they can to beat the Government, particularly on the grounds that the measures we are putting in place for children and young people are being taken primarily, sometimes even exclusively, to drive parents into the workplace. Not only do I think that there is nothing wrong with having an early years programme and an extended schools programme that allow parents who choose to work to do so, safe in the knowledge that their children will be looked after, but I have always been convinced that the Government's approach to those agendas is founded in something bigger and even more important than that perfectly worthy objective. We have to enrich the lives of our children, particularly those whose opportunities are narrowest.</p>
	<p pid="a.96.1/3">As someone who represents an inner-city constituency that includes not only some of the wealthiest parts of the country, but many areas that are amongst the poorest, I am reminded daily of the challenge that we face with our young people, who are, overwhelmingly, growing up in flats. The great majority of young people are growing up without access to their own garden space and in families who are poor, workless, or in work but in poverty&mdash;as we all know, half of all families in poverty are also in employment. Young people are growing up on the edges of central London with incredibly rich and diverse cultural opportunities nearby, but they simply never access them. Among my son's classmates are children who have never been to the theatre, never been to the country and never had any opportunities to access what those of us with even relatively modest incomes can take for granted. Their lives are blighted as a consequence. The alienation of young people, which sometimes leaves them in the group that we call NEETs&mdash;those not in education, employment or training&mdash;or caught up in crime and antisocial behaviour, is underpinned by an inability to move in the adult world of interaction that is taken for granted by those of us who have had those opportunities, and by a lack of confidence that is brought about by that inability. They are surrounded by the riches of one of the greatest cities in the world, but they do not access those riches.</p>
	<p pid="a.96.1/4">The underlying philosophy of extended schools includes not just homework clubs, catch-up clubs and extra educational opportunities, but, as the Government's own document spells out, music, drama, arts, sport, trips and cultural visits. One of the most important things that we can do for our young people is extend the curriculum and bring it to life by giving the opportunities that make it concrete and broaden the educational experience by making it more practical. That will give people the confidence they need to be able to move in the sophisticated world that some of them have been denied&mdash;in many cases, because their parents are not able to do so, perhaps because they have massive barriers of their own such as being drug and alcohol users. Some have been in prison, have mental health problems or are new to this country and do not speak the language. Some, tragically, are simply indifferent and do not provide their children with those experiences even though they could. For such children, it is absolutely marvellous that we have the extended school programme.</p>
	<p pid="a.96.1/5">I know that the Minister will say that the investment in extended schools is significant and increasing. I acknowledge and welcome that. I am also particularly pleased with the extended schools disadvantage subsidy, which goes some way towards meeting my concerns, because it will direct additional resources into the neighbourhoods, schools and populations that need it most. Perhaps the Minister will say more about that in her reply.</p>
	<p pid="a.96.1/6">We now know the extent to which the number of schools offering the full core offer is increasing&mdash;we have the figures. The Minister is well aware of my concern that my borough, Westminster, has been trailing badly in delivering the offer. A few months ago, when I was doing some work that resulted in an excellent article in <i>The Guardian</i> on the subject, only half of all schools were offering the full core offer. Given how much we need, that causes me real heartache. There has been significant improvement in my borough recently as well, and I put that down to a dynamic new appointment. I put on record my admiration for Peter Turner, who has taken the programme by the scruff of the neck. Previously, we lacked that sort of senior management buy-in and the ability to deliver the programme, but there have been real improvements in delivering the service in my area.</p>
	<p pid="a.96.1/7">That is the good news, and there is plenty of it, but I asked for this opportunity to discuss the programme again because I am still very anxious about a few aspects. First and foremost, although it is early days and the disadvantaged children's subsidy is yet to kick in&mdash;it was piloted last year and there will be an extended pilot this year&mdash;the Government's own research confirms that children from more deprived backgrounds are less likely than the average to use the activities and child care services available in the extended schools programme. It worrying that a programme that was designed explicitly to reach out to and lift children with the narrowest opportunities is not delivering as well to them as to the average. That is not, as slick headlines would have it, a damning indictment of the whole programme, but it gives us cause to ask what is not being done that needs to be done.</p>
	<p pid="a.96.1/8">Last year's child care and early years survey, conducted by the National Centre for Social Research, found that fewer than one in five older children were using out-of-school services at all. That figure was unchanged since 2004. I am sure that there will have been some improvement since then, but that is a cause of concern. In the extended schools survey that was conducted for the Department for MORI, published in January, only 6 per cent. of the parents surveyed said that their children had attended an activity during the school holidays, whereas the demand for holiday schemes expressed in that survey was 60 per cent. There are therefore two problems: the relatively low and stable participation in the whole out-of-school programme for older children in particular, and the gap in holiday play schemes. Given that the Daycare Trust's research, which it produces every summer, on the cost of holiday schemes found that last year alone the cost of holiday programmes jumped by 10 per cent., MORI's finding of a relatively low level of participation is worrying.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.98.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.98.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.98.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.98.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.98.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1777" speakername="Karen Buck" colnum="98"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0005.htm#09042266000475">
	<p pid="a.98.1/1">I totally agree; my right hon. Friend is spot on. His comments chime with my next point, which is that the MORI research also found that the people most likely to participate in the programmes were those in two-parent families and those with younger children. That is very welcome. The people less likely to participate were the parents of children in special schools&mdash;that is a great worry&mdash;and those with secondary-age children, especially parents of children in years 7, 8 and 9. Those are the years in which children make the transfer from primary to secondary education, and it is when they most need that level of intensive support.</p>
	<p pid="a.98.1/2">Secondary school transfer is already a real cause of concern. The alienation to which my right hon. Friend refers is, in most cases, inadvertently compounded by secondary school transfer. The relationship between parents and schools and between children and schools is worse in secondary schools than in primary schools. That is often connected with secondary transfer. It is worrying that fewer services are available to those groups and participation is lower. It shows that there is a demand for exactly the work he describes. Intensive outreach to parents is, in a sense, parallel with the work of children centres and Sure Start. We know well that some schools are involved with that work, but not all are.</p>
	<p pid="a.98.1/3">Worryingly, the MORI findings also show&mdash;it is not picked out in the executive summary&mdash;that the group that found it most difficult to fund out-of-school activities were families with no parents in work. That brings me to the heart of the dilemma: the question of co-payment and sustainability, of which my right hon. Friend the Minister is well aware. From the research, we know that one of the reasons participation is not as great as it should be is that, according to the children and parents surveyed, the activities on offer are not always what children want. That brings us back to the menu. What is the menu of activities that can engage children, especially those who need it most? We need to give them not just catch-up classes, but enjoyable activities. Those activities should deal with the problem of alienation mentioned by my right hon. Friend the Member for Oxford, East.</p>
	<p pid="a.98.1/4">The other issue is, of course, payment. Lone parents, parents of children in special education and parents who are not in employment find it most difficult to deal with the payments. Obviously, some schools&mdash;the disadvantage subsidy will help with this&mdash;provide cross-subsidies. The dilemma is that the schools with the smallest proportion of parents able to pay the charges are the schools that need the service most but are least able to draw upon co-payment. There are schools in my constituency that have large numbers of children on free school dinner entitlements and parents in low-paid work. The argument is that such schools would benefit the most from that rich menu of activities, but unfortunately they are less likely to be able to generate an income that makes such services sustainable.</p>
	<p pid="a.98.1/5">My right hon. Friend the Minister is aware that I am concerned about the replies I get from her Department that say, &quot;Well, this is, of course, what the child care element of the working tax credit should do.&quot; However, hardly anybody gets the child care element of the working tax credit. There is no evidence&mdash;if she can point me to the evidence, I will apologise and back off from this line of argument&mdash;that parents of older, school-aged children are claiming the child care element of the working tax credit to pay for out-of-school activities and holiday schemes. It is precisely because they do not do so that we have this dilemma.</p>
	<p pid="a.98.1/6">Although 80 per cent. of schools are ticking the box to say that they provide the full core offer&mdash;next year, the Government intend to have all schools ticking the box that says that they do so&mdash;if we look at the Department's guidance for schools, it states in the small print that if a school has decided that there is neither the need nor the demand for the services, it can still tick the box to say that it is providing the full core offer. Slightly weirdly, therefore, it is entirely possible for a school to say that it is providing a full core offer when it is actually not providing a single service. That problem might well come back to bite the Government and it is something about which we need to be concerned. I do not think that many schools will play that game, but it is a concern because what we understand by the full core offer is a school that is providing a full menu of the four categories of activity set out in the guidance.</p>
	<p pid="a.98.1/7">As I have said, further attention needs to be paid to those on low incomes, those with free school dinner entitlements and those who are out of work. Of course, we also need to recession-proof the measures to help all those who are in low-paid work, many of whom do not receive the child care element of the tax credit. How will we ensure that the full delivery that we are promising is there on the ground? How will we ensure that we are delivering sustainable and affordable services, particularly for the children who need it most?</p>
	<p pid="a.98.1/8">As I have said, I am aware that the disadvantage subsidy will be a real help in that sense, but I am not convinced that the deep pockets of disadvantage, particularly in our expensive inner cities, will benefit from a Government approach that delivers the support that is needed&mdash;that reaches out and genuinely offers a programme of activities that will enrich and improve the lives of our young people.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.100.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.100.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.102.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.102.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.102.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.102.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.102.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.102.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.102.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.102.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.104.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.104.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.104.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.104.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.104.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.104.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.104.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1474" speakername="Malcolm Moss" colnum="104"  time="014:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0005.htm#09042266000481">
	<p pid="a.104.2/1">Mr. Pope, may I say what a pleasure it is to serve under your chairmanship for the first time? Normally, at this time on a Wednesday afternoon we are both in the Select Committee on Foreign Affairs. A change is as good as a rest, so they say, so I am delighted to have the opportunity to speak in this important debate. I am most grateful to colleagues for turning up on the busiest day, in Parliamentary terms. I imagine that we have all had a rushed lunch. I thank all hon. Members for coming.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.2/2">Let us first remind ourselves of the facts. Cardiac and vascular conditions are those affecting and related to the heart and to blood vessels throughout the body. They include heart attack, stroke, diabetes and chronic kidney disease, affect the lives of more than 4 million people in England, cause 170,000 deaths each year and are responsible for about one fifth of all hospital admissions. The challenge posed by those conditions is stark: cardiac and vascular disease remains the number one cause of death and disability in the United Kingdom. The death rate for coronary heart disease and stroke in men and women is still higher in the UK than in comparable western European countries. It was primarily to address that serious challenge that the national service framework for coronary heart disease, a 10-year plan of action, was launched in 2000. In England, it certainly has delivered significant progress in the fight against coronary heart disease.</p>
	<p pid="a.104.2/3">The national framework for CHD, with the additional arrhythmias chapter added in 2005, led the way as one of the first national plans developed to take a root-and-ranch approach to improving the treatment and care of people with a particular condition and to take action on prevention. Progress reports have shown the following: first, the target of reducing deaths from cardio-vascular disease in people under 75 by 40 per cent. was met five years early; secondly, the number of people suffering a heart attack who received thrombolysis within 60 minutes of a call for help increased from 24 per cent. of patients in early 2001 to almost 70 per cent. in 2007; and thirdly, the waiting times for heart surgery dropped dramatically, from more than 5,500 people waiting more than three months for heart surgery in 2000 to none in 2007. However, we must not risk failing to build on what we have achieved to date. It is vital that these achievements and those of other strategies for stroke, diabetes and kidney disease are sustained and built upon. Simply to rely on a project-based approach is not enough.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.104.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.104.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.104.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.104.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.105.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.105.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.105.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.105.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.105.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.105.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.105.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.105.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.105.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.105.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.105.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.105.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.105.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.105.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.105.7" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.105.7" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.106.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.106.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.106.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.106.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.107.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.107.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.107.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.107.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.108.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.108.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.108.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.108.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.108.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.108.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.108.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.108.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.108.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.108.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.109.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.109.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.110.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.110.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.112.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.112.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.112.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" speakername="David Taylor" colnum="112"  time="015:05:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0007.htm#09042266000503">
	<p pid="a.112.0/1">I warmly congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1474" name="Malcolm Moss">the hon. Member for North-East Cambridgeshire (Mr. Moss)</phrase> on securing this important debate. He is known to be a fair-minded man, and he delivered merited praise to the Government when justified. He also presented a thoughtful analysis and an objective critique when appropriate. All in all, his contribution was delivered in a non-partisan manner, despite provocation from the Taliban tendency of the Conservative Front Bench.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.0/2">The Cardio and Vascular Coalition's excellent &quot;Destination 2020&quot; strategy, to which the hon. Member for North-East Cambridgeshire referred, is both timely and significant. The aim is to reduce rates of cardio and vascular disease in the United Kingdom to one of the lowest in western Europe. That is a commendable aim, and we should have no trouble in welcoming and supporting it, and taking the appropriate decisions to ensure that it is delivered. As the coalition readily acknowledges, the Government have made important progress, tackling these generally fatal diseases through the national service frameworks to which the hon. Gentleman referred. That is particularly so for coronary heart disease, kidney disease, stroke and diabetes.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.0/3">Vast improvements have been made to the way in which the NHS diagnoses and treats cardiac and vascular diseases, but although everyone in Parliament should be proud of that, it is vital to recognise that it is only a stepping stone to better health outcomes throughout society. In my view, the key areas for improvement are preventing cardiac and vascular disease and the rehabilitation of patients.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.0/4"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/2036" name="Andrew Pelling">The hon. Member for Croydon, Central (Mr. Pelling)</phrase> gave a helpful and encouraging speech. I declare an interest as chair of the Ibstock stroke club. The hon. Gentleman was talking about specialist stroke units. We have one in Leicester general hospital, which serves getting on for 1 million people in the city and the county. A feature of its care is the rehabilitation offered as an intermediate step at community hospitals in the county, including at my community hospital at Coalville. I hope that the Minister, who is an able, approachable and articulate member of the ministerial team, will accept an invitation to visit the Coalville hospital to see the work done in the stroke rehabilitation unit. Such an offer is probably difficult to refuse.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.0/5">I return to the thrust of the debate. Lord Darzi's review of the NHS will undoubtedly lead to fundamental changes to the organisation and commissioning strategies of the national health service. I am a confessed sceptic of the personalised health budget, polyclinics and the choice mantra&mdash;I hope that the Minister has not already cancelled her ticket to Coalville. Lord Darzi's emphasis on local commissioning has the potential to continue the Government's record of improving standards and patient outcomes in the NHS. However, in an era in which local health authorities are commissioning rather than providing primary health care, it is vital that the Government retain a strategic view of prevention, diagnosis, treatment and rehabilitation for cardiac and vascular patients, and for all other long-term chronic conditions.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.0/6">As the report &quot;Destination 2020&quot; spells out, and as the hon. Member for North-East Cambridgeshire said, project-based approaches on their own will not necessarily realise our ambition of reducing the number of cardiac and vascular disease patients or improving their care pathway. The Government need to spell out their strategic policy&mdash;I guess that we will hear something about that in the Minister's reply&mdash;and the changes to the NHS proposed in the Darzi review must fit around that policy, not the other way around.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.0/7">I want to focus my main comments on the third principle outlined in &quot;Destination 2020&quot;, which talked about the CVC's ambitions being delivered through standards of excellence, a patient-centred approach, effective commissioning, research, addressing specific areas of need and particularly by a new focus on prevention. At this point, I should declare an interest as the chair of the all-party group on smoking and health, and that is the issue to which I now wish to turn.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.0/8">The Government's Health Bill, which is proceeding through the House, is key to a new approach to preventing the diseases that we are discussing. There are overt links between smoking and many fatal diseases, such as cancer, and deaths from coronary heart disease are about 60 per cent. higher in smokers. That means that tobacco smoking accounts for more than 30,000 deaths from cardiovascular disease in the UK every year. As a result of smoking, 100 people will die from CVD today, 14 or 15 of them in the city of London.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.0/9">Smoking is a major cause of death from CVD and of the morbidity associated with it, although its prevalence is decreasing, which has made a significant contribution to decreasing CVD rates. It has been estimated that about 48 per cent. of the decline in coronary heart disease mortality in England and Wales between 1981 and 2000&mdash;a period of 20 years&mdash;was attributable to the reduction in the prevalence of smoking. Smoking rates have declined since my teens and 20s&mdash;that was 40 years ago&mdash;when about half the adult population probably smoked, although prevalence varied widely by social class and age. None the less, as the Minister well knows, more than 20 per cent. of the population still smoke, and the figure is significantly higher in deprived communities. We therefore need to maintain momentum and to continue to recognise smoking as a risk factor that can and, indeed, must be minimised. It is important to recognise that even by the most optimistic estimates of smoking cessation rates, there will still be at least 5 million smokers in the UK in 10 to 12 years' time, when a fifth Labour Government will be coming to a very satisfactory conclusion.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.0/10">Even a temporary cessation in smoking improves health outcomes. Crucially, the ability of cardiovascular patients to survive surgery and avoid post-operative complications improves significantly. I do not know whether my hon. Friend the Minister, who is a London MP, was aware of this, but the London Health Observatory reached the following conclusion in its 2006 report on the short-term benefits of pre-operative smoking cessation in London:</p>
	<p pid="a.112.0/11" class="indent">&quot;If patients admitted for planned surgery were to stop smoking prior to operation 2,500-5,300... post operative complications would be avoided each year, and the NHS would make the following savings: 2,600-4,000 bed days could be saved; &pound;0.5-&pound;1.1 million each year across London's PCTs could be saved&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.0/12">In addition, a sum of between &pound;1 million and &pound;3 million could be saved across London's hospital trusts. Those are significant figures in financial and health terms. If they were extrapolated to the rest of the country, that would result in hundreds of thousands of bed days being freed up and hundreds of millions of pounds being saved.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.0/13">The risk of CVD increases in young smokers. It has been shown that people under the age of 40 have a five times greater risk of heart attack if they smoke. The immensely successful and well-organised pressure group, Action on Smoking and Health, to which I pay tribute, recently conducted work on the issue. Its report, &quot;Beyond Smoking Kills&quot; found that smoking accounts for 16 per cent. of circulatory disease treatment costs for patients aged 35 and over and for more than twice that figure&mdash; 34 per cent.&mdash;in the 35 to 64 age group. Coronary heart disease caused by smoking accounts for &pound;180 million&mdash; 20 per cent.&mdash;of all CHD treatment costs for patients aged 35 and over, and the figure rises to 41 per cent. for those under 65.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.0/14">We know that prevention must start early&mdash;we often say that and we know that it is common sense&mdash;but it must start even earlier where tobacco is concerned. The best way to minimise smoking as a risk factor in CVD is to prevent children from taking it up at all. Most smokers start before the age of 18, and most will never manage to quit. Smoking is a childhood addiction, not generally an adult choice. The Health Bill, which is currently in the House of Lords, is an important part of our prevention strategy. Encouragingly, it proposes a ban on point-of-sale display and on the sale of tobacco from vending machines, as well as plain packaging for tobacco products. I hope that all three of those initiatives survive through to Third Reading in the Commons.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.0/15">During the Bill's earlier stages in the Lords, the tobacco industry used front groups&mdash;a common tactic for the industry&mdash;to promote scare stories about costs, which are not justified by the facts, and to undermine this important public health measure. Ending the display of tobacco in shops will, like the ban on tobacco advertising, help to ensure that tobacco is not seen as normal for our children and that it is not seen and bought alongside sweets and newspapers. Smoking accounts for half the difference in life expectancy between the richest and the poorest in our nation. Breaking the cycle of addiction in the poorest parts of society is the only way seriously to reduce and eventually end such health inequalities. Population-level prevention measures have been shown to work, and the proposed legislation will work across all our communities to help put tobacco out of sight and out of the reach of our children.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.0/16">When the Bill comes to the Commons, I hope that there will be cross-party consensus in voting to support bans on point-of-sale display and tobacco vending machines, as well as the introduction of plain packaging. I am sure that the hon. Member for North-East Cambridgeshire will raise such issues with the leader of his party, who refreshingly confessed to his personal experience of the difficulties of giving up smoking. I hope that the Leader of the Opposition will be persuaded of the significance of the measures in the Bill and support the CVC's vital ambition of ensuring that the Government adopt a new approach to preventing the diseases that we are discussing. Worthy as they are, however, and highly likely though they are to be effective, the proposed measures will not work in isolation and must be part of a comprehensive approach. Such an approach should be supported and linked to a CVD strategy of the type outlined in the excellent and concise report &quot;Destination 2020&quot;, which the Minister will have read.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.0/17">I have two final points to make. First, the provision of appropriate smoking cessation services in secondary care&mdash;the hon. Member for North-East Cambridgeshire mentioned this briefly&mdash;must be a standard part of care for all those with CVD or CVD risk factors. That must be an element of our strategy. Secondly, second-hand smoke makes its own deadly contribution to CVD. We banned smoking in enclosed workplaces only in July 2007. Evidence from Scotland, which implemented the measure rather earlier, shows that smoke-free legislation does lead, has lead and will lead to fewer heart attacks across the population and that second-hand smoking is often a serious risk factor for those with a pre-existing CVD condition.</p>
	<p pid="a.112.0/18">The Minister has readily assented to a meeting with the all-party groups that have an interest in this issue, and I hope that we can talk to her. As I said, she is a very approachable Minister, and we have confidence that she will be able to carry forward some of the things that we say to her. Everyone on both sides of the Chamber&mdash;there is no serious political divide on this issue&mdash;wants to build on the Government's progress to date. The Department of Health would do well to root its future cardiovascular disease strategies deeply in the work that the coalition has recorded in its very clear and concise document. We all&mdash;politicians and the general population alike&mdash;owe it a debt of gratitude for that work. I hope that the Minister will give her personal, professional and political response to the contents of what is a very useful document for framing the health policy of the next 10 to 15 years and more.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.116.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.116.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.119.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.119.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.121.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.121.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.121.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.121.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.122.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.122.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.124.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.124.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.124.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.124.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.124.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1448" speakername="Ann Keen" colnum="124"  time="015:44:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0009.htm#09042266000510">
	<p pid="a.124.1/1">The hon. Gentleman makes an interesting point. Mental health is not within my portfolio, so it would be unfair to the Minister with responsibility for it if I were to comment on it. As I said, I can see why people have the 10 years figure in their heads. Our recently published 2008 progress report for the CHD NSF stated that we must continue not only to build on the success that we have realised so far, but to consider where we need to do better. There is no doubt that we need to focus relentlessly on improvement and on making quality the organising principle of the NHS.</p>
	<p pid="a.124.1/2">I should now like to reflect on the successes of our NSFs and the progress that has been made on the implementation of our national stroke strategy. Our greatest achievement in cardiac services has been getting waiting times down. That has been acknowledged by hon. Members today, for which I thank them. That was achieved with a massive increase in cardiologists and other key staff and a 50 per cent. increase in capacity thanks to a &pound;735 million capital investment programme.</p>
	<p pid="a.124.1/3">The improvements in recent years could not have happened without the hard work and commitment of NHS staff. Cardiologists, cardiothoracic surgeons, cardiac nurses, technicians and rehabilitation specialists have all played their part. I have the great good fortune to meet front-line workers in the health service frequently. I visited St. Peter's hospital in Chertsey, where I saw the angiography suite, which is a very impressive nurse-led unit, and in November last year I was able to accompany the Prime Minister on a visit to Harefield Heart Science Centre, which is led by the eminent cardiologist, Professor Sir Magdi Yacoub. I saw the energy of the young scientists in the centre. They look at stem cell research and other things to research the causes and nature of heart disease and, of course, they consider the importance of its prevention and treatment. I also visited the cardiac catheter laboratory and the walk-in emergency centre at Harefield, which is led by another eminent cardiologist, Dr. Charles Ilsley, and I witnessed a cardiac catheter angioplasty being performed at King's college. I pay tribute to all those people.</p>
	<p pid="a.124.1/4">We have tried very hard not to have a party political, partisan debate, but I should like to give the hon. Member for Boston and Skegness the opportunity to dissociate himself totally from the remarks made by Daniel Hannan, a Member of the European Parliament, to Fox News. He told what he called his &quot;friends in America&quot; not to go down the same route as us. He said that the NHS was &quot;a mistake&quot; that</p>
	<p pid="a.124.1/5" class="indent">&quot;we have lived through for 60 years&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.124.1/6">and that it</p>
	<p pid="a.124.1/7" class="indent">&quot;has made people iller&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.124.1/8">Would the hon. Gentleman like to dissociate himself from those remarks?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.124.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.124.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.125.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.125.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.125.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.125.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.125.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.125.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.126.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.126.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.126.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.126.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.127.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.127.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.127.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.127.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.127.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.127.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.128.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.128.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.128.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.128.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.128.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.128.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.130.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.130.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.132.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.132.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.132.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.132.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.132.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1594" speakername="Paul Clark" colnum="132"  time="016:16:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0010.htm#09042266000524">
	<p pid="a.132.1/1">I understand the hon. Gentleman's concern and I shall come to where I see our way forward. As he has said, a number of sites have been considered, but it is not easy to find a route through that is suitable to meet the required standards for the new test, which is of benefit in making sure that we have good standards of training and good test sites available for those whom we want to make sure are safe drivers and motorcyclists. We have taken the opportunity, in the past six months, to increase the number of facilities available and to increase from 70-odd per cent. to 88 per cent. the percentage of the population now falling within the criteria that we laid out. However, I recognise that we have difficulties and that the situation is nowhere near ideal for his constituents and constituents in some other areas.</p>
	<p pid="a.132.1/2">We have to strike a balance. Some &pound;71 million has been invested into MPTCs, as the hon. Gentleman has recognised. He has said on his website that he hopes that Ministers will find a sensible way forward. I think that way forward is to continue to introduce sensible reforms to cycle and test provisions, because we want safer cyclists and we want them and others on the road to be better protected. We continue to work together and with county councils to take forward the various sites that have been identified, of which some have been too small and some too large.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.134.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.134.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.134.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.134.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.134.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1714" speakername="Ashok Kumar" colnum="134"  time="016:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0010.htm#09042266000525">
	<p pid="a.134.1/1">I thank Mr. Speaker for granting me this debate, which is important to my area. I want to put on record the contribution that health service staff are making in dealing with sexual health matters in Middlesbrough, and to highlight some of the good practices that are being followed. Given that it is Budget day, I will not ask the Minister for any more money&mdash;she can put herself at ease on that subject&mdash;but I shall demonstrate what good practice is being followed and express one or two concerns that I have for the future.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/2">Securing improvements in sexual health and well-being will continue to present a real challenge to all of those charged with that responsibility nationally, locally and regionally. Sexual health services have been required continually to adapt to changes in the communities that they serve. That was evident in the most recent Department of Health document on the issue, which was entitled &quot;Progress and Priorities&mdash;Working for High Quality Sexual Health&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/3">That document shows us, for example, how the shape of HIV in this country has changed significantly, particularly in relation to increases in the diagnosis of heterosexual people infected overseas and the undiminished levels of newly acquired infections in gay men. Despite the availability of more effective drug treatments and expanded testing opportunities, too many people are still diagnosed too late. Overall, diagnoses of sexually transmitted infections have continued to increase. Other social changes also impact significantly on sexual health, such as the frequent use of alcohol and other drugs.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/4">One subject that has not been well reported or analysed is the need for sexual health services for older people. Sexual behaviour research in that group is minimal, but recently, in a large survey of almost 8,000 people over 50, two thirds said that they were sexually active and more than one in 10 said that they did not use contraception with their current partner. They also did not know about their partner's sexual history. The document concludes:</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/5" class="indent">&quot;Whilst progress has been encouraging in some areas, overall the picture is one of worsening sexual health&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/6">That is the case in Middlesbrough and Teesside, too. Middlesbrough, Redcar and Cleveland, and Hartlepool primary care trusts, as well as Stockton-On-Tees teaching PCT, have developed proposals for the improvement of local sexual health services as part of a Teesside-wide investment. That is an example of best practice in collaboration across geographical boundaries. Flowing from that, a Teesside-wide sexual health reorganisation is taking place to help to facilitate a fully integrated sexual health service.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/7">A tendering process is underway in the area to appoint a lead provider, which will be responsible for organising the delivery of an integrated sexual health service. That will include genito-urinary medicine&mdash;GUM&mdash;contraceptive and sexual health services, and teenage pregnancy. It is intended that such a future pattern of integrated sexual health services will start to address the issues that I have mentioned. Those developments will support the changes needed to take a radical step forward in service delivery on Teesside. That vision of sexual health services sets out an ambition for everyone across Teesside to have access to comprehensive sexual health services, and to promote sexual health and well-being. Our providers say that that</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/8" class="indent">&quot;will be delivered through high quality, fully integrated care pathways, that will be both holistic and client focused&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/9">That is, and will be, delivered through PCT primary services at street and clinic level, and the James Cook university hospital in my constituency. The South Tees Hospitals NHS Trust GUM services are currently meeting Government targets on the number of patients seen and appointments offered. In fact, South Tees GUM services were recent finalists in the <i>Nursing Times</i> GUM service awards.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/10">On HIV, approximately 300 patients attend South Tees services&mdash;the majority attend the department of infection and travel medicine. Patients are usually seen by the department of infection within 48 hours of referral. Medical, nursing, psychological, dietary and social input gives holistic care to patients with HIV.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/11">For too long, our area has had to suffer poverty and health inequalities, and it has long been recognised that there are serious health inequalities in the Cleveland area. More than 16 per cent. of the population have health problems and that is significantly higher than the national figure of 13.1 per cent. Standardised mortality ratios are higher than national averages for all causes of death&mdash;for example, standardised mortality ratios for coronary heart disease show that, in some wards, levels of heart disease are more than 50 per cent. higher than national rates.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/12">The same is true of sexually transmitted infections. Across the Tees area, the four primary care trusts have the highest levels of teenage pregnancy and sexually transmitted infections in the country. The evidence collected by the four PCTs shows a clear picture of an increasing trend in sexual risk-taking behaviour, with the resultant increase in sexually transmitted infections. That is often exacerbated by alcohol and drug taking.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/13">The first priority is to deal with these infections at the sharp end, both in clinics and in hospitals, as I have mentioned. However, a longer-term view is also needed. So, alongside the need to manage the growing demand, the PCTs are acutely aware that they must have a better understanding of social causes and provide better education and prevention. The PCTs have recognised that, although they commission a range of sexual health services, there is not a comprehensive approach to the issue. They also acknowledged that strong, strategic leadership was needed to build on a vision and strategy for this delicate but crucial area of service. As a result, there should be a strong, robust, patient-and-public-involvement focus to address the needs of vulnerable groups.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/14">The PCTs also recognised that although there are good informal service links, commissioning is gradual and service developments are generally not well co-ordinated across the Teesside area. That is expressed in a key document entitled &quot;The Shaping of Sexual Health Services Across Teesside&quot;, which is a patient survey conducted in October 2008. The survey ran for four weeks and closed on <phrase class="date" code="2008-09-26">26 September 2008</phrase>. It asked the public to comment on issues such as their understanding of what sexual health services do, where they can go to find information and, if they had received treatment, their opinion of the service.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/15">The survey&mdash;an online and paper questionnaire&mdash;received 591 responses from members of the public and 24 responses from inmates at the local Kirklevington Grange prison. There was high awareness&mdash;over 85 per cent. in all cases&mdash;of sexual health services provision, but respondents were not knowledgeable about where to access services, which is a concern.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/16">The internet and GP surgeries are the main sources of information, and, for many members of the public, the GP's surgery is the preferred location for a check-up. People expressed a strong desire to see a same-sex health professional. In addition, many respondents expressed a desire for the clinic to be located where they were not likely to be known, and in a setting not identified as a dedicated sexual health centre.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/17">The responses were received not from those who might be called serial users of sexual health clinics: over 60 per cent. of respondents were recorded as not having had to use a sexual health service in the past two years. The majority of respondents were female, over 86 per cent. were heterosexual, less than 7 per cent. were gay or lesbian, and 3.4 per cent. were bisexual. Nearly half of respondents were 35 to 64 years old, and 95 per cent. considered themselves to be white British. In summary, the vast majority had not required sexual health services, and there was high awareness of what services were offered but not where to access them.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/18">One aspect of the survey that caused me some concern was the location of respondents by postcode area. I will do my best to spare the Minister the ordeal of my running through a social analysis of all the postcodes in my constituency and the general area, but, in short, the distribution of replies reflected respondents from the wealthier areas of Teesside. Worryingly, some of the more affluent wards in our area seemed to have a higher number of respondents than would be the case if analysis were done on a population basis. I do not intend to accuse those responsible for the survey of producing a distorted picture, but I suspect that the findings indicate that the poorer population of inner Middlesbrough has a pattern of needs even deeper than the survey may indicate. As such, I feel that there is a need for a follow-up survey in areas such as central Middlesbrough.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/19">However, the good news from the survey was that, despite the need to extend the service, there was an appreciation of the services provided and of the people providing them. For instance, one respondent said:</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/20" class="indent">&quot;The Doctor took time to listen to my concerns and gave me a full explanation without being patronising.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/21">Someone else said:</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/22" class="indent">&quot;I went to the hospital because I'd been in a sexual attack and the doctor worked with me with areas I wasn't comfortable in expressing.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/23">In June last year, the national support team for sexual health reviewed services on Teesside. The review reflected examples of local good practice but also made several key recommendations, including a move towards much more integration of services. The development of a service specification is an attempt not only to change service delivery but also to try to look more holistically at people's physical, emotional and social needs. In turn, that will be used to try to implement change through positive attitudes and behaviours. I understand that this is the first such reorganisation in this field in the country.</p>
	<p pid="a.134.1/24">In conclusion, I hope that the Minister will follow the progress made in the process and outcomes of the reorganisation, given that it provides one of the first standard models for England. I hope that she will keep a close eye on it, given the concerns that I have expressed. However, great progress has been made, given some of the problems and difficulties that we have experienced. I will leave it at that.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.137.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22b.137.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2009-04-22a.137.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1457" speakername="Dawn Primarolo" speakeroffice="The Minister of State, Department of Health"  colnum="137"  time="016:44:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200809/cmhansrd/cm090422/halltext/90422h0011.htm#09042266000526">
	<p pid="a.137.0/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1714" name="Ashok Kumar">the Member for Middlesbrough, South and East Cleveland (Dr. Kumar)</phrase> on securing this debate.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.0/2">My hon. Friend and I would agree that there is no doubt that the issues around sexual and reproductive health in the 21st century present us with immense challenges&mdash;he touched on some of them&mdash;but that we are making some progress. The problems include rising numbers of sexually transmitted infections, waiting times for clinic appointments, the emergence of chlamydia as a major infection, the need for better contraceptive services and the need to inform all sexually active people about how to reduce their risk of infection and maintain their sexual health and that of their partner. Underpinning all those issues is the need for consistent improvement, not just in Middlesbrough but across the whole country, and bringing services up to the best possible standard.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.0/3">My hon. Friend spoke about health inequalities and the importance of reaching out in particular to members of the population to whom services are still not delivering the kind of response that we would like. I concede that Middlesbrough, in common with many other parts of the country, is very much a work in progress. My hon. Friend touched on that when he discussed improving sexual health. There are stories of real innovation and improvement, which he mentioned but, as he said, the picture is still mixed. It is clear that local services must continue to strive to do better to meet the ambitious national targets that we have set them, as Middlesbrough is doing with its new sexual health strategy. I hope that it will ensure that progress is made. I assure my hon. Friend that I will keep an eye not only on Middlesbrough but on the development of sexual health services in all local health areas across the country.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.0/4">It is important to focus on a few things in Middlesbrough. The town experienced a fall of nearly 24 per cent. in under-18 conceptions between 1998 and 2006, which was very good. Regrettably, it experienced a substantial rise in such conceptions between 2006 and 2007, which left it lagging behind the trajectory for reaching the 2010 targets. After reflecting on that, I, like my hon. Friend, would urge the organisations in Middlesbrough to ensure that, within the important strategy that they are developing, they examine what they need to do to bring teenage conception rates down again.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.0/5">On STIs, we have data only at strategic health authority level, which show an upward trend in HIV, syphilis and gonorrhoea in recent years. I realise that some increases result from more people coming forward for testing, which is a good thing, but it is important that Middlesbrough considers other reasons for the trend within the strategy. There are, however, signs of better things to come. For example, I am encouraged that Middlesbrough's chlamydia screening programme is starting to grow. It is still a little behind where we would like it to be from a national perspective, but it is heading in the right direction. Again, I urge local organisations to commit to faster progress over the next 12 months. My hon. Friend touched on that when he spoke about the need to ensure that there is a proper focus on all communities and on accurate information, and that there is dialogue and partnership not just with the organisations that provide the service but with local communities as well.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.0/6">It is good to see that last year, Middlesbrough offered 99.9 per cent. of all patients an appointment at a sexual health clinic within 48 hours&mdash;a hair's breadth from the national expectation of 100 per cent.&mdash;but consistently, between May 2008 and February 2009, it hit 100 per cent, which is encouraging.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.0/7">My hon. Friend mentioned the visit of the sexual health national support team in June last year. The team made a number of recommendations to local trusts across Teesside, including the need for stronger strategic leadership, more patient involvement in planning new services and campaigns, better governance and integration across genito-urinary medicine, community and primary care services, and specific improvements in the way in which the chlamydia screening programme was being delivered.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.0/8">I am encouraged by the fact that the four primary care trusts covering Teesside have joined forces on the new five-year strategy to improve health and wellbeing, which, as my hon. Friend said, has a particular focus on sexual health for children and young people. Implementation only started this year, but the plans are sensible and they need to pick up on the recommendations of the national support team, as he rightly said. Specific measures include better partnership working between general practitioners, schools and youth workers, facilitated through Children's Trust arrangements in the area. We know from experience across the country that that is crucial in addressing teenage pregnancy.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.0/9">The PCTs also launched a series of new information campaigns to get the safe sex message across to targeted groups. Let me stress that it is particularly important that these campaigns are targeted. I echo the points that my hon. Friend made in saying that the campaigns need to reach excluded young people who have been expelled from school, involved in drink and drug abuse or who have entered the criminal justice system. In many cases, young people, particularly young women who are pregnant, or those who catch STIs, have other problems in their lives and unless we reach out to them early on and deliver a joined-up solution, we are not making the difference that my hon. Friend and I would like to see.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.0/10">Drawing together the sexual health strategy and looking at it over a five-year period, I hope that we will not only shut the door before the horse has bolted&mdash;that is important in the provision of these services&mdash;but that we will still ensure that there is concentration wherever necessary to make people wise after the event. In respect of the plans routinely delivering contraceptive services, I am particularly encouraged that anyone attending an abortion clinic across Teesside will receive automatic advice, support and counselling, which is a step in the right direction.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.0/11">Like my hon. Friend, I have focused on the local dimensions and the work on sexual health in the Middlesbrough area, because, ultimately, it is about local services&mdash;schools, GPs, youth services and prisons services&mdash;all working together in this important area. Local action, however, is not a fig leaf for inaction from Westminster. My hon. Friend said that he was not&mdash;at least, not today&mdash;asking for more money for Middlesbrough, but it is important that we consider the high profile campaigns and the work that is going on.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.0/12">A significant investment is being made by the Government to improve access to contraceptive services. We have invested some &pound;26.8 million over the last financial year to improve women's access to contraception, particularly long-acting reversible contraception. We have allocated these substantial resources. I say to my hon. Friend and to organisations in Middlesbrough that it is important that they ensure that that money is spent speedily and efficiently to support and reinforce the important points that my hon. Friend made with regard to the five-year strategy.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.0/13">A great deal of work is under way to broaden services. I mentioned the national target for everyone who needs one to receive an appointment at a sexual health clinic within 48 hours. We also expect PCTs to look at how they can deliver more choice and a wider range of services, because not everyone feels comfortable going to a GUM clinic. We therefore want more primary care and nurse-led services. I hope that we will see those sorts of things blossoming in Middlesbrough. Many GPs are now broadening their skills by delivering routine sexual health services through locally enhanced services.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.0/14">Although I have already mentioned it, teenage pregnancy is a key concern, which is why we launched the teenage pregnancy strategy, following a detailed report by the social exclusion unit. My hon. Friend touched on inequality in health, leading to economic inequalities and the impact that that has on people's quality of life and their general well-being. Although there has been dramatic progress&mdash;falls are welcome&mdash;we need to recognise that progress is not fast enough: we are behind in our stated objectives and we need to ensure that our ambitious target to halve the under-18 conception rate by 2010 is achieved. To speed up that process, I announced, with my right hon. Friend the Minister for Children, Young People and Families, additional support to help local areas further reduce their rates. That support includes &pound;20.5 million extra funding to improve young people's access to effective contraception, as well as additional support for parents to talk to their children about sex and relationships, so that young people are able to make those choices and feel empowered with regard to their sexual health, rather than feeling pressurised by their peers.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.0/15">In October 2008, my right hon. Friend the Minister for Schools and Learners announced that personal, social and health education, which includes sex and relationships education, will become statutory in all schools. This is crucial, added to other policies, including the strategy in Middlesbrough, if we are to ensure that young people have the knowledge and skills to make safe and responsible choices about their sexual health.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.0/16">We know that where local areas are following the national teenage pregnancy strategy, and where we see strong strategic leadership from PCTs and local authority chiefs, as well as effective partnership working bringing together education, health and youth services to confront the underlying causes of teenage pregnancy, the impact can be significant. We know from experiences across the country, in places such as Hackney and Liverpool, that teenage pregnancy is not inevitable and that if we deliver the services in the right way, fantastic results can be delivered.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.0/17">I appreciate that Middlesbrough faces particular challenges, with pockets of severe deprivation and disadvantage across the city but, together with my hon. Friend, I urge all local organisations involved with the sexual health strategy in Middlesbrough to make a renewed commitment to the strategy and to tackle speedily the key concerns that he has raised today by ensuring that they have not only the framework and the strategy in place, but that they have ways to deliver it to individuals in the communities across his constituency to make real changes.</p>
	<p pid="a.137.0/18" class="italic">Sitting adjourned without Question put (<phrase class="standing-order" code="10(11)">Standing Order No. 10(11)</phrase>).</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

