<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.69.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.69.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.69.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.69.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.69.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.69.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.73.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.73.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.73.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.73.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.74.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.74.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.74.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.74.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.75.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.75.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.75.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.75.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.75.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.75.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.75.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.75.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.79.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.79.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.79.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40379" speakername="Kelvin Hopkins" colnum="79"  time="010:10:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0002.htm#10061517000474">
	<p pid="a.79.0/1">May I say first what a pleasure it is to serve under your chairmanship this morning, Mr. Streeter, and secondly may I convey my sympathy to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40584" name="William Cash">the hon. Member for Stone (Mr Cash)</phrase> on his bereavement? I congratulate the hon. Gentleman on raising this important debate. I thought it important to come along and put a democratic socialist perspective, arriving at the same conclusions from a different perspective on the European Union.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.0/2">This is a critical time in the development of the European Union and in Britain's history. The European Union and, indeed, Britain, are suffering severe economic difficulties. The eurozone is in crisis and the plans of the extreme federalists are unravelling before our eyes. That is a welcome movement, and is happening not before time. It is possible that Germany may be in the process of re-establishing the Deutschmark, or a Deutschmark area. It has great difficulty in doing that, because it is so exposed to other member states of the European Union, which have great economic difficulties, but that shows the folly of imposing a single currency on different economies, with different levels of economic success. It does not work and on many occasions elsewhere it has been proved not to work.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.0/3">The peoples of Europe are deeply sceptical about the European Union and the direction that it has taken. The danger, as the hon. Gentleman said, is that there could be a rise in nationalism as a reaction. Such a reaction results from the fact that the peoples are not listened to. The opposition to much of what the European Union has been doing recently comes from the left. The referendum in France was won-that is the sense in which I see it-by people of the left. The left was also in the lead in the Dutch referendum. Even to go back to the Swedish referendum on joining the euro, which was another substantial no vote, it was the left-trade unionists, socialists and social democrats-who pressed that case.</p>
	<p pid="a.79.0/4">Over and again I have to point out that, although we keep talking about Europe, we are discussing not Europe but the European Union. Europe is a geographical entity with many historical and cultural links. The European Union is an invention of humankind, imposing a political structure on many of the nations of Europe, but it is not Europe itself. Although I may be accused of being a Europhobe I genuinely love Europe. I am culturally European. Clearly, Britain is European. I love European music, languages and literature. I love and enjoy everything about Europe, but I do not approve of the European Union.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.80.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.80.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.80.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.80.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.80.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40379" speakername="Kelvin Hopkins" colnum="80"  time="010:10:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0002.htm#10061517000476">
	<p pid="a.80.1/1">I thank the hon. Gentleman for that positive intervention. In a few weeks I shall be sojourning in Provence, sampling wonderful European wine, listening to music and so on. Europe is a wonderful place, but the European Union is deeply flawed.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.1/2">The hon. Gentleman has said that even this week the European Union is trying to interfere and to impose its will on Britain's decisions about its budgetary situation and economic policies. That was reported yesterday in the <i>Evening Standard</i>, so it is not going away. I hope and trust that the new Government will tell the European Union in no uncertain terms that decisions about our budgetary and economic policies will be decided by the British Government, who will be accountable to the British Parliament, and will not be determined by the European Union. Perhaps the EU is under the illusion that it can manage Britain as well as it has managed the eurozone. That would lead us pretty much into disaster.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.1/3">While I am on the question of the European Union's recent policies, I shall mention enlargement. It is interesting that the hon. Gentleman mentioned Edward Heath. I listened to one of his last speeches to Parliament before he retired 10 years ago, and he made a strong point to the effect that enlargement would not work. He was against it. I do not speak for or against it today, but Edward Heath was strongly opposed to it because he thought that a European Union covering more than the developed nations of western Europe would not work. He wanted a deeper and stronger European Union, possibly with a single currency, but he believed that it could not work if it were to be widely enlarged. One of the reasons I have supported enlargement is that I believed it could weaken the European Union. That may be a cynical view but I thought that over time people would realise that ramming countries or nation states together in that way would not ultimately work. Therefore I have gone along with enlargement. I think it is a way of ensuring that in the end people come to their senses.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.1/4">I am not against international alliances or co-operative relationships with all our neighbours. Indeed, those are vital. I am sure that everyone would be in favour of those things if they were based on democratic Governments agreeing to work together for mutual benefit on behalf of their peoples. That is what the European Union should become, in my view. We must stop the drive towards a federal Europe now, retain what sovereignty we have, and begin to roll things back: the EU and what it has taken over from Britain and other member states.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.1/5">I have often mentioned my concern about the common fisheries policy, which is completely barmy. I think that Edward Heath decided at the last minute that we should go into that, but it has been disastrous. Some of the biggest fisheries in Europe are Britain's, and the EU itself has reported, in the past week or two, that 30 per cent. of fish stocks are at the point of collapse, and all fisheries are being overfished. The only way to overcome that is for fisheries to be restored to member states, which will then have the sense of ownership and responsibility for managing the areas in question. Then fish stocks can start to recover. Reforms have taken place and there are non-fishing areas, but it will not work until member states take over responsibility for their historic fisheries and husband them as they did in the past.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.1/6">The costs of agriculture are enormous and every member state in the European Union has its own approach. Some are more agricultural than others. We are one of the most efficient agricultural nations, but that is only a small part of our economy. Other countries are overwhelmed by agricultural costs and inefficient, small-scale agriculture, but it is up to those member states to manage their own agriculture. If we need to transfer revenues between member states that can be done on a voluntary basis, and if poorer states need to be sustained by richer states perhaps fiscal transfers can take care of that. The common agricultural policy distorts the whole of agriculture and operates in an inequitable way. Some member states pay more than they should and some receive more than they should, in a way that bears little relationship to their relative wealth. We should start to roll back agricultural policy.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.1/7">I hope that the Government will give notice that we want to return to a world in which member states manage their own fisheries-an abandonment of the common fisheries policy. If other member states or the European Union refuse, Britain should give notice that, after a period, we would re-establish control of our historic fishing grounds. I hope that that would put sufficient pressure on the EU to make some sense of it.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.1/8">The real question is one of democracy-of whether the populations of the various member states have control of their own destinies and can choose to be free market capitalist or democratic socialist countries. I have campaigned all my life for a democratic socialist Britain, and I do not want that possibility to be taken away by EU bureaucrats. Equally, some want to see a more free market capitalist world in Britain. We will not want bureaucrats in Brussels telling us that we cannot do things if the people of Britain have chosen to go in those directions. It is about democracy. One of the great advantages of our system of government is that when the population gets fed up with the Government or do not like what they are doing, it can kick them out and put in another Government with a different view. The essence of democracy is a real choice of policy in how people are governed.</p>
	<p pid="a.80.1/9">British economic policy should be decided by British Governments that are elected by the British electorate. As and when we need to co-operate with other member states and other nations, we should do so on a democratically agreed basis. I am sure that that would be most agreeable to everyone, as well as being beneficial. It would also help us resist the tendency to nationalism. If people become frustrated about the EU and the lack of democracy, they may turn to other forms of politics, some of which would be much more unpleasant-one such is nationalism-and there is talk, even in Germany, of serious disorder if things are not made democratic. If the Germans and the Greeks can decide their future, so can we. Although we have friendly relations with other member states, if we rather than the European Commission and the European Union were able to decide our future, everyone would be a lot happier. The danger of extreme politics would go.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.82.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.82.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.82.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.82.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.82.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.82.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.82.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.82.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.82.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40379" speakername="Kelvin Hopkins" colnum="82"  time="010:10:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0003.htm#10061517000480">
	<p pid="a.82.3/1">I thank the hon. Gentleman for that. I take a slightly different view on some of these things because I think that trade union rights should be decided though the democratic governance of member states.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.3/2">International involvement comes though the International Labour Organisation, with its minimum standards for labour regulation. That is where we should stand, but we fall below those standards. I want us to move forward and restore trade union and worker rights at least to the ILO standards, in many ways going back to the sort of regime we had in the past. That would not be agreeable to the Government, no doubt; and other countries, too, might choose another approach. However, that is the approach that I would like to see, and I would like to see it voted on by the working people of Britain, who I hope would support the election of a Labour Government committed to re-establishing trade union and worker rights. It is another example of democracy. I do not want to see the European Union telling me or other trade unionists or socialists that we cannot legislate in a particular way. We should decide our trade union rights, not the EU.</p>
	<p pid="a.82.3/3">The EU and its ultra-federalists have over-reached themselves. It is time to roll back the EU, and restore sovereignty and democracy to member states. Member states may choose to go down a socialist road or a non-socialist road, but the direction should be down to them and to their electorates and peoples. I congratulate the hon. Gentleman on raising this important subject, and I hope that my brief comments are helpful.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.83.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.83.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.83.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40040" speakername="Richard Shepherd" colnum="83"  time="010:25:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0003.htm#10061517000481">
	<p pid="a.83.0/1">I apologise, Mr Streeter, for having missed the opening of the debate and the remarks of my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40584" name="William Cash">the Member for Stone (Mr Cash)</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.83.0/2">I see this debate as being divided into two sections. Sovereignty of Parliament is questioned-indeed, threatened-by the development of the European Union. That may be so if custom and usage has a part in it; sovereignty of Parliament is the profound constitutional doctrine that has determined the course of our development over nearly three centuries. I do not see that concept being threatened for as long as the judges apply it.</p>
	<p pid="a.83.0/3">The conflict that arises with the European Union is entirely of Parliament's making. If there is a conflict, it is because Parliament assents to each and every dreadful transfer of powers-powers of initiation, and powers of legislation-to the EU. The conflict lies with Parliament asserting-contrary, I would argue, to the will of the people-that all these transfers and mechanisms used by the EU are appropriate. That will doubtless be the Government's position today; they will fudge along, arguing that we are, of course, taking strong measures to protect our sovereignty. However, there is no need to protect our sovereignty if we in Parliament are clear about its relationship with the people.</p>
	<p pid="a.83.0/4">I have argued during my time as a Member of the House of Commons that it is not the sovereignty of Parliament in the current age but the sovereignty of the British people that matters, and that for as long as Governments are not prepared to refer the issues involved in that concept to the people themselves, then the question of legitimacy arises. Those are the issues that I think thread through the problem.</p>
	<p pid="a.83.0/5">Anyone who has experienced modern British government knows the tyranny of the majority; the sovereignty of Parliament can indeed assert itself and, as a raw concept, be a great tyranny. Instead of the old traditions, with Governments attempting to win arguments to pursue their policies, they now resort to sheer, simple, straightforward majoritarianism. It is evidenced, of course, in the proceedings of the House, where guillotines are the order of the day. No one can say, in a proper and reliable sense, that the sovereignty of Parliament rests upon consent, in the sense that due and proper process, the seeking of an argument and the ability to develop an argument, is scrupulously observed by Parliament.</p>
	<p pid="a.83.0/6">In respect of the European Union, one speech on what was happening was perhaps the best that I ever heard. Leaving aside all the manoeuvrings, it was an observation made on <phrase class="date" code="1992-02-28">28 February 1992</phrase>, when I was moving my Referendum Bill on Maastricht, that it was incredible that what will now be two generations of those who had run our country's affairs were prepared to surrender that thing which this island, this nation, had believed was among its crown jewels-self-government. That is what this conflict is about.</p>
	<p pid="a.83.0/7">In my lifetime, Governments of both parties have, since the referendum, pursued the giving away of whole areas of self-government. <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40379" name="Kelvin Hopkins">The hon. Member for Luton North (Kelvin Hopkins)</phrase> referred to the right of others to determine our employment laws and the relationship with the trade union movement. Such matters were brought up by Peter Shore, whom we remember as the author of Gaitskill's &quot;a thousand years of history&quot; speech. That was not a rabid anti-European Community measure, or the Common Market as it was then called, but a speech made in the absence of knowing what this would lead to-cautious, intelligent and well worth reading today.</p>
	<p pid="a.83.0/8">Why have the two generations who have run our public policy pursued a policy that undermines the very sense of sovereignty of the British people, and done so often contrary to the wishes of the parties-it destroyed Major-and the people, as regularly diagnosed by public opinion polls? Those who make the laws are accountable. That is what self-government is about in a democratic age. They are accountable to the people, in our instance; hence, I call it the sovereignty of the people. What in those relationships makes the European Union, to which we have outsourced the making of our laws, accountable to the British people? Of course it is not accountable, nor was it ever intended to be. The biography of Edward Heath was mentioned; his regard for the wholehearted consent of the British people was contemptuously disregarded. It took Mr Wilson and a split Labour Cabinet to give a &quot;sort of&quot; referendum to the British people on something of which Mr Gaitskell would have said, &quot;We do not know where this leads&quot;. And we did not know where it led.</p>
	<p pid="a.83.0/9">I praise my hon. Friend the Member for Stone for initiating this wide-reaching debate about where we are and the significance of what we should be. I stand, as does my hon. Friend, for the British people in this argument. In the end, those who give cast-iron guarantees on referendums, or otherwise, destroy faith and trust in themselves and in our system. This debate gives us a way forward to show that our political parties believe in their people, their nation and the trust conferred when they make a pledge.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.84.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.84.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.84.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40497" speakername="Chris Bryant" colnum="84"  time="010:33:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0003.htm#10061517000482">
	<p pid="a.84.0/1">It is a great pleasure to see you chairing the debate, Mr Streeter. Following the contributions this morning, I think the Minister and I will be the more pro-European contributors, which is perhaps ironic. I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40584" name="William Cash">the hon. Member for Stone (Mr Cash)</phrase> on securing the debate and on his consistency, constancy and determination. I am sure he will apply as much rigour to his scrutiny of the new Minister for Europe as he did to that of the previous one; indeed, if anything I suspect his scrutiny will increase slightly. I am sure he will look forward to that. I, too, pass on my condolences to the hon. Gentleman; he spoke movingly about his father and mother. Many of the positions we adopt on European matters spring not only from an intellectual position but from an emotive argument that has sustained itself in our hearts. I do not say it is a bad thing, but an entirely laudable one.</p>
	<p pid="a.84.0/2">One area on which I agree with the hon. Gentleman is European scrutiny: we still do not do it properly-not only in this House but across Parliament. It tends to be done by a very small number of people who could perhaps be described as obsessives or anoraks-I include the hon. Gentleman, my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40379" name="Kelvin Hopkins">the Member for Luton North (Kelvin Hopkins)</phrase> and myself in that category-and we need to find a means of doing it better. The hon. Gentleman is right: we rarely vote on European matters and that ought to change. I have never understood why European affairs debates have to be on the motion for the Adjournment or a general debate. I do not know why they cannot be on a substantive motion before the House, which might encourage the Whips to take a greater interest in ensuring that more people attend such debates, and might extend the range of issues that we discuss. The focus is often narrow-on what is going on in the European Union-rather than broad.</p>
	<p pid="a.84.0/3">My hon. Friend the Member for Luton North and I both nominated the same person for leadership of our party, but we may end up voting for different candidates. I say gently that I also believe in democratic socialism, but I do not believe that it can be built in one country alone. We have to strive for it internationally, because the rights and principles that one adheres to apply to all.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.85.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.85.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.85.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.85.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.85.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.85.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.85.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.85.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.85.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40497" speakername="Chris Bryant" colnum="85"  time="010:33:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0003.htm#10061517000486">
	<p pid="a.85.3/1">If the hon. Gentleman does not mind I will not give way, which means I will shut up sooner. He spoke for some time and we want to hear from the new Minister.</p>
	<p pid="a.85.3/2">There are some significant paradoxes and problems facing the Union. We all rightly fight for fiscal autonomy for each of the member states, but also know that we are economically interdependent. If the euro collapsed it would be bad for the British economy, not least because to all intents and purposes, in many regards we are Europe's banker. We want the rest of Europe to shoulder more of the security burden around the world, particularly in Afghanistan. At the same time, the only way we can achieve that is by cajoling and persuading. We want Europe to punch its weight in relation to the emerging economies-Brazil, Russia, India, China and so on-but we rely on self-discipline to achieve that and often, self-discipline does not work when Russia holds out its paw with an enormous financial offer.</p>
	<p pid="a.85.3/3">We want better protection-for instance, for British people who have chosen to live in Spain and whose houses are being pulled down-but we are not prepared to ensure that Europe has the enforcement powers when rights are not being protected. We want better EU regulations so that financial services organisations in Cyprus, for instance, do a better and more legitimate job, but at the same time we want to ensure the autonomy of the UK financial services industry. We want Romania and Bulgaria to be members of the Union, but at the moment I can see no prospect of allowing Romanians and Bulgarians to work in the UK. I suspect that the same might be true of Croatia and the other countries we hope will become members of the European Union in the near future, such as the western Balkan countries. We want them to join, but I suspect that the Government want a derogation so that those nationals cannot enjoy freedom of employment in the UK from day one; perhaps the Minister will clarify that point later.</p>
	<p pid="a.85.3/4">Likewise, I have always considered the operation of the common agricultural policy immoral in many ways, as other countries are unable to compete because we subsidise so much. At the same time, if there was not a common agricultural policy there would be a French, Italian, German or Greek one, which could be considerably worse. There is a constant clash at the heart of Europe between subsidiarity and collective action, and now is a key moment in European politics to decide how to reconcile such issues. I suspect that such a reconciliation will happen at a dinner on Wednesday evening when Angela Merkel and President Sarkozy meet up. Let me say gently to the Minister that I hope he ends up joining the European People's party, because it is easier to do business sitting at the table when the decisions are being made, rather than waiting for the moment after the decisions have been made by the big players.</p>
	<p pid="a.85.3/5">The hon. Member for Stone did not refer much to his or the Government's sovereignty of Parliament Bill. I have expressed views on the matter before, so I will not bore the Chamber with them again. Suffice it to say that it will either mean nothing because Parliament is already sovereign-it could, if it wanted to, withdraw from the European Communities Act 1972, it could repeal the Act or decide that the legislation no longer applies-or it will mean something, in which case this House can say, &quot;We don't care what has been decided through the co-decision process; we simply disagree.&quot; It could say, &quot;I don't care whether the Government have signed up to it; we disagree and we are going to strike down that legislation.&quot; Such a move, however, is potentially very dangerous because it puts us on course for leaving the Union.</p>
	<p pid="a.85.3/6">I have a few questions for the Minister. He told us that there will be a new Europe Committee-a Cabinet Sub-Committee. Has it met yet and is it to meet in public? It will be fascinating to see the Deputy Prime Minister and the Foreign Secretary publicly debating Europe. Will the Committee include Members from the devolved Administrations in Wales, Northern Ireland and Scotland? Some of the issues that come up at such meetings are devolved responsibilities, so there might be a particular value in including those Members. I have similar questions about the committee on parliamentary sovereignty. Who will chair it and who will be on it? When will it meet and what resources will it have? Will it effectively be a parliamentary commission, and if not how will it conduct its business; and when will it complete its work? Finally, what is its precise position on whether Britain and countries outside the euro should be required to present their budgets to the Commission? It seems bizarre that the European Union or the Commission-in whatever format-should be able to have sight of a British Budget before the British Parliament.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.86.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.86.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.87.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.87.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.87.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.87.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.88.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.88.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.88.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.88.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.89.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.89.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.89.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.89.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.89.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.89.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.90.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.90.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.90.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.90.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.90.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.90.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.92.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.92.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.92.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.92.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.92.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40655" speakername="Karen Buck" colnum="92"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0004.htm#10061517000498">
	<p pid="a.92.1/1">I am grateful for the opportunity to introduce this debate. I appreciate that the whole House had an opportunity to debate the situation in the middle east yesterday, but I am sure that hon. Members will be tolerant our having a debate today that concentrates specifically on issues affecting Gaza, given that they have been of so much concern in the past few weeks.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.1/2">The crisis in Gaza is central to the broader crisis between Israel and Palestine, and that conflict, in turn, is one of the most important in global political terms. It is crucial that British parliamentarians and the UK Government, along with the European Union, the United Nations and the Quartet partners, redouble our efforts to ensure that the blockade of Gaza blockade is lifted. However, that is simply the most immediate step towards a lasting peace settlement, without which we are doomed to see repeats of the present situation. Not least because this point is often misrepresented, it is essential to restate that Israel has entirely legitimate security needs that must be met; but that can happen only if the Palestinian people have the right to a viable and secure state within sovereign borders.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.1/3">As we are all aware, the latest crisis was triggered on <phrase class="date" code="2010-05-31">31 May</phrase>, when Israeli forces boarded one of six vessels in the flotilla carrying aid to Gaza, killing nine Turkish nationals. Accounts of the event vary widely, of course, and have varied over time as different presentations of events have appeared in the media. From the footage that we have seen, there seems to be no doubt that Israeli soldiers were themselves subject to violent attack. However, Israel originally stated that its soldiers were fired on first-a claim for which no evidence has been provided-and that they were equipped with paintball guns, whereas the BBC's &quot;Newsnight&quot; on <phrase class="date" code="2010-06-01">1 June</phrase> showed that Israeli solders had been carrying lethal weapons from the beginning. Although we can draw some conclusions from the footage made available to date, we cannot yet be certain of all that happened on that day.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.1/4">It is crucial that the inquiry into those events wins the confidence of the international community. Whether that can be true of an internal inquiry with foreign observers, as opposed to the independent investigation requested by the UN, is open to doubt at the very least. It would be interesting to hear the Minister's view of the robustness of the internal inquiry promised by Israel.</p>
	<p pid="a.92.1/5">However grave the events involving the flotilla were, they also serve to draw attention to the wider predicament of Gaza.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.92.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.92.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.93.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.93.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.93.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.93.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.93.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.93.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.93.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40655" speakername="Karen Buck" colnum="93"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0004.htm#10061517000502">
	<p pid="a.93.2/1">I have not instituted this debate in order to act as an apologist for Hamas. There is absolutely no doubt that Hamas is a critical player in the crisis in the middle east, and neither I nor, I am sure, other parliamentarians are here to defend its role. The conflict is deep and intractable and Hamas must take responsibility for its share. However, with that important caveat, it seems to me that issue underlying the wider crisis in Palestine and the situation in Gaza is the proportionality of the response and the collective punishment of the civilian population of Gaza.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.93.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.93.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.93.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.93.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.94.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.94.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.94.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.94.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.94.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.94.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.94.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.94.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.94.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.94.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.94.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40279" speakername="Richard Graham" colnum="94"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0005.htm#10061517000509">
	<p pid="a.94.4/1">I congratulate the hon. Lady on securing the debate. Regarding imports and exports to Gaza, she is aware that one of my constituents, Ibrahim Musaji, travelled recently to the area with Bristol Gaza Link-the third time that that organisation has travelled with humanitarian aid for the people of Gaza. Does she agree that, given the heavy decline in both imports to and exports from Gaza, with 95% of private business in effect going bankrupt, life is no longer normal in Gaza? Restoring the normal pattern of trade and humanitarian aid into Gaza is a crucial element for helping the people of Gaza, but doing so managing to exclude weapons from being transported there is a conundrum that we hope the Government might be able to help to resolve.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.95.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.95.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.96.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.96.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.96.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.96.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.97.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.97.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.97.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40072" speakername="Simon Hughes" colnum="97"  time="011:20:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0005.htm#10061517000513">
	<p pid="a.97.0/1">I am grateful for the opportunity to contribute to the debate. I thank <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40655" name="Karen Buck">the hon. Member for Westminster North (Ms Buck)</phrase>, who regularly does this House a service by choosing topical issues, which she has done again. I hope that the way in which she spoke-her carefulness and informed contribution-will commend her comments to all parties.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/2">I welcome you to the chair, Mr Streeter, not only because you are a good chair, but because you, with <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40306" name="John McDonnell">the hon. Member for Hayes and Harlington (John McDonnell)</phrase> and I, co-chaired the all-party group on conflict issues in the previous Parliament. If there is one strategy that we as a Parliament and the new Government need to deploy, it is to use our skill in conflict prevention and conflict resolution. In that context, I also welcome my very good friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40435" name="Alistair Burt">the hon. Member for North East Bedfordshire (Alistair Burt)</phrase> to his new ministerial responsibilities. He was sensitive when participating in the debate on the middle east yesterday in the House, and I know that he and his colleagues come to the subject with huge understanding and dedication.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/3">To make a passing comment to link those words, those of us of the Jewish, Muslim or Christian faith-of course, other people in the House have other faiths or have no religious faith-should have a particular responsibility in this matter. If followers of the three great world faiths, for whom the part of the world that we are discussing is so important, cannot understand that the logic of our faith is that we should seek to accommodate followers of other faiths who share the same belief in the same God, not much of an example is set to the rest of the world when we seek to preach to them.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/4">I have always described myself as both a friend of Palestine and a friend of Israel. I have been actively supporting the case for a Palestinian state since I was a teenager and have always argued that Israel has a right to exist with secure boundaries. I have had the privilege of visiting the area on several occasions, and although I have yet to have the opportunity to go to Gaza, I have frequently visited the west bank.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/5">Let me make some brief comments following the worthwhile contribution of my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40125" name="Stephen Williams">the Member for Bristol West (Stephen Williams)</phrase> to yesterday's debate. First, we all hope that what Tony Blair said publicly yesterday will soon come to pass. The work done by the Quartet to bring about an end of the blockade, either wholly or significantly, is hugely welcome. Achieving such an end will be great progress, not least because the current situation is clearly nonsense, in the sense that although it is terrible imposition on the people of Gaza by virtue of the tunnels and other things, it is a blockade with a conniving exemption. The whole thing has become a sort of international fiction, and the sooner we achieve orderly relations between people on either side of the border, the better.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/6">Regarding the Government of Gaza, people must be allowed to choose their own Governments. They are not always comfortable choices, but the world must understand that it does not help by alienating those Governments entirely. I understand the difficulty. The Government of Gaza, Hamas, must understand-as they were moving to do-that the renunciation of violence and acceptance of the right of the state of Israel to exist have to be preconditions for international acceptance. However, that cannot mean that the people of Gaza or the west bank are not allowed to choose Hamas as their Government. The reason why they do so, as I understand it, is that that party stands strongly for the welfare of the people whom it seeks to represent. In many ways, it has done that more effectively than the other parties in the west bank. We must understand that. We must also understand that we may well have to deal with Hamas for a long time to come. I know that there are forces of enlightenment in the Government that want to make progress, and other Governments are helping them to do that. May we please be clear that precluding Hamas from being participants in the future is not a realistic option?</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/7">Israel is a democracy. As colleagues made clear in the House yesterday, it should be praised for being a democracy, although I share the view that certain forms of proportional representation are not helpful and that the Israeli system with a single chamber of Parliament might be one of them. The implication of a democracy is that the country respects international law. It cannot have it both ways. It cannot say, &quot;We uphold democracy at home,&quot; as it does, &quot;and an enlightened social and other policy,&quot; but then deny international law outside its own territorial waters or abroad.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/8">I have talked to Israeli Ministers and officials about such matters. They really have to understand that international law has to apply to us all or it is discredited. When an inquiry such as the Goldstone report takes place, Israel cannot just then cast it aside because it does not like the findings. The eminent Judge Goldstone clearly did his job appropriately and properly. I heard the cautious words of the Minister yesterday; the Israeli Government must understand that their credibility regarding the events on the flotilla at the end of May will be established only if there is an international inquiry rather than just an Israeli Government inquiry with some international observers. I really believe that.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/9">I and others have met constituents who were on the flotilla. I have heard vivid accounts of how they saw Israeli troops in large numbers-for example, 400 troops on the sixth boat-descend on the fighting. There is video footage and recordings, so there is no shortage of evidence. I just ask the Israeli Government to reconsider their limited willingness to hold an inquiry and for it to be conducted only by them. I want it to be done in a way that they find acceptable, but under the UN's authority, as it has requested.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/10">In that context, my hon. Friend the Member for Bristol West referred yesterday to the motion of the executive of Liberal International, the organisation that represents all Liberal parties throughout the world, which met on Sunday in Berlin. To summarise, it</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/11" class="indent">&quot;Deplores the use of force by Israel commandos&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/12">on that occasion. It</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/13" class="indent">&quot;Deplores the violence caused by some activists on board the flotilla&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/14">The executive expressed</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/15" class="indent">&quot;shock at the resultant deaths and inquiries&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/16">and</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/17" class="indent">&quot;Demands the restoration of liberty of the Israeli Arabs who have been on board the flotilla&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/18">It</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/19" class="indent">&quot;Supports the UN Security Council's call for a prompt, impartial, credible and transparent inquiry&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/20">examining the actions of all parties, and</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/21" class="indent">&quot;Strongly calls on the Middle East quartet, and the US government in particular, to urge all parties to return to the Road Map and observe international law.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/22">Let me make one last point about the future. Gaza has a very difficult future. It is a small enclave surrounded by other countries, as the hon. Member for Westminster North rightly described. The history of enclaves in international law is not happy. Berlin is the last one that springs to mind-separate from the rest of its country with a corridor established. I understand the policy of both my party, and that of the Government. The traditional policy of countries such as ours is to accept a two-state solution: a Palestinian state and an Israeli state. That might be right but, just as there will need to be an imaginative solution to the future of Jerusalem, which will have to be the capital of both countries if there is to be lasting peace, so there needs to be an imaginative solution to how Gaza is linked with the west bank.</p>
	<p pid="a.97.0/23">To have simply two separate territories without connection will not be an adequate way forward. There might have to be a special and protected connecting strip. There might have to be a renegotiation of land settlements that would include those settlements that are illegal as part of the package, as well as a return to old boundaries. There may have to be in the long term a United Nations presence to give security on what was mandated territory for us between the '20s and the '40s, and other international friends to support it. We, as a country, may have to play a significant role with the Quartet and other countries in guaranteeing the territories, the boundaries and the peace of Israel and Palestine if we are to persuade both Governments to feel confident about the future. I hope that my friend the Minister and his colleagues will be positive and think laterally about the way in which a solution might work, as well as work enthusiastically to make sure that the matter is one of the highest foreign policy priorities of the Government in the days and months ahead.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.100.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.100.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.100.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40335" speakername="Emily Thornberry" colnum="100"  time="011:29:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0005.htm#10061517000514">
	<p pid="a.100.0/1">I rise to my feet as a friend of Palestine, and much to the furious incomprehension of a large number of my constituents, I do so as a steadfast friend of Israel, despite the provocation. Last summer, I sponsored an Adjournment debate on the Spirit of Humanity-a boat carrying humanitarian supplies that was trying to break the siege of Gaza. On that occasion, Israeli forces intercepted the boat-we presume in international waters, although the Israeli Government refused to provide details of the boat's position, despite requests from British Ministers-but thankfully there was no violence. In the light of that and other previous incidents, should not the British Government have been alert to possible problems with the latest flotilla? Given that the Israeli media reported threats from the Israeli defence forces, making it clear that the ships were likely to be attacked, what actions, if any, had the British Government taken to avert those attacks, particularly knowing that British citizens were on board?</p>
	<p pid="a.100.0/2">My constituent, Alex Harrison, was on board the Spirit of Humanity last year, and undeterred by that experience, she was also a passenger on the Challenger 1 ship, which formed part of the flotilla that was attacked again by Israeli forces on <phrase class="date" code="2010-05-31">31 May</phrase>. Could the Minister tell us what assessment the Government have made of the legality of the Israeli attack on the humanitarian convoy? What assurances has he had from the Government of Israel about whether there will be any more attacks in international waters on boats carrying British citizens?</p>
	<p pid="a.100.0/3">Over the weekend, we heard more detail about the inquiry that is to be set up by Israel. We understand that it will include a foreign element and observers such as David Trimble. Will the international community have full confidence in that inquiry and its findings? Will it be independent and transparent? Will the Israelis, the Palestinians and, perhaps most importantly, the people of Turkey have full confidence in its findings? As Cathy Ashton, the High Representative of the European Union put it in <i>T</i><i>he T</i><i>imes</i> yesterday, will that inquiry be &quot;credible, rigorous and impartial&quot;?</p>
	<p pid="a.100.0/4">In the debate yesterday, my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40085" name="Richard Burden">the Member for Birmingham, Northfield (Richard Burden)</phrase> stated the obvious: there have been inquiries in the past on Israel, and perhaps one need go no further than to ask Tom Hurndall's family about their experience of Israeli inquiries to explain why some people might be slightly cynical about an Israeli inquiry. Another issue is just how wide that inquiry will be and who will be questioned? Will Alex Harrison be asked about her experience on that boat?</p>
	<p pid="a.100.0/5">In preparation for this debate, I spoke to Alex. As I said, she was on board Challenger 1. It was flagged in the United States. She would like me to highlight the illegality of the Israeli action. The men who were killed were on the Marmora, which was registered in the Comoros islands, which are off Madagascar. It is her view, and that of many others, that the seizing and killing of the flotilla's passengers while in international waters is nothing less than piracy. She says that they were some 80 miles away from Israel and were sailing away from Israel when they were boarded.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.0/6">The Israeli action on <phrase class="date" code="2010-05-31">31 May</phrase> may constitute breaches of international law that could be tried in the International Criminal Court. Alex was one of the boat's crew. She told me that the Israeli forces came on to the boat, firing plastic bullets. All the glass on the boat broke. People were then pushed to the ground on to the glass. She was the last to be stopped, as she was on the bridge. Two members of the Israeli defence forces came up. Two Australian journalists-Kate and Paul from <i>T</i><i>he Sydney Morning Herald</i>-were with her, and they identified themselves. In response, they were tasered. It was a completely terrifying experience.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.0/7">There was no violence from Alex's boat towards the Israeli defence forces, yet those on board were treated with huge violence. She says that she has hand marks on her arms and legs from when she was picked up and carried from the boat. Once they were carried from the boat, all their items were bagged up and labelled. They have not had them back. The Israelis now say that they do not know where they are. She was told that she would be deported to Turkey. She had the clothes she stood up in. She had no passport and no money. She had not been to Turkey-she had come from Greece-and yet the Israelis said that they would deport her to Turkey.</p>
	<p pid="a.100.0/8">Alex refused to go and so was one of the last to be deported. She was in a pen with 15 other women, and she witnessed some women next to her being hit about the head. They were not treated as badly as the men. She saw some men at the airport who were badly beaten, including Ken O'Keefe, who was so badly injured that he was not able to board the plane. She was some 5 yards away from an Irishman called Fiachra O'Luain as he was beaten around the head-she saw that going on. She also saw Turkish men, who had been injured and come out of hospital, being put on to the plane. Well, to say that they were put on to the plane is inaccurate-they were walking on to the plane as best they could. Some had been shot in the feet and were on crutches. There were no wheelchairs. She was not allowed to assist the men. If any attempt to try and assist them was made, people were hit again. Although she had experienced brutality from a distance in the past, she had never experienced such face-to-face, one-to-one brutality over such a sustained period. She said that they were sworn at, abused and laughed at throughout. That was unnecessary-gratuitous, in her view-and she certainly would like to give evidence to any inquiry. If necessary, she would like the matter to be taken to the International Criminal Court. One can understand why, given her experiences.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.101.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.101.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.101.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40239" speakername="Mark Lazarowicz" colnum="101"  time="011:29:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0006.htm#10061517000515">
	<p pid="a.101.0/1">May I put on the record that the constituent whom I referred to was also one of the protestors on the Challenger 1? She reports a similar account of what happened on the boat and in Israeli custody. Her account illustrates the real issues being raised by a number of credible people from the UK, and I hope that the Government will respond to them in the positive way that my hon. Friend requests.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.102.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.102.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.102.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.102.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.102.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.102.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.102.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.102.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.102.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.102.4" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.102.4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40335" speakername="Emily Thornberry" colnum="102"  time="011:29:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0006.htm#10061517000520">
	<p pid="a.102.4/1">It goes further than psychological damage: the fact that there is not a steady stream of proper goods going into Gaza also undermines people's health. Moreover, the fact that no exports are allowed out of Gaza means that the economy has been undermined and that the people are dependent on Hamas, which allows and taxes the tunnels. Civil society is therefore undermined even further and people become increasingly dependent upon Hamas. When a poor woman wakes up in the morning wondering how to feed her six children, she does not think to herself, &quot;This is Hamas's fault,&quot; but, &quot;This is the Israel's fault.&quot; That continues to feed extremism and undermine the very security of Israel. Those of us who believe in a two-state solution are fundamentally worried about that and are very concerned about what is happening.</p>
	<p pid="a.102.4/2">I will not go through all my examples-I am sure that hon. Members are aware of them-but Cadbury's creme eggs somehow get through the tunnels and nobody can afford them. Some 12,000 buildings need to be rebuilt, and 44% of Gazans are unemployed and so on. The fundamental point, however, is that the siege of Gaza is not hurting Hamas; it is destroying the lives of thousands of ordinary Gazans. The EU is the largest donor to Palestine, but aid is not enough. It is also Israel's largest trading partner, and we have some clout at EU level. We in the EU must be more confident and do more to put pressure on Israel to ensure that the people of Gaza are treated fairly. I very much hope that EU Foreign Ministers will adopt a united position and that Britain will fully support it. That may include questioning whether an internal Israeli investigation of what happened to the flotilla on <phrase class="date" code="2010-05-31">31 May</phrase> is sufficient.</p>
	<p pid="a.102.4/3">It is also important for us to be more active diplomatically in the middle east. The problem is not going away-we must address it. We must end the blockade, which is morally outrageous and politically self-defeating, and as I said here last summer, we must open the gates and close the tunnels. Many organisations based in my constituency-such as Medical Aid for Palestinians, Save the Children, UNICEF and Merlin-work very hard to support the people of Gaza; but, ultimately, their good work simply gives us the space to exert moral and political courage to ensure a two-state solution and peace for everyone.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.103.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.103.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.105.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.105.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.105.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.105.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.106.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.106.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.106.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.106.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.107.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.107.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.107.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40370" speakername="Louise Ellman" colnum="107"  time="011:52:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0006.htm#10061517000526">
	<p pid="a.107.0/1">The reality is that Gaza is run by Hamas, an Islamist organisation that is proscribed by the EU, the USA and Canada as a terrorist organisation. Its regime has led to this dreadful situation for the people of Gaza. That cannot be ignored; it is a fact. More questions need to be asked about that flotilla, focusing on that sixth vessel. What is the role of the Turkish IHH-again, a charitable organisation linked to Hamas and other terrorist organisations? What about the recording that was made in relation to that sixth vessel, showing that when the Israelis repeatedly asked it to land at Ashdod, the reply came back, &quot;Go back to Auschwitz&quot;? What about the fact that people on that sixth vessel were armed with metal rods with knives, and that a lynching of Israelis was attempted? I have no doubt that the majority of people on those vessels were genuine peace activists, but were they infiltrated by somebody else with other ideas?</p>
	<p pid="a.107.0/2">What about the reports that we have seen since those events in the Turkish media? Families of people who were regrettably killed on that vessel have stated that their partner-the husband in one case-said that he wanted to be a martyr. Even more damning, what about the broadcast that was made on Hamas TV on <phrase class="date" code="2010-05-30">30 May</phrase>, the day before the incident happened, when a university lecture said that the participants in that flotilla wanted to die as martyrs even more than they wanted to reach Gaza? What a condemnation.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.107.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.107.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.107.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.107.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.107.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.107.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.107.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.107.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.108.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.108.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.108.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.108.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.108.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.108.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.108.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.108.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.109.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.109.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.109.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.109.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.109.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40295" speakername="Andy Slaughter" colnum="109"  time="012:03:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0007.htm#10061517000535">
	<p pid="a.109.1/1">I do not think that I shall have time to take interventions.</p>
	<p pid="a.109.1/2">Travelling on that convoy were many independent, well-respected people, including an Israeli-Arab member of the Knesset, Hanin Zoabi, and Henning Mankell, the respected Swedish author. All those people have given eye-witness testimony as to the brutality and violence of the Israeli forces, who wholly unnecessarily stormed the convoy in international waters in the middle of the night. No real explanation can be given as to why that was necessary. I have heard a number of those eye-witness accounts, which are compelling and have the ring of truth about them. However, the solution to the absolutely black-and-white situation that we have heard described by the two sides so far is an independent inquiry.</p>
	<p pid="a.109.1/3">I have three sets of questions for the Minister. On the responsibilities of the British Government, the treatment of British citizens needs to be looked into. Issues include the violence and brutality that many of them allege the Israeli forces meted out to them over a prolonged period, and the confiscation of their belongings. There is also the refusal of consular access. There has been great criticism of the embassy in Tel Aviv for not pressing as hard as other countries' embassies to get access to our citizens. All those matters require answers.</p>
	<p pid="a.109.1/4">The second issue on which the Government should be prepared to act is the search for a more independent role for the inquiry. It would be useful to hear the Minister talk about the effectively tokenistic gesture of appointing Lord Trimble, who is known as a supporter of the boycott of Hamas and a friend of Israel, and who cannot be seen as impartial, and a judge who does not believe in an international element to the inquiry. That is not an independent inquiry; it is the basis for a whitewash, and it would be useful if the British Government asked for a genuine international inquiry.</p>
	<p pid="a.109.1/5">Thirdly, the Minister was quoted as saying that he did not think that</p>
	<p pid="a.109.1/6" class="indent">&quot;the British Government is talking about lifting the blockade&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.109.1/7">on Gaza. That quotation, which was in <i>The Guardian</i> last Thursday, may be wrong, but it would be disappointing if it was correct. We need to lift the blockade on Gaza; we need not to ease the restrictions or simply to see a greater number of supplies going in, but to restore full commercial and civil life to Gaza. Again, that is something that the Government should strongly support.</p>
	<p pid="a.109.1/8">We are talking not about factional organisations, but about organisations such as the United Nations Relief and Works Agency and the International Committee of the Red Cross, which have said clearly and in terms over the past few days not only that the blockade is &quot;illegal&quot; and a &quot;humanitarian catastrophe&quot;, but that it constitutes</p>
	<p pid="a.109.1/9" class="indent">&quot;a collective punishment imposed in clear violation of Israel's obligations under international humanitarian law.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.109.1/10">I would like the British Government to make similar pronouncements and at last to put pressure on the Israelis to lift the wholly unjustifiable and inhuman punishment of 1.6 million civilians, which they have imposed simply because they have the ability to do so and because the rest of the world is not, at the moment, prepared to stand up to them.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.110.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.110.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.110.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.110.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.110.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.110.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.110.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40135" speakername="Ivan Lewis" colnum="110"  time="012:11:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0007.htm#10061517000538">
	<p pid="a.110.2/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40655" name="Karen Buck">the Member for Westminster North (Ms Buck)</phrase> on securing this debate and on her passionate, balanced and highly effective contribution, which was an extremely good start.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.2/2">There is absolutely no doubt that the plight of the people of Gaza is both an humanitarian tragedy and a political crisis. The blockade of Gaza is unacceptable and unsustainable, and it is now essential to remove all obstacles not only to humanitarian assistance but to the materials and resources required to begin rebuilding homes, public infrastructure and the Gazan economy. However, that will happen only if Israel can be assured that systems are in place to ensure that arms and arms components cannot be smuggled or got in any way into Gaza. It is therefore essential that the Quartet and the Arab League work with Israelis and Palestinians to come up with a credible plan to end the blockade while meeting Israel's legitimate security concerns, which is the basis of resolution 1860. The Opposition warmly welcomes the work of Tony Blair and Baroness Ashton on those matters.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.2/3">I have a couple of questions for the Minister. What do the British Government believe should be the EU contribution to such a plan? How quickly can a plan be put in place? Neither in this debate nor in yesterday's did anyone refer to the Egyptians putting in place security infrastructure to close the tunnels and prevent smuggling. Has that been done and, if so, what effect has it had on the tunnels?</p>
	<p pid="a.110.2/4">On the Israel defence forces' raid on the Gaza flotilla, I made it clear during last night's debate that we welcome the Israeli Government's decision to set up an inquiry with the involvement of two international observers. However, we will watch closely to ensure that the inquiry meets the tests of independence, transparency and credibility. My questions to the Minister about the flotilla relate to many of my hon. Friends' contributions. Will British citizens who were on the flotilla have the opportunity to give evidence to the inquiry, and what efforts will the British Government make to facilitate that? What happened to the humanitarian assistance on the flotilla? We hear different accounts.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.2/5">On aid, this country can be very proud of the aid that we provided to both the west bank and Gaza. The sad irony of this debate, for reasons that many hon. Members have raised, is the contrast between progress on the west bank and in Gaza. We should always pay tribute in such debates to the leadership of Prime Minister Fayyad and to President Abbas for the improvements in security and economic growth on the west bank. We should also continue to support the two-year plan launched by Prime Minister Fayyad towards Palestinian statehood.</p>
	<p pid="a.110.2/6">I have some specific questions for the Minister. Will the new Government maintain our commitment to &#163;210 million in aid over three years for the west bank and Gaza? Was the &#163;19 million for UNRWA in Gaza announced by the Secretary of State for International Development last week new money, or part of the &#163;210 million that was already committed?</p>
	<p pid="a.110.2/7">Let me briefly raise the continued detention of Gilad Shalit. I think that all Members agree that his detention is unacceptable and that he should be released without delay or precondition. It was very moving for me to meet his father not that long ago and hear the human misery that the family is going through. What more does the Minister think that the UK and the EU can do to secure the release of Corporal Shalit, particularly in their dialogue and contact with Arab states?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.111.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.111.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.111.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.111.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.112.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.112.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.112.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.112.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.112.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.112.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.113.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.113.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.113.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.113.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.113.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.113.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.113.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.113.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.113.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.113.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.113.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.113.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.114.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.114.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.114.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.114.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.114.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.114.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.114.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.114.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.114.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.114.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.114.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.114.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.114.6" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.114.6" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.115.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.115.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.116.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.116.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.116.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.116.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.118.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.118.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.118.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.118.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.119.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.119.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.123.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.123.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.123.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.123.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.126.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.126.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.128.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.128.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.128.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40195" speakername="Jon Cruddas" colnum="128"  time="013:14:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0010.htm#10061517000564">
	<p pid="a.128.0/1">I want to put on the record that we had this row about the BSF plans in Barking and Dagenham with the previous Government. There was a controversy in the first phase of the BSF programme, in that we were on the list and were taken off it because of some difficulties with the imposition of academies. So this is an argument we have had with Governments either side of the aisle.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.128.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.128.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.130.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.130.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.130.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.130.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.130.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.130.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.130.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40333" speakername="Andrew Turner" colnum="130"  time="013:25:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0010.htm#10061517000566">
	<p pid="a.130.2/1">First, I take this opportunity to congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40263" name="Mark Harper">the Member for Forest of Dean (Mr Harper)</phrase>, on his appointment as Parliamentary Secretary, Cabinet Office. I have known him for many years. The Prime Minister quickly recognised the many qualities that I know he possesses, and the people of the Forest of Dean also knew a good thing when they saw it: they had the wisdom to elect him in 2005, and again last month with an increased majority. I know that he will bring common sense and good judgment to his office.</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/2">I am grateful for the opportunity to discuss constituency boundaries for islands. Not many of us are greatly affected by the issue, but it is extremely important to those of us who are. Islands come in many shapes and sizes. There are those with a tiny population, such as the Scillies with scarcely 2,000 residents. There are islands joined to the mainland by road or rail, such as Anglesey and Hayling island, and even Portsmouth. Most important for this debate is that there are islands with significant populations that remain isolated, with no physical link to the mainland. They include Na h-Eileanan an Iar-more commonly known as the Western Isles-Orkney and Shetland, and my own constituency of the Isle of Wight.</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/3">Last month's election was fought on boundaries with average constituency sizes of 71,000 electors in England, 66,000 in Scotland, 56,500 in Wales and just over 63,000 in Northern Ireland. The UK average was 69,500. I agree wholeheartedly with the Minister that England as a whole is under-represented in the current system, particularly since devolution has introduced another layer of politicians in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland. With roughly 110,000 electors, my constituency is the largest by quite a margin. The constituency of <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40413" name="Angus MacNeil">the hon. Member for Na h-Eileanan an Iar (Mr MacNeil)</phrase>, whom I am glad to see here today, has fewer than 23,000. His, at a fifth of the size of mine, is the smallest constituency, again by a significant margin.</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/4">The coalition Government intend to increase the size of constituencies generally, creating fewer, more evenly sized and, in the majority of cases, more populous ones. I understand that the aim is to have an average electorate of 77,000, which would reduce the number of MPs by 10% and cut the cost of politics. The principle of greater equality is good, the aim of reducing the cost of politics is laudable and, from experience, I know that it is perfectly possible to represent a large constituency. My noble Friend Lord Norton of Louth's excellent report from the commission to strengthen Parliament found that larger constituencies may foster</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/5" class="indent">&quot;a closer, longer-term relationship between member and constituents&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/6">We must, however, remember and examine the practicalities</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/7">We can learn from the wisdom of those who have looked at the issues in depth before us. The Boundary Commission last reported on the Isle of Wight constituency in 2007, using figures from 2000. The electorate in 2000 was 103,000, 33% larger than the average. The commission considered severing part of the island and putting it with a mainland constituency, but concluded that to do so would</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/8" class="indent">&quot;disregard the historic and unique geographical situation&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/9">and</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/10" class="indent">&quot;create confusion and a feeling of the loss of identity&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/11">for islanders. It also stated that</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/12" class="indent">&quot;communications would be difficult both for the electorate and the Member of Parliament.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/13">We were on the point, under the current system, of having two MPs, which I would have supported, but I understand that that proposition is no longer on the table.</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/14">If the island had one MP with 77,000 electors, 32,000 people or 12 electoral wards on the island would need to be included with a mainland seat. I have looked at all the possibilities. It could mean either a ferry from Ryde, with a hinterland from Wootton to Arreton to Bembridge, or a ferry from Yarmouth, with a hinterland from Cowes to Ventnor-the southern most point on the island-or from Cowes, East Cowes and Newport. I have to say that all of those proposals are barmy.</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/15">Experts from the Boundary Commission for Scotland have looked carefully over the years at the case for merging the Western Isles with Skye. The commission found in 1981 that that would be &quot;unworkable or intolerably difficult&quot;, and, in 2004, it came to the same conclusion, saying that the arguments against change</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/16" class="indent">&quot;remained as strong now as they were then.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/17">To get anywhere near an electorate of 77,000 would mean the Western Isles being lumped in with a huge part of the Scottish mainland. If including Skye in the constituency would prove &quot;unworkable or intolerably difficult&quot;, how on earth would merging the Western Isles with the mainland work in practice?</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/18">Such difficulties are even more acute in Orkney and Shetland, a constituency with a population of more than 32,000. Meeting the new quota would likely entail a union with the nearest mainland constituency, Caithness, Sutherland and Easter Ross. Such a drawing of boundaries would result in a constituency that was hundreds of miles from end to end.</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/19">Part of the problem is geographical. The only access to the Isle of Wight is by sea. There is no tunnel, bridge or scheduled air service, and crossing the Solent can be expensive and time-consuming. The even bigger problem, however, is that islands and islanders are very different from the mainland and mainlanders. Those who live on islands are, by definition, more insular. The word &quot;insular&quot; means being of or pertaining to an island or islands, but it also means being detached, standing alone or isolated. It is clear to me why the word is used in both ways, but one must live on an island to really understand. Many people on the Isle of Wight travel to the mainland only rarely. The Solent is much more of a barrier, both physical and psychological, than any other English county boundary. If any part of the island were to be merged with the mainland, it would be reasonable for the mainland MP to live on the north island. After all, that is where the majority of his constituents-about 46,000-would live. He would not, however, be considered a part of the island community. I suspect that the hon. Member for Na h-Eileanan an Iar recognises that feeling in the communities that he represents. It would be a very sad outcome if people were made to feel more distant and remote from their elected representatives.</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/20">There are good reasons why both the largest and smallest UK constituencies are island constituencies, and those reasons should be respected. We should not simply disregard the work of those who have looked at the issues before, sacrificing workable and sensible proposals on the altar of principle, however good and well-intentioned that principle might be.</p>
	<p pid="a.130.2/21">It might seem odd that I am arguing for more rather than less work than other Members of the House, while at the same time arguing for the continued existence of the smallest UK constituency. However, it is because I live on an island that I understand the unique nature of islands. They are very special communities and special places that need special consideration. I understand that these matters are still being deliberated and that final decisions have yet to be made about how the policy is to be implemented. Will the Minister please give me an assurance that, when the Government move forward with plans to equalise constituency sizes, they will recognise the unique nature of island electorates? I hope that his common sense and good judgment will applied in spades to this question.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.132.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.132.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.132.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40413" speakername="Angus MacNeil" colnum="132"  time="013:36:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm100615/halltext/100615h0010.htm#10061517000567">
	<p pid="a.132.0/1">Today, we see an alliance of islanders-an alliance that was perhaps created by the <i>Daily Mail.</i> During the election campaign, the newspaper sent one of its reporters, Mr Robert Hardman-perhaps all the reporters from the <i>Daily Mail</i> are hard men-to both Na h-Eileanan an Iar and the Isle of Wight. Whether his aim was to create some mischief, I do not know-far be it from me to cast aspersions on such an august publication as the <i>Daily Mail</i>-but we were chosen because I represented the smallest constituency in terms of the number of voters, and the Isle of Wight is, of course, the constituency with largest number of voters. The <i>Daily Mail</i> succeeded in uniting us in a common cause. The largest and the smallest numerical constituencies in the UK are of one mind: their islands are indeed special.</p>
	<p pid="a.132.0/2"><phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/40333" name="Andrew Turner">The hon. Member for Isle of Wight (Mr Turner)</phrase> spoke eloquently and forcefully for his constituency. I will confine my remarks to my constituency, other than to point out to the Minister that it is odd for a democracy to be looking to cut the elected element of Parliament while almost daily-certainly monthly-we have news of further appointments to the unelected portion of Parliament. Does that mean that, when the Government leave office, the percentage of Parliament elected by democratic means will be far smaller than when they entered office? Quite how that makes the UK look internationally, other than like a laughing stock, I am not certain. Quite how the Government feel about that, other than queasy, I shall not speculate.</p>
	<p pid="a.132.0/3">My constituency is the length of Wales. The Prime Minister might want to give me a territory the size of the Yukon, but that would not serve voters well at all. Areas, of course, need coverage. When a population grows in an area, a constituency with a maximum headage is usually created, obviously with some sensible anomalies, such as the Isle of Wight. That is to ensure an equality of treatment so that all voters have the same kind of representation and access to their MP as voters have in a more urban and populated setting. I speak particularly from my own perspective in Na h-Eileanan an Iar.</p>
	<p pid="a.132.0/4">To give the Minister a small example, last Friday I conducted what I consider to be a small surgery on part of one the islands in my constituency, on the west side of Lewis-actually, we went down to Harris for part of it. We had an ordinary day. We covered 279 miles that Friday-a distance just a little longer than that between Glasgow and Liverpool. That is what I have to do to serve people in a remote island rural setting. I mention that just to give an idea of what has perhaps not been considered when people look on a purely numerical headage basis.</p>
	<p pid="a.132.0/5">I think that it is right that people in rural areas have the same services and access as those in an urban setting. In the islands, we are used to a poor broadband service-British Telecom has a number of exchanges in the area that it has not upgraded yet, although I hope that it will-and I would hate to see democracy and people's expectations of democracy reach the same standards. In a democracy, everybody requires equality of treatment, representation and access to their MPs.</p>
	<p pid="a.132.0/6">Finally, I wish to make a more political and perhaps more constitutional point. The Union is supposed to be a union between two nations; it does not mean having a 50:50 split of MPs between Scotland and England, as the Minister is no doubt aware. Obviously, as a Scottish National party Member, I would like there to be no MPs at Westminster who represent Scottish constituencies, but we live with the present situation and the way in which the cards have been dealt. In the meantime, I cannot allow what is proposed to proceed without protest and without making common cause with the Isle of Wight in the far south of England and alerting the Government to the dangers of exactly what the Prime Minister and his Liberal Democrat friends might do if they cut the representation of the highlands and islands.</p>
	<p pid="a.132.0/7">I am sure that the Government will not do that. They will reflect, particularly on the strong arguments made by the hon. Member for Isle of Wight, and act with thought and consideration. They will make sure that Scotland does not lose any more MPs, because that would be a retrograde step for people in the highlands and islands and, as the hon. Gentleman pointed out earlier, it would be almost impossible to represent the Western Isles and Skye. We hope that such a mistake is not made, that the Minister will listen and that the right decision is reached. In the meantime, until the day of independence, I shall continue to make common cause with the hon. Member for Isle of Wight.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.133.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.133.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.135.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.135.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.135.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.135.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.135.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.135.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.135.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.135.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.136.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.136.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15a.136.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2010-06-15b.136.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

