<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.179.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.179.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.179.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.179.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.179.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="179"  time="unknown" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080603/halltext/80603h0001.htm#08060369000001">
	<p pid="a.179.1/1"><i>Motion made, and Question proposed</i>, That the sitting be now adjourned.&mdash;[Mark Tami.]</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.179.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.179.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.179.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1896" speakername="Anne McIntosh" colnum="179"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080603/halltext/80603h0001.htm#08060369000474">
	<p pid="a.179.2/1">I welcome you to the Chair, Mr. Martlew; it is a pleasure to serve under you today. I am delighted to have secured this debate, particularly given the timing, because there is a meeting next week on <phrase class="date" code="2008-06-12">12 June</phrase> to confirm the proposed location that affects my region.</p>
	<p pid="a.179.2/2">I welcome the Under-Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1620" name="Iain Wright">the hon. Member for Hartlepool (Mr. Wright)</phrase>. It is always a pleasure to see him. I did my level best to prevent him from taking his seat in a previous by-election, but he is welcome today. I hope that he is able to share with hon. Members the reason that the Minister for Housing felt unable to be here. I raised this issue in business questions just before the House rose for the recess. To my certain knowledge, the Minister for Housing has never presented herself to the House to make the case in person for eco-towns, take questions from hon. Members and respond to our constituents' concerns. I am sure that there is a good reason for that and I am sure that the Under-Secretary will be able to share it with us. However, it bodes ill for the Government's policy when the Minister mainly responsible for it and who presents it on occasions in the Cabinet does not feel able to attend.</p>
	<p pid="a.179.2/3">This sorry scenario started on <phrase class="date" code="2008-04-03">Thursday 3 April</phrase> at 9 am, when parliamentary convention was breached in the first instance. Rather than the Minister for Housing coming to the House to make an oral statement&mdash;there was no pressing business that would have prevented such a statement being made, as is normal practice&mdash;I was invited for the first time ever to a conference call with a Minister. I showed willing. I had never experienced such a call before. I found it a little offensive and insulting that the constituents that I have the honour to represent were excluded from the process of open parliamentary scrutiny. I was kept on the phone for a full three or four minutes before deciding that this was not the best way forward. So we were faced with a written ministerial statement on <phrase class="date" code="2008-04-03">Thursday 3 April</phrase>.</p>
	<p pid="a.179.2/4">The first noteworthy point is that in the written statement the Housing Minister mentioned the prospectus that the Government announced on the web in July 2007, which set out the key criteria for eco-towns:</p>
	<p pid="a.179.2/5" class="indent">&quot;Eco-towns must be new settlements, separate and distinct from existing towns but well linked to them. They need to be additional to existing plans, with a minimum target of 5,000-10,000 homes&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.179.2/6">Presumably, the Government consulted on the basis of that prospectus. So it was surprising that in the written ministerial statement the Minister mentioned new settlements of between 5,000 and 20,000 people. Therefore, the size of the settlements already consulted on had doubled or quadrupled. That goes to the heart of my concerns about the eco-towns policy and the process of presenting it.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.180.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.180.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.180.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.180.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.180.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.180.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.180.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.180.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.180.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.180.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.180.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.180.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.181.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.181.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.181.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.181.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.181.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.181.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.182.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.182.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.182.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.182.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.182.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.182.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.182.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.182.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.183.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.183.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.183.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.183.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.183.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.183.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.184.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.184.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.184.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.184.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.184.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.184.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.184.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.184.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.184.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.184.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.184.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.184.5" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.184.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1896" speakername="Anne McIntosh" colnum="184"  time="009:30:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080603/halltext/80603h0001.htm#08060369000496">
	<p pid="a.184.5/1">My hon. Friend makes a powerful point. Surely people would prefer to live in an established town such as Bognor Regis, which is so well represented by him, if I may say so. I do not see what the attraction would be to the new towns.</p>
	<p pid="a.184.5/2">I have received a number of representations. Some of the most interesting ones, to which I would like the Minister to respond because I am sure that he has received them as well, are from the Royal Society for the Protection of Birds and the Wildlife Trusts, which are very concerned not only that eco-towns should have regard to newts and other such creatures, but that they should have a concept of being eco-friendly and having green credentials in that regard. The Campaign to Protect Rural England is very disappointed at the eco-towns shortlist, because the eco-towns are being put in the wrong place; they are remote and unsustainable.</p>
	<p pid="a.184.5/3">I have welcomed the opportunity to have this debate. I understand that the city of Leeds region will confirm its proposals. I am delighted that it has excluded Skelton as an eco-town site, because that would be completely inappropriate, for the reasons that I have given. The timing of today's debate is very opportune. I regret that the Minister for Housing is not in her place and that the Minister who will respond to the debate has been put in this difficult position, but I am sure that he will rise to the occasion. Not once has the Minister for Housing come to the House and defended her decision, put herself under scrutiny or taken questions from colleagues. I hope that this Minister will send a firm message from this Chamber today that there is no place in parliamentary procedures for a conference call that involved my hon. and learned Friend the Member for Harborough and I being kept hanging on for up to 10 minutes, without a formal record being made, even by the Minister's colleagues in the Department, of what was said in the call.</p>
	<p pid="a.184.5/4">I put it to the Minister that the consultation process is flawed. It is a sham. It barely pays lip service to democracy. It flouts normal planning procedures. As my hon. Friend the Member for Banbury said, we have not even had sight of a planning statement, which should be the very essence of the consultation at this stage. It is very difficult for parliamentarians to consult and be consulted on this matter. It is very difficult for the elected councillors to be consulted. It is very difficult for those residents whose properties will be blighted. The Minister must respond to that point. What message is his Department giving to those such as the Henman family, who have vigorously opposed the proposed site in Oxfordshire? What response will the Department give if their property prices are blighted?</p>
	<p pid="a.184.5/5">These eco-towns are neither sustainable nor environmentally friendly. That poses the question why most of them&mdash;all but three&mdash;are to be built in Conservative-held seats, not Labour areas. If the Government feel so strongly about them, their flagship policies should be in their flagship constituencies.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.185.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.185.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.185.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.185.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.186.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.186.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.186.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.186.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.186.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.186.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.187.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.187.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.187.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.187.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.187.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.187.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.187.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.187.3" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.187.3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1953" speakername="Hugh Bayley" colnum="187"  time="009:57:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080603/halltext/80603h0002.htm#08060369000505">
	<p pid="a.187.3/1">I am not persuaded by the hon. Gentleman's argument. The Government rightly set out the ambition of achieving zero-carbon homes, but they will achieve that aim only by pushing through pilots to show how it will be done&mdash;to test the new technology in order to discover what works on the larger scale and what does not.</p>
	<p pid="a.187.3/2">The Government have financed some important small-scale pilots. In my constituency, City of York council recently gained funding from a developer, as a result of planning gain, for a new headquarters for its neighbourhood services direct works department. However, there was only enough money to build a conventional building. The council wanted to do better than that, and it sought funding from the Government. The Government provided &pound;681,000 to allow the new headquarters to be built with environmentally friendly technology. It has a timber-framed construction, with straw bale cladding&mdash;my hon. Friend the Member for Vale of York will be pleased to hear that the straw was grown in the Vale of York. It has low-energy under-floor heating, a wind turbine and photovoltaic cells, and that it collects rainwater for washing the council's vehicles. It is designed to high environmental standards.</p>
	<p pid="a.187.3/3">A second small-scale housing pilot is being built in Victoria way in York by York Housing Association with Government funding. Eight new homes are being built to the German PassivHaus standard, which includes high levels of insulation. They will gain heat from the sun through windows that allow the greenhouse effect to warm them; they will have excellent airtightness, using a whole-house ventilation system which will extract 95 per cent. of the heat of the warm air from the house and put it into the cold air being drawn from outside to save energy. It is expected that no fuel will be used for 10 months of the year, and fuel use will be much lower than normal for the remaining one or two months.</p>
	<p pid="a.187.3/4">Those small-scale pilots demonstrate the technology that will be required when building homes for the future. It is not something that can be left for 10 or 20 years: once a house is built it is difficult to retro-fit such high environmental technology. We will be left with those houses for 100 years. We have to make the changes now. It is one thing to make changes on a small scale by piloting the technology, but we need also to do it on a community scale so that we can deal with the sort of issues that the hon. Member for Vale of York so rightly pointed out, such as the environmental impact of travel to work or for shopping. It is not quite as simple as she suggests&mdash;that one should not build in rural areas because it is bad; and that one should build in urban areas because it is good. One must balance the whole environmental envelope, including, of course, the transport issues that she raises.</p>
	<p pid="a.187.3/5">Unless we find places to pilot that new technology on a community scale, we will not learn enough, or learn it quickly enough, to meet the goal of zero-carbon housing set out by the Government. I support the Government on the principle of piloting environmentally sustainable building on a large scale. They clearly need to consult carefully over locations, and take account of local views&mdash;although almost any large-scale housing development will attract opposition. However, I also ask them to consider putting money into the building of eco-districts in existing towns and cities&mdash;and they could certainly be Labour towns and cities.</p>
	<p pid="a.187.3/6">When the first eco-towns prospectus came out, I discussed the requirements with people in York and asked whether it would be possible to make a bid, using two large brownfield sites in York&mdash;one a large site on old railway land about two thirds the size of the area within the city walls; and the other on a large site currently occupied by British Sugar. At the limit, those two sites, which are almost connected, would together be enough for 5,000 homes. I took the view that the area was probably too small for what I imagined would be the one Yorkshire eco-town pilot. However, if the Government want to pilot the ability to create viable communities within urban areas as well as the countryside, they should be piloting eco-districts within existing towns.</p>
	<p pid="a.187.3/7">Many colleagues wish to speak, so I shall conclude with some specific questions for the Minister. The latest &quot;Eco-towns: Living a greener future&quot; document identifies the Leeds city region as an area for an eco-town. It says that eco-towns will have a 30 to 50 per cent. affordable component and that they will include social housing to rent. If the 10 local authorities of the Leeds city region work together, identify a site and build a new community, the nomination rights of that social housing will lie directly with one of those local authorities, yet it is clear that the entire sub-region will need to work together. The north Leeds-Harrogate-York triangle is often called the golden triangle&mdash;housing pressures are most intense in that part of Yorkshire. Will the Minister tell us whether the nomination rights for social housing will be shared by authorities in the region once a site has been identified and built?</p>
	<p pid="a.187.3/8">City of York council has put forward a bid to the Government for housing growth point status for the combined railway land and sugar factory site, which is called the York Northwest project. The plan appears not to fit the criteria for eco-town or eco-district status under the Government rules, so will they support the growth point bid?</p>
	<p pid="a.187.3/9">Clearly, York has enormous housing demand, huge problems with housing affordability and a lack of political consensus about where to build, partly because it has never defined the green belt&mdash;that did not happen under the Conservatives, Labour or Liberal Democrats, nor under the current hung council arrangements. I have asked the Joseph Rowntree Housing Trust to organise a round-table conference to bring everyone together to build a consensus on where the housing in York should be built. I hope that my hon. Friend the Member for Vale of York will attend, but will the Minister ensure that Yorkshire Forward, the Government regional office and DCLG are represented at the meeting?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.189.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.189.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.189.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1476" speakername="Andrew Lansley" colnum="189"  time="010:11:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080603/halltext/80603h0002.htm#08060369000506">
	<p pid="a.189.0/1">I congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1896" name="Anne McIntosh">the Member for Vale of York (Miss McIntosh)</phrase> on securing this timely debate&mdash;it is only four weeks until the end of the consultation on the original shortlist of eco-towns.</p>
	<p pid="a.189.0/2">The Government announced last July that they were in favour of eco-towns. The Prime Minister said that he wanted five and for the first to be built at the Oakington barracks in my constituency&mdash;the Minister has visited the site&mdash;which will become the new town of Northstowe. We welcomed that and said that we wanted Northstowe to be the first eco-town. However, since the announcement, an outline planning application for Northstowe that does not meet eco-town standards has been submitted.</p>
	<p pid="a.189.0/3">As the Minister knows, a high-quality guided busway is being built to provide a rapid transit solution to Cambridge's major employment sites. Northstowe could certainly accommodate 8,000, and the outline planning application is for 9,500. The new town ought to be the first eco-town, which would mean that it meets a higher standard for sustainable homes, for example, but the outline planning application came in at level 3, so the local authority is having to go back and say that it wants at least level 4 to begin with. Ministers said that the development ought to be powered by solar and wind, but the application is for only 20 per cent. renewable energy, so the local authority has had to say that it should be better.</p>
	<p pid="a.189.0/4">The Government do not have no control over the situation because English Partnerships is a principal partner in the new town. We in Cambridgeshire wanted Northstowe to be in the eco-town list and for it to be the first eco-town. If the Government get behind Northstowe with English Partnerships and support the local authority&mdash;we have high-quality transport and the housing growth fund is examining new biomass combined heat and power for energy supply&mdash;we could create the first eco-town and begin building homes perhaps within only two years.</p>
	<p pid="a.189.0/5">We were therefore surprised, when the Government published the shortlist of eco-towns, that Northstowe was not in the list after the Prime Minister said it would be. By contrast, Hanley Grange&mdash;for the benefit of my constituents who will read the <i>Official Report </i>of the debate, it will be at Hinxton Grange&mdash;is in the list. Why is Northstowe, which could be the first prototype eco-town, not in the list, and why is Hanley Grange, which is in my constituency, in the list when it should not be? Time will not permit me to go through all the reasons why the Hanley Grange proposal does not meet the criteria for an eco-town&mdash;the consultation will demonstrate that&mdash;and this is not the occasion on which to set those out in detail.</p>
	<p pid="a.189.0/6">As my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1382" name="Tony Baldry">the Member for Banbury (Tony Baldry)</phrase> rightly pointed out, the policy is the planning framework that the Government are creating to bring the list forward. The county structure plan inquiry in Cambridgeshire went through all the sites of potential new towns and established that Northstowe and Waterbeach were the first and second priorities respectively and that the third, which is being actively promoted by Cambridge city council, is for an urban district like that described by <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1953" name="Hugh Bayley">the hon. Member for City of York (Hugh Bayley)</phrase>&mdash;for an urban extension of 12,000 on the east Cambridge site on the airport to have an eco-town that is part of Cambridge city. We are actively working toward that, as set out in the county structure plan. The developers for Hanley Grange put forward their proposal for the county structure plan&mdash;it was submitted in April 2004&mdash;but it was rejected because there was no infrastructure south of Cambridge to support the development. The only green thing about the proposal is that it has been recycled since 2004.</p>
	<p pid="a.189.0/7">The critical point is that we have the planning structure in place. We have the county structure plan and the local development plan has been adopted, but three weeks ago the Minister published a regional spatial strategy that said that the infrastructure south of Cambridgeshire would not support a large new settlement. The RSS said that an examination leading to the next RSS of the possibilities for a large new settlement with the associated changes to infrastructure necessary to support it should begin.</p>
	<p pid="a.189.0/8">We supposedly have a plan-led system and the whole of the local plans have been adopted&mdash;there is no bit of draft planning outstanding. The plan in Cambridgeshire is for 42,500 new homes, of which 17,000 will be affordable, and I must tell hon. Members who talked about urban and rural areas that my constituency is the combined urban and rural district in which new homes are being built faster than anywhere else in Britain. On what basis can Ministers say, &quot;Hang on a minute: do something that isn't in the plan, that slows the process of development locally, and that every local authority believes will impede progress in building the homes that are required for the local population and for the employment growth in the area&quot;? Why is Northstowe not in the list, and why is the plan-led system not following the established plans?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.191.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.191.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.192.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.192.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.192.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.192.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.192.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.192.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.194.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.194.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.194.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.194.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.194.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.194.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.195.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.195.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.195.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.195.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.195.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1513" speakername="Daniel Rogerson" colnum="195"  time="010:29:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080603/halltext/80603h0003.htm#08060369000515">
	<p pid="a.195.1/1">The hon. Gentleman makes a sensible proposal, and a bidding process that involves local authorities, representing their communities, is a far more effective one. The hon. Member for South Cambridgeshire explained how it had been hoped that one proposal would move forward with the full benefit of Government support; however, those hopes were dashed, and to add insult to injury, another site not too far away, which does not necessarily meet the criteria, was selected. That seems bizarre.</p>
	<p pid="a.195.1/2">We must be sceptical about whether the transport links can bring about truly sustainable settlements that will offer the country the benefits it wants in meeting CO2 reduction targets. It is not only that the houses that are built need to be energy efficient; there are questions about the materials that will be used, and whether the techniques will be available for sustainable building practices. The hon. Member for City of York mentioned a public building in his constituency that meets those standards, and houses that are intended to do so. However, that will not necessarily happen, and I will welcome any reassurance that the Minister can give about how the building is to take place, and whether the settlements will truly be able to be called eco-towns.</p>
	<p pid="a.195.1/3">My party wants reform of the planning system, not along the lines that we discussed yesterday, but more to ensure that local authority development plans are sustainable, incorporating targets for CO2 emission reductions to encourage the development of renewable energy facilities, and accounting for the climate change consequences of policies, including transport. Of course, strong feeling was expressed in the very close votes last night about whether the Planning Bill goes far enough, with respect to major infrastructure projects, in putting climate change at the heart of what is happening.</p>
	<p pid="a.195.1/4">We believe that we should move much closer to the passive house standard that Germany has had for some time, which the hon. Member for City of York mentioned&mdash;certainly no later than 2011. If we did that, carbon emissions from new homes would be reduced by 95 per cent., compared with existing stock. That would bring us far closer to where we need to be. As the CPRE has pointed out, even if the eco-towns provide the number of houses that are being suggested, that is only about 7 per cent. of the homes that will be built in the relevant period. That will not have a huge effect. It is somewhat tokenistic as far as fulfilling a commitment to reduce carbon emissions.</p>
	<p pid="a.195.1/5">Planning policy must be based on evidence, on local and regional need and on consultation, and carrying the community along. I am reminded of a recent debate on large-scale housing development, in Northamptonshire. We discussed exactly the same issues, and exactly the same point of view in the community, whose hopes of having their views listened to were raised and then seemed to be dashed. Planning policy does not deliver for those communities. The process that we are discussing is not based on evidence or need, and is certainly not based on consultation.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.196.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.196.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.198.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.198.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.198.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.198.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.198.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.198.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.198.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.198.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.199.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.199.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.200.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.200.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.200.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.200.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.200.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.200.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.200.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.200.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.201.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.201.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.201.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.201.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.202.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.202.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.202.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.202.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.202.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.202.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.202.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.202.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.203.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.203.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.203.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.203.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.203.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1570" speakername="Colin Burgon" colnum="203"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080603/halltext/80603h0004.htm#08060369000532">
	<p pid="a.203.1/1">I want to start a debate and challenge what I think is a too-cosy consensus among all the political parties about the unchallenged supremacy of market forces. I also want to challenge the dominant idea&mdash;again, held across the political stage&mdash;that there should be automatic support for the free movement of capital, goods and, in the context of today's debate, labour. We must also therefore discuss the role of the Government in&mdash;some people would say interfering, we would say intervening in&mdash;the market. Today, we are talking about the impact of the free movement of labour on people working in this country, but I also want to consider the impact of economic conditions on determining and dictating the situation for migrant workers.</p>
	<p pid="a.203.1/2">All political parties and leaders applaud the theory of flexible labour markets. I, for one, do not share their enthusiasm, because in the current climate of weak employment regulation, it means low pay and diminished employment rights for both migrant workers and resident workers. I draw the House's attention to the recently published House of Lords Select Committee report that dealt with the economic impact of immigration. It made it clear that what I would argue to be under-regulated migration has sustained, and is helping to sustain, an economy that, again, I would argue&mdash;the facts seem to substantiate this&mdash;is increasingly dominated by employment that is low paid, insecure and leaves workers, resident and migrant alike, vulnerable and ill equipped to face the rising costs of living and all the increasing challenges of today's period of economic turbulence.</p>
	<p pid="a.203.1/3">The recent TUC report, &quot;Hard Work, Hidden Lives&quot; makes it clear that the proposed agency worker developments&mdash;the Government's discussions with the TUC and the CBI&mdash;may not make any meaningful difference to the status quo. The Minister will be pleased to know that I shall look at that issue, I hope, in some depth. Perhaps my colleagues will join me.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.203.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.203.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.203.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1677" speakername="David Taylor" colnum="203"  time="011:00:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080603/halltext/80603h0004.htm#08060369000533">
	<p pid="a.203.2/1">My hon. Friend will recall the 2004 Warwick agreement. Is he as disappointed as I am about the lack of progress on the Temporary and Agency Workers (Equal Treatment) Bill, introduced by our hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1569" name="Andrew Miller">the Member for Ellesmere Port and Neston (Andrew Miller)</phrase>, which would tackle some of the concerns that my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1570" name="Colin Burgon">the Member for Elmet (Colin Burgon)</phrase> is about to detail to the Chamber this morning? I congratulate him on securing the debate, which is very important indeed.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.203.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.203.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.204.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.204.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.204.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.204.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.204.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.204.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.204.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.204.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.206.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.206.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.206.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.206.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.206.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.206.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.206.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.206.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.207.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.207.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.207.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.207.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.207.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.207.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.207.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.207.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.208.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.208.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.208.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.208.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.208.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.208.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.208.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.208.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.210.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.210.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.210.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.210.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.210.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.210.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.210.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1526" speakername="Jon Cruddas" colnum="210"  time="011:32:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080603/halltext/80603h0006.htm#08060369000553">
	<p pid="a.210.2/1">I know it is customary as part of the protocol on these occasions to congratulate my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1570" name="Colin Burgon">the Member for Elmet (Colin Burgon)</phrase> on securing the debate, but I also wish to do so because of the content of his contribution. He touched on some profoundly difficult territory in terms of race, class and demographic change in this country, but he navigated through those issues creatively and touched on some public policy remedies that need to be part of the mix&mdash;not least, because of the point he made at the end of his speech.</p>
	<p pid="a.210.2/2">As we enter more difficult economic waters, there is a possibility that the scramble over scarce resources and the race to the bottom that is arguably occurring in certain sectors of the labour market will become more intense and racialised. That raises real issues for the future in terms of what is euphemistically called community cohesion. My hon. Friend touched on that creatively. In the community that I represent, these are not abstract matters, and the issues of migration, low pay and insecure work need to be centre stage in terms of our public policy debates&mdash;not least because, as my hon. Friend mentioned, certain forms of compound abuse are involved. Often relates to systemic failures in the Home Office, but forms of landlordism that I thought had been abolished 20 years ago, and forms of exploitation at work also compound the insecurities of some of the most vulnerable people in our communities.</p>
	<p pid="a.210.2/3">I congratulate my hon. Friend on securing the debate because we often ignore such issues. We convince ourselves that we have presided over an economic miracle during the past 10 years, but the problems will not go away when we hit choppier times during the next few months and years.</p>
	<p pid="a.210.2/4">I, too, listened to the programme on the radio this morning about the report from the Gangmasters Licensing Authority that painted a much worse picture of exploitation than it had imagined a few years ago. Last year, the authority revoked the licences of some 20 gangmasters for abuse and it expects to revoke about 60 by the end of this year. There has been a series of dreadful abuses in terms of transport and accommodation deductions, which make people's relative poverty even more intense than in terms of their nominal hourly wage cost. The TUC commission on vulnerable employment estimated that 2 million people are in such employment across the economy. It defined vulnerable employment as</p>
	<p pid="a.210.2/5" class="indent">&quot;precarious work that places people at risk of continuing poverty and injustice resulting from an imbalance of power in the employer-worker relationship&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.210.2/6">We cannot have this debate without a broader discussion about poverty in the UK today. Let us consider the broader context in terms of in-work poverty. I refer hon. Members to the recent Institute for Public Policy Research report entitled &quot;Working out of poverty: A study of the low-paid and the 'working poor'&quot;, and the figures that it has provided for us. More than 5 million people&mdash;more than one in five of those in work, or 23 per cent. of all employees&mdash;are paid less than &pound;6.67 an hour. That is in the formal economy. Some 1.4 million poor children&mdash;the same number as in 1997&mdash;live in working households. Although since 1997 the number of poor children in workless households has fallen from 2 million to 1.4 million, the level of working poverty has been maintained and, as a proportion of total poverty, has increased over the last decade.</p>
	<p pid="a.210.2/7">Arguably, therefore, we have seen a Government anti-poverty strategy that has been an in-work strategy. We need to develop a more systematic working poverty strategy that confronts issues relating to people's day-to-day employment. Half of all poor kids are in working households, up from 40 per cent. 10 years ago; and 57 per cent. of poor households are working households, up from 47 per cent. 10 years ago. The issue of working poverty, which relates to some of the points raised by my hon. Friend the Member for Elmet, will not go away. Indeed, as a proportion of total poverty, it is rising, which means that different remedies are needed from those based simply on getting people into work. The poverty that people face in work now needs to be addressed.</p>
	<p pid="a.210.2/8">The report by the House of Lords Economic Affairs Committee, &quot;The Economic Impact of Immigration&quot; refers to the role of immigration in the creation and expansion of a broader low-paid economy. I refer, too, to some of the evidence that my hon. Friend recited, as sent to me by the Fair Pay Network. There were three pieces of evidence that he used to describe a contemporary, modern-day incomes policy. The use and abuse of migrant workers in that respect is demonstrated by some of the specific empirical evidence that he documented.</p>
	<p pid="a.210.2/9">The first piece of evidence is from Professor Dustmann: every 1 per cent. increase in the ratio of immigrants to natives in the working age population led to a 0.5 per cent. decrease in wages for the lowest 10 per cent. of wage earners. Secondly, my hon. Friend used evidence from the City of London corporation that reinforced the argument that significant downward pressure on wages at the bottom end of the labour market is occurring through the abuse of migrant workers. Thirdly, there was evidence from Steve Nickell that negative wage effects are concentrated in sectors, including social care and cleaning, where low-paid hourly work is most concentrated.</p>
	<p pid="a.210.2/10">A series of different empirical studies reinforce the idea that migrant workers are used in certain segmented labour markets to reinforce patterns of low-wage, low-skill employment, and that the bulk of recent migration to the UK is gravitating towards jobs that are low paid&mdash;around the level of the minimum wage. Professor Dustmann concludes that immigrants appear to be most concentrated at precisely the same points where we find the most negative wage effects.</p>
	<p pid="a.210.2/11">All of that reinforces the evidence in academic economic texts over some years of the intensification of what is called an hourglass economy&mdash;growth at the top end of the labour market, but a broadly expanding low-wage, low-skill labour market. It is often linked to patterns of public service contract structures and is interlinked with patterns of net migration and abuse by employers.</p>
	<p pid="a.210.2/12">For me, as I said, this is not an abstract debate. Our borough has the lowest-cost housing market in Greater London and is the lowest-cost wage economy in terms of the wage rates of the resident population, so we have seen the effects at first hand. Our community is the fastest changing, not least because of right to buy, which has created a private housing market that we have never had before. Over the past few years, there has been an intensified scramble for limited resources&mdash;most noticeably housing, but also public services more broadly.</p>
	<p pid="a.210.2/13">In the workplace, we have seen a race to the bottom, with tensions over access to, and the quality of, paid employment. That takes us back to the empirical evidence that employees are being paid below the national minimum wage, as was mentioned earlier. The best example of that, which we pointed out to the Low Pay Commission when it was gathering evidence for its recent report, involved Lithuanian employees on a public contract in London at the back end of 2007 who were paid about &pound;2.50 an hour, or barely half the minimum wage. They were eating cold beans from a tin for their lunch while they were on the job. That is not a unique experience; such stories ricochet around the community, so everyone knows them, which creates a heightened sense of vulnerability across broader labour markets.</p>
	<p pid="a.210.2/14">There is thus the challenge of massive demographic change, intensified insecurity in the workplace and a scramble for limited public services, with a legacy of poor public services in a poor community. The collision between change and that legacy of need is creating a rich, fertile ground for the far right to inhabit, so it is no surprise that the fastest-changing community in Britain is also on the front line of the battle against the far right, which is moving in and intensifying the racialisation of access to public services. There are also tensions over workplace activity and insecurity, and unless the Government step in to provide remedies for the heightened sense of vulnerability in the workplace, the situation will become more intense.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.213.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.213.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.213.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.213.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.213.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.213.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.213.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.213.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.214.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.214.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.216.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.216.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.217.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.217.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.217.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.217.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.218.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.218.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.218.0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1445" speakername="Sarah Teather" colnum="218"  time="011:59:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080603/halltext/80603h0007.htm#08060369000560">
	<p pid="a.218.0/1">I congratulate <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1570" name="Colin Burgon">the hon. Member for Elmet (Colin Burgon)</phrase> on securing the debate. He made a very interesting and detailed speech, and it is obviously something that he feels passionate about. It will not surprise him to hear that I am not sure I agree with all of his philosophy. I agree with some of his solutions, but disagree with many.</p>
	<p pid="a.218.0/2">Not all migrant workers are vulnerable. The CBI's 2007 employment trends survey shows that demand for skilled and managerial professional workers remains strong. Most firms hiring staff from the new EU member states, for example, expect them to be skilled, so although many migrant workers fall into the category being discussed today, it is important to make it clear that many are highly skilled and do not fall into that class of vulnerable workers. I certainly welcome, however, the focus on vulnerable workers, who are in issue in my constituency, but it is important that we distinguish between those working illegally and those working legally but being exploited. The outcome might be the same, but the solutions are clearly different.</p>
	<p pid="a.218.0/3">The hon. Member for Elmet quoted the TUC and Lords reports as examples of recent reports discussing this issue. However, another recent report, by the Work Foundation, provided a highly academic analysis of the impact of migration on wages and employment. I recommend that all hon. Members interested in this issue read that report. It reached slightly different conclusions from the House of Lords report and quotes the OECD meta-analysis of all the work done in the developing world and found a very limited impact on employment and wages. Certainly on employment, if anything, the impact was found to be slightly positive, although that is a temporary effect. On wages, it found that the impact was negligible for most countries&mdash;the exception being the USA, where there is no effective minimum wage law. That is very important.</p>
	<p pid="a.218.0/4">The Work Foundation also examined the trends in wages in low-paid employment, particularly in the hotel, catering and construction industries, and found great transience in wages, but the pattern largely followed the trend in minimum wage rises. Wage rises slowed when the increase in the national minimum wage also slowed. The picture is obviously very complicated, and it is difficult to demonstrate an overall effect at the macro level, but that is not to say that there are not local impacts. A number of hon. Members have discussed local impacts in their own constituencies. It is also very clear that there are particular impacts where there is abuse of migrant workers working legally. The hon. Member for Elmet and others spoke about the chances of being inspected for breaching minimum wage legislation&mdash;the figures are shocking&mdash;and about other abuses of existing legislation. The question is: how do we deal with that? There is always a temptation to legislate further, which has been part of the debate so far. I agree with <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1463" name="John Bercow">the hon. Member for Buckingham (John Bercow)</phrase> when he said that there is a tendency to instinctively legislate, but we can enforce existing legislation. There is no point in creating new legislation if we cannot enforce existing practices.</p>
	<p pid="a.218.0/5">I welcome the agreement between the CBI, the TUC and the Government on temporary agency workers. I look forward to seeing the details, however, because it is difficult to see from this vantage-point exactly what we are dealing with without knowing the detail of the behind-the-scenes discussions. We will certainly look at that when legislation is published, later this year, I assume. However, I am concerned that the rights of many people already working legally for an agency for more than three months are not enforced, and I question whether tightening up the legislation will necessarily yield our desired outcome. New legislation will not necessarily create a change in practice. The priorities must be a change in the levels of information and enforcement.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.219.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.219.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.219.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.219.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.219.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.219.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.219.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.219.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.219.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.219.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.219.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.219.5" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.219.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1445" speakername="Sarah Teather" colnum="219"  time="011:59:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080603/halltext/80603h0007.htm#08060369000566">
	<p pid="a.219.5/1">I absolutely agree. The hon. Gentleman makes a sensible point.</p>
	<p pid="a.219.5/2">I shall move on to the issue of illegal workers, which the hon. Members for Dagenham (Jon Cruddas) and for Islington, North (Jeremy Corbyn) spoke about extensively. I feel particularly strongly about it because I see it in my constituency. If there is an impact on the low-paid, that is where it comes from, because illegal workers are neither covered by minimum wage legislation nor protected by employment legislation. One only has to take an unlicensed minicab in London and have a conversation with the driver to understand that we have the most over-qualified minicab drivers in the world. The number of people I have spoken to who are doctors or professors in their home country but who in this country are forced to drive minicabs illegally is particularly shocking.</p>
	<p pid="a.219.5/3">In my constituency, on Chichele road, whenever the media are looking for a story about illegal casual labour, they tend to film the number of casual labourers waiting, sitting on walls outside people's homes from dawn each day. Some of them are legal and just looking for casual labour, but many are not, and as successive waves of immigrants have been unable to regularise their status, we have seen the change in the nature of those people sitting on that wall on Chichele road. It is a tragic situation and those people are very vulnerable.</p>
	<p pid="a.219.5/4">The Government's own estimate is that there may be as many as 600,000 irregular migrants in the UK. Many of them are working illegally. Several hon. Members talked about the Churches' campaign, &quot;Strangers into Citizens&quot;, which is a very good and interesting campaign. It is good to have a coalition of people campaigning on behalf of vulnerable people who are often overlooked. We really must face the facts about that group of people: we simply cannot deport all the people who are here illegally. It costs about &pound;11,000 for each deportation, and I have seen a number of shocking examples of botched deportations, when people should have been sent home but the Government have been unable to manage it. No way are we going to deport them all, so the Government should concentrate on those who are criminals and make no contribution to the UK, ensuring that we bring the others out of the shadows so that they have an opportunity to integrate. They should be paying tax in this country.</p>
	<p pid="a.219.5/5">If one has been in the UK for 10 years, has not committed a criminal offence and can speak English, one should be eligible for a two-year work permit, which should be the beginning of an earned route to citizenship. We should ask people to demonstrate their long-term commitment to the UK, enable them to do it and fast-track them on to indefinite leave to remain.</p>
	<p pid="a.219.5/6">Complementarity is the argument used by employers for the need to recruit workers from overseas. Everybody says that it is a short-term solution to the lack of skills in this country, but we are not doing anything to ensure that we aim that work at areas where there are skills shortages. I would like the Government to consider the possibility of increasing the cost of those work permits but ring-fencing the money to be used in targeted areas to increase skills, particularly where there are shortages in the economy. That interesting solution might meet many people's concerns.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.220.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.220.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.222.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.222.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.222.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.222.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.222.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.222.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.222.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.222.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.222.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.222.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.222.5" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.222.5" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.223.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.223.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.224.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.224.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.225.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.225.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.227.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.227.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.227.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.227.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.229.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.229.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.229.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.229.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.230.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.230.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.230.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.230.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.231.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.231.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.232.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.232.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.232.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.232.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.234.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.234.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.234.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.234.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.235.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.235.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.235.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.235.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.235.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1850" speakername="David Drew" colnum="235"  time="012:59:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080603/halltext/80603h0009.htm#08060369000587">
	<p pid="a.235.1/1">I am delighted to introduce the debate at this time. I wish that my thinking about the issue at the same time as the Food and Agriculture Organisation meeting takes place in Rome were more than a coincidence, but these things sometimes conspire for all the best purposes. At least the presence of Mugabe has given the meeting some added piquancy, although I would like to have thought that the presence of my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for International Development and another friend, the Chairman of the Select Committee on Environment, Food and Rural Affairs, <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1590" name="Michael Jack">the right hon. Member for Fylde (Mr. Jack)</phrase>, would have been enough to generate some interest in it.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/2">Food and food politics are highly contentious issues at the moment. We all know that recent price increases have raised the issue to a new height of awareness, and I wish mainly to talk about the UK scene, although I shall finish by saying a few things about the international scene. I am well aware of what the Under-Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs, my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1491" name="Jonathan R Shaw">the Member for Chatham and Aylesford (Jonathan Shaw)</phrase>, speaks on, and I wish to keep the debate mainly in the domestic context.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/3">It is quite difficult to define food policy, let alone food policy security, but I am clear that we have a problem in this country and in the western world, and I want to highlight some things that we ought to take account of. As always with these debates, I can raise the issues, but I hope that the Minister will respond with some answers about the Government's thinking.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/4">There is obviously a question from the outset, because it is difficult to identify which Department and which Minister will take responsibility for the issue. My hon. Friend is in the Chamber to answer today, and in the true sense of joined-up government, I hope that he will talk to other Ministers about it, because the Food Standards Agency reports to the Department of Health, the Cabinet Office is spending a great deal of time on the issue of food co-ordination, and other Departments&mdash;such as the Department for Business, Enterprise and Regulatory Reform and the Department for Children, Schools and Families&mdash;are involved with the issues about what we feed our children in schools. A panoply of Ministries take partial responsibility for the matter.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/5">I am going to cheat and not come up with my own definition of food security, because it has been very well done in the recent Cabinet Office paper, to which I shall give some publicity, because it is very good at trying to settle the old differences and delineate how to take the new strategy forward. The Cabinet Office says:</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/6" class="indent">&quot;The term 'food security' is used in different ways but it is essentially a matter of identifying, assessing and managing risks in food supply.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/7">It continues:</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/8" class="indent">&quot;The multiple dimensions and interpretations of 'food security' can hinder any discussion.&quot;</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/9">It then looks at the six key criteria by which food security should be measured. They are: availability, which is to do with production, supply and so on; access&mdash;to do with affordability and physical accessibility; affordability in its own right&mdash;to do with what households can and cannot afford; safety&mdash;to do with what we eat and feeling secure in the knowledge that what we eat will not poison us or do long-term damage to our bodies; resilience, as the food chain has to be capable of being protected and supported; and finally, confidence, as there must be public confidence in all those issues, so that people feel that they can purchase the food.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/10">There is so much that I could say in the debate, but I shall keep to the main bones of my contention, whereby I hope that the Government are moving towards a proper food policy based on addressing the current problems of where we get our food from and how it can be supplied at a reasonable price. We all know that people are becoming increasingly aware of the issue globally, but we have seen rising food prices over the past few months in this country. Questions are being asked of the Prime Minister, the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs as to how we can perhaps forestall some of the increases or at least put them in the context of how we can make progress. The price rises vary enormously.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/11">I will go on the record about this. I have said it before; it is not something that I mind being reported. I always saw the dangers of a cheap food policy. We became pretty complacent, believing that food prices would always stay low. We were not asking enough questions about where that food was coming from and we certainly never foresaw what might happen on the world stage. We did not foresee what could happen if we suddenly moved away from a cheap food policy and began to realise that that was not ordained from above; it was something that we had to make work and happen. Supply had to be put in place and we had to look at who was demanding it and why.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/12">We have seen prices going up. Bread and cereals are up 8.5 per cent. and milk and cheese are up 15.7 per cent. Those are dramatic increases. I have never been one who takes a cheap food policy for granted, because it has been my belief that suppliers in this country have had something of a raw deal. I could argue as to why they have had a raw deal, but at least now some of those suppliers may begin to get appropriate rewards, which could change our food provision for the better. However, there are other aspects to the issue that are increasingly worrying.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/13">We have seen self-sufficiency decline. It has not declined dramatically, but it has declined, and I think that we need to consider whether there should be a requirement for a minimum proportion of our food to be supplied from within this country, because of the dangers of relying on imports. Also, I feel strongly that this is not just about a national policy but about local food chains, which I very much support.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/14">The other aspect is rising fuel prices. That issue takes two forms. People are paying more to move food around. I am referring to food miles&mdash;the Tim Lang phrase that is now in common parlance. More particularly, one of the reasons why food prices are rising is that we have chosen to turn land over to biofuel. I personally think that that is completely explicable and I strongly support it. I know that there is a debate on the issue later in the week&mdash;the Minister may respond to it, too&mdash;but I am worried by the exaggeration that takes place. Everyone said, &quot;This is a jolly good thing because we are moving away from our dependency on petrol and diesel,&quot; so we move to another product and then there is a huge row. People say, &quot;This is terrible. We should stop it immediately. It is a completely inappropriate use of our land space.&quot; I do not go along with that. I think that there is a role for biofuels. We need to find other ways in which we can move vehicles about but, again, anyone who thinks that that is the answer per se will be sadly disillusioned.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/15">The other aspect of food coming from abroad that worries me, as the Minister will know because I have asked him about it and there have been various DEFRA investigations, is the threat of animal disease. I have felt for a long time that we underestimate that. We could be seen to be obsessed with terrorism. One aspect of that could always be the threat of animal disease being deliberately put into our food supply, but more particularly, we are talking about accidents of fate. This country has had foot and mouth and we are threatened currently by avian influenza and bluetongue. It costs huge amounts of money to deal with such matters. I am proud that the Department has strategies in place and we are working incredibly hard but, again, we ignore those threats at our peril. That issue must be part of how we deal with security and evolve a proper food policy.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/16">One of the criteria must be food safety. Of course, that is linked to animal disease. It involves what we eat and who supplies it. However, there is a more general issue to do with safety. If we take the widest definition of that, we are talking not just about what is safe to eat, but how much people eat. The obesity debate&mdash;the obesity epidemic, some people would say&mdash;is part and parcel of the debate about where we supply, what we supply and how much we supply.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/17">This issue is topical. The Chancellor wrote to Dr. Andrej Bajuk, the Minister of Finance in the Slovenian Government. He did that because Slovenia will shortly take on the EU presidency; indeed, it has already taken it on because it is <phrase class="date" code="2008-06-01">1 June</phrase>&mdash;<i>[</i><i>Interruption.</i><i>]</i> It is finishing off its presidency&mdash;I thank the Minister for reminding me of that. I have not yet had the opportunity to visit Slovenia, so it is a bit distant to me. However, I congratulate the Chancellor on sending that letter, which at least raised the question of how the common agricultural policy relates to the issues before us.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/18">As a died-in-the-wool sceptic, I feel strongly that we are, yet again, not asking the pertinent questions about the common agricultural policy. I know that these recent developments have upset the National Farmers Union because they look as though they will lead to more instability. We must, however, ask whether we have the appropriate policy in place at this time of rising fuel and food prices to provide most of Europe's food, and I would say that we have not. The Chancellor is therefore to be congratulated on at least opening up a debate on the issue. We have, of course, chosen to subsidise food, and I have no problem with that, but I do have a problem with the way in which we subsidise it in the EU. We need to look carefully at whether there are better policies and mechanisms and at whether those that we do have are appropriate as we go forward in this century. At the very least, the jury is out on that.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/19">Let me put food security in the context of wider food policy. As I said, we do not have a lead Department on the issue in this country, although food is one of the three points of delivery for Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs. As I said, however, the responsibilities of other Departments abut food policy, and we need some clarity about where food security fits in our wider food policy. I hope that the Minister can at least begin to provide that.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/20">I want to move on to a couple of final points about where we are going in terms of food. We have more choice than we have ever had, although that choice will perhaps become a bit more limited as food prices rise and people eat out less often. However, there are also issues such as obesity and the changing nature of food. Clearly, there is the debate on genetically modified food, and the Government are right to have been incredibly hesitant in their approach to GM, although I would like them to be even more hesitant because I do not agree with GM, which is the wrong way to go. However, GM does not represent the totality of the way in which food is provided. We now live in the era of functional foods, some of which can be incredibly important to people with health-related problems, who can, in effect, eat to overcome those problems. However, I am somewhat worried about other aspects of functional foods and about what is being supplied to whom. Such issues matter in terms of security, because there is only so much food that we can produce.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/21">On the world context, I am not going to second-guess what comes out of the Rome conference. It is important that the conference is seen as a significant staging post in terms of how we look at what food is available. It is extremely good that food supplies have risen more quickly than population. However, there is the problem of climate change, and there have been conflicts in places in Sudan that I know very well, as well as in Bangladesh. Is that a sign of things to come? Much though I am talking about the national need to highlight food security within a wider food policy, the international context must be writ large. If there is a lack of food and an ongoing population increase, the relationship between food supply and demand will increasingly become one of disequilibrium, and that will have a huge impact on us. We have been rather complacent in believing that food will be available to us and that it will be cheap and plentiful, because what happens elsewhere in the world&mdash;either in the developed or developing world&mdash;has huge ramifications for us.</p>
	<p pid="a.235.1/22">Will the Minister examine the issues that I have raised? This is part of an ongoing debate and the matter is worthy of further examination in an international context when Ministers and others return from Rome. It is about time that we in this country spelled out what our worries are and the need to highlight food security. As I said throughout the debate, we should say where that fits into the wider food policy debate, which is as close to our basic integrity as human beings as we can get.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.238.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.238.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.242.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.242.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.242.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.242.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.242.1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1538" speakername="Hugo Swire" colnum="242"  time="013:29:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080603/halltext/80603h0010.htm#08060369000589">
	<p pid="a.242.1/1">I am glad to have secured this debate on threatened post office closures in my constituency of East Devon. Time is fast running out and many important factors have still not been taken into account.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/2">The local post office is a key service in an area such as east Devon, which is a rural district with a higher than average proportion of older people and pockets of deprivation. The countryside, whose essential services have gradually been systematically and unfairly decimated by the Labour Government, has suffered cuts that are often felt far more keenly than in urban areas and it is now about to see the post office network pared down once again.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/3">Post offices provide important social and economic benefits to isolated communities across the country; they support vulnerable residents and serve as a focal point for numerous communities in urban and rural areas alike. In many sparsely populated parts of my constituency there is a greater need for local post office services. However, despite that, under the Government 4,000 post offices have already been closed and another 2,500 are to shut, with the East Devon constituency alone being threatened with the loss of another four. In fact, despite assurances both now and in 2007 on maintaining the network size, there is neither a policy in place to prevent the further shrinkage of the network, nor is the Government's commitment shared by Post Office Ltd, which does not believe that</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/4" class="indent">&quot;it is possible or desirable to set a minimum number of fixed outlets&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/5">Why is that? I invite the Minister to restate the Government's policy.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/6">It seems to many of us that the countryside is under sustained attack. Our rural communities, which should be supported, are declining rapidly, neighbourhoods have already lost vital amenities such as general practitioners' surgeries, jobcentres, magistrates courts, shops and schools, and now post offices are being added to that ever-expanding list. Rural services provide the glue that holds local rural communities together. In that respect, they play a far more significant social role than in towns and cities.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/7">The decline of rural services has been exacerbated by continuing inequalities of funding. Statistics reveal that, since 1997, councils in London receive twice as much per head as their rural counterparts, with a country dweller receiving 57 per cent. of the money spent on the average Londoner. Why? Rural post offices give valuable human contact and informal support for those who are socially isolated or vulnerable. Two thirds of postmasters in rural areas each keep an eye on between one and 30 people by helping them with forms and official papers, as well as inquiring about their health if they do not make their normal visit to the post office. Does the Minister concede that this is an important but immeasurable benefit?</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/8">In 2000, the Government made a clear and continuing commitment to rural-proof their policies and programmes, yet the Commission for Rural Communities has repeatedly reported that it is disappointed in the overall performance of Departments in meeting that commitment. Stuart Burgess, the Prime Minister's own so-called rural advocate, has warned that poorer people in the countryside</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/9" class="indent">&quot;form a forgotten city of disadvantage&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/10">If the Prime Minister is genuinely listening to what the people want rather than indulging in a cynical public relations stunt, will the Minister raise with him that particular point?</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/11">Although the Government pay lip service to green credentials, the post office closure programme does not consider the wider environmental impacts on rural areas resulting from increased car use and car dependency. Much of the increased travel that will result from closures can be expected to require use of a private car, given the infrequency or lack of rural bus services in some areas. That will increase carbon dioxide emissions and further reduce rural tranquillity.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/12">Rural needs are not being consistently addressed through policy making. The countryside is facing many challenges that are not being taken into account. According to research carried out for the Commission for Rural Communities, the loss of 2,500 post office branches could entail the loss of between 560 and 900 village shops. However, since the access criteria reflect only post office provision and not the presence or otherwise of other local services in rural communities, the proposals are having the perverse effect of forcing the closure of the only local service centre or hub of the community in a locality, to enable a post office in another &quot;nearby&quot; location to be more viable.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/13">The loss of the last remaining service hub in a village would be a critical threat to social interaction and the informal social support it can generate. That argues for more sensible and more sensitive criteria so that other services in the area&mdash;a village store, a petrol station with retail, a pub and so forth&mdash;are taken into consideration in any closure decision, alongside the proposed stricter distance criteria. The Government criteria have given specific protection to post offices in urban deprived areas, but they neglected to introduce a similar provision for rural deprived areas. Why? The Government must recognise that in some rural areas deprivation is just as acute and they should, therefore, reassess the need for rural deprivation criteria.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/14">It is imperative to stress how important it is for local consultation to take full account of the needs of rural communities, if any restructuring process is to have legitimacy or prove successful. Rural areas receive a significantly lower level of per capita public investment than urban areas, even before the additional disadvantage of rural population scarcity is factored in. The way in which the closure programme is being implemented is unfortunate, because communities are being pitted against each other in a dog-eat-dog style as they are forced to work to save only their own post office. It is also wrong that the consultation period is six weeks rather than three months, as recommended by the Cabinet Office guidelines. The time allowed for local consultation is insufficient, and does not permit due consideration of those who rely on post offices. The proposed closures will serve only further to fracture community structures and make life increasingly difficult for older people and the most vulnerable.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/15">It is hard to disagree that post offices often provide the focal point for a local community, particularly in rural villages, and perhaps that is no more the case than with a post office in my constituency threatened with closure. The post office in Offwell, which I had the pleasure of opening four years ago, is a perfect example of community cohesion. In December 2002, it was discovered that the local post office was to close and it was recognised that there was a community need for a post office. This prompted the formation of a local rural services association which, with the aid of local fundraising and grants of &pound;28,000 secured, set up a combined post office and shop in a temporary building on the village recreation ground.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/16">Four years ago, Post Office Ltd helped the village with guidance and grants to open its post office. Presumably, it was thought a viable business venture at the time, yet after four years of successful trading the company now considers it suitable for closure. Why? From the outset, the need for good free parking and disabled access to the shop was recognised, which has proved very popular, and the large farming community that uses the service can actually park tractors on the doorstep. A community-led and sustained effort is now being threatened by the closure proposal, and it is not certain that the shop itself can survive without the added attraction of the post office. That could have an adverse effect on the local ageing population and on local suppliers, which would spell a tragic end for a venture that was supported by the Post Office authorities from the outset and one which surely should be encouraged given the visible and sustained community involvement.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/17">That post office is an example of rural community life at its best and has been maintained through volunteers and fundraising. With the full backing of Post Office Ltd, in the four years since the post office opened, it has become a pivotal part of the village. The village put its heart and soul&mdash;not to mention a great amount of money&mdash;into the project and it has had the wholehearted support of not only Offwell, but many surrounding villages. The variety of products on offer in the shop has increased and it has been so successful that those involved want to move to a permanent building. The post office is a much needed lifeline for elderly local people, and is a proud achievement for the entire village. That achievement is now apparently in danger of being taken away from them.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/18">The vast majority of residents who rely on the service are over 50. Many do not drive and are therefore reliant on the post office and village shop. Post Office Ltd has quoted the fact that, as the crow flies, Offwell post office is 2.9 miles from Honiton post office and states that its criteria are that anything under 3 miles can be closed. However, it has neglected to note that the post office serves not only Offwell but the surrounding villages of Northleigh, Southleigh, Farway, Wilmington and Cotleigh, which do not have retail facilities and are more than 3 miles away from the Honiton branch. Post Office Ltd is also arguing that Offwell receives fewer customers than Honiton. However, the Business, Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Committee stated in its recent report that</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/19" class="indent">&quot;pure commercial logic cannot be the overriding factor here; the Post Office performs a social function&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/20">It went on to conclude that</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/21" class="indent">&quot;we believe that there should be a presumption against closing a Post Office where this is the last shop in the village or in a deprived urban area&quot;.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/22">The post office is an important part of the local community and has been maintained through the hard work and co-operation of individuals for the sake of everyone in the area. The Government are letting those people down and are undermining a well co-ordinated and important service. A clear erosion of village life is taking place. There is no disabled parking outside Honiton post office, so the nearest parking is 275 yards away and slightly uphill. A taxi fare to Honiton is &pound;15.60 return. Therefore, the change will make life difficult for elderly and disabled residents. The route is a busy main road, which is certainly unsuitable for walking and dangerous to cross, and for many elderly people, walking 3 miles alone is simply not a viable option. Buses run through the village only four times a day and there is no direct bus service to Honiton post office. Paradoxically, if Offwell rural services association had bought or rented a plot on East Devon business park five years ago instead of having the post office beside the village hall, although it would have been much less convenient for the villagers, as it would have been more than 3 miles from Honiton post office, the Offwell post office would probably not be threatened with closure now.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/23">The second post office in east Devon currently threatened with closure is Millwey Rise in Axminster. The post office serves the largest single housing estate in East Devon where there is a higher than average representation of those dependent on some kind of benefit&mdash;including those in receipt of state pensions. Millwey Rise also serves several local businesses at the nearby industrial park. In addition, there are plans for significant housing development in the area in the next 10 years. Axminster has been participating in the market and coastal towns initiative and a key issue is that it is one of the few towns in East Devon where expansion is possible and desired by the local community. It makes no logical sense to close down a post office in an area of proposed expansion.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/24">Millwey Rise is a vibrant and growing sub-post office with a sub-postmaster whose entrepreneurial spirit has been recognised by East Devon district council, which has invested approximately &pound;100,000 in the property. The council has also created a free car parking facility and full disabled access from all directions into the shop, which already meets requirements for the disabled.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/25">The post office and associated shop are the only retail outlets on the estate and the sub-postmaster has recently installed a free automated teller machine that has proved increasingly popular. All that has made an enormous difference for the elderly, disabled and vulnerable residents of the estate who would be unfairly disadvantaged by having to travel further. To reach the next available post office, pedestrians would have to negotiate a busy roundabout and, in places, steeply sloping ground. For those who are unable to use the bus service because of a disability, the cost of a taxi is currently &pound;3.80 in each direction, which is a substantial sum for someone on a low income, such as a single state pension.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/26">In Post Office Ltd's branch access report for the post office its opening times are incorrectly recorded. In reality, the main post office in Axminster closes earlier on Saturday and does not open as late during the week. If the Millwey Rise post office is lost there will be greater use of cars in the area and more congestion in the town, and businesses will have to transport mail to the sorting office, all at increased expense to them, in addition to the associated environmental costs.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/27">The third post office in my constituency that is threatened with closure is the Greenway Lane post office in Budleigh Salterton. Budleigh Salterton has a higher than average proportion of people who are of retirement age and 58 per cent. of households contain pensioners. That is significantly higher than the sub-regional average. In addition to its usefulness to the large number of elderly residents in the area the Greenway Lane post office is vital to disabled people. Many constituents say that parking in Budleigh Salterton High street near the post office is often impossible even with a blue badge.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/28">In a recent consultation by Help the Aged more than half of older people said that local post offices are essential to their way of life. Closure of post office branches has a big impact on the lives of the many older people who depend on the services they provide. Those on pensions and benefits are more likely to be financially excluded, and will tend to rely on post offices disproportionately, whether they live in an urban or rural area, yet they are the very people who will suffer most from the proposed closures.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/29">The needs of the elderly and disadvantaged are felt just as keenly in the area surrounding St. Andrew's road post office in Exmouth, the fourth post office threatened with closure. Exmouth, East Devon's largest town, has a higher proportion of people who are of retirement age and 38 per cent. of households are all-pensioner households. That is, again, above the sub-regional average. It is predicted that by 2021 the percentage of those aged 65 and over will increase by a further 20.9 per cent., and that the percentage of those aged between 70 and 74 will increase by 37.9 per cent. In addition, the town has two of the most deprived wards in Devon&mdash;Littleham and Town, where St. Andrew's road is located. They are in the upper quartile of social deprivation in the country, with 46.9 per cent. of households on an annual income of less than &pound;20,000.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/30">St. Andrew's road post office has a loyal customer base who do not want that essential service to be taken away from them. Sixty-one per cent. of customers in deprived urban areas say that they use their local post office for access to free community services, and 36 per cent. meet friends there. The post office has convenient roadside parking nearby while there is no direct bus route to the proposed alternative, which is the main, busy post office in Exmouth. At a time of rising fuel costs it simply defies logic to force people to make longer journeys.</p>
	<p pid="a.242.1/31">In Exmouth alone the Government have rationalised jobcentres, magistrates courts, police custody suites, sub-post offices and NHS dental services. Enough is enough. The Government claim to be aware of the rapidly ageing population; yet in an area such as East Devon where there is, as I have proved, a disproportionately large number of elderly people, it would appear that their interests and needs are being completely overlooked while their way of life is dismantled. We are told that the Government consider the environment. However, owing to the closure programme people in rural areas are being forced into their cars to travel further, because they cannot rely on often inadequate bus services to get to their closest post office. It is simply not enough to tell people where their alternative branch is. Real solutions need to be found to very real problems, and the Government need urgently to restate their commitment to the countryside.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.247.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.247.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.247.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.247.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.247.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.247.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.247.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1936" speakername="Patrick McFadden" colnum="247"  time="013:49:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080603/halltext/80603h0011.htm#08060369000592">
	<p pid="a.247.2/1">I do not accept for a moment the charge that the Government have somehow created an evil use of the internet or pioneered direct debit. Those things were wanted by our constituents. I am sure that even in East Devon, people use the internet to pay bills and carry out transactions. They are not being forced to do so by the Government.</p>
	<p pid="a.247.2/2">The hon. Gentleman mentioned pensioners. He is right that traditionally we have seen the post office as a venue for people to collect their pensions, but eight out of 10 pensioners no longer do so. Among new retirees, that figure is nine out of 10, and it is unlikely to reverse. I hope that he has a long and happy retirement, but I am not sure whether he will collect his pension every week at the local post offices.</p>
	<p pid="a.247.2/3">Other services, such as car tax online, did not even exist a few years ago. Car tax online is now used by 1 million people a month who previously would have gone to the post office to renew their car tax. It is a popular service. The question for Government is not whether to sit in the face of change and say, &quot;We don't want to put any of these services online&quot;; it is whether we are behind the curve of change, not ahead of it and driving it, as the hon. Gentleman implied in his intervention. In addition, the Post Office faces competition from new outlets. That is why it lost the contract for the BBC TV licence. The decision was taken not by Government but by the BBC.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.248.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.248.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.248.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.248.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.248.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.248.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.248.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1538" speakername="Hugo Swire" colnum="248"  time="013:49:00" url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200708/cmhansrd/cm080603/halltext/80603h0011.htm#08060369000595">
	<p pid="a.248.2/1">I fully agree with that statement. It is necessary to sustain and to encourage the viability of the remaining network. However, if the Minister was being more positive about the sub-post office network, he might allude to the new developments brought about by the technology to which he refers. They include the real growth in demand caused by internet shopping. The number of post offices providing front-line services for eBay&mdash;a place in which people can deposit their things&mdash;is growing. If the Minister would allow the Post Office to compete in such areas and to do what they want to do, he might find that, lo and behold, he has rather a vibrant service on his hands.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03a.248.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/westminhall/2008-06-03b.248.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

