<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE publicwhip [

<!ENTITY pound   "&#163;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">

<!ENTITY agrave  "&#224;">
<!ENTITY aacute  "&#225;">
<!ENTITY egrave  "&#232;">
<!ENTITY eacute  "&#233;">
<!ENTITY ecirc   "&#234;">
<!ENTITY iacute  "&#237;">
<!ENTITY ograve  "&#242;">
<!ENTITY oacute  "&#243;">
<!ENTITY uacute  "&#250;">
<!ENTITY Aacute  "&#193;">
<!ENTITY Eacute  "&#201;">
<!ENTITY Iacute  "&#205;">
<!ENTITY Oacute  "&#211;">
<!ENTITY Uacute  "&#218;">
<!ENTITY Uuml    "&#220;">
<!ENTITY auml    "&#228;">
<!ENTITY euml    "&#235;">
<!ENTITY iuml    "&#239;">
<!ENTITY ouml    "&#246;">
<!ENTITY uuml    "&#252;">
<!ENTITY fnof    "&#402;">
<!ENTITY aelig   "&#230;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">
<!ENTITY reg     "&#174;">
<!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
<!ENTITY shy     "&#173;">
<!ENTITY deg     "&#176;">
<!ENTITY middot  "&#183;">
<!ENTITY ordm    "&#186;">
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY hellip  "&#8230;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">

<!ENTITY acirc   "&#226;">
<!ENTITY Agrave  "&#192;">
<!ENTITY Aring   "&#197;">
<!ENTITY aring   "&#229;">
<!ENTITY atilde  "&#227;">
<!ENTITY Ccedil  "&#199;">
<!ENTITY ccedil  "&#231;">
<!ENTITY Egrave  "&#200;">
<!ENTITY Icirc   "&#206;">
<!ENTITY icirc   "&#238;">
<!ENTITY Igrave  "&#204;">
<!ENTITY igrave  "&#236;">
<!ENTITY ntilde  "&#241;">
<!ENTITY ocirc   "&#244;">
<!ENTITY oelig   "&#339;">
<!ENTITY Ograve  "&#210;">
<!ENTITY Oslash  "&#216;">
<!ENTITY oslash  "&#248;">
<!ENTITY Scaron  "&#352;">
<!ENTITY scaron  "&#353;">
<!ENTITY sup1    "&#185;">
<!ENTITY sup2    "&#178;">
<!ENTITY sup3    "&#179;">
<!ENTITY ugrave  "&#249;">
<!ENTITY Ugrave  "&#217;">
<!ENTITY yacute  "&#253;">
<!ENTITY frac12  "&#189;">
<!ENTITY micro   "&#181;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8225;">
]>

<publicwhip>

<source url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm"/>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.0.mh" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm">Written Answers Wednesday 3 December 2008</major-heading>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.1.mh" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm">Scottish Executive</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18092.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#1">Alcohol</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18092.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80383" speakername="Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-18092" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#1">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether proposals for the prevention of the display of promotional materials in licensed premises will include window displays by specialist whisky shops.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18092.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80341" speakername="Kenny MacAskill" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#1">

  <p>The Scottish Government has made clear that it is not anti-alcohol and we are proud of our distillers and the premium products they make. However, Scotland&rsquo;s relationship with alcohol is out of kilter and we need to rebalance it.</p>

  <p>Issues concerning the promotion of alcohol and potential measures under the Licensing (Scotland) Act 2005 are being considered in light of the responses to the Scottish Government&rsquo;s consultation <em>Changing Scotland&rsquo;s Relationship with Alcohol, </em>but we are clear that we do not intend to ban promotions that explain the method of production, history and heritage of Scotland&rsquo;s quality products. We have already given the Scotch Whisky Association an assurance that we will discuss these matters with them before proposing any regulatory action to end the irresponsible promotion of alcohol. We have also made clear that there is no question that distilleries will be prevented from offering drams as part of a distillery tour.</p>

  <p>The Scottish Government will announce it&rsquo;s response to the consultation early in 2009.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18104.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#2">Alcohol Misuse</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18104.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80290" speakername="Gavin Brown (Lothians) (Con)" spid="S3W-18104" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#2">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, further to the answer to question S3W-17512 by Kenny MacAskill on 12 November 2008, how many off-licences in the Lothians that were found to have sold alcohol to under-18s had further tests to determine whether they continued to do so, broken down by local authority.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18230.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80341" speakername="Kenny MacAskill" spid="S3W-18230" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#2">

  <p>The information requested is not held centrally. It is common practice for the police to retest any premises which fails a test purchase. However, this is an operational decision taken by the relevant police force.</p>

  <p>John Lamont (Roxburgh and Berwickshire) (Con): To ask the Scottish Executive which local authorities have imposed a ban on the consumption of alcohol in public places and in what year each ban took effect.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18230.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80341" speakername="Kenny MacAskill" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#2">

  <p>Following a successful pilot in the use of byelaws to prohibit drinking in designated parts of Galashiels, Motherwell and Dundee, local authorities were invited in 1993 to submit proposals for similar byelaws under powers contained in the Local Government (Scotland) Act 1973.</p>

  <p>There are currently 30 local authorities that have alcohol byelaws in operation. These byelaws cover over 480 settlements and local authorities amend the byelaws on a regular basis.</p>

  <p>Set out below are the local authorities which have alcohol byelaws currently in operation and the date their first byelaw came into operation:</p>

  <p><table width="50%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Local Authority</td>
<td width="43%" align="center" valign="top">Date</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Aberdeen City</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">30 September 2002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Aberdeenshire</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">13 July 2007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Angus</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">4 September 2002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Argyll and Bute</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">7 July 1997</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">City of Edinburgh</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">8 January 2007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Clackmannanshire</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">5 January 1998</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Comhairle nan Eilean Siar</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">23 March 1998</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Dumfries and Galloway</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">16 October 2000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Dundee City</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">1 August 1993</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">East Ayrshire</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">26 May 1997</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">East Dunbartonshire</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">20 December 1996</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">East Lothian</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">11 December 1995</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">East Renfrewshire</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">5 January 1998</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Falkirk</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">5 January 1998</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Fife</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">24 November 1997</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Glasgow City</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">19 August 1996</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Highland</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">1 August 1996</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Inverclyde</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">4 August 1997</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Midlothian</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">6 April 1998</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Moray</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">1 June 1998</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">North Ayrshire</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">1 June 1998</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">North Lanarkshire</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">5 January 1998</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Perth and Kinross</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">26 June 1998</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Renfrewshire</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">3 October 1997</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Shetland Islands</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">2 March 2007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">South Ayrshire</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">22 September 2002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">South Lanarkshire</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">7 April 1997</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">Stirling</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">10 August 1998</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">West Dunbartonshire</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">27 April 1998</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="57%" valign="top">West Lothian</td>
<td width="43%" valign="top">1 September 1997</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18150.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#3">Asbestos</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18150.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80344" speakername="Ken Macintosh (Eastwood) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18150" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#3">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what steps are being taken to protect staff and students at the University of Glasgow Dental School while asbestos is being removed from the building.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18151.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" spid="S3W-18151" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#3">

  <p>I have been assured that the removal of asbestos from the facility is being carried out in accordance with health and safety legislation in particular the Control of Asbestos Regulations 2006.</p>

  <p>If asbestos is present and to be removed the area is isolated and sealed off and the removal works carried out in accordance with the Control of Asbestos Regulations 2006 by a licensed, specialist contractor. In addition to these regulations, NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde carry out perimeter air monitoring to the surrounding areas adjacent to the scope works to ensure the integrity of the sealed area and providing advance warning of any breaches. The area remains isolated until an Air Clearance Certificate and a Certificate of Re-occupation are issued by an independent analyst confirming that the asbestos has been successfully removed and the area free from contamination. Only then can the area be put back into use.</p>

  <p>Ken Macintosh (Eastwood) (Lab): To ask the Scottish Executive whether ministers are confident that all necessary precautions are being taken at the University of Glasgow Dental School to protect those who continue to use the premises while asbestos is being removed from the building.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18152.q2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" spid="S3W-18152" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#3">

  <p>Scottish Government Health Directorates property management policy requires all NHSScotland bodies to comply with all requirements laid down by statutes bearing upon the health, safety and welfare of staff, patients and visitors in relation to and in respect of the management of the property which they own or occupy.</p>

  <p>The removal of asbestos from existing buildings is subject to health and safety regulations, in particular the Control of Asbestos Regulations 2006. NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde have confirmed that the removal of asbestos from the facility is being carried out in accordance with these regulations. I am therefore confident that all necessary precautions are being taken to protect staff, students, patients and all visitors to the facility whilst this work is carried out.</p>

  <p>Ken Macintosh (Eastwood) (Lab): To ask the Scottish Executive whether health and safety guidance on the dangers and management of asbestos in the workplace are being observed at the University of Glasgow Dental School while asbestos is being removed from the building.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18152.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#3">

  <p>The removal of asbestos is subject to the Control of Asbestos Regulations 2006 and I can confirm that in compliance with these regulations NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde has an asbestos register in place for the dental hospital and school that, based on surveys carried by specialist consultants, identifies the existence of asbestos within the building.</p>

  <p>If contract works are being carried out on the premises the register is consulted to determine whether asbestos is present in that area. If so present and the asbestos requires encapsulation or removal then the Health and Safety Executive is notified and the appropriate works carried out by a licensed, specialist contractor. The register is then updated to reflect the works carried out.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-17952.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#4">Bees</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-17952.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80384" speakername="John Scott (Ayr) (Con)" spid="S3W-17952" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#4">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what research it has conducted into the control of the varroa mite.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-17953.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80340" speakername="Richard Lochhead" spid="S3W-17953" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#4">

  <p>While the Scottish Government has not, as yet, funded any research into the control of the varroa mite, the UK Government&rsquo;s investment in research on varroa exceeds &pound;2.2 million over the past 12 years.</p>

  <p>There is also active research in many countries, information about which is shared internationally, an example of which can be accessed at:</p>

  <p><a href="http://www.Ento.Psu.Edu/Honeybeeresearch.Html" target="_blank">http://www.ento.psu.edu/honeybeeresearch.Html</a>.</p>

  <p>The UK Animal Health and Welfare funders forum, which includes government research councils and the Wellcome Trust, is aware of the effects of varroa infestation. The Scottish Government is engaging with this group.</p>

  <p>John Scott (Ayr) (Con): To ask the Scottish Executive whether the reduction in the honeybee population as a result of the spread of the varroa mite poses a threat to the pollination of agricultural crops.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-17954.q2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80340" speakername="Richard Lochhead" spid="S3W-17954" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#4">

  <p>The Scottish Government has received no reports or suggestions to date of any reduction in crop production due to any decline in the honeybee population in Scotland.</p>

  <p>John Scott (Ayr) (Con): To ask the Scottish Executive whether a risk assessment has been carried out on the implications of the spread of the varroa mite on pollination levels.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-17954.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80340" speakername="Richard Lochhead" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#4">

  <p>The Scottish Government has not received and is not aware of any reports or suggestions of any reduction in crop production due to declining honeybee populations as a result of varroa infestation. It has, therefore, not been considered necessary to carry out a risk assessment on the implications of the spread of varroa mite on pollination levels.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18155.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#5">Child Protection</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18155.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80403" speakername="Karen Whitefield (Airdrie and Shotts) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18155" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#5">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many services were evaluated as (a) satisfactory, (b) weak and (c) unsatisfactory in the HM Inspectorate of Education (HMIE) joint inspection of services to protect children and young people in the Aberdeen City Council area, and how this compares to the evaluation of Midlothian Council&rsquo;s child protection services.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18155.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80331" speakername="Adam Ingram" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#5">

  <p>HMIE joint inspection of services for children evaluates against 18 quality indicators (QIs), set out in the framework <em>How well are children and young people protected and their needs met? </em> In the case of Aberdeen City Council, four QIs were found to be &quot;satisfactory&quot;, 10 &quot;weak&quot; and four &quot;unsatisfactory&quot;.</p>

  <p>The report on Midlothian Council, published in February 2007, found three QIs to be &quot;adequate&quot;, 12 to be &quot;weak&quot; and three &quot;unsatisfactory&quot;. The interim follow-through report on Midlothian of March 2008 shows substantial improvement since the publication of its report in February 2007.</p>

  <p>HMIE changed the &quot;adequate&quot; evaluation title to &quot;satisfactory&quot; in June 2008, with no change in meaning.</p>

  <p>HMIE reports are published on their website: <a href="http://www.hmie.gov.uk" target="_blank">www.hmie.gov.uk</a>.</p>

  <p><table width="100%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="67%" align="center" valign="top">Quality Indicator</td>
<td width="17%" align="center" valign="top">Midlothian</td>
<td width="16%" align="center" valign="top">Aberdeen</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">1.1 Children are listened to, understood and respected</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Weak</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Satisfactory</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">1.2 Children benefit from strategies to minimise harm</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Weak</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Satisfactory</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">1.3 Children are helped by the actions taken in response to immediate concerns</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Weak</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Unsatisfactory</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">1.4 Children&rsquo;s needs are met</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Unsatisfactory</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Weak</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">2.1 Public awareness of the safety and protection of children</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Adequate</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Satisfactory</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">3.1 Involving children and their families in key processes</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Weak</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Satisfactory</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">3.2 Information-sharing and recording</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Weak</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Weak</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">3.3 Recognising and assessing risks and needs</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Weak</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Unsatisfactory</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">3.4 Effectiveness of planning to meet needs</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Unsatisfactory</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Unsatisfactory</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">4.1 Policies and procedures</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Adequate</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Weak</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">4.2 Operational planning</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Weak</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Weak</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">4.3 Participation of children families and other relevant people in policy development</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Weak</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Unsatisfactory</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">4.4 Recruitment and retention of staff</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Weak</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Weak</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">4.5 Development of staff</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Weak</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Weak</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">5.1 Vision values and aims</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Adequate</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Weak</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">5.2 Leadership and direction</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Unsatisfactory</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Weak</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">5.3 Leadership of people and partnerships</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Weak</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Weak</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="67%" valign="top">5.4 Leadership of change and improvement</td>
<td width="17%" valign="top">Weak</td>
<td width="16%" valign="top">Weak</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-17967.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#6">Communities</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-17967.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80312" speakername="George Foulkes (Lothians) (Lab)" spid="S3W-17967" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#6">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, further to the answer to question S3W-15009 by Fergus Ewing on Wednesday 3 September 2008, whether it will list the occasions on which each minister has met Mr Osama Saeed of the Scottish Islamic Foundation in that or any other capacity, also showing the location of the meeting and what topics were discussed.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18017.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80306" speakername="Fergus Ewing" spid="S3W-18017" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#6">

  <p>I refer the member to the answer to question S3W-15009 on 3 September 2008. All answers to written parliamentary questions are available on the Parliament&rsquo;s website, the search facility for which can be found at <a href="../../../Apps2/Business/PQA/Default.aspx">http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/Apps2/Business/PQA/Default.aspx</a> .</p>

  <p>Johann Lamont (Glasgow Pollok) (Lab): To ask the Scottish Executive, further to the answer to question S3W-16822 by Fergus Ewing on 30 October 2008, whether it can confirm that the application for funding to the Equality Unit referred to was the sole funding application to the unit approved in principle by the First Minister.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18017.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80306" speakername="Fergus Ewing" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#6">

  <p>I refer the member to the answer to question S3W-16822 on 30 October 2008. All answers to written parliamentary questions are available on the Parliament&rsquo;s website, the search facility for which can be found at <a href="../../../Apps2/Business/PQA/Default.aspx">http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/Apps2/Business/PQA/Default.aspx</a> .</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18216.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#7">Digital Technology</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18216.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80329" speakername="Jim Hume (South of Scotland) (LD)" spid="S3W-18216" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#7">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many rural or remote households in the Scottish Borders are unable to receive broadband.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18217.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" spid="S3W-18217" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#7">

  <p>This information is not held centrally.</p>

  <p>Jim Hume (South of Scotland) (LD): To ask the Scottish Executive what action it will take to ensure that residents in rural or remote communities in the Scottish Borders are able to receive broadband.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18217.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#7">

  <p>As a result of direct intervention by the Scottish Government, broadband availability in Scotland is already over 99%. Our current Broadband Reach Project, for which a contract worth &pound;3.3 million was awarded to Avanti Communications in June 2008, furthers our commitment and aims to address 100% of known demand.</p>

  <p>Avanti are using a mix of technologies, including satellite and wireless, to deliver an affordable, basic (512Kbps) broadband service, appropriate to the location and density of those eligible households and business that have made themselves known to the Scottish Government.</p>

  <p>Around 4,000 premises, including a number from the Scottish Borders, are included in this project. Rollout commenced in July 2008 and completion is expected by May 2009.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18179.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#8">Drug Misuse</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18179.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80334" speakername="James Kelly (Glasgow Rutherglen) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18179" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#8">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the average waiting time for drug rehabilitation services is in (a) NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde and (b) NHS Lanarkshire.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18179.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80396" speakername="Nicola Sturgeon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#8">

  <p>Information on the average waiting time of clients for drug treatment interventions is not held centrally.</p>

  <p>A national waiting times information framework was implemented in April 2004 to enable alcohol and drug action teams (ADATs) and local services to monitor waiting times for drug treatment and care in their local area. ADATs send aggregated data to Information Services (ISD) on a quarterly basis, and ISD submit reports to the Scottish Government each quarter these may be viewed on:</p>

  <p><a href="http://www.drugmisuse.isdscotland.org/wtpilot/reports.htm" target="_blank">http://www.drugmisuse.isdscotland.org/wtpilot/reports.htm</a>.</p>

  <p>Lanarkshire ADAT covers the same geographical area as NHS Lanarkshire. Due to the reorganisation of Argyll and Clyde ADAT, ISD now receives drug treatment waiting times data for (1) Argyll and Bute (2) Greater Glasgow and Clyde (excluding Glasgow City) and (3) Glasgow City. Separate data is presented below for Greater Glasgow and Clyde and Glasgow City which taken together covers the NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde area.</p>

  <p>Table 1 presents information, by ADAT, on clients who have been offered an appointment date for any intervention during the period April to June 2008.</p>

  <p>Table 2 presents information, by ADAT, on clients who were still waiting for an appointment date for any intervention by the end of June 2008.</p>

  <p>Table 1: Drug Treatment Waiting Times - Clients Offered an Appointment Date for Any Intervention<sup>1,3 </sup>by ADAT<sup> </sup>: April to June 2008</p>

  <p><table width="100%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="19%" valign="top"> </td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="top">&lt;7 Days</td>
<td width="8%" align="center" valign="top">8 to 14Days</td>
<td width="8%" align="center" valign="top">15 to 21Days</td>
<td width="8%" align="center" valign="top">22 to 28 Days</td>
<td width="8%" align="center" valign="top">5 to 8 Weeks</td>
<td width="8%" align="center" valign="top">9 to 12 Weeks</td>
<td width="9%" align="center" valign="top">13 to 26 Weeks</td>
<td width="8%" align="center" valign="top">27 to 52 Weeks</td>
<td width="9%" align="center" valign="top">52+ Weeks</td>
<td width="8%" align="center" valign="top">Total</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="19%" valign="top">Glasgow City<sup>4</sup></td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="top">568</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">63</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">24</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">11</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">9</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">8</td>
<td width="9%" align="right" valign="top">37</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">41</td>
<td width="9%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">761</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="19%" valign="top">Greater Glasgow <br />
                and Clyde<sup>4</sup></td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="top">327</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">61</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">25</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">19</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">17</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">6</td>
<td width="9%" align="right" valign="top">3</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top"> 0</td>
<td width="9%" align="right" valign="top">1</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">459</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="19%" valign="top">Lanarkshire</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="top">284</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">19</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">12</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">6</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">5</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top"> 0</td>
<td width="9%" align="right" valign="top"> 0</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top"> 0</td>
<td width="9%" align="right" valign="top"> 0</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">326</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Table 2: Drug Treatment Waiting Times - Clients Still Waiting for an Appointment Date for Any Intervention<sup>2,3 </sup>by ADAT<sup> </sup>as at 30 June 2008</p>

  <p><table width="100%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="19%" valign="top"> </td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="top">&lt;7 Days</td>
<td width="8%" align="center" valign="top">8 to 14 Days</td>
<td width="8%" align="center" valign="top">15 to 21 Days</td>
<td width="8%" align="center" valign="top">22 to 28 Days</td>
<td width="8%" align="center" valign="top">5 to 8 Weeks</td>
<td width="8%" align="center" valign="top">9 to 12 Weeks</td>
<td width="9%" align="center" valign="top">13 to 26 Weeks</td>
<td width="8%" align="center" valign="top">27 to 52 Weeks</td>
<td width="9%" align="center" valign="top">52+ Weeks</td>
<td width="8%" align="center" valign="top">Total</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="19%" valign="top">Glasgow City<sup>4</sup></td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="top">21</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">7</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">2</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">11</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">10</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">8</td>
<td width="9%" align="right" valign="top">7</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">4</td>
<td width="9%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="19%" valign="top">Greater Glasgow and Clyde<sup>4</sup></td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="top">11</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">7</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">12</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">5</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">7</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">8</td>
<td width="9%" align="right" valign="top">6</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">4</td>
<td width="9%" align="right" valign="top">2</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">62</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="19%" valign="top">Lanarkshire</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="top">9</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top"> 0</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top"> 0</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">1</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">4</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">3</td>
<td width="9%" align="right" valign="top">7</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">72</td>
<td width="9%" align="right" valign="top">18</td>
<td width="8%" align="right" valign="top">114</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Notes:</p>

  <p>1. Time between date care plan is agreed/decision on treatment is made/date client ready for treatment and the first appointment date offered for any intervention (for those offered an intervention date during the reporting period).</p>

  <p>2. Time between date care plan is agreed/decision on treatment is made/date client ready for treatment and the end of the reporting period (for those still waiting to be offered an intervention date).</p>

  <p>3. The interventions include: structured preparatory and motivational intervention, prescribed drug treatment, community support/rehabilitation and residential detoxification/ rehabilitation.</p>

  <p>4. Due to the reorganisation of Argyll and Clyde ADAT, ISD now receives data for (1) Argyll and Bute (2) Greater Glasgow and Clyde (excluding Glasgow City) and (3) Glasgow City. Data is therefore presented separately for Greater Glasgow and Clyde and Glasgow City.</p>

  <p>The member may also wish to note that the Scottish Government recently announced that there would be a measure in the NHS HEAT system for 2009-10 to offer drug misusers faster access to appropriate treatment to support their recovery.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18108.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#9">Electricity</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18108.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80370" speakername="Alex Neil (Central Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S3W-18108" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#9">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the peak demand for electricity was in each of the last 10 years and on what dates it occurred.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18108.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#9">

  <p>From 2005, following the introduction of the British Electricity Trading and Transmission Arrangements, official figures for Scotland are not available separately. However, available information is listed in the following table:</p>

  <p><table width="75%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="12%" valign="top" rowspan="2">Year</td>
<td colspan="2" align="center" valign="top">Simultaneous Maximum Load Met (MW)</td>
<td width="41%" rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">Date</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="22%" align="center" valign="top">UK</td>
<td width="25%" align="center" valign="top">Scotland</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="12%" valign="top">2007</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">61,527</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">-</td>
<td width="41%" align="right" valign="top">17.12.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="12%" valign="top">2006</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">59,071</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">-</td>
<td width="41%" align="right" valign="top">23.01.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="12%" valign="top">2005</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">61,697</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">-</td>
<td width="41%" align="right" valign="top">29.11.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="12%" valign="top">2004</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">61,013</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">5,579</td>
<td width="41%" align="right" valign="top">13.12.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="12%" valign="top">2003</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">60,501</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">5,909</td>
<td width="41%" align="right" valign="top">08.12.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="12%" valign="top">2002</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">61,717</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">5,688</td>
<td width="41%" align="right" valign="top">10.12.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="12%" valign="top">2001</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">58,589</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">5,504</td>
<td width="41%" align="right" valign="top">January 2001 (no specific date|)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="12%" valign="top">2000</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">58,452</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">5,861</td>
<td width="41%" align="right" valign="top">December 1999(no specific date|)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="12%" valign="top">1999</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">57,849</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">5,847</td>
<td width="41%" align="right" valign="top">-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="12%" valign="top">1998</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">56,312</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">-</td>
<td width="41%" align="right" valign="top">-</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Source: Digest of United Kingdom Energy Statistics (Department for Business Enterprise &amp; Regulatory Reform).</p>

  <p>Data covers the period ending March of the following year. For example, data for 2007 are for the year ending March 2008.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18198.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#10">Energy Efficiency</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18198.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80308" speakername="Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18198" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#10">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how much of the &pound;55.8 million Energy Assistance Package funding will be provided to the Energy Saving Scotland Advice Centre network to ensure that it can manage the expected increase in contacts following the introduction of the package.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18200.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" spid="S3W-18200" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#10">

  <p>This is in the process of being finalised. We are currently discussing with the various partners who will help us deliver the Energy Assistance Package the details of implementation and the most appropriate allocation of resources to achieve this.</p>

  <p>Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab): To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will provide information on the subsidy that will be provided to those who do not qualify for free standard insulation measures under stage 3 of the Energy Assistance Package.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18201.q2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80308" speakername="Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18201" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#10">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether there are specific criteria for the provision of a subsidy to those who do not qualify for free standard insulation measures under stage 3 of the Energy Assistance Package.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18203.q3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" spid="S3W-18203" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#10">

  <p>The level of subsidy for those who do not qualify for the free measures under the Energy Assistance Package will be a matter for the individual energy companies as part of their programmes to meet the carbon emissions reduction target. As now, the Energy Savings Scotland Advice Centre network will be able to provide advice on the offers available.</p>

  <p>Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab): To ask the Scottish Executive whether it is exploring equity release schemes or development of the Scheme of Assistance process for those who are not entitled to assistance under stage 4 of the Energy Assistance Package.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18204.q4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" spid="S3W-18204" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#10">

  <p>The Fuel Poverty Forum recommended that funding for the Energy Assistance Package could be further augmented through top-up funding or low-interest loans, or equity release. The Scottish Government is intending to consult on a number of issues related to the energy efficiency of housing in the next few months, and we are considering whether this issue should be included as part of that consultation.</p>

  <p>Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab): To ask the Scottish Executive in relation to the Energy Assistance Package, whether it intends to set regional budgets or a target for the number of houses in each region assisted under the package.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18221.q5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" spid="S3W-18221" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#10">

  <p>In its report, the Fuel Poverty Forum proposed that regional budgets or regional targets should be set for Stage 4 of the Energy Assistance Package based on the proportion of Scotland&rsquo;s fuel poor in each region according to the latest Scottish House Condition Survey. We are currently discussing with the various partners who will help us deliver the Energy Assistance Package the details of implementation and the most appropriate allocation of resources to achieve this, including this issue.</p>

  <p>Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab): To ask the Scottish Executive whether, as a result of the transition to the new Energy Assistance Package, there will be an impact on people who have registered for the existing central heating and warm deal programmes.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18221.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#10">

  <p>No. Those who apply under the existing programmes up to 31 March 2009 will continue to have their applications progressed as now.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18136.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#11">Enterprise</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18136.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80404" speakername="David Whitton (Strathkelvin and Bearsden) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18136" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#11">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many (a) grocery, (b) butcher, (c) baker, (d) fishmonger, (e) newsagent, (f) confectionery and (g) tobacco retail outlets there were in the most recent period for which information is available and how many such wholesalers there were.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18136.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#11">

  <p>The number of retail outlets in Scotland as at March 2008 was as follows (separate figures are not available for newsagents and confectionery):</p>

  <p><table width="100%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="8%" valign="top"> </td>
<td width="65%" align="center" valign="top">Business Activity</td>
<td width="27%" align="center" valign="top">Number of Business Sites</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="8%" valign="top">(a)</td>
<td width="65%" valign="top">Retail Sale of Fruit and Vegetables</td>
<td width="27%" align="right" valign="top">400</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="8%" valign="top">(b)</td>
<td width="65%" valign="top">Retail Sale of Meat and Meat Products</td>
<td width="27%" align="right" valign="top">755</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="8%" valign="top">(c) </td>
<td width="65%" valign="top">Retail Sale of Bread, Cakes, Flour Confectionery and Sugar Confectionery</td>
<td width="27%" align="right" valign="top">815</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="8%" valign="top">(d)</td>
<td width="65%" valign="top">Retail Sale of Fish, Crustaceans and Molluscs</td>
<td width="27%" align="right" valign="top">275</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="8%" valign="top">(g)</td>
<td width="65%" valign="top">Retail Sale of Tobacco Products</td>
<td width="27%" align="right" valign="top">280</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="8%" valign="top">(e,f,g)</td>
<td width="65%" valign="top">Retail Sale by Confectioners, Tobacconists and Newsagents (CTNs)</td>
<td width="27%" align="right" valign="top">1,295</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>The total number of wholesalers in Scotland as at March 2008 was as follows:</p>

  <p><table width="100%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="72%" valign="top">Business Activity</td>
<td width="28%" align="center" valign="top">Number of Enterprises</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="72%" valign="top">Wholesale Trade and Commission Trade,Except of Motor Vehicles and Motorcycles</td>
<td width="28%" align="right" valign="top">6,180</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Of this, the number active in the wholesale of food, beverages and tobacco was:</p>

  <p><table width="100%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="72%" valign="top">Business Activity</td>
<td width="28%" align="center" valign="top">Number of Enterprises</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="72%" valign="top">Wholesale of Food, Beverages and Tobacco</td>
<td width="28%" align="right" valign="top">1,150</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Source: Inter-Departmental Business Register (IDBR) which is maintained by the Office for National Statistics.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18182.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#12">General Practitioners</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18182.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80334" speakername="James Kelly (Glasgow Rutherglen) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18182" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#12">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many GPs currently practise, also broken down by (a) NHS board and (b) parliamentary constituency.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18183.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80396" speakername="Nicola Sturgeon" spid="S3W-18183" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#12">

  <p>(a) The number of GPs currently practising broken down by NHS board is provided in the following table. (b) The breakdown by Scottish parliamentary constituency has been placed in the Scottish Parliament Information Centre (Bib. number 47014).</p>

  <p><table width="50%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="49%" align="center" valign="top">NHS Board</td>
<td width="51%" align="center" valign="top">Number of Contracted GPs<sup>1</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Ayrshire and Arran</td>
<td width="51%" align="right" valign="top">318</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Borders</td>
<td width="51%" align="right" valign="top">114</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Dumfries and Galloway</td>
<td width="51%" align="right" valign="top">153</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Fife</td>
<td width="51%" align="right" valign="top">277</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Forth Valley</td>
<td width="51%" align="right" valign="top">253</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Grampian</td>
<td width="51%" align="right" valign="top">541</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Greater Glasgow and Clyde</td>
<td width="51%" align="right" valign="top">1,022</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Highland</td>
<td width="51%" align="right" valign="top">399</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Lanarkshire</td>
<td width="51%" align="right" valign="top">387</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Lothian</td>
<td width="51%" align="right" valign="top">784</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Orkney</td>
<td width="51%" align="right" valign="top">44</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Shetland</td>
<td width="51%" align="right" valign="top">32</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Tayside</td>
<td width="51%" align="right" valign="top">351</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Western Isles</td>
<td width="51%" align="right" valign="top">42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Scotland Total <sup>2</sup></td>
<td width="51%" align="right" valign="top">4,714</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Data source: GP Contractor Database, ISD Scotland, as at 26 November 2008</p>

  <p>Notes:</p>

  <p>1. The table shows the number of GPs working in Scottish practices, by NHS board, as at 30 September 2007. The table does not provide information on the whole-time equivalent (WTE) commitment in each board area and the figures do not include out-of-hours services and GPs doing only locum work.</p>

  <p>2. It is possible for a GP to hold a contract in more than one NHS board, therefore the Scotland total does not equal the sum of the NHS board counts.</p>

  <p>3. GP numbers for 2008 will be published at NHS board level on 27 January 2009 at <a href="http://www.isdscotland.org/GPpracs&amp;pops" target="_blank">www.isdscotland.org/GPpracs&amp;pops</a>.</p>

  <p>James Kelly (Glasgow Rutherglen) (Lab): To ask the Scottish Executive how many GP practices there are with two or more GPs, broken down by (a) NHS board and (b) parliamentary constituency.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18183.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80396" speakername="Nicola Sturgeon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#12">

  <p>(a) The number of GP practices with two or more GPs broken down by NHS board is illustrated in the following table. (b) The information broken down by parliamentary constituency has been placed in the Scottish Parliament Information Centre (Bib. number 47015)</p>

  <p><table width="50%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="53%" align="center" valign="top">NHS Board</td>
<td width="47%" align="center" valign="top">Number of GP Practices<sup>1</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="53%" valign="top">Ayrshire and Arran</td>
<td width="47%" align="right" valign="top">59</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="53%" valign="top">Borders</td>
<td width="47%" align="right" valign="top">23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="53%" valign="top">Dumfries and Galloway</td>
<td width="47%" align="right" valign="top">34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="53%" valign="top">Fife</td>
<td width="47%" align="right" valign="top">54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="53%" valign="top">Forth Valley</td>
<td width="47%" align="right" valign="top">56</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="53%" valign="top">Grampian</td>
<td width="47%" align="right" valign="top">82</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="53%" valign="top">Greater Glasgow and Clyde</td>
<td width="47%" align="right" valign="top">228</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="53%" valign="top">Highland</td>
<td width="47%" align="right" valign="top">91</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="53%" valign="top">Lanarkshire</td>
<td width="47%" align="right" valign="top">82</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="53%" valign="top">Lothian</td>
<td width="47%" align="right" valign="top">117</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="53%" valign="top">Orkney</td>
<td width="47%" align="right" valign="top">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="53%" valign="top">Shetland</td>
<td width="47%" align="right" valign="top">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="53%" valign="top">Tayside</td>
<td width="47%" align="right" valign="top">68</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="53%" valign="top">Western Isles</td>
<td width="47%" align="right" valign="top">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="53%" valign="top">Scotland Total</td>
<td width="47%" align="right" valign="top">921</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Data source: GP Contractor Database, ISD Scotland, as at 26 November 2008.</p>

  <p>Note: 1. Number of practices having two or more contracted GPs as at 30 September 2007.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-17951.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#13">Health</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-17951.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80386" speakername="Dr Richard Simpson (Mid Scotland and Fife) (Lab)" spid="S3W-17951" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#13">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether the procedures for child screening will (a) remain universal and (b) be undertaken by or under the supervision of a fully trained health visitor for neonates or for infants in the first (i) 10 days, (ii) eight weeks, (iii) three months, (iv) four months, (v) 13 months and (vi) three to five years of life.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18134.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" spid="S3W-18134" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#13">

  <p>Child health screening, surveillance and health promotion will remain a universal service as described in Health for all Children guidance issued by the Scottish Executive in 2005. Contacts outlined in the core programme include neonate, first 10 days of life, six to eight weeks, three months, four months, 13 months and three to five years as well as entry to primary school, primary 7 and at stages within Secondary School. Currently Health Visitors do not supervise or provide the child health screening, surveillance and health promotion programme in its entirety. The programme is provided by a team of appropriately trained practitioners which includes paediatricians, midwives, GPs, health visitors, staff nurses and others with the necessary skills required for each contact. The programme will continue to be provided by an appropriately trained team. A link to the guidance which contains details of the core programme can be found at:</p>

  <p><a href="http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Publications/2005/04/15161325/13269" target="_blank">www.scotland.gov.uk/Publications/2005/04/15161325/13269</a>.</p>

  <p>Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con): To ask the Scottish Executive what has been done to improve services to people with aphasia, following publication of the report referred to on page 21 of NHS QIS&rsquo;s <em>Annual Report 2007-2008</em>.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18135.q2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" spid="S3W-18135" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#13">

  <p>The NHS Quality Improvement Scotland (NHS QIS) annual report refers on page 21 to the report it published in November 2007 on the incidence of aphasia following a stroke, the services currently available, its current management and its impact on individuals and their families. Since then, NHS QIS has published, in June 2008, a response entitled <em>The Road to Recovery</em> , setting out recommendations on raising awareness of the condition and the future development of services for people with aphasia in Scotland.</p>

  <p>NHS QIS is currently considering with key stakeholders the holding of collaborative events in Spring 2009. These will enable practitioners and key organisations to come together to review their current practice and identify opportunities for improvements based on the findings from the aphasia in Scotland report and other policy drivers.</p>

  <p>We are also considering the actions to improve services for those with aphasia following a stroke which might be included in our revised coronary heart disease and stroke strategy.</p>

  <p>Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con): To ask the Scottish Executive what action has been taken by it and each NHS board in response to the NHS QIS report <em>Getting to GRIPS with Chronic Pain in Scotland</em>.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18171.q3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" spid="S3W-18171" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#13">

  <p>The Scottish Government has made clear, as recommended in the GRIPS report, that we recognise chronic pain as a long term condition, thereby aligning it with the work on long term conditions which we are taking forward in partnership with the Long Term Conditions Alliance Scotland, including implementation of the national strategy for self-management.</p>

  <p>NHS boards are being asked by the Long Term Conditions Collaborative to include chronic pain in their long term conditions delivery plans. The North of Scotland Planning Group is considering the development of a pain management service in its area, rather than sending people to the specialist pain management hospital in Bath.</p>

  <p>The Scottish Government has provided pump-priming funding for the Chronic Pain Managed Clinical Network that now operates in NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde. We want to encourage other NHS boards to adopt that model, to promote the systematic integration of pain services across primary, secondary and tertiary care.</p>

  <p>NHS QIS will also report on progress with each of the actions in the GRIPS report on a regular basis to the Long Term Conditions Steering Group which the Chief Medical Officer chairs.</p>

  <p>Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con): To ask the Scottish Executive how each NHS board performed in terms of involving patients&rsquo; carers and the public in decisions on the planning, design and delivery of care, as reported by the Scottish Health Council.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18172.q4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80396" speakername="Nicola Sturgeon" spid="S3W-18172" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#13">

  <p>NHS boards complete a self-assessment of their Patient Focus and Public Involvement (PFPI) activities following discussion with key patient and community groups, including public partnership forums. The self-assessment reports on how they have involved patients, carers and the public. This is then endorsed by the Scottish Health Council as an accurate account of PFPI progress, based on the council&rsquo;s own discussion with the community. The individual NHS board reports can be found on their respective websites.</p>

  <p>An overview report of the NHS boards&rsquo; performance in relation to their PFPI activities during 2007-08 will be published shortly by the Scottish Health Council.</p>

  <p>Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con): To ask the Scottish Executive what support was given to the Scottish Health Council to improve how NHS boards engage with patients and the public.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18173.q5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80396" speakername="Nicola Sturgeon" spid="S3W-18173" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#13">

  <p>The Scottish Health Council is part of NHS Quality Improvement Scotland and is sponsored by the Scottish Government Health directorates. As part of that sponsoring role the Health directorates provide funding and on-going advice, guidance and support for the Scottish Health Council.</p>

  <p>Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con): To ask the Scottish Executive how the Scottish Health Council assists in ensuring that patients, carers and the public can express their views on NHS services.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18196.q6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80396" speakername="Nicola Sturgeon" spid="S3W-18196" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#13">

  <p>I refer the member to the answer to question S3W-18171 on 3 December 2008.</p>

  <p>At its annual review on 23 September 2008, the Scottish Health Council identified the following approaches it is taking to ensure that patients, carers and the public are able to make their views on health services known:</p>

  <p>Support the development of Public Partnership Forums;</p>

  <p>Support boards to develop mechanisms that will help them to hear the views of seldom heard groups;</p>

  <p>Support patient feedback through the Council&rsquo;s input to &quot;Better Together&quot;, the patient experience programme;</p>

  <p>Ensure availability and access to the Independent Advice and Support Service, which is commissioned by boards from Citizens&rsquo; Advice Scotland, and</p>

  <p>Monitoring how NHS boards are fulfilling their duties to ensure that advocacy services are provided to those who need them.</p>

  <p>The annual review process, which is led by ministers, holds all NHS boards to account for their performance and provides an opportunity for patients, carers and the public to express their views on NHS services.</p>

  <p>All answers to written parliamentary questions are available on the Parliament&rsquo;s website, the search facility for which can be found at <a href="../../../Apps2/Business/PQA/Default.aspx">http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/Apps2/Business/PQA/Default.aspx</a>.</p>

  <p>Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con): To ask the Scottish Executive what data are being collected in order to audit the outcomes of the Counterweight programme.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18197.q7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" spid="S3W-18197" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#13">

  <p>Counterweight are collecting a range of data to help assess and audit the impact of the programme. This includes:</p>

  <p>Numbers of practices/service implementing the programme;</p>

  <p>Numbers of patients eligible to take part in the programme (based on body mass index);</p>

  <p>Numbers of patients being offered the programme;</p>

  <p>Numbers of patients starting the intervention;</p>

  <p>Number of appointments per patient attending the programme;</p>

  <p>Numbers dropping out and at what stage, and</p>

  <p>Weight change outcomes for patients followed up at three, six,12 and 24 months.</p>

  <p>Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con): To ask the Scottish Executive what the evidence base is for the success of the Counterweight programme.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18279.q8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" spid="S3W-18279" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#13">

  <p>The evidence base for the success of the Counterweight programme is based on the ability of the programme to deliver clinically beneficial weight change.</p>

  <p>Clinically beneficial weight change is recognized to be greater than or equal to 5% loss of body weight. The Counterweight programme was designed to assess if this clinically beneficial weight loss could be achieved in a primary care setting, where the intervention was delivered by busy primary care team as part of other day-to-day activities. Counterweight was originally evaluated from 2000 to 2005 in 65 general practices across the UK. The research demonstrated that 30% of all patients who attend Counterweight appointments achieve greater than or equal to 5% weight loss and this weight loss is maintained at 1 and 2 year follow-up.</p>

  <p>The Counterweight programme is seeing similar results in NHS boards to those previously seen during the research.</p>

  <p>George Foulkes (Lothians) (Lab): To ask the Scottish Executive what steps it is taking to address the fact that NHS Lothian has the highest number of delayed discharges of any NHS board as of October 2008.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18279.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#13">

  <p>The Lothian NHS/local authority partnership, along with every partnership in Scotland, achieved the target to have no-one delayed outwith the agreed six week discharge planning period at April 2008. This has risen in Lothian, which had 27 such delays at October. This compares with 55 at October 2007 and 119 at October 2006. The figures peaked at July 2002 when there were 319 patients delayed in Lothian for longer than six weeks.</p>

  <p>The principal reasons for delay in Lothian were awaiting care home place availability and awaiting social care assessments.</p>

  <p>I expect the partners in Lothian, and all partnerships who are not sustaining the zero level, to be back on track at the January census.</p>

  <p>The Joint Improvement Team has been invited to help tackle the problem in East Lothian.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18195.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#14">Homecoming Scotland</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18195.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80334" speakername="James Kelly (Glasgow Rutherglen) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18195" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#14">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what discussions have been held with South Lanarkshire Council in relation to its involvement in hosting events as part of Homecoming Scotland 2009.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18195.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#14">

  <p>The Homecoming Scotland 2009 team at EventScotland have had a good level of engagement with South Lanarkshire Council. A local authority email distribution list was used to invite local authorities to distribute the Homecoming partner events registration form to events organisers in the area that met the funding criteria. Two partner event registration forms were submitted from the South Lanarkshire area - the Biggar Little Festival and Scotland&rsquo;s Living History Festival/Lanark Medieval Festival. Both of these events are now in the Homecoming programme and will feature in the next printed events guide and on the Homecoming events search engine.</p>

  <p>South Lanarkshire Council also have a Homecoming contact and the Homecoming team have been in touch with that official, who has received two local authority e-updates that have been issued by the Homecoming team. She has confirmed that South Lanarkshire will have approximately 25 events in the local Homecoming programme.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18046.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#15">Identity Cards</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18046.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80312" speakername="George Foulkes (Lothians) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18046" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#15">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive when (a) ministers and (b) officials have met UK ministers or officials from the Home Office to discuss identity cards and what concerns were expressed at the meetings.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18046.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80306" speakername="Fergus Ewing" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#15">

  <p>Ministers have been in communication with the Home Office both by telephone and by letter throughout the year. These communications have explored the implications for Scotland of the National Identity Scheme and latterly, the launch of ID cards for foreign nationals.</p>

  <p>In October, at the request of the IPS, Scottish Government officials met with IPS officials to discuss if and how the ID card proposals might impact on the functions of Scottish ministers. No decisions were made at that meeting and the discussions have not yet concluded.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18024.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#16">Justice</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18024.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80406" speakername="Bill Wilson (West of Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S3W-18024" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#16">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it is aware of concerns that Laurence Connelly Snr and the authors of the report The ICL/Stockline Disaster: An Independent Report on Working Conditions Prior to the Explosion have not been invited to give evidence in the second phase of the ICL/Stockline inquiry and what action it can take in this regard.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18024.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80341" speakername="Kenny MacAskill" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#16">

  <p>The ICL Inquiry is an independent inquiry established jointly by the Scottish ministers and the Secretary of State for Work and Pensions under the Inquiries Act 2005, which provides that the way in which the Inquiry is conducted, including decisions about who is called to give evidence, are entirely matters for the Inquiry chairman and it would therefore not be appropriate for ministers to intervene.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18160.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#17">Livestock</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18160.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80350" speakername="Liam McArthur (Orkney) (LD)" spid="S3W-18160" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#17">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what assessment has been made of the Royal Society of Edinburgh&rsquo;s report, published on Monday 10 November, calling for the European Union to change its approach to vaccination procedures across Europe in order to reduce the spread of viral pathogens and what discussions the Scottish Government has had, or intends to have, with the UK Government in relation to raising the proposals with the European Commission and with other member states.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18160.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80340" speakername="Richard Lochhead" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#17">

  <p>This report is highly relevant to the current situation in Europe, and now Scotland, regarding bluetongue vaccination.</p>

  <p>The Scottish Government has long understood that the best way to secure Scotland&rsquo;s long-term protection against bluetongue is to secure the ability to vaccinate without being forced to accept potentially infected imports. I wrote to Commissioner Vassillou in September 2008 to urge consideration of an amendment to the rules that would allow the use of vaccine as a tool for disease prevention rather than disease control and my officials have been working with UK and European colleagues towards this end. A draft amendment to the EU bluetongue regulation that would achieve this aim is currently under discussion.</p>

  <p>The work by the Royal Society of Edinburgh has provided a welcome and constructive scientific assessment of the issues, which supports the stance taken by the Scottish Government.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18319.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#18">Ministerial Meetings</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18319.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80363" speakername="Des McNulty (Clydebank and Milngavie) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18319" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#18">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive who represented the Cairngorms National Park Authority and Highland Council at the meeting involving the Minister for Community Safety in Aviemore on 26 October 2007 and whether any officials were present.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18319.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#18">

  <p>As this meeting was attended in a constituency capacity, no records are held by the Scottish Government.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18165.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#19">NHS Staff</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18165.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80283" speakername="Jackie Baillie (Dumbarton) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18165" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#19">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many staff are employed at the Vale of Leven Hospital, broken down by profession.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18165.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80396" speakername="Nicola Sturgeon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#19">

  <p>The information requested is not centrally available. However, NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde have provided the Scottish Government with the information, set out at Table 1. Table 1 shows that at October 2008:</p>

  <p>the Vale of Leven hospital employed 720.3 staff whole-time equivalent (WTE).</p>

  <p>the largest staff group at the Vale of Leven Hospital is nursing and midwifery staff (47% of WTE staff or 337.4 WTE), followed by support services staff (15% of WTE staff or 108.3 WTE), and administrative services staff (15% of staff or 104.8 WTE)</p>

  <p>Table 1: Staff Numbers, by Job Family, Vale of Leven Hospital, October 2008</p>

  <p><table width="75%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="40%" valign="top">Job Family</td>
<td width="25%" align="center" valign="top">Head Count</td>
<td width="35%" align="center" valign="top">Whole-Time Equivalent (WTE)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="40%" valign="top">Administrative Services</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">126</td>
<td width="35%" align="right" valign="top">104.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="40%" valign="top">Allied Health Professions</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">43</td>
<td width="35%" align="right" valign="top">33.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="40%" valign="top">Healthcare Science</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">39</td>
<td width="35%" align="right" valign="top">36.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="40%" valign="top">Medical and Dental</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">45</td>
<td width="35%" align="right" valign="top">42.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="40%" valign="top">Medical and Dental Support</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">1</td>
<td width="35%" align="right" valign="top">1.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="40%" valign="top">Nursing and Midwifery</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">394</td>
<td width="35%" align="right" valign="top">337.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="40%" valign="top">Other Therapeutic Services</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">17</td>
<td width="35%" align="right" valign="top">14.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="40%" valign="top">Personal and Social Care</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">2</td>
<td width="35%" align="right" valign="top">1.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="40%" valign="top">Support Services</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">155</td>
<td width="35%" align="right" valign="top">108.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="40%" valign="top">Unallocated / Not Known</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">49</td>
<td width="35%" align="right" valign="top">41.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="40%" valign="top">Total</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">871</td>
<td width="35%" align="right" valign="top">720.3</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Source: NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18073.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#20">Prison Service</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18073.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80284" speakername="Richard Baker (North East Scotland) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18073" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#20">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive when it expects that HM Prison Grampian will be completed and what the overall cost of building it will be.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18074.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80341" speakername="Kenny MacAskill" spid="S3W-18074" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#20">

  <p>I have asked Mike Ewart, Chief Executive of the Scottish Prison Service to respond. His response is as follows:</p>

  <p>The Scottish Government <em>Infrastructure Investment Plan 2008</em>, published in March 2008, provides details of the funding and planned investment in the Prison estate, including the redevelopment of HM Prison Edinburgh, HM Prison Glenochil, HM Prison Perth and HMYOI Polmont. Construction continues at each site and work is expected to be completed at HM Prison Edinburgh and HMYOI Polmont during 2009-10 followed by HM Prison Glenochil and HM Prison Perth during 2010-11.</p>

  <p>Richard Baker (North East Scotland) (Lab): To ask the Scottish Executive when it expects that HM Prison Bishopbriggs will be completed and what the overall cost of building it will be.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18075.q2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80341" speakername="Kenny MacAskill" spid="S3W-18075" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#20">

  <p>I have asked Mike Ewart, Chief Executive of the Scottish Prison Service to respond. His response is as follows:</p>

  <p>The Scottish Government <em>Infrastructure Investment Plan 2008</em>, published in March 2008, provides details of the funding and planned investment in the prison estate, including the redevelopment of HM Prison Edinburgh, HM Prison Glenochil, HM Prison Perth and HMYOI Polmont. Construction continues at each site and work is expected to be completed at HM Prison Edinburgh and HMYOI Polmont during 2009-10 followed by HM Prison Glenochil and HM Prison Perth during 2010-11.</p>

  <p>The procurement process is underway with a view to construction commencing, subject to planning permission, during 2009-10.</p>

  <p>Richard Baker (North East Scotland) (Lab): To ask the Scottish Executive what proportion of its budget for the current spending review period will be spent on the construction of HM Prison Bishopbriggs and HM Prison Grampian.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18075.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80341" speakername="Kenny MacAskill" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#20">

  <p>The Scottish Government <em>Infrastructure Investment Plan 2008</em> , published in March 2008, provides details of the funding and planned investment in the prison estate. The Scottish Prison Service budget for prison development, including HM Prison Bishopbriggs and HM Prison Grampian, amounts to &pound;356 million during the current spending review period, and forecast to continue at &pound;120 million per annum thereafter to complete the modernisation of the prison estate.</p>

  <p>The planned investment in the prison estate during the current spending review is 0.4% of the Scottish Government&rsquo;s Departmental Expenditure Limit (DEL) budget for that period.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-17961.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#21">Public Transport</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-17961.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80358" speakername="David McLetchie (Edinburgh Pentlands) (Con)" spid="S3W-17961" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#21">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how much of its &pound;500 million contribution to the Edinburgh trams project has already been spent, broken down by (a) date of release and (b) size and purpose of each payment.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-17961.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#21">

  <p>The Scottish Government pays a proportionate share (91.7%) of the City of Edinburgh Council&rsquo;s expenditure on development and implementation costs for the Edinburgh Tram project. A total of &pound;206.881 million has been drawn down to date as set out in table 1.</p>

  <p>Table 1</p>

  <p><table width="100%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="36%" align="center" valign="top">Edinburgh Tram Expenditure</td>
<td width="16%" rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">2002-03 (&pound;000)</td>
<td width="16%" rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">2003-04 (&pound;000)</td>
<td width="16%" rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">2004-05 (&pound;000)</td>
<td width="16%" rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">2005-06 (&pound;000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="36%" align="center" valign="top">Month of Payment</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="36%" valign="top">June</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">121,369</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">4,271,101</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="36%" valign="top">July</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">578,554</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="36%" valign="top">August</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">29,656</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">528,096</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">471,370</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="36%" valign="top">September</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">1,684,648</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">615,262</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="36%" valign="top">October</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="bottom">331,678</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">687,422</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="36%" valign="top">November</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="bottom">0</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">554,906</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">114,731</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">859,387</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="36%" valign="top">December</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">311,949</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">376,207</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">291,646</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="36%" valign="top">January</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">180,575</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">909,258</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">2,035,697</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="36%" valign="top">February</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">140,871</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="36%" valign="top">March</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">332,021</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">389,423</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">141,786</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">1,632,190</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="36%" valign="top">April</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">486,807</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">1,101,081</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">120,656</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">5,368,775</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="36%" valign="top">May</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">925,222</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">1,917.781</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">1,369,172</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="36%" valign="top">June</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">218,985</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="36%" valign="top">Totals</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">2,032,542</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">7,156,263</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">6,408,853</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top">13,500,625</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p><table width="75%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="39%" align="center" valign="top">Edinburgh Tram Expenditure</td>
<td width="20%" rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">2006-07 (&pound;000)</td>
<td width="19%" rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">2007-08 (&pound;000)</td>
<td width="22%" rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">2008-09 To Date (&pound;000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="39%" align="center" valign="top">Month of Payment</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="39%" valign="top">June</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">14,128,172</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="39%" valign="top">July</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">9,049,325</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="39%" valign="top">August</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="top">5,316,445</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">43,086,443</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="39%" valign="top">September</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">9,957,687</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="39%" valign="top">October</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="top">12,109,729</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">1,462,720</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="39%" valign="top">November</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">2,480,528</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="39%" valign="top">December</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="top">6,972,186</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="39%" valign="top">January</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="39%" valign="top">February</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="39%" valign="top">March</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="top">1,234,591</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="39%" valign="top">April</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">14,524,929</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="39%" valign="top">May</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top">69,918,838</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">5,863,750</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="39%" valign="top">June</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="39%" valign="top">Totals</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="top">25,632,951</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top">69,918,838</td>
<td width="22%" align="right" valign="top">82,231,111</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18452.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#22">Queen's Speech</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18452.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80278" speakername="Brian Adam (Aberdeen North) (SNP)" spid="S3W-18452" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#22">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what legislative consent motions it will lodge in the Parliament in connection with the legislative programme of the UK Government to be announced in the Queen&rsquo;s Speech on 3 December 2008.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18452.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80300" speakername="Bruce Crawford" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#22">

  <p>In accordance with the Sewel Convention, the UK Parliament does not legislate with regard to devolved matters in Scotland without the consent of the Scottish Parliament.</p>

  <p>This is an important part of the devolution settlement, which acknowledges the special constitutional position of the Scottish Parliament and the democratic mandate conferred on this Parliament by the people of Scotland. In the view of the Scottish Government, the Sewel Convention will remain an essential part of the constitution of the UK for as long as the UK Parliament retains its current powers and functions in relation to Scotland.</p>

  <p>In the normal course of business, legislation on devolved matters should be scrutinised and determined in the Scottish Parliament. There may however be situations in which it is helpful and appropriate for legislation dealing with devolved matters to be taken forward at Westminster.</p>

  <p>The Scottish Government is committed to assessing opportunities of this kind on their merits and to working closely and constructively with the UK Government, on a case-by-case basis, to deliver legislation which best meets Scotland&rsquo;s needs. The Scottish Government is equally committed to working with the UK Government to pursue opportunities to extend devolved competence.</p>

  <p>The formal consent of the Scottish Parliament is required in relation to all proposals for Westminster primary legislation on devolved matters, including alterations to devolved competence, in accordance with Chapter 9B of Standing Orders.</p>

  <p>Within the legislative programme announced today by the UK Government, we have identified and agreed a number of potential opportunities to legislate for the benefit of Scotland on matters that are within the legislative competence of the Scottish Parliament or which alter legislative or executive competence.</p>

  <p>The UK bills which we currently expect to give rise to Legislative Consent Motions in the Scottish Parliament are:</p>

  <p>Equality &ndash; to include Scotland in the extension of public sector duties and address inequities on age, sexual orientation and belief.</p>

  <p>Coroners &amp; Justice &ndash; ensuring that criminals in Scotland do not profit from writing about their crimes by joining with the UK Government in a UK wide civil scheme for the recovery of profits from criminal memoires.</p>

  <p>Local Democracy, Economic Regeneration &amp; Construction &ndash; to include Scotland in amendments to new Construction Contracts legislation, ensuring consistency across the UK, a desire expressed by the industry in consultations.</p>

  <p>Marine &amp; Coastal Access - introduces measures to Scotland which ensure the sustainable development of the marine environment within environmental limits and gives an enhanced role to Scottish Government to address issues exclusive to Scottish waters, as well as to provide for greater integration with UK Marine Planning.</p>

  <p>Policing &amp; Crime &ndash; To close the loophole regarding Football Banning Orders, as requested by the Cabinet Secretary for Finance &amp; Sustainable Growth after the incidents witnessed at the UEFA Cup final in Manchester earlier this year.</p>

  <p>The Scottish Government expects, in due course, to lodge memoranda and motions for these bills, once they are introduced in the UK Parliament. It will then be for the Scottish Parliament to determine whether to give or withhold consent.</p>

  <p>It is possible that further opportunities to legislate for Scotland by means of Legislative Consent Motions may occur in connection with other UK bills, as their provisions are developed and finalised. Any additional proposals of this kind will be drawn to the attention of the Parliament as they arise, in line with the requirements of Standing Orders.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-17944.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#23">Rural Development</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-17944.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80384" speakername="John Scott (Ayr) (Con)" spid="S3W-17944" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#23">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive why there is only one closing date for applications to the Rural Development Contracts - Rural Priorities scheme.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-17945.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80340" speakername="Richard Lochhead" spid="S3W-17945" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#23">

  <p>The Rural Development Contracts &ndash; Rural Priorities Scheme is constantly open to new applications. There are no closing dates for applications.</p>

  <p>It is currently intended to hold at least three assessment rounds per year for this scheme. Two assessment rounds have already been held this year (in August and October) with a further two rounds scheduled for December 2008 and February 2009.</p>

  <p>Prior to each assessment round, all of the project proposals which are ready for assessment on a specific date are collated and the relevant information circulated to the members of the Regional Proposal Assessment Committees to enable them to consider these projects for funding. Where projects are not ready for assessment on the date the information is collated, they are simply rolled forward to the next assessment round.</p>

  <p>John Scott (Ayr) (Con): To ask the Scottish Executive what plans it has to increase the number of closing dates per annum for applications to the Rural Development Contracts - Rural Priorities scheme.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18157.q2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80340" speakername="Richard Lochhead" spid="S3W-18157" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#23">

  <p>The Rural Development Contracts &ndash; Rural Priorities Scheme is constantly open to new applications. There are no closing dates for applications.</p>

  <p>It is currently intended to hold at least three assessment rounds per year for this scheme. Two assessment rounds have already been held this year (in August and October) with a further two rounds scheduled for December 2008 and February 2009.</p>

  <p>Prior to each assessment round, all of the project proposals which are ready for assessment on a specific date are collated and the relevant information circulated to the members of the Regional Proposal Assessment Committees to enable them to consider these projects for funding. Where projects are not ready for assessment on the date the information is collated, they are simply rolled forward to the next assessment round.</p>

  <p>The number of assessment rounds in any one year will be reviewed in response to the number of project proposals coming forward for consideration.</p>

  <p>Liam McArthur (Orkney) (LD): To ask the Scottish Executive what action it is taking to ensure that the Scottish Rural Development Plan provides adequate and effective support for the agricultural industry.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18157.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80340" speakername="Richard Lochhead" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#23">

  <p>The Scotland Rural Development Programme was designed in consultation with stakeholders and is monitored continuously by a programme monitoring committee. The Scottish Government has already in 2008 submitted to the European Commission modifications to the programme to improve its effectiveness. We will have the opportunity in 2009 to submit further modifications, for which we will take account of a review of the programme which we expect to undertake early next year.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18087.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#24">School Meals</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18087.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80394" speakername="David Stewart (Highlands and Islands) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18087" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#24">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what cost would fall to (a) Highland, (b) Moray, (c) Argyll and Bute, (d) Comhairle nan Eilean Siar, (e) Orkney Islands and (f) Shetland Islands councils if school meals were provided free to all school children in these local authority areas.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18087.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80331" speakername="Adam Ingram" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#24">

  <p>The Scottish Government has not calculated the cost of providing free school meals to all primary school and secondary school pupils. The most recent school meals data are available on the Scottish Executive website at <a href="http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Publications/2008/06/24125730/0" target="_blank">http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Publications/2008/06/24125730/0</a> .</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18109.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#25">Scottish Futures Trust</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18109.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80378" speakername="Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD)" spid="S3W-18109" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#25">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what costs were involved in advertising the post of chief executive of the Scottish Futures Trust, including payment to MacDonald Kinnaird recruitment consultancy.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18110.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" spid="S3W-18110" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#25">

  <p>The total cost of advertising the post of Chief Executive of the Scottish Futures Trust was &pound;13,040.</p>

  <p>Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD): To ask the Scottish Executive where the position of chief executive of the Scottish Futures Trust was advertised.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18112.q2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" spid="S3W-18112" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#25">

  <p>This is a matter for the Scottish Futures Trust. I understand that the position was advertised on 9 and 16 November in the <em>Sunday Times</em> , on 12 <sup> </sup> and 13 November in the <em>Daily Telegraph</em> and on 16 November in the <em>Sunday Telegraph</em> .</p>

  <p>Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD): To ask the Scottish Executive whether the Scottish Futures Trust is a private limited company.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18113.q3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" spid="S3W-18113" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#25">

  <p>The Scottish Futures Trust is a private company limited by shares under the Companies Acts. HM Treasury guidance indicates that it will be classified to the public sector in the Whole of Government Accounts.</p>

  <p>Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD): To ask the Scottish Executive whether the Scottish Futures Trust is wholly owned by ministers.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18114.q4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" spid="S3W-18114" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#25">

  <p>Yes. All of the shares in the company are owned by the Scottish ministers.</p>

  <p>Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD): To ask the Scottish Executive what opportunity the Parliament will have to scrutinise the operation of the Scottish Futures Trust, as it is entitled to do with other government departments and agencies.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18115.q5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80378" speakername="Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD)" spid="S3W-18115" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#25">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what information on the operation of the Scottish Futures Trust will be publicly available.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18116.q6" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" spid="S3W-18116" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#25">

  <p>Scottish ministers are ultimately accountable to the Parliament for the activities of Scottish Futures Trust and will keep Parliament informed about its performance.</p>

  <p>Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD): To ask the Scottish Executive where a full job description and salary details are available for the post of the chief executive of the Scottish Futures Trust.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18118.q7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" spid="S3W-18118" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#25">

  <p>Information about the post of Chief Executive to the Scottish Futures Trust is available from Douglas Kinnaird at Macdonald Kinnaird recruitment (dk@macdonaldkinnaird.com). Remuneration will reflect the responsibilities and experience of the successful candidate and their previous employment.</p>

  <p>Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD): To ask the Scottish Executive who will interview applicants for the post of chief executive of the Scottish Futures Trust.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18119.q8" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" spid="S3W-18119" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#25">

  <p>The interview panel will consist of the Chair of the Scottish Futures Trust (SFT), one of the non-Executive Directors of SFT, and a senior official from the Scottish Government.</p>

  <p>Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD): To ask the Scottish Executive to whom the Chief Executive of the Scottish Futures Trust will report.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18120.q9" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" spid="S3W-18120" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#25">

  <p>The Chief Executive will report to the board of the Scottish Futures Trust.</p>

  <p>Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD): To ask the Scottish Executive what the leadership structure of the Scottish Futures Trust will be.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18120.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#25">

  <p>This will be for the board of the Scottish Futures Trust to determine.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18010.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#26">Sectarianism</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18010.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80293" speakername="Bill Butler (Glasgow Anniesland) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18010" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#26">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, further to the answer to question S3W-17040 by Fergus Ewing on 29 October 2008, whether it will provide funding to Nil by Mouth for 2009-10.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18010.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80306" speakername="Fergus Ewing" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#26">

  <p>The Scottish Government has on-going constructive discussions with Nil by Mouth on a range of issues relating to tackling sectarianism. This includes looking for opportunities for the Scottish Government and Nil by Mouth to work together, and further decisions will be announced in due course.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18011.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#27">Social Care</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18011.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80338" speakername="Johann Lamont (Glasgow Pollok) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18011" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#27">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, in light of the analysis of single outcome agreements (SOAs) by Community Care Providers Scotland, how it will address the finding that SOAs have little to say about the role of the voluntary sector in social care.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18012.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80338" speakername="Johann Lamont (Glasgow Pollok) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18012" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#27">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, in light of the analysis of single outcome agreements (SOAs) by Community Care Providers Scotland, how it will address the finding that SOAs have little to say about the importance of the social care workforce.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18013.q2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80338" speakername="Johann Lamont (Glasgow Pollok) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18013" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#27">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, in light of the analysis of single outcome agreements (SOAs) by Community Care Providers Scotland, how it will address the finding that SOAs have little to say about the role of technology in independent living.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18014.q3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80338" speakername="Johann Lamont (Glasgow Pollok) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18014" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#27">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, in light of the analysis of single outcome agreements (SOAs) by Community Care Providers Scotland, how it will address the finding that SOAs have little to say about the importance of personalisation in service design and delivery of community care.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18015.q4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80338" speakername="Johann Lamont (Glasgow Pollok) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18015" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#27">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, in light of the analysis of single outcome agreements (SOAs) by Community Care Providers Scotland, how it will address the finding that SOAs do not reflect many of the aspirations of Changing Lives.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18016.q5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80338" speakername="Johann Lamont (Glasgow Pollok) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18016" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#27">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, in light of the analysis of single outcome agreements (SOAs) by Community Care Providers Scotland, how it will address the finding that SOAs have little to say about the means by which people will be assisted to live independently.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18016.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80331" speakername="Adam Ingram" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#27">

  <p>Single outcome agreements do not replace all of the underlying service planning and performance management arrangements in place in local authority areas. They provide an outcome framework and focus for service planning, resource planning and performance management. They are high-level documents and should focus strategically on priority areas for improvement and end outcomes in terms of quality of life, opportunity and the context in which people live and on a limited and manageable number of priorities, not necessarily the detail of how these will be achieved. Not everything could or should be included in the SOA.</p>

  <p>Organisations that have good local knowledge about people and their service needs, and collect valuable information that will help support the SOA process &ndash; and through the Community Planning arrangements, should have the opportunity to influence. The Scottish Government expects the third sector to be important Community Planning partners as strategic partners as well as being involved in the design and delivery of services.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18034.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#28">Voluntary Sector</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18034.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80375" speakername="Peter Peacock (Highlands and Islands) (Lab)" spid="S3W-18034" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#28">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what funds Highlands and Islands Enterprise made available in the form of grants under the Strengthening Communities budget for distribution to the voluntary sector in (a) 2006-07, (b) 2007-08 and (c) 2008-09.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18035.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" spid="S3W-18035" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#28">

  <p>Distribution of grants to the voluntary sector is an operational matter for Highlands and Islands Enterprise. I have asked its chief executive to write to you on this matter.</p>

  <p>Peter Peacock (Highlands and Islands) (Lab): To ask the Scottish Executive what arrangements it has put in place to ensure that voluntary organisations are aware of where they may seek alternative project funding, in the circumstance where the organisation was previously eligible to apply for funding through the Highlands and Islands Enterprise (HIE) but is no longer eligible as a result of introduction of the social enterprise criteria.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18036.q2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" spid="S3W-18036" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#28">

  <p>In line with the reforms to the enterprise agencies, HIE will increasingly focus its strengthening communities interventions on the most remote and fragile areas and on activity which will promote the sustainable economic development of those areas. This includes developing the social economy, to which end it will work closely with Councils for Voluntary Service (CVS) and the <em>Scottish Council</em> for <em>Voluntary Organisations.</em></p>

  <p>The Scottish Government provides funding to the CVS network to help the third sector to thrive and grow at local level across Scotland. This funding includes support for the provision of funding advice and support. CVS across Highlands and Islands, as elsewhere, has the experience and capability to provide this advice. I would advise any voluntary organisation in need of funding support to contact its local CVS in the first instance.</p>

  <p>Peter Peacock (Highlands and Islands) (Lab): To ask the Scottish Executive, following the change to Highlands and Islands Enterprise funding arrangements, what importance it places on providing adequate funding to the voluntary sector in the Highlands and Islands.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18037.q3" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" spid="S3W-18037" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#28">

  <p>The Scottish Government places great importance on strong support to the third sector. This is why we have increased funding levels to the support networks of Volunteer Centres and Councils for Voluntary Service over this spending period, and why we are working with the third sector and the public sector to ensure the third sector is supported and strengthened at local level. In total, the Scottish Government has committed &pound;93 million to building the capacity of the third sector in the period 2008-11, a 37% increase over the previous spending review period. This will help create the right environment in which the third sector can thrive, and create the conditions in which direct investment in the sector can have the greatest effect.</p>

  <p>Local and national funding programmes &ndash; including the Scottish Government&rsquo;s &pound;30 million Scottish Investment Fund &ndash; will therefore be made in the context of the wider support that is being provided to the third sector.</p>

  <p>Peter Peacock (Highlands and Islands) (Lab): To ask the Scottish Executive, following the change to Highlands and Islands Enterprise funding arrangements, whether it anticipates that it will have an increased role in funding of the voluntary sector in the Highlands and Islands.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18038.q4" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" spid="S3W-18038" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#28">

  <p>The Scottish Government expects all community planning partners to take into account the role and potential of the third sector in delivering public services, in helping to stimulate growth in the Scottish economy and in supporting community action at grassroots level.</p>

  <p>For its part the Scottish Government has committed &pound;93 million to building the capacity of the third sector in the period 2008-11, a 37% increase over the previous spending review period. This will help create the right environment in which the third sector can thrive, and create the conditions in which direct investment in the sector can have the greatest effect. Local and national funding programmes &ndash; including the Scottish Government&rsquo;s &pound;30 million Scottish Investment Fund &ndash; will therefore be made in the context of the wider support that is being provided to the third sector.</p>

  <p>Peter Peacock (Highlands and Islands) (Lab): To ask the Scottish Executive, following the change to Highlands and Islands Enterprise funding arrangements, whether it believes that Highlands and Islands councils have an increased role in funding of the voluntary sector.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18039.q5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" spid="S3W-18039" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#28">

  <p>In line with the reforms to the enterprise agencies, HIE will increasingly focus its strengthening communities interventions on the most remote and fragile areas and on activity which will promote the sustainable economic development of those areas. This includes developing the social economy, to which end it will work closely with Councils for Voluntary Service and the <em>Scottish Council</em> for <em>Voluntary Organisations.</em></p>

  <p>With responsibility for design and delivery of the single outcome agreement moving to all community planning partners, there will continue to be an important role for councils, as well as for the Scottish Government, the wider public sector and independent funders, in supporting the work of the third sector in the Highlands and Islands.</p>

  <p>Peter Peacock (Highlands and Islands) (Lab): To ask the Scottish Executive, following the change to Highlands and Islands Enterprise funding arrangements, whether additional funds have been provided to local authorities in the Highlands and Islands parliamentary region to allow the authorities to offer additional financial support to voluntary sector organisations.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2008-12-03.S3W-18039.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-08/wa1203.htm#28">

  <p>Councils, along with their community planning partners and the Scottish Government, will continue to have an important role in supporting the work of the third sector in the Highlands and Islands.</p>

  <p>For its part the Scottish Government has committed &pound;93 million to building the capacity of the third sector in the period 2008-11, a 37% increase over the previous spending review period. This will help create the right environment in which the third sector can thrive, and create the conditions in which direct investment in the sector can have the greatest effect.</p>

</reply>
</publicwhip>