<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE publicwhip [

<!ENTITY pound   "&#163;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">

<!ENTITY agrave  "&#224;">
<!ENTITY aacute  "&#225;">
<!ENTITY egrave  "&#232;">
<!ENTITY eacute  "&#233;">
<!ENTITY ecirc   "&#234;">
<!ENTITY iacute  "&#237;">
<!ENTITY ograve  "&#242;">
<!ENTITY oacute  "&#243;">
<!ENTITY uacute  "&#250;">
<!ENTITY Aacute  "&#193;">
<!ENTITY Eacute  "&#201;">
<!ENTITY Iacute  "&#205;">
<!ENTITY Oacute  "&#211;">
<!ENTITY Uacute  "&#218;">
<!ENTITY Uuml    "&#220;">
<!ENTITY auml    "&#228;">
<!ENTITY euml    "&#235;">
<!ENTITY iuml    "&#239;">
<!ENTITY ouml    "&#246;">
<!ENTITY uuml    "&#252;">
<!ENTITY fnof    "&#402;">
<!ENTITY aelig   "&#230;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">
<!ENTITY reg     "&#174;">
<!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
<!ENTITY shy     "&#173;">
<!ENTITY deg     "&#176;">
<!ENTITY middot  "&#183;">
<!ENTITY ordm    "&#186;">
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY hellip  "&#8230;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">

<!ENTITY acirc   "&#226;">
<!ENTITY Agrave  "&#192;">
<!ENTITY Aring   "&#197;">
<!ENTITY aring   "&#229;">
<!ENTITY atilde  "&#227;">
<!ENTITY Ccedil  "&#199;">
<!ENTITY ccedil  "&#231;">
<!ENTITY Egrave  "&#200;">
<!ENTITY Icirc   "&#206;">
<!ENTITY icirc   "&#238;">
<!ENTITY Igrave  "&#204;">
<!ENTITY igrave  "&#236;">
<!ENTITY ntilde  "&#241;">
<!ENTITY ocirc   "&#244;">
<!ENTITY oelig   "&#339;">
<!ENTITY Ograve  "&#210;">
<!ENTITY Oslash  "&#216;">
<!ENTITY oslash  "&#248;">
<!ENTITY Scaron  "&#352;">
<!ENTITY scaron  "&#353;">
<!ENTITY sup1    "&#185;">
<!ENTITY sup2    "&#178;">
<!ENTITY sup3    "&#179;">
<!ENTITY ugrave  "&#249;">
<!ENTITY Ugrave  "&#217;">
<!ENTITY yacute  "&#253;">
<!ENTITY frac12  "&#189;">
<!ENTITY micro   "&#181;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8225;">
]>

<publicwhip>

<source url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm"/>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.0.mh" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm">Written Answers Monday 26 November 2007</major-heading>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.1.mh" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm">Scottish Executive</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.2.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#1">Agriculture</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.2.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80375" speakername="Peter Peacock (Highlands and Islands) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6497" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#1">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it has any plans for, or will consider, suspending Integrated Pollution Prevention and Control Regulations to assist agriculture.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.2.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80340" speakername="Richard Lochhead" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#1">

  <p>The Scottish Government currently has no plans to suspend the Pollution Prevention and Control (Scotland) Regulations 2000 (the PPC Regulations) for agriculture. Such action would be incompatible with Scotland&rsquo;s obligations under the Scotland Act 1998 to implement European Community law in full.</p>

  <p>The Scottish Environment Protection Agency (SEPA), which implements the PPC Regulations, is required to ensure it does not impose a greater burden than necessary on businesses affected by the regulations. SEPA has been working with the NFU Scotland and farmers to identify ways in which the impact of PPC controls on agriculture can be minimised, whilst ensuring proper protection for the environment and human health. As a result SEPA has introduced, for example, Standard Farming Installation Rules for intensive farming designed to make it simpler to meet PPC requirements.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.3.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#2">Air Services</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.3.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80342" speakername="Lewis Macdonald (Aberdeen Central) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6308" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#2">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive when it will make a decision about the replacement of the route development fund for direct flights to and from Scottish airports.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.3.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#2">

  <p>The route development fund (RDF) which ended on 31 May 2007 will not be replaced. The Spending Review outcome will provide continuing support for RDF routes launched before that date. We will continue to work with airlines and airport operators on the development of new international air routes which improve business connectivity, encourage inward investment and make Scotland more accessible for inbound tourism.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.4.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#3">Airports</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.4.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80368" speakername="John Farquhar Munro (Ross, Skye and Inverness West) (LD)" spid="S3W-6485" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#3">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what plans there are to upgrade facilities at Inverness Airport.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.4.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#3">

  <p>In keeping with Scottish Transport Appraisal Guidance (STAG), Highlands and Islands Airports Ltd (HIAL) has prepared a report on the expansion of Inverness Airport Terminal reflecting the passenger growth envisaged in its master plan published in August 2007. The STAG report appraised an option which would provide capacity for 1.5 million passengers and which the master plan envisaged would not be reached until 2021. HIAL, in discussion with officials, is now considering other options which meet regulatory requirements and Inverness Airport&rsquo;s short to medium term anticipated passenger growth needs, while taking full account of environmental concerns.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.5.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#4">Alcohol Misuse</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.5.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80383" speakername="Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6352" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#4">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether the &pound;85 million allocated to reduce harm done by the misuse of alcohol, as referred to in <em>Scottish Budget: Spending Review 2007</em> , will include treatment and prevention programmes.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.5.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#4">

  <p>Draft budget proposals include an &pound;85 million boost over three years to increase access to early intervention and treatment for people with alcohol problems; the single largest increase ever for tackling alcohol misuse in Scotland.</p>

  <p>Decisions on the exact allocation of this funding will be taken over the coming months, but treatment and prevention programmes will benefit from increased resources.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.6.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#5">Biofuels</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.6.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80304" speakername="Bob Doris (Glasgow) (SNP)" spid="S3W-6486" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#5">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will consider establishing a biofuels task force.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.6.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#5">

  <p>There is no evidence that such an approach to the use of biofuels is required. The Scottish Government is pursuing a package of measures to address both transport CO <sub>2</sub> emissions and the research, development and production of renewable energy. In relation to reducing emissions, measures include investment in public transport, and the promotion of behavioural change which includes supporting the development and use of travel plans, eco-driving, green fleet reviews and the use of fuel and vehicle technologies that result in reduced emissions which includes biofuels.</p>

  <p>A strategic approach to the use of both biofuels and other fuel and vehicle technologies as they emerge, is supported by this wider range of behavioural measures being pursued and is consistent with expert opinion and both UK and EU policy. The production and use of biofuels is framed by UK and EU legislation. The Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation (RTFO) sets targets for the use of biofuels (5% by 2010) and Scotland has contributed to the development of this UK legislation which complies with the EU directive on biofuels (2003/30/EC).</p>

  <p>In terms of renewables, electrical output from stations using biomass fuel sources are supported under the Renewables Obligation (Scotland) Order, which obliges all licensed suppliers of electricity in Scotland to procure increasing amounts of power from renewable sources. The Scottish Government is also funding developments in the sector more generally under its Scottish Biomass Support Scheme.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.7.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#6">Central Heating</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.7.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80367" speakername="Mary Mulligan (Linlithgow) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6747" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#6">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many households with children aged five or under have no central heating, broken down by tenure, in the most recent year for which figures are available.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.7.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#6">

  <p>The Scottish House Condition Survey estimates that in the period from October 2003 to September 2005 6,000 households with children aged five or under have no central heating. This corresponds to 2% of households with children aged five or under.</p>

  <p>The Scottish House Condition Survey can only provide an overall national estimate of the number of households with children aged five or under which have no central heating. The sample size is too small to allow a breakdown of this number by tenure.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.8.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7">Class Sizes</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.8.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80287" speakername="Rhona Brankin (Midlothian) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6167" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7" holdingdate="2007-11-22">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive when it will publish the final report of the Class Sizes, Staffing and Resources Working Group.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.8.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80330" speakername="Fiona Hyslop" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7">

  <p>The Class size and Resources Working Group final report was published on 20 November 2007.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.9.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80287" speakername="Rhona Brankin (Midlothian) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6169" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7" holdingdate="2007-11-22">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive why the final report of the Class Sizes, Staffing and Resources Working Group has not been published.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.9.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80330" speakername="Fiona Hyslop" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7">

  <p>The final report of the Class Size and Resources Working Group was published on 20 November 2007. It is largely a historic document, with much of its material already in the group&rsquo;s interim report published on 28 June 2006. Ministers and officials have been engaged in driving forward this government&rsquo;s priorities in education.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.10.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80287" speakername="Rhona Brankin (Midlothian) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6170" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7" holdingdate="2007-11-22">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what impact the final report of the Class Sizes, Staffing and Resources Working Group will have on its class sizes policy.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.10.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80330" speakername="Fiona Hyslop" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7">

  <p>The final report of the Class Size and Resources Working Group was published on 20 November 2007. Its conclusions focus on undertaking further research on the impact of class sizes on attainment and I will consider the research proposals in due course.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.11.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80287" speakername="Rhona Brankin (Midlothian) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6193" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7" holdingdate="2007-11-23">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will publish the minutes of meetings of the Class Sizes, Staffing and Resources Working Group held in 2007.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.11.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80330" speakername="Fiona Hyslop" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7">

  <p>The Class Size and Resources Working Group met on 7 March (Bib. number 44148) and 21 June 2007 (Bib. number 44149) and copies of the minutes of these meetings have been placed in the Scottish Parliament Information Centre.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.12.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80287" speakername="Rhona Brankin (Midlothian) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6195" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7" holdingdate="2007-11-23">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the main conclusions were of the Scottish Council for Research in Education&rsquo;s review of the literature on class sizes.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.12.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80330" speakername="Fiona Hyslop" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7">

  <p>The Scottish Council for Research in Education&rsquo;s review of the literature on class sizes was published as part of the interim report of the Class Size and Resources Working Group on 28 June 2006. It can be accessed using the following link: <a href="http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Publications/2006/06/26102419/10" target="_blank">http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Publications/2006/06/26102419/10</a> .</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.13.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80287" speakername="Rhona Brankin (Midlothian) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6222" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it plans to publish annual figures on the number of schools meeting the maximum class size pledge of 18 pupils in primary 1 to primary 3 (a) by local authority and (b) for Scotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.13.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80330" speakername="Fiona Hyslop" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7">

  <p>Data on individual class sizes is collected annually as part of the annual school census and subsequently published as a dataset. This practice will continue.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.14.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80287" speakername="Rhona Brankin (Midlothian) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6227" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how it will support schools and local authorities in meeting the planning and organisational implications arising from the formation of new composite classes to meet the maximum class size pledge of 18 pupils in primary 1 to primary 3.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.14.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80330" speakername="Fiona Hyslop" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7">

  <p>The formation of classes to meet our class size commitments is a matter for local authorities in the light of the requirements of individual schools. As part of our commitment we would also expect composite classes in primary 1 to primary 3 to have a maximum of 18 pupils rather than the current maximum of 25.</p>

  <p>As part of the new partnership relationship the Scottish Government is seeking to agree, there will be a move to a Single Outcome Agreement for every council, based on an agreed set of national outcomes, including class sizes.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.15.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80287" speakername="Rhona Brankin (Midlothian) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6228" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what contingency plans it will make for schools where classes are already at the maximum class size of 18 pupils in primary 1 to primary 3 and additional pupils enrol mid-session.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.15.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80330" speakername="Fiona Hyslop" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7">

  <p>For practical reasons there needs to be a degree of flexibility in setting class size maxima. The Education (Lower Primary Class Sizes) (Scotland) Regulations 1999 which reduced primary 1 to primary 3 classes to a maximum of 30 allowed certain exceptions to the class size maxima such as pupils joining a school after the end of a placing round. We intend similar flexibilities to apply to class size maxima of 18 pupils in primary 1 to primary 3.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.16.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80327" speakername="Hugh Henry (Paisley South) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6361" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether sufficient teachers are in post to allow class size reductions to 20 in maths and English for S1 and S2 across Scotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.16.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80400" speakername="Maureen Watt" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7">

  <p>We confirmed the previous administration&rsquo;s commitment to provide &pound;50.3 million in 2007-08 to increase teacher numbers and reduce S1/S2 maths and English classes to a maximum of 20 pupils. That level of funding was deemed sufficient by the previous administration to enable local authorities to employ teachers to meet the commitment.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.17.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80327" speakername="Hugh Henry (Paisley South) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6512" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether ministers were told prior to the First Minister&rsquo;s statement on 5 September 2007 that reduction in class sizes to 18 in primary 1 to primary 3 would be delivered in this parliamentary session ( <em>Official Report</em> c. 1378) that this could not be achieved by 2011.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.17.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80330" speakername="Fiona Hyslop" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#7">

  <p>Advice passed from officials to ministers is considered to be confidential, to allow the full and frank exchange of views necessary to take forward government objectives.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.18.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#8">Common Agricultural Policy</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.18.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80354" speakername="Jamie McGrigor (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6218" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#8">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how much is in the Scottish common agricultural policy national reserve for 2007-08 and future years.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.18.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80340" speakername="Richard Lochhead" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#8">

  <p>We will not know how much is in the Scottish component of the National Reserve until after the clawback of unused entitlements has been completed; there will be a further clawback exercise in January 2008.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.19.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">Dentistry</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.19.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80374" speakername="Gil Paterson (West of Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S3W-6458" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many NHS dentists worked in West Dunbartonshire in each year from 1997 to 2007.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.19.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>The number of NHS dentists who provide general dental services (GDS) in West Dunbartonshire local authority in each year from 1997 to 2007 is shown in the following table.</p>

  <p>Number of NHS Dentists<sup>1,2,3</sup> Providing General Dental Services in the Years Ending 31 March 1997-2007</p>

  <p><table width="50%" border="BORDER" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="24%" align="left" valign="bottom"> Local Authority Area<sup>3</sup></td>
<td width="7%" align="left" valign="bottom"> 1997</td>
<td width="7%" align="left" valign="bottom"> 1998</td>
<td width="7%" align="left" valign="bottom"> 1999</td>
<td width="7%" align="left" valign="bottom"> 2000</td>
<td width="7%" align="left" valign="bottom"> 2001</td>
<td width="7%" align="left" valign="bottom"> 2002</td>
<td width="7%" align="left" valign="bottom"> 2003</td>
<td width="7%" align="left" valign="bottom"> 2004</td>
<td width="7%" align="left" valign="bottom"> 2005</td>
<td width="7%" align="left" valign="bottom"> 2006</td>
<td width="7%" align="left" valign="bottom"> 2007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="24%" align="left" valign="bottom"> West Dunbartonshire</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 40</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 46</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 43</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 40</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 37</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 37</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 35</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 36</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 36</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 39</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 41</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Source: MIDAS (Management Information and Dental Accounting System).</p>

  <p>Notes:</p>

  <p>1. Includes non-salaried and salaried GDS dentists, assistants and vocational dental practitioners. Excludes dentists working in NHS hospitals and the Community Dental Service in Scotland.</p>

  <p>2. An NHS general dental practitioner may have more than one arrangement with an NHS board if he/she has more than one practice, or an arrangement with more than one NHS board if he/she practises in more than one NHS board area.</p>

  <p>3. The number of dentists in post, not the whole-time equivalent figure, as information on the working hours of each dentist is not collected.</p>

  <p>4. Based on location of dental practice.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.20.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80374" speakername="Gil Paterson (West of Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S3W-6459" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many salaried NHS dentists worked in West Dunbartonshire in each year from 1997 to 2007.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.20.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>The number of salaried dentists working in West Dunbartonshire local authority in each year from 1997 to 2007 is shown in the following table.</p>

  <p>Number of Salaried NHS Dentists<sup>1,2 </sup>Providing General Dental Services in the Years Ending 31 March 1997-2007</p>

  <p><table width="50%" border="BORDER" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="24%" align="left" valign="bottom"> Local Authority Area<sup>3</sup></td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1997</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1998</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1999</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2000</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2001</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2002</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2003</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2004</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2005</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2006</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="24%" align="left" valign="bottom"> West Dunbartonshire</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 1</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 2</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Source: MIDAS (Management Information and Dental Accounting System).</p>

  <p>Notes:</p>

  <p>1. Excludes dentists working in NHS hospitals and the Community Dental Service in Scotland.</p>

  <p>2. The number of salaried dentists in post, not the whole-time equivalent figure, as information on the working hours of each salaried dentist is not collected.</p>

  <p>3. Based on location of dental practice.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.21.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80374" speakername="Gil Paterson (West of Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S3W-6460" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many NHS dentists worked in East Dunbartonshire in each year from 1997 to 2007.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.21.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>The number of NHS dentists who provide general dental services (GDS) in East Dunbartonshire local authority in each year from 1997 to 2007 is shown in the following table.</p>

  <p>Number of NHS Dentists<sup>1,2,3</sup> Providing General Dental Services in the Years Ending 31 March 1997-2007</p>

  <p><table width="50%" border="BORDER" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="24%" align="center" valign="bottom"> Local Authority Area<sup>4</sup></td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1997</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1998</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1999</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2000</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2001</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2002</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2003</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2004</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2005</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2006</td>
<td width="7%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="24%" height="25" align="center" valign="bottom"> East Dunbartonshire</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 47</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 46</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 52</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 53</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 52</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 54</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 58</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 63</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 66</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 70</td>
<td width="7%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 68</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Source: MIDAS (Management Information and Dental Accounting System).</p>

  <p>Notes:</p>

  <p>1. Includes non-salaried and salaried GDS dentists, assistants and vocational dental practitioners. Excludes dentists working in NHS hospitals and the Community Dental Service in Scotland.</p>

  <p>2. An NHS general dental practitioner may have more than one arrangement with an NHS board if he/she has more than one practice, or an arrangement with more than one NHS board if he/she practises in more than one NHS board area.</p>

  <p>3. The number of dentists in post, not the whole-time equivalent figure, as information on the working hours of each dentist is not collected.</p>

  <p>4. Based on location of dental practice.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.22.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80374" speakername="Gil Paterson (West of Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S3W-6461" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many salaried NHS dentists worked in East Dunbartonshire in each year from 1997 to 2007.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.22.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>No salaried dentists worked in East Dunbartonshire local authority in the requested period.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.23.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80374" speakername="Gil Paterson (West of Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S3W-6462" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many NHS dentists worked in the Dumbarton parliamentary constituency in each year from 1997 to 2007.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.23.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>The number of NHS dentists who provide general dental services (GDS) in the Dumbarton parliamentary constituency in each year from 1997 to 2007 is shown in the following table.</p>

  <p>Number of NHS Dentists<sup>1,2,3</sup> Providing General Dental Services in the Years Ending 31 March 1997-2007</p>

  <p><table width="50%" border="BORDER" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="29%" valign="bottom"> Parliamentary Constituency<sup>4</sup></td>
<td width="6%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1997</td>
<td width="6%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1998</td>
<td width="6%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1999</td>
<td width="6%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2000</td>
<td width="6%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2001</td>
<td width="6%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2002</td>
<td width="6%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2003</td>
<td width="6%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2004</td>
<td width="6%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2005</td>
<td width="6%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2006</td>
<td width="6%" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="29%" align="left" valign="bottom"> Dumbarton</td>
<td width="6%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 37</td>
<td width="6%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 41</td>
<td width="6%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 37</td>
<td width="6%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 37</td>
<td width="6%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 34</td>
<td width="6%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 33</td>
<td width="6%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 32</td>
<td width="6%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 31</td>
<td width="6%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 32</td>
<td width="6%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 37</td>
<td width="6%" align="right" valign="bottom"> 38</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Source: MIDAS (Management Information and Dental Accounting System).</p>

  <p>Notes:</p>

  <p>1. Includes non-salaried and salaried GDS dentists, assistants and vocational dental practitioners. Excludes dentists working in NHS hospitals and the Community Dental Service in Scotland.</p>

  <p>2. An NHS general dental practitioner may have more than one arrangement with an NHS board if he/she has more than one practice, or an arrangement with more than one NHS board if he/she practises in more than one NHS board area.</p>

  <p>3. The number of dentists in post, not the whole-time equivalent figure, as information on the working hours of each dentist in not collected.</p>

  <p>4. Based on location of dental practice.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.24.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80374" speakername="Gil Paterson (West of Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S3W-6463" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many NHS dentists worked in the Clydebank and Milngavie parliamentary constituency in each year from 1997 to 2007.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.24.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>The number of NHS dentists who provide General Dental Services in the Clydebank and Milngavie parliamentary constituency in each year from 1997 to 2007 is shown in the following table.</p>

  <p>Number of NHS Dentists<sup>1,2,3</sup> Providing General Dental Services in the Years Ending 31 March 1997-2007</p>

  <p><table width="50%" border="BORDER" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="33%" height="17" align="left" valign="bottom"> Parliamentary Constituency<sup>4</sup></td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1997</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1998</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1999</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2000</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2001</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2002</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2003</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2004</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2005</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2006</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="33%" height="3" align="left" valign="bottom"> Clydebank and Milngavie</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="right" valign="bottom"> 28</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="right" valign="bottom"> 29</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="right" valign="bottom"> 30</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="right" valign="bottom"> 30</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="right" valign="bottom"> 30</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="right" valign="bottom"> 30</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="right" valign="bottom"> 31</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="right" valign="bottom"> 29</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="right" valign="bottom"> 30</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="right" valign="bottom"> 32</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="right" valign="bottom"> 32</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Source: MIDAS (Management Information and Dental Accounting System).</p>

  <p>Notes:</p>

  <p>1. Includes non-salaried and salaried GDS dentists, assistants and vocational dental practitioners. Excludes dentists working in NHS hospitals and the Community Dental Service in Scotland.</p>

  <p>2. An NHS general dental practitioner may have more than one arrangement with an NHS board if he/she has more than one practice, or an arrangement with more than one NHS board if he/she practises in more than one NHS board area.</p>

  <p>3. The number of dentists in post, not the whole-time equivalent figure, as information on the working hours of each dentist is not collected.</p>

  <p>4. Based on location of dental practice.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.25.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80374" speakername="Gil Paterson (West of Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S3W-6464" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many NHS dentists worked in the Strathkelvin and Bearsden parliamentary constituency in each year from 1997 to 2007.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.25.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>The number of NHS dentists who provide General Dental Services in the Strathkelvin and Bearsden parliamentary constituency in each year from 1997 to 2007 is shown in the following table.</p>

  <p>Number of NHS Dentists<sup>1,2,3</sup> Providing General Dental Services in the Years Ending 31 March 1997-2007</p>

  <p><table width="50%" border="BORDER" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="33%" valign="bottom" height="3"> Parliamentary Constituency<sup>4</sup></td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1997</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1998</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1999</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2000</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2001</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2002</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2003</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2004</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2005</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2006</td>
<td width="6%" height="3" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="33%" height="17" align="left" valign="bottom"> Strathkelvin and Bearsden</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> 30</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> 30</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> 34</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> 34</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> 33</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> 35</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> 40</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> 47</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> 50</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> 51</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> 47</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Source: MIDAS (Management Information and Dental Accounting System).</p>

  <p>Notes:</p>

  <p>1. Includes non-salaried and salaried GDS dentists, assistants and vocational dental practitioners. Excludes dentists working in NHS hospitals and the Community Dental Service in Scotland.</p>

  <p>2. An NHS general dental practitioner may have more than one arrangement with an NHS board if he/she has more than one practice, or an arrangement with more than one NHS board if he/she practises in more than one NHS board area.</p>

  <p>3. The number of dentists in post, not the whole-time equivalent figure, as information on the working hours of each dentist is not collected.</p>

  <p>4. Based on location of dental practice.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.26.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80374" speakername="Gil Paterson (West of Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S3W-6465" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many salaried NHS dentists worked in the Dumbarton parliamentary constituency in each year from 1997 to 2007.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.26.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>The number of salaried dentists working in the Dumbarton parliamentary constituency in each year from 1997 to 2007 is shown in the following table.</p>

  <p>Number of Salaried NHS Dentists<sup>1,2</sup> Providing General Dental Services in the Years Ending 31 March 1997-2007</p>

  <p><table width="50%" border="BORDER" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="30%" height="17" align="left" valign="bottom"> Parliamentary Constituency<sup>3</sup></td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1997</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1998</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 1999</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2000</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2001</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2002</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2003</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2004</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2005</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2006</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom"> 2007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="30%" height="17" align="left" valign="bottom"> Dumbarton</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> -</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> 1</td>
<td width="6%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom"> 2</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Source: MIDAS (Management Information and Dental Accounting System).</p>

  <p>Notes:</p>

  <p>1. Excludes dentists working in NHS hospitals and the Community Dental Service in Scotland.</p>

  <p>2. The number of salaried dentists in post, not the whole-time equivalent figure, as information on the working hours of each salaried dentist is not collected.</p>

  <p>3. Based on location of dental practice.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.27.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80374" speakername="Gil Paterson (West of Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S3W-6466" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many salaried NHS dentists worked in the Clydebank and Milngavie parliamentary constituency in each year from 1997 to 2007.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.27.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>No salaried dentists worked in the Clydebank and Milngavie parliamentary constituency in the requested period.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.28.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80374" speakername="Gil Paterson (West of Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S3W-6467" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many salaried NHS dentists worked in the Strathkelvin and Bearsden parliamentary constituency in each year from 1997 to 2007.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.28.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#9">

  <p>No salaried dentists worked in the Strathkelvin and Bearsden parliamentary constituency in the requested period.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.29.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#10">Ferry Services</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.29.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80375" speakername="Peter Peacock (Highlands and Islands) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6279" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#10">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many car journeys were made on the (a) Ullapool to Stornoway and (b) Stornoway to Ullapool ferry routes during 2006.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.29.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#10">

  <p>During 2006, Caledonian MacBrayne Ltd carried 23,988 cars on its Ullapool to Stornoway service and 22,911 cars on its Stornoway to Ullapool service.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.30.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80354" speakername="Jamie McGrigor (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6384" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#10">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, in light of Scotland having been given approval to access a &pound;200 million budget of European funds in order to boost cross-border links with Ireland and Northern Ireland, whether the Executive will make efforts to secure funding from this source to re-establish the Campbeltown to Ballycastle ferry.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.30.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#10">

  <p>The Scottish Budget Spending Review 2007 which was announced on 14 November 2007 makes provision for subsidised ferry services in Scotland. I can confirm that an increase of &pound;37 million in the ferry services budget includes provision for a new service between Campbeltown and Ballycastle.</p>

  <p>Scottish Government and Northern Ireland Executive officials continue to liaise closely to discuss joint working arrangements for taking the project forward. Respective ministers in Scotland and Northern Ireland will be discussing matters shortly with a view to reaching agreement on the next steps to be taken. Further information will be made available as soon as practicable.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.31.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#11">Food</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.31.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80310" speakername="Ross Finnie (West of Scotland) (LD)" spid="S3W-6685" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#11">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what measures it intends to take to make healthy food more affordable.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.31.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#11">

  <p>The Scottish Government is considering how it can best improve the affordability, availability and awareness of healthier food options as part of wide-ranging discussions on a National Food Policy for Scotland.</p>

  <p>The 2007 Spending Review commits &pound;11.5 million per annum for the next three years to a programme on diet and physical activity for health and to prevent obesity.</p>

  <p>In the meantime, we are continuing to work with a variety of partners including Community Food and Health (Scotland) and the Scottish Grocers Federation to make it easier for people in low-income communities to buy healthier foods.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.32.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#12">General Practitioners</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.32.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80282" speakername="Alasdair Allan (Western Isles) (SNP)" spid="S3W-6598" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#12">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what descriptor it uses to establish the adequacy of medical staffing levels in GP practices in remote and rural settings, in light of the new contracts for such practices.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.32.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#12">

  <p>It is for health boards to ensure the quality of services from general practitioners. Boards must ensure that such services are available for all patients and the most common approach is to enter into contractual arrangements with doctors. It is for those who have agreed to provide services to ensure their practice is adequately staffed to meet the requirements of their contract with the health board.</p>

  <p>If services were not provided to an acceptable standard, regulations provide that a health board can take remedial action. In an extreme case a contract could be terminated.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.33.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#13">Health</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.33.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80394" speakername="David Stewart (Highlands and Islands) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6326" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#13">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what plans it has to review the criteria for qualification for entitlement to insulin pumps.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.33.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80396" speakername="Nicola Sturgeon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#13">

  <p>The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) is currently consulting on the terms of a multiple technology appraisal of continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion. This represents a review of its February 2003 Technology Appraisal Guidance No. 57 <em>Guidance on the use of continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion for the treatment of diabetes</em> , setting out the criteria with which NHS Boards are currently expected to comply.</p>

  <p>As is standard practice in these cases, NHS Quality Improvement Scotland (QIS) will consider the NICE appraisal in order to advise on whether there are any contextual differences between Scotland and England and Wales which should be taken into account in applying the multiple technology appraisal here.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.34.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80394" speakername="David Stewart (Highlands and Islands) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6327" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#13">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what analysis (a) has been carried out or (b) is planned on the effectiveness of insulin pumps as a treatment tool for insulin-dependent diabetes.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.34.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80396" speakername="Nicola Sturgeon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#13">

  <p>The most recent evidence on the effectiveness of insulin pumps as a treatment for those with Type 1 (insulin dependent) diabetes is contained in the appraisal consultation document currently available on the website of the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE).</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.35.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80394" speakername="David Stewart (Highlands and Islands) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6328" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#13">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the cost is of providing insulin pumps as a treatment tool for insulin-dependent diabetes and what percentage this represented of the Executive&rsquo;s health budget in each year since 2004.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.35.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80396" speakername="Nicola Sturgeon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#13">

  <p>The total cost of providing insulin pump therapy is around &pound;836,000 in the current financial year, assuming 200 patients on CSII, an average cost of &pound;2,500 per pump and consumables of &pound;1,680 a year per patient. The total NHS budget for the current financial year is &pound;10.254 billion.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.36.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80383" speakername="Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6345" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#13">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether the &pound;37 million to strengthen primary health care in the most deprived areas, as referred to in Scottish Budget: Spending Review 2007, will include remote and rural communities where deprivation is not localised.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.36.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#13">

  <p>This budget will be used to support anticipatory care programmes, targeted at chronic disease prevention, largely through primary health care programmes, which reach deprived individuals and communities. Such anticipatory care programmes will build on the experience of delivering Keep Well in areas of multiple deprivation.</p>

  <p>However, we are also planning to implement a programme, prepared by the North of Scotland Public Health Network, which addresses the anticipatory care needs of deprived people living in remote and rural areas.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.37.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80383" speakername="Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6417" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#13">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what screening programmes will benefit as a result of the increased funding outlined in the 2008-11 spending plans.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.37.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80383" speakername="Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6418" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#13">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it is considering introducing any new screening programmes in the NHS.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.37.q2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80292" speakername="Derek Brownlee (South of Scotland) (Con)" spid="S3W-6452" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#13">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what screening programmes are covered by the expenditure shown on page 56 of <em>Scottish Budget: Spending Review 2007</em> and why spending declines over the period of the spending review.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.37.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#13">

  <p>The cancer and pregnancy and newborn screening programmes will benefit from the increased funding outlined in the 2008-11 spending plans. In addition we expect to announce details of new screening programmes in due course.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.38.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#14">Hepatitis</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.38.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80383" speakername="Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6370" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#14">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive when the public inquiry into how people were infected with hepatitis C from contaminated blood products is due to commence.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.38.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#14">

  <p>I wish to wait until Lord Archer of Sandwell&rsquo;s independent inquiry into infection from blood and blood products in the 1970s and 1980s concludes and reports, before deciding what remains to be done. I will then be in a position to consider the legal framework, scope, remit and timing of the Scottish public inquiry.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.39.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#15">Higher Education</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.39.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80284" speakername="Richard Baker (North East Scotland) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6519" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#15">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it has conducted any research on how not providing the additional funding for universities requested by Universities Scotland may affect the performance of Scottish universities in the Research Assessment Exercise.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.39.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80330" speakername="Fiona Hyslop" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#15">

  <p>No such research has been conducted. The performance of Scottish universities in the current Research Assessment Exercise (RAE) will not be affected as the research activity which underpins RAE 2008 submissions will be completed before the start of the next Spending Review period.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.40.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80284" speakername="Richard Baker (North East Scotland) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6520" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#15">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it has conducted any research on how not providing the additional funding for universities requested by Universities Scotland may affect commercialisation of research.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.40.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80330" speakername="Fiona Hyslop" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#15">

  <p>No such research has been conducted. The allocation of funding for universities is a matter for the Scottish Funding Council. We will work closely with the Scottish Funding Council and the universities over the coming months to determine how our investment in higher education can be used most effectively across the full range of our priorities.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.41.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#16">Housing</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.41.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80383" speakername="Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6347" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#16">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what action it is taking to review planning guidance in relation to building new homes near high voltage overhead transmission lines.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.41.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#16">

  <p>The Stakeholder Advisory Group on Extremely Low Frequency Electromagnetic Fields (SAGE) published their <em>First Interim Assessment: Power Lines and Property, Wiring in Homes and Electrical Equipment in Homes</em> on 27 April 2007. The report of the Cross Party Inquiry into Childhood Leukaemia and Extremely Low Frequency Electric and Magnetic Fields was published in July of 2007. Both of these reports include consideration of how planning guidance might be used to control development near high voltage overhead powerlines.</p>

  <p>The Scottish Government will consider the content of these reports, including implications for planning guidance, in close liaison with colleagues in relevant UK Government Departments and devolved administrations.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.42.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#17">Mental Health</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.42.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80383" speakername="Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6419" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#17">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive why its budget for mental wellbeing remains at &pound;6.3 million until 2011.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.42.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#17">

  <p>The budget of &pound;6.3 million funds national activity in support of local delivery of objectives.</p>

  <p>Recent significant and sustained investment in mental wellbeing has allowed a strong momentum to build up across Scotland through the Scottish Government&rsquo;s national leadership and support. For example, this has included step changes in action on raising awareness of positive mental health and wellbeing, on promoting and supporting recovery from mental ill-health, on suicide prevention and on elimination of stigma and discrimination around mental illness.</p>

  <p>Our focus in Spending Review 2007 &ndash; and in <em>Towards a Mentally Flourishing Scotland</em>, our current discussion paper outlining the proposed future direction for mental health improvement and population mental health for 2008-11, is on a significant shift in emphasis from predominantly national support activity to local action. The budget which we announced recently for national-led work remains at a significant level and will allow continued progress on improving the mental health and wellbeing of all who live in Scotland; it is complemented by other government funding to NHS boards for mental health services and by government funding to charitable organisations which undertake national work in the mental health field. Government funding to local authorities for mental health has been rolled into local authorities&rsquo; total funding. We will work with local authorities and our other partners to ensure that mental health remains a priority.</p>

  <p>In addition, many activities that are funded through other budget lines, such as promotion of physical activity, healthy working lives, access to the arts and creativity, and community regeneration, also incorporate aspects that can contribute to improved mental wellbeing.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.43.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#18">Ministerial Correspondence</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.43.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80367" speakername="Mary Mulligan (Linlithgow) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6335" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#18">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive when I can expect a reply from the Minister for Transport, Infrastructure and Climate Change to my letter of 25 October 2007 asking when an announcement on a Blackridge Station will be made.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.43.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#18">

  <p>A response to your letter was issued on 20 November 2007.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.44.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#19">NHS Waiting Times</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.44.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80383" speakername="Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6415" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#19">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, in relation to its 2008-11 spending plans, how the &pound;90 million increase to the Waiting Times Co-ordination Unit will be allocated.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.44.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80396" speakername="Nicola Sturgeon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#19">

  <p>This funding will help ensure delivery of our commitment to a maximum referral to treatment waiting time of 18 weeks by the end of 2011. It will be invested in a number of programmes to increase capacity for NHS patients, modernise systems and processes within NHS boards, and redesign services to streamline the patient&rsquo;s journey through the NHS.</p>

  <p>The primary and community care sectors will also play an important role through developing alternatives to hospital admissions, providing care closer to patients and by working in partnership to optimise the responsiveness and effectiveness of care arrangements.</p>

  <p>Investment will be made against a background of securing greater efficiency and productivity across the NHS and its partner organisations, and of encouraging innovative, high-quality and sustainable solutions.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.45.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80321" speakername="Christine Grahame (South of Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S3W-6732" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#19">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the average waiting time has been for a first appointment with a psychologist from referral in each year since 1999, broken down by NHS board area.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.45.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#19">

  <p>This information is not held centrally.</p>

  <p>We are working to improve the availability of mental health information through the NHS Scotland National Benchmarking Project.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.46.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#20">Road Accidents</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.46.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80317" speakername="Marlyn Glen (North East Scotland) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6394" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#20">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many breathalyser tests were administered in (a) Dundee and (b) Angus following road accidents in each year since 1997 and what percentage of these were recorded as failed.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.46.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#20">

  <p>Data about injury road accidents are collected by the police and reported to the Scottish Executive using the STATS 19 statistical report form. These returns cover only road accidents in which one or more people were injured and which become known to the police. The returns do not cover damage only accidents or accidents of which the police are unaware because they were not reported by the public.</p>

  <p>The following table gives the number of reported injury road accidents which were identified in the STATS 19 returns occurring within (a) Dundee and (b) Angus Council areas since 1997 where a breathalyser test was administered with positive/refused and negative readings and the percentage of the total which failed.</p>

  <p>It should be noted that as well as drivers and riders of motor vehicles, the figures also include a small number of cases where pedal cyclists or horse riders were breath tested.</p>

  <p>(a) Dundee</p>

  <p><table width="50%" border="BORDER" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="center" valign="top"> Year</td>
<td width="18%" align="center" valign="top"> Positive or Refused</td>
<td width="16%" align="center" valign="top"> Negative</td>
<td width="26%" align="center" valign="top"> Drivers or Riders Breath-Tested</td>
<td width="29%" align="center" valign="top"> Positive or Refused % of Breath-Tested</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 1997</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 17</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 496</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 513</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.3%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 1998</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 16</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 469</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 485</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.3%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 1999</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 16</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 490</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 506</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.2%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 2000</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 12</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 524</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 536</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 2.2%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 2001</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 9</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 541</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 550</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 1.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 2002</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 8</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 481</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 489</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 1.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 2003</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 15</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 424</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 439</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.4%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 2004</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 11</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 408</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 419</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 2.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 2005</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 9</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 342</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 351</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 2.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 2006</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 20</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 430</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 450</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 4.4%</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>(b) Angus</p>

  <p><table width="50%" border="BORDER" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="center" valign="top"> Year</td>
<td width="18%" align="center" valign="top"> Positive or Refused</td>
<td width="16%" align="center" valign="top"> Negative</td>
<td width="26%" align="center" valign="top"> Drivers or Riders Breath-Tested</td>
<td width="29%" align="center" valign="top"> Positive or Refused % of Breath-Tested</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 1997</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 17</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 483</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 500</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.4%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 1998</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 11</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 484</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 495</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 2.2%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 1999</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 18</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 422</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 440</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 4.1%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 2000</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 10</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 447</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 457</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 2.2%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 2001</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 13</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 416</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 429</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 2002</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 25</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 436</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 461</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 5.4%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 2003</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 11</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 350</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 361</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.1%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 2004</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 7</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 427</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 434</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 1.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 2005</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 15</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 391</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 406</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.7%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="11%" align="left" valign="top"> 2006</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="top"> 12</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 351</td>
<td width="26%" align="right" valign="top"> 363</td>
<td width="29%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.3%</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.47.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80317" speakername="Marlyn Glen (North East Scotland) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6395" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#20">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what percentage of breathalyser tests administered following road accidents in each year since 1997 were recorded as failed.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.47.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#20">

  <p>Data about injury road accidents are collected by the police and reported to the Scottish Executive using the STATS 19 statistical report form. These returns cover only road accidents in which one or more people were injured and which become known to the police. The returns do not cover damage only accidents or accidents of which the police are unaware because they were not reported by the public.</p>

  <p>The following table gives the number of reported injury road accidents which were identified in the STATS 19 returns occurring on Scottish roads since 1997 where a breathalyser test was administered with positive/refused and negative readings and the percentage of the total which failed.</p>

  <p>It should be noted that as well as drivers and riders of motor vehicles, the figures also include a small number of cases where pedal cyclists or horse riders were breath tested.</p>

  <p><table width="50%" border="BORDER" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="9%" align="center" valign="top"> Year</td>
<td width="19%" align="center" valign="top"> Positive or Refused</td>
<td width="16%" align="center" valign="top"> Negative</td>
<td width="25%" align="center" valign="top"> Drivers or Riders Breath-Tested</td>
<td width="31%" align="center" valign="top"> Positive or Refused % of Breath-Tested</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="9%" align="left" valign="top"> 1997</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top"> 587</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 17,750</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top"> 18,337</td>
<td width="31%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.2%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="9%" align="left" valign="top"> 1998</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top"> 549</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 17,650</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top"> 18,199</td>
<td width="31%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="9%" align="left" valign="top"> 1999</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top"> 515</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 16,200</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top"> 16,715</td>
<td width="31%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.1%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="9%" align="left" valign="top"> 2000</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top"> 530</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 15,537</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top"> 16,067</td>
<td width="31%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.3%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="9%" align="left" valign="top"> 2001</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top"> 511</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 14,782</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top"> 15,293</td>
<td width="31%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.5%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="9%" align="left" valign="top"> 2002</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top"> 512</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 14,239</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top"> 14,751</td>
<td width="31%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="9%" align="left" valign="top"> 2003</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top"> 504</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 13,474</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top"> 13,978</td>
<td width="31%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="9%" align="left" valign="top"> 2004</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top"> 487</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 13,220</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top"> 13,707</td>
<td width="31%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="9%" align="left" valign="top"> 2005</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top"> 475</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 12,174</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top"> 12,649</td>
<td width="31%" align="right" valign="top"> 3.8%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="9%" height="25" align="left" valign="top"> 2006</td>
<td width="19%" align="right" valign="top"> 511</td>
<td width="16%" align="right" valign="top"> 12,132</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top"> 12,643</td>
<td width="31%" align="right" valign="top"> 4.0%</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.48.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">Roads</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.48.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80354" speakername="Jamie McGrigor (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6216" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what action has been taken to implement the recommendations of the Scottish Road Network Landslides Study, published in 2005.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.48.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>The main recommendation of the 2005 report was that more extensive research should be undertaken to develop and implement a methodology for the assessment of landslide hazards, the exposure to road users and the resulting hazard rankings. This work is detailed, highly complex and time consuming. However, it is progressing well and will allow us to predict in the future where landslips are most likely to occur, prioritising areas for further site specific investigation and strategies to minimise the impact of future landslips.</p>

  <p>Other recommendations identified as Early Opportunities in the 2005 report have since been implemented and evidence of actions taken can be observed on the network.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.49.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80354" speakername="Jamie McGrigor (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6217" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what financial support is available to tackle possible landslides that would cause road closures and where such money has been spent since 2003.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.49.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>Transport Scotland manages landslip risks on the trunk road network within its existing roads maintenance budgets and without any external financial support. As landslips are unpredictable modifications are made within existing budgets and programmes to accommodate this expenditure.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.50.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80354" speakername="Jamie McGrigor (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6292" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive when the A83 will reopen as normal.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.50.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>The A83 reopened to traffic at 1600hrs on Wednesday 14 November 2007, and traffic is restricted to single file for a short distance under the control of temporary traffic lights. The traffic lights will remain in place until further investigations and measures are implemented to ensure the continued safety of the road and traffic.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.51.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80354" speakername="Jamie McGrigor (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6293" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what assessment it has made of losses incurred by businesses in Argyll and Bute as a result of the closure of the A83.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.51.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>None.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.52.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80354" speakername="Jamie McGrigor (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6294" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what contingency plans it is making in the event of further landslides causing the closure of the A83.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.52.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>Transport Scotland has held discussions with a broad range of authorities, including the emergency services, and will be considering a number of strategies to minimise the effect of any future landslips on the A83.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.53.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80354" speakername="Jamie McGrigor (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6295" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what plans it has to upgrade the A82 and whether any such plans will be brought forward in light of the closure of the A83.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.53.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>The A82 Route Action Plan announced in April 2006 outlined a 10 year improvement programme at an estimated cost of &pound;90 million which will be considered for future investment as part of the Strategic Transport Projects Review which is due to report to ministers in summer 2008.</p>

  <p>Transport Scotland is currently planning to take forward some &pound;16 million of improvements from the Route Action Plan to improve safety and speed up journey times for local communities, tourists and business. This includes improvement work at Pulpit Rock and a bypass for Crianlarich which we aim to deliver within the current programme to 2012.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.54.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80342" speakername="Lewis Macdonald (Aberdeen Central) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6316" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it supports the construction of a new road to connect Aberdeen airport to the A96 at its intended junction with the Aberdeen western peripheral route.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.54.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>The design of the proposed junction of the A96 and the Aberdeen Western Peripheral Route makes provision for a new road connecting with the Dyce industrial area and Aberdeen Airport. The funding and construction of this road will be for others.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.55.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80394" speakername="David Stewart (Highlands and Islands) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6329" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what recent discussions have been held with Moray Council about the development of the Elgin bypass.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.55.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>Transport Scotland works in close and continuous collaboration with Moray Council officials to identify alternative short and medium term traffic management solutions for Elgin&rsquo;s traffic problems along the route of the A96 trunk road through Elgin.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.56.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80394" speakername="David Stewart (Highlands and Islands) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6330" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what timescale is planned for the construction of the Elgin bypass.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.56.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>I refer the member to the answer to question S3W-231 on 11 June 2007. All answers to written parliamentary questions are available on the Parliament's website, the search facility for which can be found at <a href="../../../webapp/wa.search">http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/webapp/wa.search</a> .</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.57.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80383" speakername="Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6343" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what improvement initiatives are planned for the A9 and A96, as referred to in <em>Scottish Budget: Spending Review 2007</em> .</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.57.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>In our current trunk road investment programme to 2012 we plan to deliver over a dozen improvement schemes on the A9 and the A96 which will improve safety, provide additional overtaking opportunities and help to reduce platooning and driver frustration.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.58.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80368" speakername="John Farquhar Munro (Ross, Skye and Inverness West) (LD)" spid="S3W-6360" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what plans it has to improve the Kessock roundabout on the A9 and what the timescale is for any such plans.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.58.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#21">

  <p>Transport Scotland instructed Scotland TranServ to conduct a study into the capacity of the Longman roundabout, south of Kessock Bridge, and a draft report was received in October 2007. The study examined the existing and future traffic flows and the capacity of the existing layout, and proposed an engineering solution to reduce peak hour congestion on a phased basis.</p>

  <p>Transport Scotland will now review the draft report and discuss the outcome with Scotland TranServ by the end of December 2007. The preferred solution will require to be prioritised against other competing schemes within the overall trunk road improvement plan.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.59.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#22">Scottish Government Expenditure</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.59.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80310" speakername="Ross Finnie (West of Scotland) (LD)" spid="S3W-6542" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#22">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the changes are from the 2007-08 baseline for each proposed budget line at levels (a) one, (b) two and (c) three of the Health and Wellbeing portfolio resulting from Scottish Budget: Spending Review 2007, expressed in real (i) cash and (ii) percentage terms for each year of the spending review.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.59.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80396" speakername="Nicola Sturgeon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#22">

  <p>The information requested for levels one and two is given in Draft Budget 2008-09: Real Terms Analysis, a copy of which has been placed in the Scottish Parliament Information Centre (Bib. number 44133.)</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.60.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80383" speakername="Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S3W-6546" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#22">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how it can meet the SNP manifesto commitment to abolish sportscotland, given the increase in its budget from &pound;34.3 million to &pound;43.3 million by 2011, as referred to in Scottish Budget: Spending Review 2007.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.60.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#22">

  <p>The Cabinet Secretary for Finance and Sustainable Growth announced in the 2007 Strategic Spending Review on 14 November 2007 that the baseline funding for sport will increase by 25% over the period 2008-11. While the future of sportscotland is currently under consideration, its core functions will continue to be delivered in any future arrangements and our commitment to an increase in the baseline funding for sport will remain.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.61.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#23">Scottish Government Funding</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.61.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80313" speakername="Murdo Fraser (Mid Scotland and Fife) (Con)" spid="S3W-6390" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#23">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how much it has paid to LGBT Youth Scotland in each year since 1999.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.61.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#23">

  <p>The Scottish Executive has not given core funding to LGBT Youth Scotland, nor does it fund campaigning activity. Grant Funding awarded to LGBT Youth Scotland has been time limited project funding for specific pieces of work relating mainly to community engagement and capacity building and services for young people.</p>

  <p>The grant funding awarded to LGBT Youth Scotland in each year since 1999 is as follows:</p>

  <p><table width="25%" border="BORDER" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="35%" align="center" valign="top"> Year</td>
<td width="65%" align="center" valign="top"> LGBT Youth Scotland</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="35%" align="left" valign="top"> 1999-2000</td>
<td width="65%" align="right" valign="top"> Nil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="35%" align="left" valign="top"> 2000-01</td>
<td width="65%" align="right" valign="top"> Nil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="35%" align="left" valign="top"> 2001-02</td>
<td width="65%" align="right" valign="top"> Nil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="35%" align="left" valign="top"> 2002-03</td>
<td width="65%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;12,000.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="35%" align="left" valign="top"> 2003-04</td>
<td width="65%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;23,500.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="35%" align="left" valign="top"> 2004&ndash;05</td>
<td width="65%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;129,950.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="35%" align="left" valign="top"> 2005&ndash;06</td>
<td width="65%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;181,715.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="35%" align="left" valign="top"> 2006&ndash;07</td>
<td width="65%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;280,277</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="35%" align="left" valign="top"> Total</td>
<td width="65%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;627,442</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.62.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80284" speakername="Richard Baker (North East Scotland) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6521" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#23">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what consultation was carried out with trade unions prior to its decision not to provide the additional funding for universities requested by Universities Scotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.62.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80330" speakername="Fiona Hyslop" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#23">

  <p>In the lead up to the strategic spending review the government held meetings with the University and College Union and the Scottish TUC. University funding was covered at these meetings within a wider range of topics. The government also carefully considered spending review advice from the University and College Union.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.63.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80284" speakername="Richard Baker (North East Scotland) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6522" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#23">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the funding for Scottish universities is relative to that of universities in England as a result of Scottish Budget: Spending Review 2007.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.63.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80330" speakername="Fiona Hyslop" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#23">

  <p>The Department for Innovation, Universities and Skills has not yet published specific spending plans for universities over the period of the 2007 spending review.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.64.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80348" speakername="Michael Matheson (Falkirk West) (SNP)" spid="S3W-6691" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#23">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how much funding was allocated to each local authority in each of the last two years to assist with the introduction of the Mental Health (Care and Treatment) (Scotland) Act 2003 and how much will be allocated in the next financial year.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.64.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#23">

  <p>The Scottish Executive increased the block grant to local authorities by &pound;13 million over each of the last two years 2006-07 and 2007-08 in relation to the implementation of the Mental Health (Care and Treatment) (Scotland) Act 2003. It should be noted that as this sum was added to the block grant it is not possible to say how much each individual local authority was allocated.</p>

  <p>The Scottish Government will be providing local government in Scotland with record levels of funding over the period covered by the spending review 2008-11. The vast majority of the funding, including any funding for mental health funding, will be provided by means of a block grant. It is the responsibility of each local authority to allocate the total financial resources available to it on the basis of local needs and priorities having first fulfilled its statutory obligations and the jointly agreed set of national and local priorities including the Scottish Government&rsquo;s key strategic objectives and manifesto commitments.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.65.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80348" speakername="Michael Matheson (Falkirk West) (SNP)" spid="S3W-6692" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#23">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how much funding was allocated to each local authority in each of the last five years for implementation of the carers strategy and how much will be allocated in the next financial year.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.65.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#23">

  <p>In the past, local authorities were allocated funding for carers support as part of the annual local government finance settlement. It was for each authority to determine the level of funding it allocated to each activity, in accordance with local priorities. Details of each authority&rsquo;s service level Grant Aided Expenditure allocations (which were used to distribute the funding) up to 2007-08 are published on the Scottish Government&rsquo;s website at: <a href="http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Topics/Statistics/18209/12073" target="_blank">www.scotland.gov.uk/Topics/Statistics/18209/12073</a> .</p>

  <p>The Scottish Government will be providing local government in Scotland with record levels of funding over the period covered by the spending review 2008-11. The vast majority of the funding, including the funding for carers<em>,</em> will be provided by means of a block grant. It is the responsibility of each local authority to allocate the total financial resources available to it on the basis of local needs and priorities having first fulfilled its statutory obligations and the jointly agreed set of national and local priorities including the Scottish Government&rsquo;s key strategic objectives and manifesto commitments.</p>

  <p>The joint Concordat between the Scottish Government and the Convention of Scottish Local Authorities includes a commitment to progress towards delivering an extra 10,000 respite weeks per annum.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.66.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#24">Sexual Abuse</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.66.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80283" speakername="Jackie Baillie (Dumbarton) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6412" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#24">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will provide an update on the progress being made by the Adult Survivors of Childhood Sexual Abuse Reference Group.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.66.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#24">

  <p>The first year&rsquo;s achievements of the National Strategy for Adult Survivors of Childhood Sexual Abuse Reference Group were presented at a major national conference, the first of its kind in Scotland, in February 2007. Since then the group has worked with the Scottish Government to progress a number of actions including:</p>

  <p>Development - and announcement on 1 November 2007 &ndash; of the SurvivorScotland website to improve the lives of survivors with access to a wide range of data, training and good practice examples.</p>

  <p>Award of &pound;1.7 million Service Development Fund to 25 statutory and voluntary organisations to develop a range of services for survivors.</p>

  <p>The conference report and further details of progress on the strategy is provided at <a href="http://www.survivorscotland.org.uk" target="_blank">www.survivorscotland.org.uk</a>. Awareness raising and public education are key issues now being addressed by the group&rsquo;s focus on a communications campaign.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.67.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">Sport</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.67.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80284" speakername="Richard Baker (North East Scotland) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6251" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether the Grampian Institute for Sport will receive additional funding and technical support for developing world-class athletes in the north east.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.67.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>It will be the responsibility of sportscotland to determine if additional funding and technical support is required.</p>

  <p>However it should be noted that the review of sportscotland currently underway involves examining whether sportscotland&rsquo;s current functions continue to be necessary and, if so, which organisational arrangements are most effective in delivering them. The review will also inform decisions regarding the future of sportscotland and the roles of the Scottish Institute of Sport and the Area Institutes.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.68.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80338" speakername="Johann Lamont (Glasgow Pollok) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6388" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, further to the answer to question S3W-6091 by Stewart Maxwell on 14 November 2007, whether copies of the correspondence with all those from whom he has sought views on the future of sportscotland will be published.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.68.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>I refer the member to the answer to question S3W-6094 on 14 November 2007, when I advised that it would not be appropriate to release copies of correspondence received from stakeholders whilst the review of sportscotland is still actively under consideration.</p>

  <p>All answers to written parliamentary questions are available on the Parliament&rsquo;s website, the search facility for which can be found at <a href="../../../webapp/wa.search">http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/webapp/wa.search</a>.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.69.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80308" speakername="Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6421" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive with which organisations it has engaged about its proposals for sportscotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.69.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>The following bodies have been formally invited to submit their views:</p>

  <p>Sportscotland</p>

  <p>Scottish Institute of Sport</p>

  <p>Scottish Cycling</p>

  <p>Scottish Gymnastics</p>

  <p>Scottish Swimming</p>

  <p>Badminton Scotland</p>

  <p>Judo Scotland</p>

  <p>COSLA</p>

  <p>VOCAL</p>

  <p>Scottish Athletics</p>

  <p>Scottish Sport Association</p>

  <p>Scottish Institute of Sport Foundation</p>

  <p>Scottish Golf Union</p>

  <p>Scottish Rugby Union</p>

  <p>Scottish Football Association</p>

  <p>Scottish University of Sport</p>

  <p>The Health and Sport Committee of the Scottish Parliament.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.70.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80308" speakername="Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6422" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive with which individuals it has engaged about its proposals for sportscotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.70.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>The Scottish Government has held a series of meetings with the chair and senior staff of sportscotland, the executive director of the Scottish Institute of Sport, staff from the Welsh Assembly Government, representatives of the Scottish Sports Association, representatives of the Scottish Association of Local Sports Councils, senior officials from COSLA and VOCAL, representatives of two sport governing bodies, and individuals working at local authority level.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.71.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80308" speakername="Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6423" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive why it chose not to conduct a formal consultation exercise on its proposals for sportscotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.71.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>The review of sportscotland has been undertaken as part of our approach to simplify Scotland&rsquo;s public service landscape. By getting rid of duplication, simplifying structures and stopping activities that do not contribute to the government&rsquo;s objectives, we will be freeing up Scotland&rsquo;s public servants to provide the services people need.</p>

  <p>The terms of reference for the review of sportscotland were set to &quot;examine whether sportscotland&rsquo;s current functions continue to be necessary and, if so, which organisational arrangements are most effective in delivering them<em>.</em>&quot; Consultation has been undertaken with the key stakeholders to ensure those at the centre of the delivery of sport, were able to input into the consideration of which organisational arrangements will be most effective in securing the future delivery of sport.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.72.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80308" speakername="Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6424" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what action it has taken to encourage individuals and organisations to engage with its review of sportscotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.72.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>I am very conscious that the final decision on the future of sportscotland will have an enormous impact on the lives and future of the staff at sportscotland. It is therefore crucial that the consultation process is completed quickly and efficiently with a view to announcing the result before the end of the year. I continue to meet and discuss this review with the key stakeholders and encourage their views and responses which will be given the fullest consideration that is possible, at the time they are received.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.73.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80308" speakername="Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6425" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will provide a detailed explanation as to the criteria used to select those individuals and organisations with whom it has engaged in its review of sportscotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.73.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>All of the principal organisations that represent sports interests in Scotland have been formally consulted. The governing bodies of several major sports were also consulted on an individual basis. Officials have met with a range of organisations and individuals who specifically requested meetings or who were suggested by key consultees.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.74.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80308" speakername="Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6426" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive which organisations it has met specifically to discuss its review of sportscotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.74.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>Scottish Government ministers or officials have met with the following organisations to discuss the review of sportscotland:</p>

  <p>Sportscotland</p>

  <p>Scottish Institute of Sport</p>

  <p>COSLA</p>

  <p>VOCAL</p>

  <p>Scottish Sports Association</p>

  <p>Scottish Institute of Sport Foundation</p>

  <p>Scottish Association of Local Sports Councils</p>

  <p>Scottish Hockey</p>

  <p>Scottish Rugby.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.75.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80308" speakername="Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6427" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what criteria it is using to assess the future of sportscotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.75.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>The Scottish Government has set terms of reference for the review of sportscotland as follows: &quot;to examine whether sportscotland&rsquo;s current functions continue to be necessary and, if so, which organisational arrangements are most effective in delivering them.&quot;</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.76.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80308" speakername="Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6428" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what factors it will consider in its review of sportscotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.76.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>The Scottish Government will consider whether sportscotland&rsquo;s current functions continue to be necessary and, if so, which organisational arrangements are most effective in delivering them. The needs of sport will be central to the review process.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.77.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80308" speakername="Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6429" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether Glasgow&rsquo;s successful bid for the 2014 Commonwealth Games bid will influence its decision on the future of sportscotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.77.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>The needs of sport are central to the Scottish Government&rsquo;s decisions on the future of sportscotland.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.78.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80308" speakername="Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6430" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, further to the answer to question S3W-6015 by Stewart Maxwell on 14 November 2007, what options are being considered in relation to the disbursement of lottery funding for sport if it abolishes sportscotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.78.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>The Scottish Government is committed to ensuring that lottery funding for sport remains accessible. It is the intention that a decision on the future of sportscotland will be announced before the end of the year.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.79.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80308" speakername="Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6431" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, further to the answer to question S3W-6016 by Stewart Maxwell on 14 November 2007, whether it is committed to the continued existence of the Scottish Institute of Sport.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.79.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>I refer the member to the answer to question S3W-6016 on 14 November 2007. All answers to written parliamentary questions are available on the Parliament's website, the search facility for which can be found at <a href="../../../webapp/wa.search">http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/webapp/wa.search</a> .</p>

  <p>We fully acknowledge the key delivery role the Scottish Institute of Sport plays within the sporting landscape. Until the outcome of the review of sportscotland has been made we cannot comment on what impact any decision will have.</p>

  <p>We are committed to improving sport in Scotland and it is not our intention to make any decision that will impact negatively on sport.</p>

</reply>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.80.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80308" speakername="Patricia Ferguson (Glasgow Maryhill) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6487" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, further to the answer to question S3W-6013 by Stewart Maxwell on 14 November 2007, when it will publish the responses received from key stakeholders in relation to the future of sportscotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.80.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80349" speakername="Stewart Maxwell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#25">

  <p>The review of sportscotland is not a public consultation and the question of publication of responses has not been discussed with stakeholders. We will however invite those who have responded to consent to their responses being published, with a view to publication once the outcome of the review has been announced.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.81.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#26">Student Finance</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.81.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80327" speakername="Hugh Henry (Paisley South) (Lab)" spid="S3W-6357" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#26">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it has the legal capacity to assume financial responsibility for servicing student debt owned by third parties.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-11-26.81.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80330" speakername="Fiona Hyslop" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa1126.htm#26">

  <p>Questions of legal capacity are for the courts and it would not be the intention of the government to assume such financial responsibility without first satisfying itself that it has the necessary legal capacity.</p>

</reply>
</publicwhip>