<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE publicwhip [

<!ENTITY pound   "&#163;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">

<!ENTITY agrave  "&#224;">
<!ENTITY aacute  "&#225;">
<!ENTITY egrave  "&#232;">
<!ENTITY eacute  "&#233;">
<!ENTITY ecirc   "&#234;">
<!ENTITY iacute  "&#237;">
<!ENTITY ograve  "&#242;">
<!ENTITY oacute  "&#243;">
<!ENTITY uacute  "&#250;">
<!ENTITY Aacute  "&#193;">
<!ENTITY Eacute  "&#201;">
<!ENTITY Iacute  "&#205;">
<!ENTITY Oacute  "&#211;">
<!ENTITY Uacute  "&#218;">
<!ENTITY Uuml    "&#220;">
<!ENTITY auml    "&#228;">
<!ENTITY euml    "&#235;">
<!ENTITY iuml    "&#239;">
<!ENTITY ouml    "&#246;">
<!ENTITY uuml    "&#252;">
<!ENTITY fnof    "&#402;">
<!ENTITY aelig   "&#230;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">
<!ENTITY reg     "&#174;">
<!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
<!ENTITY shy     "&#173;">
<!ENTITY deg     "&#176;">
<!ENTITY middot  "&#183;">
<!ENTITY ordm    "&#186;">
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY hellip  "&#8230;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">

<!ENTITY acirc   "&#226;">
<!ENTITY Agrave  "&#192;">
<!ENTITY Aring   "&#197;">
<!ENTITY aring   "&#229;">
<!ENTITY atilde  "&#227;">
<!ENTITY Ccedil  "&#199;">
<!ENTITY ccedil  "&#231;">
<!ENTITY Egrave  "&#200;">
<!ENTITY Icirc   "&#206;">
<!ENTITY icirc   "&#238;">
<!ENTITY Igrave  "&#204;">
<!ENTITY igrave  "&#236;">
<!ENTITY ntilde  "&#241;">
<!ENTITY ocirc   "&#244;">
<!ENTITY oelig   "&#339;">
<!ENTITY Ograve  "&#210;">
<!ENTITY Oslash  "&#216;">
<!ENTITY oslash  "&#248;">
<!ENTITY Scaron  "&#352;">
<!ENTITY scaron  "&#353;">
<!ENTITY sup1    "&#185;">
<!ENTITY sup2    "&#178;">
<!ENTITY sup3    "&#179;">
<!ENTITY ugrave  "&#249;">
<!ENTITY Ugrave  "&#217;">
<!ENTITY yacute  "&#253;">
<!ENTITY frac12  "&#189;">
<!ENTITY micro   "&#181;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8225;">
]>

<publicwhip>

<source url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm"/>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.0.mh" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm">Written Answers Wednesday 19 September 2007</major-heading>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.1.mh" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm">Scottish Executive</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.2.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#1">Constitution</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.2.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80314" speakername="Rob Gibson (Highlands and Islands) (SNP)" spid="S3W-3886" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#1">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many meetings have taken place since May 2007 between its Enterprise, Energy and Tourism Directorate and the UK Department for Business, Enterprise and Regulatory Reform or its predecessor regarding the devolution of further powers for the Scottish Parliament under UK marine legislation.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.2.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#1">

  <p>The Enterprise, Energy and Tourism Directorate has not taken part in any such meetings. However, there is regular dialogue between officials in the Marine Directorate and a variety of UK Government Departments in relation to marine issues. The Marine Directorate takes into account enterprise, energy and tourism issues in such dialogue and liaises with relevant officials.</p>

  <p>In relation to the UK Marine Bill, officials from the Marine Directorate attend Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs&rsquo; steering group which consists of officials from UK departments and the devolved administrations, including the UK Department for Business, Enterprise and Regulatory Reform. This group has considered the proposals for UK marine legislation and the implications for Scotland, including the potential for further devolution.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.3.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#2">Domestic Abuse</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.3.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80338" speakername="Johann Lamont (Glasgow Pollok) (Lab)" spid="S3W-3782" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#2">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive when it will confirm the future of the Glasgow Domestic Abuse Court and the Assist support service.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.3.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80338" speakername="Johann Lamont (Glasgow Pollok) (Lab)" spid="S3W-3783" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#2">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what plans it has to roll out the Domestic Abuse Court and Assist support service pilot to the rest of Glasgow.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.3.q2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80338" speakername="Johann Lamont (Glasgow Pollok) (Lab)" spid="S3W-3784" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#2">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive when it will outline its proposals for domestic abuse courts beyond Glasgow.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.3.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80341" speakername="Kenny MacAskill" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#2">

  <p>I refer the member to the answer to question S3W-1296 on 16 July 2007. All answers to written parliamentary questions are available on the Parliament&rsquo;s website, the search facility for which can be found at <a href="../../../webapp/wa.search">http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/webapp/wa.search</a> .</p>

  <p>I set out then the various factors I would take into account in reaching a view about how the Scottish Government can best support the courts in dealing with domestic abuse cases. I reaffirmed our commitment to developing a range of complementary and mutually supportive measures, within and beyond the justice system, for combating domestic abuse.</p>

  <p>Domestic abuse is a serious crime. The Scottish Government will uphold a zero tolerance policy towards it. Our criminal justice partners are firmly committed to investigating all allegations of domestic abuse and to bringing all appropriate cases before the courts. We already have a powerful framework of national policy and operational guidance in place for the pursuit of this crime.</p>

  <p>I have carefully considered the evaluation of the domestic abuse pilot court in Glasgow, which was published in the spring. The court has clearly brought benefits to victims and families. Yet the research does not recommend replication of the pilot model across Scotland: it proposes that local solutions should be developed to meet local needs. To this end I propose to take two specific actions.</p>

  <p>First, I want to extend our thinking about the range of options for handling domestic abuse cases from the point they enter court until disposal. We will prepare, consult upon and publish a guide to research and practice across Scotland. We will put this at the disposal of sheriffs principal and local criminal justice boards in order to support self-assessment and innovation at local level. I do not expect to see specialist domestic abuse courts in all parts of the country. I do expect to see criminal justice partners in each area examining their own practice and pursuing new approaches where appropriate.</p>

  <p>Secondly, I will take practical steps to further the aim of the sheriff principal for Glasgow and Strathkelvin to ensure the vigorous and sensitive handling of domestic abuse cases across the city. The current pilot only serves cases arising in G Division of Strathclyde Police. There is a need for new capacity to deal with the heavy caseload arising across Glasgow. My officials will convene a short-life working group with relevant interests including the police, Glasgow City Social Work Department and providers of victim support services. I have asked for a report by January 2008 to enable me to decide how the Scottish Government can best support a domestic abuse court serving the whole of Glasgow. This is not simply a matter of extending the work of the current pilot. We will need to develop a new and cost-effective model, including for the provision of support services to victims and witnesses and family members, that is sustainable in the longer term.</p>

  <p>In addition, I am keen to use the opportunities of summary justice reform to improve the handling of domestic abuse cases right across the country and irrespective of whether there is a specialist court. Many of the efficiency gains reported in the evaluation of the Glasgow pilot should be attainable across the board as we implement changes to streamline summary business and move cases more quickly through the system.</p>

  <p>To provide continuity during the transitional period whilst the Glasgow feasibility study is underway, the government will extend until the end of March 2008 the funding provided to the pilot specialist court.</p>

  <p>These initiatives are part of the Scottish Government&rsquo;s wider programme of work to combat domestic abuse. We will make further announcements on this in due course.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.4.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#3">E.Coli</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.4.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80295" speakername="Jackson Carlaw (West of Scotland) (Con)" spid="S3W-4112" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#3">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, in light of the recent outbreak of E. coli O157 in Paisley, what plans it has to reduce the likelihood of similar incidents of food poisoning across Scotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.4.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#3">

  <p>An expert group, under the Chairmanship of Professor Hugh Pennington, was established in December 1996 to examine the circumstances which led to the e.coli outbreak in central Scotland and to advise on the implications for food safety and lessons to be learned. This group made a total of 32 recommendations, all of which were accepted and actioned by the Scottish Government.</p>

  <p>The group&rsquo;s recommendations focussed mainly on improving hygiene standards and strengthening enforcement controls in fresh meat plants and butcher shops. There were also recommendations around consumer education and awareness, improving surveillance methods, research and outbreak management.</p>

  <p>A leaflet entitled <em>Shedding Light on Ecoli 0157 &ndash; What you need to know</em> was produced by the Scottish Government in 2005 to raise awareness and give advice to those visiting the outdoors and enjoying outdoor activities such as farms and petting zoos. The document is available electronically on the dedicated website <a href="http://www.handsclean.info/" target="_blank">www.handsclean.info/ </a>and is distributed once a year to a range of interested parties such as Directors of Public Health, Scouts and Girl Guides and outdoor organisations.</p>

  <p>The Scottish Government also continues to promote a Hand Hygiene Campaign to ensure that all health workers, the general public and young children are made aware of the importance of good hand washing in preventing the spread of infection.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.5.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#4">Employment</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.5.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80292" speakername="Derek Brownlee (South of Scotland) (Con)" spid="S3W-2665" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#4" holdingdate="2007-08-28">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many people were employed in (a) manufacturing and (b) financial services in each year since 1997 and what percentage of the workforce these represented.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.5.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#4">

  <p>Table 1 shows the number of employee jobs in the manufacturing and the financial intermediation industries and the percentage of total employees jobs these industries represent.</p>

  <p>Table 1 Employee Jobs in Manufacturing and Financial Intermediation Industries</p>

  <p><table width="75%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="15%" height="17" rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">Year</td>
<td width="42%" height="17" colspan="2" align="center" valign="top">Manufacturing</td>
<td width="42%" height="17" colspan="2" align="center" valign="bottom">Financial Intermediation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="center" valign="top">Level</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom">% of Total Jobs</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="center" valign="top">Level</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="center" valign="bottom">% of Total Jobs</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="15%" valign="bottom" height="17">1997</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">320,200</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">15.4%</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">81,500</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">3.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="15%" valign="bottom" height="17">1998</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">326,700</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">15.1%</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">82,900</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">3.8%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="15%" valign="bottom" height="17">1999</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">315,000</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">14.5%</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">86,100</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">4.0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="15%" valign="bottom" height="17">2000</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">302,000</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">13.5%</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">93,600</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">4.2%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="15%" valign="bottom" height="17">2001</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">285,000</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">12.4%</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">105,100</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">4.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="15%" valign="bottom" height="17">2002</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">263,400</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">11.6%</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">106,900</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">4.7%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="15%" valign="bottom" height="17">2003</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">243,300</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">10.5%</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">109,800</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">4.8%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="15%" valign="bottom" height="17">2004</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">235,900</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">10.1%</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">112,600</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">4.8%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="15%" valign="bottom" height="17">2005</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">229,700</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">9.6%</td>
<td width="15%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">108,200</td>
<td width="27%" height="17" align="right" valign="bottom">4.5%</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Source: Annual Business Inquiry.</p>

  <p>Notes:</p>

  <p>1. These data are based on employee jobs rather than people in employment i.e. one person may have more than one job.</p>

  <p>2. These data do not include self-employed jobs.</p>

  <p>3. The manufacturing industry is defined as standard industrial classification D and the financial intermediation industry is defined as standard industrial classification J.</p>

  <p>4. Data are rounded to the nearest hundred.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.6.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#5">Enterprise</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.6.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80378" speakername="Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD)" spid="S3W-3606" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#5">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what formal consultation has taken place between it and the board of Scottish Enterprise Borders on the review of the enterprise networks.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.6.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#5">

  <p>The nominated Chair of Scottish Enterprise Borders was one of a number of local enterprise companies chairs who met with the Cabinet Secretary for Finance and Sustainable Growth and I on Monday 3 September to discuss the reform of the enterprise networks.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.7.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#5">Enterprise</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.7.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80378" speakername="Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD)" spid="S3W-3607" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#5">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what written communication there has been from it to the board of Scottish Enterprise Borders on the review of the enterprise networks.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.7.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#5">

  <p>All local enterprise companies (LEC) chairs were invited to the consultation event held on 17 August 2007 to discuss sustainable economic development and the role of the enterprise networks. The nominated chair of Scottish Enterprise Borders was also one of a number of LEC chairs who met with the Cabinet Secretary for Finance and Sustainable Growth and I on Monday 3 September 2007 to discuss the reform of the enterprise networks.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.8.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#6">Fire Service</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.8.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80371" speakername="Hugh O'Donnell (Central Scotland) (LD)" spid="S3W-4079" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#6">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it has any plans to replace Scotland&rsquo;s eight fire control rooms with larger control rooms.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.8.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80306" speakername="Fergus Ewing" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#6">

  <p>As noted in the answer to question S3W-1610 on 19 July 2007, ministers are currently considering the issue in the context of advice on Scotland&rsquo;s preparedness to deal with simultaneous major emergencies.</p>

  <p>All answers to written parliamentary questions are available on the Parliament&rsquo;s website the search facility for which can be found at <a href="../../../webapp/wa.search">http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/webapp/wa.search</a>.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.9.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#6">Fire Service</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.9.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80371" speakername="Hugh O'Donnell (Central Scotland) (LD)" spid="S3W-4080" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#6">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what meetings it has had since May 2007 with the Fire Brigades Union and other key stakeholders on the future of emergency fire control rooms.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.9.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80306" speakername="Fergus Ewing" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#6">

  <p>No meetings have taken place on the specific issue of control rooms. However, I am currently engaged in a series of meetings with a range of fire and rescue service stakeholders to hear at first hand the issues affecting the service. As part of this, I will be meeting the Fire Brigades Union on 26 September 2007.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.10.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#7">Food Safety</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.10.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80295" speakername="Jackson Carlaw (West of Scotland) (Con)" spid="S3W-4111" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#7">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what action it has taken, or plans to take, as a result of the BBC's Whistleblower programme on 22 May 2007 which highlighted health and safety concerns relating to supermarkets selling food products beyond their sell-by date.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.10.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#7">

  <p>I have been advised by the Food Standards Agency that the supermarkets concerned in the BBC programme were not based in Scotland and therefore were not under the direct responsibility of any Scottish local authority environmental health department.</p>

  <p>It is the legal responsibility of food businesses to ensure that food is safe and this includes correct use of labelling.</p>

  <p>The &quot;Use-by&quot; date is the key date in terms of food safety. &quot;Sell by&quot; and &quot;display until&quot; dates are to help shop staff know when to remove a product from sale. &quot;Best before&quot; dates are focused on quality rather than safety.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.11.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#8">International Development</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.11.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80332" speakername="Cathy Jamieson (Carrick, Cumnock and Doon Valley) (Lab)" spid="S3W-4236" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#8">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what financial support it will provide to projects which promote health and education in Malawi.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.11.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80307" speakername="Linda Fabiani" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#8">

  <p>The International Development Fund and policy are presently being reviewed to determine how best to develop Scotland&rsquo;s investment in international development. Future funding allocations will be based on the decisions arising from the review.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.12.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#9">Local Authority Expenditure</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.12.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80295" speakername="Jackson Carlaw (West of Scotland) (Con)" spid="S3W-4106" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#9">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how much local authority (a) capital and (b) revenue expenditure was in the West of Scotland parliamentary region in each of the last two years, broken down by single transferable vote ward.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.12.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#9">

  <p>The information requested is only collected at council level. The West of Scotland regional constituency does not match an exact aggregation of whole council areas.</p>

  <p>The following table contains 2004-05 and 2005-06 revenue and capital expenditure for each of the local authorities covered by the constituency. Councils which are only partly covered by the constituency are noted by an asterisk.</p>

  <p>Local Authority Expenditure of Local Authorities Covered Wholly or Partly* by West of Scotland Regional Constituency</p>

  <p><table width="75%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="29%" rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">Local Authority</td>
<td width="36%" colspan="2" align="center" valign="bottom">Net Revenue Expenditure 1</td>
<td width="35%" colspan="2" align="center" valign="top">Gross Capital Expenditure</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="18%" align="center" valign="bottom">2004-05</td>
<td width="18%" align="center" valign="bottom">2005-06</td>
<td width="17%" align="center" valign="bottom">2004-05</td>
<td width="17%" align="center" valign="bottom">2005-06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="29%" valign="bottom">Argyll and Bute*</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="bottom">197,401 </td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="bottom">220,834 </td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">32,673 </td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">37,719 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="29%" valign="bottom">East Dunbartonshire*</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="bottom">186,049 </td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="bottom">205,050 </td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">13,990 </td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">19,043 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="29%" valign="bottom">East Renfrewshire</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="bottom">165,397 </td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="bottom">179,479 </td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">15,691 </td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">21,045 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="29%" valign="bottom">Inverclyde</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="bottom">174,868 </td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="bottom">199,085 </td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">14,789 </td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">21,792 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="29%" valign="bottom">North Ayrshire*</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="bottom">245,404 </td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="bottom">292,333 </td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">24,753 </td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">46,371 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="29%" valign="bottom">Renfrewshire*</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="bottom">309,942 </td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="bottom">349,563 </td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">37,161 </td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">50,581 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="29%" valign="bottom">West Dunbartonshire</td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="bottom">194,726 </td>
<td width="18%" align="right" valign="bottom">203,470 </td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">31,561 </td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">33,945 </td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Sources: Councils covered wholly or partly* by West of Scotland regional constituency. Capital - CR FINAL returns.</p>

  <p>Note: 1. Expenditure on police, fire, registration of electors and council tax and non-domestic lands valuation is apportioned to councils using the amount that the joint boards requisition from them.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.13.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#10">Mental Health</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.13.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80363" speakername="Des McNulty (Clydebank and Milngavie) (Lab)" spid="S3W-3838" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#10">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what plans it has to improve local mental health services in (a) Clydebank and (b) Bearsden and Milngavie.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.13.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80379" speakername="Shona Robison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#10">

  <p>We continue to work with NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde, as well as the local authorities, voluntary sector and other partners, to deliver on a range of policies and initiatives. These include delivery of the 14 specific and timetabled commitments and three HEAT targets set out in <em>Delivering for Mental Health</em> a copy of which has been placed in the Scottish Parliament Information Centre (Bib. number 41410).</p>

  <p>Progress with delivery by local agencies on this agenda is assisted and informed by a range of national support mechanisms. This includes benchmarking and information gathering to support the improvement process, and publication later this year of standards for integrated care pathways which will give local services guidance on how best to structure care for those with dementia, depression, bipolar disorder, schizophrenia, and personality disorders.</p>

  <p>We have developed better performance management systems to offer support for change and more effective service delivery, such as twice yearly visits to every NHS board in Scotland. The next such visit to NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde is due to take place in October.</p>

  <p>NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde has put forward proposals for a review of mental health services in the Clyde area. These will go out for consultation following scrutiny by an independent panel. The panel is scheduled to report in November this year.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.14.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#11">NHS Hospitals</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.14.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80363" speakername="Des McNulty (Clydebank and Milngavie) (Lab)" spid="S3W-4215" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#11">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, further to the answer to question S3W-2935 by Shona Robison on 23 August 2007, what discretion Dr Andrew Walker has to undertake a full option appraisal as part of his independent scrutiny of proposals for service change to accident and emergency services in Lanarkshire and Ayrshire.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.14.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80396" speakername="Nicola Sturgeon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#11">

  <p>I refer the member to the answer to question S3W-2934 on 23 August 2007. All answers to written parliamentary questions are available on the Parliament&rsquo;s website, the search facility for which can be found at <a href="../../../webapp/wa.search">http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/webapp/wa.search</a> .</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.15.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#12">Non-Departmental Public Bodies</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.15.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80295" speakername="Jackson Carlaw (West of Scotland) (Con)" spid="S3W-4108" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#12">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many quangos there have been in each year since 1995, giving the name of each.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.15.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80295" speakername="Jackson Carlaw (West of Scotland) (Con)" spid="S3W-4109" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#12">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many people were employed by each quango in each year since 1995.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.15.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#12">

  <p>The following table shows the trend in the number of non-departmental public bodies (NDPBs) from 1999 to 2006.</p>

  <p>Number of NDPBs: 1999 to 2006</p>

  <p><table width="75%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="13%" align="center" valign="top">1999</td>
<td width="13%" align="center" valign="top">2000</td>
<td width="13%" align="center" valign="top">2001</td>
<td width="13%" align="center" valign="top">2002</td>
<td width="13%" align="center" valign="top">2003</td>
<td width="13%" align="center" valign="top">2004</td>
<td width="13%" align="center" valign="top">2005</td>
<td width="13%" align="center" valign="top">2006</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="13%" align="right" valign="top">186</td>
<td width="13%" align="right" valign="top">184</td>
<td width="13%" align="right" valign="top">183</td>
<td width="13%" align="right" valign="top">151</td>
<td width="13%" align="right" valign="top">144</td>
<td width="13%" align="right" valign="top">140</td>
<td width="13%" align="right" valign="top">142</td>
<td width="13%" align="right" valign="top">140</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Information on the number of NDPBs was maintained by the Cabinet Office prior to formation of the Scottish Parliament.</p>

  <p>The Public Bodies and Appointment pages of the Scottish Government website provide details of all current NDPBs in Scotland and includes financial and staffing data.</p>

  <p>The site is regularly updated and is the main source of publicly available information on NDPBs in Scotland. The site&rsquo;s address is <a href="http://www.scotland.gov.uk/government/publicbodies/" target="_blank">http://www.scotland.gov.uk/government/publicbodies/</a>.</p>

  <p>Prior to the website&rsquo;s establishment in 2002, detailed historical information on NDPBs was published in the annual Cabinet Office document <em>Public Bodies</em>. Copies of the 1998 to 2006 versions of the document are available at <a href="http://www.civilservice.gov.uk/other/agencies/public_bodies/index.asp" target="_blank">http://www.civilservice.gov.uk/other/agencies/public_bodies/index.asp</a>.</p>

  <p>The 1997 version is available from: <a href="http://www.archive.official-documents.co.uk/document/caboff/bodies97/contents.htm" target="_blank">http://www.archive.official-documents.co.uk/document/caboff/bodies97/contents.htm</a>.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.16.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#12">Non-Departmental Public Bodies</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.16.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80295" speakername="Jackson Carlaw (West of Scotland) (Con)" spid="S3W-4110" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#12">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the total cost of running quangos has been in each year since 1995, also giving staffing costs in (a) cash and (b) real terms.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.16.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#12">

  <p>I refer the member to the answer to question S3W-4108 on 19 September 2007. All answers to written parliamentary questions are available on the Parliament&rsquo;s website, the search facility for which can be found at <a href="../../../webapp/wa.search">http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/webapp/wa.search</a> .</p>

  <p>Non-departmental public body annual reports and accounts also provide cost information. Copies are available directly from individual organisations.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.17.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#13">Olympic Games</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.17.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80350" speakername="Liam McArthur (Orkney) (LD)" spid="S3W-4125" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#13">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how it intends to ensure that Scotland gains a tourism benefit from the London 2012 Olympic Games.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.17.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#13">

  <p>The London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games will provide Scotland with an additional opportunity to showcase its tourism product to a global market. VisitScotland is represented on the Scottish steering group which has been set up to ensure that Scotland gets maximum benefit from the games.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.18.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#14">Prison Escorts</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.18.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80295" speakername="Jackson Carlaw (West of Scotland) (Con)" spid="S3W-4242" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#14">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many prisoners have absconded while under escort in each year since 1987.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.18.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80341" speakername="Kenny MacAskill" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#14">

  <p>I have asked Mike Ewart, Chief Executive of the Scottish Prison Service (SPS) to respond. His response is as follows:</p>

  <p>The following table illustrates the number of incidents recorded where a prisoner has escaped while being escorted from an SPS establishment. Reliable information is not available prior to 2001.</p>

  <p><table width="75%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="14%" align="center" valign="top">2001</td>
<td width="14%" align="center" valign="top">2002</td>
<td width="14%" align="center" valign="top">2003</td>
<td width="14%" align="center" valign="top">2004</td>
<td width="14%" align="center" valign="top">2005</td>
<td width="14%" align="center" valign="top">2006</td>
<td width="14%" align="center" valign="top">2007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="14%" align="right" valign="top">4</td>
<td width="14%" align="right" valign="top">1</td>
<td width="14%" align="right" valign="top">1</td>
<td width="14%" align="right" valign="top">3</td>
<td width="14%" align="right" valign="top">0</td>
<td width="14%" align="right" valign="top">5</td>
<td width="14%" align="right" valign="top">3</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.19.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#15">Prison Service</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.19.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80404" speakername="David Whitton (Strathkelvin and Bearsden) (Lab)" spid="S3W-3929" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#15" holdingdate="2007-09-14">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the new timetable is for the tendering process to construct the new Low Moss prison.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.19.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80341" speakername="Kenny MacAskill" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#15">

  <p>I have asked Mike Ewart, Chief Executive of the Scottish Prison Service to respond. His response is as follows:</p>

  <p>The Scottish Prison Service will be inviting the private sector to bid for the design and construction of a new publicly built prison at Bishopbriggs. Preparatory work is underway and it is anticipated that the procurement process will commence later this year.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.20.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#15">Prison Service</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.20.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80404" speakername="David Whitton (Strathkelvin and Bearsden) (Lab)" spid="S3W-3930" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#15" holdingdate="2007-09-14">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive by what date it now expects the new Low Moss prison to be opened.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.20.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80341" speakername="Kenny MacAskill" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#15">

  <p>I have asked Mike Ewart, Chief Executive of the Scottish Prison Service (SPS) to respond. His response is as follows:</p>

  <p>The date of opening will be determined following completion of the design and construction procurement process and will also need to take account of SPS work to commission and open the prison. The SPS will seek to ensure that the retendering of the contract for a prison at Bishopbriggs will not result in an unnecessary delay.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.21.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#15">Prison Service</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.21.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80404" speakername="David Whitton (Strathkelvin and Bearsden) (Lab)" spid="S3W-3933" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#15" holdingdate="2007-09-14">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether the Scottish Prison Service can tender to build the new Low Moss prison.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.21.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80341" speakername="Kenny MacAskill" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#15">

  <p>I have asked Mike Ewart, Chief Executive of the Scottish Prison Service to respond. His response is as follows:</p>

  <p>No, the Scottish Prison Service will be inviting the private sector to bid for the design and construction of a publicly operated prison at Bishopbriggs.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.22.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#15">Prison Service</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.22.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80322" speakername="Rhoda Grant (Highlands and Islands) (Lab)" spid="S3W-4000" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#15" holdingdate="2007-09-18">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it plans to expand prisoner capacity at HM Prison Inverness.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.22.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80341" speakername="Kenny MacAskill" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#15">

  <p>I have asked Mike Ewart, Chief Executive of the Scottish Prison Service to respond. His response is as follows:</p>

  <p>The Scottish Prison Service has no plans to expand prisoner capacity at HM Prison Inverness.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.23.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#15">Prison Service</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.23.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80299" speakername="Cathie Craigie (Cumbernauld and Kilsyth) (Lab)" spid="S3W-4102" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#15">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the prison officer to inmate ratio is in the Scottish Prison Service.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.23.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80341" speakername="Kenny MacAskill" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#15">

  <p>I have asked Mike Ewart, Chief Executive of the Scottish Prison Service to respond. His response is as follows:</p>

  <p>The current prison officer ratio to prisoners in the Scottish Prison Service is 1:2.4.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.24.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#16">Public Sector</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.24.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80355" speakername="Alison McInnes (North East Scotland) (LD)" spid="S3W-4225" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#16">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive when it will publish its plans to increase flexi-working and homeworking in the Scottish Government and all other public bodies.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.24.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#16">

  <p>I refer the member to the answer to question S3W-3523 on 4 September 2007. All answers to written parliamentary questions are available on the Parliament&rsquo;s website, the search facility for which can be found at <a href="../../../webapp/wa.search">http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/webapp/wa.search</a> .</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.25.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">School Meals</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.25.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80378" speakername="Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD)" spid="S3W-4071" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the methodology is for determining the success of the pilot scheme for free school meals for primary 1 to 3 pupils in deprived areas.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.25.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80378" speakername="Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD)" spid="S3W-4163" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how it intends to measure the impact of its proposed free school meal pilots in primary 1 to primary 3.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.25.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80331" speakername="Adam Ingram" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">

  <p>The evaluation of the free school meals trial will address the following research objectives: investigate process and practical issues for local authorities and schools in implementing free school meals; measure the change in uptake of school meals by primary 1 to primary 3 pupils, and by primary 4 to 7 pupils; assess the range of health and other potential benefits of the pilot, including any changes in attitudes and behaviours by pupils and parents in relation to school meals and healthy eating; provide an assessment of the impact of the pilot on the costs of providing free school meals; identify any unexpected impacts and barriers to roll-out across the country. These objectives will be achieved by collecting data on the change in school meal uptake (i.e. both before and near the end of the pilot) and through interviews, surveys and focus groups with parents, pupils, teachers, school catering staff and local authority catering managers.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.26.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">School Meals</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.26.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80378" speakername="Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD)" spid="S3W-4072" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive who has been appointed to conduct research to determine the success of the pilot scheme for free school meals for primary 1 to 3 pupils in deprived areas.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.26.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80331" speakername="Adam Ingram" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">

  <p>Following a two stage competitive tendering exercise conducted in line with the Scottish Government&rsquo;s Procedures for Commissioning and Managing Social Research, IPSOS Mori has been appointed to conduct the independent evaluation of the free school meal trial for primary 1 to 3 pupils.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.27.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">School Meals</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.27.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80378" speakername="Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD)" spid="S3W-4073" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the budget is for the analysis of the success of the pilot scheme for free school meals for primary 1 to 3 pupils in deprived areas.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.27.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80331" speakername="Adam Ingram" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">

  <p>The cost of the evaluation of the free school meals trial is approximately &pound;60,000 including VAT.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.28.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">School Meals</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.28.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80378" speakername="Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD)" spid="S3W-4074" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what methodology it will use to assess the health benefits of the pilot scheme for free school meals for primary 1 to 3 pupils in deprived areas.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.28.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80331" speakername="Adam Ingram" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">

  <p>The evaluation will investigate the range of potential health and other benefits of the free school meals trial, including any changes in attitudes and behaviours in relation to school meals and healthy eating by pupils and parents that are evident within the period of the trial. This will be achieved through measuring the change in uptake of school meals by primary 1 to 3 pupils across all schools taking part in the trial and conducting interviews and focus groups with pupils, teachers, head teachers and catering staff in ten case study schools. The views of parents will be incorporated through focus groups and a quantitative survey <em>. </em> These findings will be considered within the context of the wider research literature and evidence base on school meals and healthy eating by children and families.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.29.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">School Meals</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.29.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80378" speakername="Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD)" spid="S3W-4164" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what criteria it believes need to be met in the proposed free school meal pilots in primary 1 to primary 3 before extending free school meals to all schools.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.29.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80331" speakername="Adam Ingram" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">

  <p>The Scottish Government will take into account the findings of the evaluation of the trial including the change in uptake of free school meals by primary 1 to 3 pupils and any other changes in attitudes and behaviours in relation to free school meals and healthy eating that are evident within the trial period. The trial will also assess the capabilities of schools to deliver the policy. These findings will be set within the context of the wider research literature and evidence base on school meals and healthy eating by children and families.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.30.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">School Meals</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.30.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80378" speakername="Jeremy Purvis (Tweeddale, Ettrick and Lauderdale) (LD)" spid="S3W-4172" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the current take up is of free school meals in the areas selected by it for pilot funding, broken down by local authority area.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.30.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80331" speakername="Adam Ingram" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#17">

  <p>This information is published in table 8 of School Meals in Scotland 2007, which is available on the Scottish Government website: <a href="http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Publications/2007/06/04134749/0" target="_blank">http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Publications/2007/06/04134749/0</a> .</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.31.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#18">Scottish Executive</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.31.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80327" speakername="Hugh Henry (Paisley South) (Lab)" spid="S3W-4381" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#18">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will provide a detailed breakdown of how it has calculated the &pound;100,000 cost of rebranding the Executive.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.31.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#18">

  <p>Design and development of the new corporate identity cost &pound;71,106 and signage cost &pound;38,922. Some of the VAT is refundable on the design and development costs, which means the cost to the organisation was &pound;99,438.</p>

  <p>Our approach does not involve money being spent on replacing items earlier than planned. We will roll out the new identity by replacing items at the end of their scheduled life, not before, to ensure the most prudent use of taxpayers&rsquo; money.</p>

  <p>Further savings will flow from the fact that the new title accurately describes its subject, reducing misunderstanding and the need for additional explanation.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.32.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#19">Scottish Government Expenditure</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.32.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80312" speakername="George Foulkes (Lothians) (Lab)" spid="S3W-4230" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#19">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what plans it has to move online the advertising that it places in newspapers; what savings it expects to make as a result, and what estimate it has made of the effect of any such change on the viability of Scottish newspapers.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.32.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#19">

  <p>The Scottish Government already employs online advertising in its social marketing campaign communications, in response to the public's increasing likelihood to turn to the internet for their information needs. It is used only where it is deemed appropriate and relevant to do so and is not perceived to be a replacement for traditional newspaper advertising, which still plays an important role in delivering some of our communications tasks. Online advertising acts as a supplementary tool for when a communication project requires a targeted channel to deliver a message to a group of people, often with a specific interest.</p>

  <p>It has already proved to be extremely cost-effective in helping us engage with our target audiences, as it is so versatile. For example, it can be used to drive up response rates to a message, promote debate on a topic, signpost the public to an information point, or provide an expedient and automated response mechanism which can remove the need for expensive staffed call centres.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.33.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#19">Scottish Government Expenditure</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.33.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80295" speakername="Jackson Carlaw (West of Scotland) (Con)" spid="S3W-4247" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#19">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will provide a breakdown of all its funded public relations and marketing campaigns in each year since 1999, also showing how much of each campaign&rsquo;s annual spend was paid to external public relations and marketing agencies.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.33.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#19">

  <p>The Scottish Executive put in place a framework contract for Public Relations (PR) on the 1 August 2004. Prior to this, all PR work was sub-contracted by the creative advertising agencies on the Scottish Government contract. Since the 1 August 2004 the following campaigns have received PR support:</p>

  <p>1 August 2004 to 31 March 2005</p>

  <p><table width="75%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="58%" align="center" valign="top">PR Spend by Campaign</td>
<td width="21%" align="center" valign="top">Net</td>
<td width="21%" align="center" valign="top">Gross</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Alcohol</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;42,891.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;50,397.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">ASB</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;39,798.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;46,763.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Care</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;22,155.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;26,032.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Child Protection on Internet</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;8,511.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;10,000.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Children's Charter Original</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;9,011.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;10,588.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Children's Hearings</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;15,948.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;18,739.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Debt Management</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;8,511.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;10,000.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Determined to Succeed</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;0.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Domestic Abuse</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;31,456.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;36,961.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Drugs</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;22,848.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;26,847.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">E-Coli</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;8,511.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;10,000.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Environment</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;26,139.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;30,713.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Fire</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;29,787.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;35,000.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Flu</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;28,422.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;33,396.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">GP Out-Of-Hours</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;4,255.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;5,000.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Health Service Recruitment</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;17,798.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;20,912.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Healthy Living</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;119,149.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;140,000.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Landlord</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;8,511.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;10,000.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Mental Health</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;6,624.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;7,783.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Organ Donation</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;10,312.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;12,062.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Race</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;46,631.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;54,792.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Road Safety</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;83,181.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;97,729.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Safer Scotland</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;0.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Smoking in Public Places (consultation)</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;5,596.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;6,575.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Smoking in Public Places (Health Dept)</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;70,000.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;82,250.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Teacher Recruitment</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;22,049.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;25,908.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Travel Awareness</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;29,787.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;35,000.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Valuing Parents</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;0.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Violence Against Public Sector Workers</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;26,403.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;31,023.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="top">Total</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;770,071.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;904,770.00</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>2005-06</p>

  <p><table width="75%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="58%" align="center" valign="bottom">PR Spend by Campaign</td>
<td width="21%" align="center" valign="bottom">Net</td>
<td width="21%" align="center" valign="bottom">Gross</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">Alcohol</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;48,990.36</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;57,563.67</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">ASB</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;36,296.60</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;42,648.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">Children's Hearings</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;17,205.89</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;20,216.92</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">Domestic Abuse</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;34,040.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;39,997.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">Drugs</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;52,717.89</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;61,943.53</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">Environment</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;42,553.19</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;50,000.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">Fire Safety</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;17,025.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;20,004.38</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">Flu</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;25,155.74</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;29,557.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">Healthy Living</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;25,531.59</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;29,999.62</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">Mental Health</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;19,577.19</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;23,003.20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">NHS Recruitment</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;68,085.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;79,999.88</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">Organ Donation</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;21,276.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;24,999.30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">Race</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;49,954.96</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;58,697.08</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">Road Safety</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;69,208.50</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;81,319.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">Smoking in Public Places</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;169,000.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;198,575.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">Teacher Recruitment</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;42,550.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;49,996.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">Violence Against Public Sector Workers</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;34,045.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;40,002.88</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">Volunteering</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;12,760.00</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;14,993.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="58%" valign="bottom">Total</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;785,972.91</td>
<td width="21%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;923,518.20</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>2006-07</p>

  <p><table width="75%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="63%" align="center" valign="bottom">PR Spend by Campaign</td>
<td width="17%" align="center" valign="bottom">Net</td>
<td width="20%" align="center" valign="bottom">Gross</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Air Discount Scheme</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;10,217.65</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;12,005.74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Choices for Life</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;4,255.32</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;5,000.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Older Person's Consultation</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;8,510.64</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;9,999.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Salmon Parasite</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;16,994.25</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;19,968.24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Social Care PR</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;12,766.00</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;15,000.10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Alcohol</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;38,444.82</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;45,172.64</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">ASB</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;51,062.00</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;59,997.87</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Children's Hearings</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;17,021.26</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;20,000.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Domestic Abuse</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;34,042.55</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;39,999.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Drugs</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;44,721.43</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;52,547.66</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Fire Safety - Domestic</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;17,021.28</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;19,999.97</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Fire Safety - Legislation</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;17,021.28</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;19,999.97</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Flu</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;27,359.00</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;32,146.86</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Healthy Living</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;38,302.00</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;45,004.85</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Hep C</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;38,302.00</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;45,004.85</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Lay Justice Appointments</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;0.00</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Mental Health</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;17,621.18</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;20,704.87</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">NHS Recruitment</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;86,772.34</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;101,957.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Organ Donation</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;33,964.53</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;39,908.30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Race</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;67,047.23</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;78,780.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Road Safety</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;47,393.00</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;55,686.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Smoking</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;28,000.00</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;32,900.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Sustainable Development</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;38,058.64</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;44,718.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Teacher Recruitment</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;42,553.19</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;49,999.96</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Violence Against Public Sector Workers</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;34,042.55</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;40,000.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Volunteering</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;17,021.18</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;19,999.87</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Vote Scotland (previously Single Transferable Vote)</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;81,965.31</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;96,309.21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="63%" valign="bottom">Total</td>
<td width="17%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;870,480.63</td>
<td width="20%" align="right" valign="bottom">&pound;1,022,814.62</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>1 April 2007 to 13 September 2007</p>

  <p><table width="50%" border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" bordercolor="#CCCCCC">
<tr>
<td width="49%" align="center" valign="bottom">PR Spend by Campaign</td>
<td width="25%" align="center" valign="bottom">Net</td>
<td width="25%" align="center" valign="bottom">Gross</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Children's Hearings</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;18,000.00</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;21,150.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Flu</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;10,212.80</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;12,000.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Organ Donation</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;8,000.00</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;9,400.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Road Safety</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;17,031.33</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;20,000.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Vote Scotland</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;1,500.00</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;1,62.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="top">Total</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;54,734.13</td>
<td width="25%" align="right" valign="top">&pound;64,312.61</td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>For spend on advertising campaigns in each year since 1999, I refer the member to the answer to question S3W-3693 on 4 September 2007. All answers to written parliamentary questions are available on the Parliament's website, the search facility for which can be found at: <a href="../../../webapp/wa.search">http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/webapp/wa.search</a>.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.34.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#20">Scottish Government Finance</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.34.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80295" speakername="Jackson Carlaw (West of Scotland) (Con)" spid="S3W-4113" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#20">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the total cost of governing Scotland has been in each year from 1979 to 2007 in (a) cash and (b) real terms.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.34.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80397" speakername="John Swinney" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#20">

  <p>Since Devolution, the cost of governing Scotland could be deemed to comprise a number of different elements, including: the cost of running the Scottish Parliament (further information can be found within the Scottish Parliamentary Corporate Body&rsquo;s accounts); a proportion of the administration costs for the Scottish Government, and an element of the expenditure by Scottish local authorities.</p>

  <p>Prior to Devolution, such costs would have been a matter for the Secretary of State for Scotland.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.35.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#21">Tourism</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.35.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80350" speakername="Liam McArthur (Orkney) (LD)" spid="S3W-4126" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#21">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it has held any meetings with VisitScotland to discuss a Scottish Olympic tourism strategy.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.35.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#21">

  <p>My officials hold regular meetings with VisitScotland about our ambition for the long-term development of Scotland&rsquo;s tourism sector, including the opportunities represented by the 2012 London Olympic Game. Scotland intends to maximise the potential tourism benefits from the 2012 London Olympic Games. Our strategy is to work closely with the UK Government to maximise the tourism benefits to Scotland from the Games, and Scottish representatives meet regularly with others from the rest of the UK on a number of working groups relating to the games, including one on tourism.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.36.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#21">Tourism</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.36.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80350" speakername="Liam McArthur (Orkney) (LD)" spid="S3W-4127" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#21">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it has developed, or intends to develop, a Scottish Olympic tourism strategy.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.36.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#21">

  <p>Our tourism strategy is based on an ambition to grow tourism revenues by 50% in the decade to 2015. We will use every opportunity, including the year of Homecoming project in 2009, the 2012 London Olympic Games, and the Ryder Cup in 2014, to attain that ambition. There is a real opportunity for Scotland&rsquo;s appeal as a tourism destination to be used to attract visitors to the UK attending the 2012 London Olympic Games to extend their stay by visiting Scotland.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.37.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#22">Transport</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.37.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80403" speakername="Karen Whitefield (Airdrie and Shotts) (Lab)" spid="S3W-3524" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#22" holdingdate="2007-09-18">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what steps it is taking to improve and increase the use of park-and-ride facilities.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.37.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80393" speakername="Stewart Stevenson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#22">

  <p>Transport Scotland, is working with rail industry partners to identify and deliver station car park expansion opportunities across the country. Schemes at five stations have already been funded for completion by the end of 2007, and more are to follow. Significant funding has also been given previously to local authorities to enable them to deliver bus park-and-ride schemes in their areas.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.38.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#23">Voluntary Sector</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.38.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80313" speakername="Murdo Fraser (Mid Scotland and Fife) (Con)" spid="S3W-3694" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#23">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the policy of Project Scotland is on funding placements with religious and faith-based organisations.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2007-09-19.38.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80347" speakername="Jim Mather" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-07/wa0919.htm#23">

  <p>Project Scotland is a company limited by guarantee and registered as a charity whose aims and objectives are to promote the welfare and relieve the needs of the population in Scotland by encouraging and assisting young people to provide their skills and services voluntarily to charitable organisations.</p>

  <p>Project Scotland does not fund placements but supports the volunteer directly through a package of support which includes expenses, subsistence allowance and mentoring. Project Scotland&rsquo;s policy will allow it to support volunteers in placements with faith-based charities provided that the placement is open to all, regardless of faith or belief, that the volunteer&rsquo;s own faith or belief is not compromised and that the placement does not require the volunteer to participate in any form of religious promotion or religious activities. Full information about the work of Project Scotland is available from its chief executive at 49 Melville Street, Edinburgh, EH3 7HL.</p>

</reply>
</publicwhip>