<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE publicwhip [

<!ENTITY pound   "&#163;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">

<!ENTITY agrave  "&#224;">
<!ENTITY aacute  "&#225;">
<!ENTITY egrave  "&#232;">
<!ENTITY eacute  "&#233;">
<!ENTITY ecirc   "&#234;">
<!ENTITY iacute  "&#237;">
<!ENTITY ograve  "&#242;">
<!ENTITY oacute  "&#243;">
<!ENTITY uacute  "&#250;">
<!ENTITY Aacute  "&#193;">
<!ENTITY Eacute  "&#201;">
<!ENTITY Iacute  "&#205;">
<!ENTITY Oacute  "&#211;">
<!ENTITY Uacute  "&#218;">
<!ENTITY Uuml    "&#220;">
<!ENTITY auml    "&#228;">
<!ENTITY euml    "&#235;">
<!ENTITY iuml    "&#239;">
<!ENTITY ouml    "&#246;">
<!ENTITY uuml    "&#252;">
<!ENTITY fnof    "&#402;">
<!ENTITY aelig   "&#230;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">
<!ENTITY reg     "&#174;">
<!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
<!ENTITY shy     "&#173;">
<!ENTITY deg     "&#176;">
<!ENTITY middot  "&#183;">
<!ENTITY ordm    "&#186;">
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY hellip  "&#8230;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">

<!ENTITY acirc   "&#226;">
<!ENTITY Agrave  "&#192;">
<!ENTITY Aring   "&#197;">
<!ENTITY aring   "&#229;">
<!ENTITY atilde  "&#227;">
<!ENTITY Ccedil  "&#199;">
<!ENTITY ccedil  "&#231;">
<!ENTITY Egrave  "&#200;">
<!ENTITY Icirc   "&#206;">
<!ENTITY icirc   "&#238;">
<!ENTITY Igrave  "&#204;">
<!ENTITY igrave  "&#236;">
<!ENTITY ntilde  "&#241;">
<!ENTITY ocirc   "&#244;">
<!ENTITY oelig   "&#339;">
<!ENTITY Ograve  "&#210;">
<!ENTITY Oslash  "&#216;">
<!ENTITY oslash  "&#248;">
<!ENTITY Scaron  "&#352;">
<!ENTITY scaron  "&#353;">
<!ENTITY sup1    "&#185;">
<!ENTITY sup2    "&#178;">
<!ENTITY sup3    "&#179;">
<!ENTITY ugrave  "&#249;">
<!ENTITY Ugrave  "&#217;">
<!ENTITY yacute  "&#253;">
<!ENTITY frac12  "&#189;">
<!ENTITY micro   "&#181;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8225;">
]>

<publicwhip>

<source url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm"/>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.0.mh" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm">Written Answers</major-heading>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.1.mh" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm">Friday 2 June 2000</major-heading>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.2.mh" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm">Scottish Executive</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6902.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6902">Ambulance Service</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6902.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80262" speakername="Dorothy-Grace Elder (Glasgow) (SNP)" spid="S1W-6902" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6902">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will investigate any shortages, including any lack of equipment, in the ambulance service in Glasgow.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6902.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6902">

  <p>There are no equipment shortages against the inventory required to provide ambulance services in Glasgow.</p>

  <p>There are occasions where, in the best interests of the patient, ambulance crews are obliged to leave equipment with the patient on arrival at hospital. This can arise in the case of cervical collars and spinal boards, which should not be removed from a patient suffering from suspected spinal injuries until x-rays are taken and the diagnosis confirmed. The crew may have to respond to new emergency calls before the equipment becomes available requiring retrieval to take place at a later time. The Scottish Ambulance Service is looking at ways of addressing this.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6887.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6887">Autism</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6887.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80151" speakername="Mrs Margaret Ewing (Moray) (SNP)" spid="S1W-6887" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6887">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what funding it has allocated for each of the next three financial years for (a) research into autism and (b) the treatment of autism.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6887.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6887">

  <p>The Chief Scientist Office (CSO) within the Scottish Executive Health Department is the main departmental funder of NHS-related research. Although CSO commissions a small amount of work in specific priority areas, it more generally supports research undertaken by the research community in Scotland. CSO is not currently funding research into autistic spectrum disorders but would be prepared to consider suitable research applications in the future.</p>

  <p>The Inclusion Programme has allocated &pound;12 million for two years starting from April 2000 to assist local authorities to include children with special educational needs in mainstream provision, and autism has been highlighted as one of the priority areas in the present round of the Special Educational Needs Innovation Grants Programme.</p>

  <p>With regard to treatment, health boards are expected to develop services for autism based on local assessments of needs. Any investment plans in autism services will be based on these ongoing assessments.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6888.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6887">Autism</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6888.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80151" speakername="Mrs Margaret Ewing (Moray) (SNP)" spid="S1W-6888" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6887">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what funding was allocated for each of the last three financial years for (a) research into autism and (b) the treatment of autism.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6888.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6887">

  <p>The Chief Scientist Office (CSO) within the Scottish Executive Health Department is the main departmental funder of NHS related research. Although CSO commissions a small amount of work in specific priority areas, it more generally supports research undertaken by the research community in Scotland. CSO received no research proposals of a sufficiently high standard and therefore did not fund any research.</p>

  <p>With regard to treatment, health boards are expected to develop services for autism based on local assessments of needs. Any investment plans in autism services would have been based on those assessments.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6946.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6946">Cancer</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6946.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80234" speakername="Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S1W-6946" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6946">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether there is any proven link between the use of anti-perspirants and the prevalence of breast cancer.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6946.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6946">

  <p>There is no evidence to suggest that there is any link between the use of anti-perspirants and breast cancer.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-4923.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#4923">Charities</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-4923.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80150" speakername="Fergus Ewing (Inverness East, Nairn and Lochaber) (SNP)" spid="S1W-4923" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#4923">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will publish, for each of the last 10 years, the total public funds received, from all sources, including the Scottish Executive, The Scottish Office, Her Majesty&#8217;s Government and other UK wide public bodies, by all charities registered in Scotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-4923.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80252" speakername="Mr Jim Wallace" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#4923">

  <p>This information is not held centrally.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6703.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6703">Dental Care</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6703.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80262" speakername="Dorothy-Grace Elder (Glasgow) (SNP)" spid="S1W-6703" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6703">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it has any plans to investigate staffing numbers and any resultant pressure on staff caused by shortages at the Glasgow Dental Hospital.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6703.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6703">

  <p>This is a matter for North Glasgow University Hospitals NHS Trust, which is in the final stages of undertaking a strategic review of dental services, including staffing issues.</p>

  <p>I understand, however, that a new locum Consultant has been appointed in<strong> </strong>Oral Medicine and that a full-time Consultant will be appointed in the next two to three months. There are ongoing discussions regarding the appointment of additional Consultants in Oral Surgery and the Trust is in the process of filling the two vacant sessions in anxiety/hypnosis. Staff replacement is also in process in Prosthetics and there is a programme for Conservation to be covered by Consultants following the transfer of University staff who previously covered this speciality.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5198.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#5198">E-Commerce</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5198.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80217" speakername="David Mundell (South of Scotland) (Con)" spid="S1W-5198" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#5198">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what part it has played in implementing the UK e-envoy&#8217;s recommendation to &quot;mount a concerted PR campaign in partnership with industry to create an e-commerce buzz in the UK&quot; and what the current status is of that campaign in Scotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5198.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#5198">

  <p>The Executive has just taken part in a UK Information Society Initiative (ISI) direct mailing campaign to increase awareness among micro-businesses of the e-commerce support available to them via the ISI IT advice centres. Further activity will follow the wider examination of the impact of the ISI brand.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6771.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#5198">E-Commerce</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6771.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80150" speakername="Fergus Ewing (Inverness East, Nairn and Lochaber) (SNP)" spid="S1W-6771" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#5198">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will review its plans to promote e-commerce in the light of problems arising from the recent &quot;love-bug&quot; computer virus.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6771.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#5198">

  <p>The &quot;Iloveyou&quot; virus was spread by e-mail, which is not the main vehicle for e-commerce transactions.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7038.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7038">Education</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7038.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80150" speakername="Fergus Ewing (Inverness East, Nairn and Lochaber) (SNP)" spid="S1W-7038" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7038">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what steps it has already taken to make enterprise education available to every primary school child and what steps it will take to make it available in the school year 2000-01.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7038.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7038">

  <p>At least one teacher in 80% of primary schools in Scotland has undertaken some training in delivering enterprise education. There are currently no plans to make enterprise education available to all primary schools in 2000-01. The curriculum in Scotland is not prescribed by statute but enterprise education can be delivered as part of a number of areas of the curriculum including, in particular, Environmental Studies.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7039.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7038">Education</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7039.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80150" speakername="Fergus Ewing (Inverness East, Nairn and Lochaber) (SNP)" spid="S1W-7039" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7038">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive in what ways it supports the work of The National Centre: Education for Work and Enterprise at Strathclyde University and whether it will offer further assistance.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7039.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7038">

  <p>The Executive were very heavily involved in the establishment of the National Centre in 1998. It came into being following an initiative by Brian Wilson MP who was then Minister for Education and Industry at the Scottish Office. The Executive continues to support the centre through core funding. There are no immediate plans to offer further financial support. Officials are in regular contact with the centre management to discuss ongoing strategic and operational matters. It is anticipated that the good working relationship which exists between the Executive and the centre will continue.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6320.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6320">Employment</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6320.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80160" speakername="Mr Kenneth Gibson (Glasgow) (SNP)" spid="S1W-6320" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6320">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive on what basis it estimates that 1,500 unemployed Glaswegians wish to work in the construction industry and how many of these workers (a) have actual experience of employment in construction, (b) are fully time served or otherwise qualified in construction related skills and (c) are currently available for work, listed by trade.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6320.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6320">

  <p>In July 1999, the Office for National Statistics claimant count system shows there were around 1,500 people claiming unemployment-related benefits in the Glasgow travel to work area who were seeking work in construction trades. At this time, the usual occupation of around 1,400 unemployed claimants was in the construction industry. Latest figures, from April 2000, show that there are now 1,400 claimants in the Glasgow travel to work area seeking work in construction trades, and 1,200 with previous experience in construction. All people claiming unemployment related benefits must be currently available for work.</p>

  <p>No information is held centrally on all Glaswegians looking for work in construction, the type and level of skills these people have.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7070.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6320">Employment</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7070.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80235" speakername="John Scott (Ayr) (Con)" spid="S1W-7070" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6320">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what assessment it has made of any employment implications for the Scottish financial sector if the proposed merger of the London and Frankfurt Stock Exchanges goes ahead.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7070.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6320">

  <p>The Executive, through regular contact with the Scottish financial sector, considers a wide range of matters which could impact on overall employment prospects for the sector. Overall, further growth in employment in the financial sector is expected, as suggested by independent forecasts.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7155.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6320">Employment</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7155.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80160" speakername="Mr Kenneth Gibson (Glasgow) (SNP)" spid="S1W-7155" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6320">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will take specific measures to reduce unemployment in Glasgow Pollok, given that the resident claimant count in that constituency is currently the highest in Scotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7155.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6320">

  <p>Scottish Enterprise Glasgow, Glasgow City Council, and the Greater Pollok Social Inclusion Partnership are already taking a number of specific measures to reduce unemployment in Greater Pollok. These measures include: the development of strategic sites for both indigenous companies and inward investors to create new jobs for local residents; facilitating access to employment for Pollok residents through a variety of training, counselling, and work experience schemes including the Glasgow Mentoring Network, Glasgow Works, the Glasgow Employment Zone, the New Deal, Skillseekers and Training for Work; removing barriers to employment through improving childcare provision; supporting the development of the Social Economy as a provider of services and employment; promoting a culture of lifelong learning through initiatives such as the creation of a Real Learning Centre in Pollok Library, and the establishment of a local economic development company "Invest in Greater Pollok" which will manage the delivery of a wide range of economic development services.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7174.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6320">Employment</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7174.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80211" speakername="Des McNulty (Clydebank and Milngavie) (Lab)" spid="S1W-7174" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6320">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, further to the answer to question S1W-6583 by Henry McLeish on 18 May 2000, how many of the planned jobs in Dunbartonshire announced over the last five years were located in Clydebank.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7174.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6320">

  <p>In the five years to March 1999, Locate in Scotland and its partners helped to attract nine projects to Clydebank which involved the planned creation or safeguarding of 480 jobs.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6658.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">Enterprise</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6658.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80142" speakername="Bruce Crawford (Mid Scotland and Fife) (SNP)" spid="S1W-6658" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what level of assistance or grants have been given by Scottish Enterprise, Fife Enterprise or other government agencies to Marconi Simulation (now Alenia Marconi Systems) at its Hillend, Fife operation since 1995.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6658.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">

  <p>This is an operational matter for Scottish Enterprise and I have asked the Chairman to reply to the member. A copy of the reply will be placed in SPICe.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7022.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">Enterprise</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7022.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80236" speakername="Tavish Scott (Shetland) (LD)" spid="S1W-7022" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether Scottish Enterprise is promoting the production of photovoltaic cells in Scotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7022.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">

  <p>Although Scottish Enterprise does not promote the production of photovoltaic cells in Scotland, it was a sponsor of the recently held European Photovolaic Conference in Glasgow, and my officials were able to use the opportunity to discuss their manufacturing plans with photovoltaic panel manufacturers.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7041.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">Enterprise</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7041.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80150" speakername="Fergus Ewing (Inverness East, Nairn and Lochaber) (SNP)" spid="S1W-7041" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, with regard to the Global Entrepreneurship Monitor which indicates that an increased incidence of entrepreneurship among the total population of a country leads to a higher level of economic growth, what measures it will take to increase the level of entrepreneurship in Scotland and whether any such measures will be targeted at school pupils.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7041.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">

  <p>We have a number of positive measures in hand to encourage and increase the level of entrepreneurship in Scotland, including initiatives targeted at school pupils. The Education for Work and Enterprise agenda covers a wide range of school-based and other activities which are designed to raise awareness of the role of enterprise and entrepreneurship. For example, Scottish Enterprise Lanarkshire Business Partnership has supported a range of enterprise activities designed to support the 5-14 curriculum. These include a &quot;Mini Enterprise&quot; programme for primary schools in Lanarkshire. In addition, the Achievers International programme supports the development of entrepreneurial skills through the innovative use of information technology.</p>

  <p>Scottish Enterprise has also published a discussion paper detailing the progress made under the Business Birth Rate Strategy since its launch in 1993 and we are continuing to work with Scottish Enterprise and Highlands and Islands Enterprise in improving their support for enterprise and business creation.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7045.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">Enterprise</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7045.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80150" speakername="Fergus Ewing (Inverness East, Nairn and Lochaber) (SNP)" spid="S1W-7045" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what methodology it uses in calculating the number of new businesses and whether bank statistics and VAT registration are taken into account in the calculation.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7045.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">

  <p>Although the Scottish Executive itself does not publish estimates for the number of new businesses in Scotland, a number of measures are used by the Executive to monitor the business birth rate in Scotland including bank statistics and VAT registration statistics.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7195.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">Enterprise</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7195.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80220" speakername="Alex Neil (Central Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S1W-7195" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how much money has been invested by Scottish Enterprise Lanarkshire in Hamilton North and Bellshill since May 1999.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7195.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">

  <p>This is an operational matter for Scottish Enterprise and I have asked the chairman to reply to the member. A copy of the reply will be placed in SPICe.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7196.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">Enterprise</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7196.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80220" speakername="Alex Neil (Central Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S1W-7196" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how much money has been invested in Regional Selective Assistance in Hamilton North and Bellshill since May 1999.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7196.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">

  <p>In the year beginning 1 May 1999, companies in the Hamilton North and Bellshill constituency received RSA payments totalling some &pound;1.8 million.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7198.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">Enterprise</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7198.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80220" speakername="Alex Neil (Central Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S1W-7198" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how much money has been invested in Regional Selective Assistance in Kilmarnock and Loudoun since May 1999.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7198.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">

  <p>In the year beginning 1 May 1999, companies in the Kilmarnock and Loudoun constituency received RSA payments totalling some &pound;850,000.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7199.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">Enterprise</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7199.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80220" speakername="Alex Neil (Central Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S1W-7199" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how much money has been invested by Scottish Enterprise Ayrshire in Kilmarnock and Loudoun since May 1999.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7199.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6658">

  <p>This is an operational matter for Scottish Enterprise and I have asked the chairman to reply. A copy of the reply will be placed in SPICe.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6932.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">Health</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6932.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80190" speakername="Ms Margo MacDonald (Lothians) (SNP)" spid="S1W-6932" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive why patients requiring new orthotic equipment in Lothian will have this equipment measured and fitted locally but manufactured in Leeds thereby rendering impossible any further customised adaptations.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6932.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">

  <p>Basic stock items of orthotic equipment are purchased through centralised contracts arranged by Scottish Healthcare Supplies. All customisations are however carried out in-house by Lothian University Hospitals Trust, as is the provision of specialist one-off items.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6933.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">Health</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6933.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80190" speakername="Ms Margo MacDonald (Lothians) (SNP)" spid="S1W-6933" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether the new Royal Infirmary will have similar orthotic workshop facilities to those currently in place in the Princess Margaret Rose Hospital.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6933.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">

  <p>Lothian University Hospitals NHS Trust are presently developing plans to relocate the orthotic workshop facilities currently located at the Princess Margaret Rose Hospital in Edinburgh. The Trust is committed to maintaining the current level of service provision.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6934.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">Health</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6934.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80190" speakername="Ms Margo MacDonald (Lothians) (SNP)" spid="S1W-6934" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will list (a) the grants available to users of orthotic equipment, (b) the voucher schemes which are currently in place to offset the costs of new orthotic equipment and (c) the government agencies which issue such grants and vouchers.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6934.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">

  <p>The vast majority of orthotic items provided through the NHS in Scotland are supplied free of charge. Wigs and fabric supports do attract a prescription charge but only for hospital outpatients who do not fall within a prescription exemption or remission category. As such, it has never been deemed necessary to create a grant or voucher scheme. Exemption and remission categories are explained in leaflet HC11. A copy of this leaflet has been placed in the Scottish Parliament Information Centre.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6940.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">Health</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6940.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80168" speakername="Mr Duncan Hamilton (Highlands and Islands) (SNP)" spid="S1W-6940" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will list, by health board area, the number of people for whom beta interferon has been prescribed in (a) 1997, (b) 1998, (c) 1999 and (d) at the current time.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6940.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">

  <p>I refer Mr Hamilton to my answer to question S1W-2734 on 29 February 2000.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6941.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">Health</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6941.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80234" speakername="Mary Scanlon (Highlands and Islands) (Con)" spid="S1W-6941" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what plans it has to provide adequate and appropriate maxillofacial and oral surgery services in the Highland Health Board area and in the Argyll and Bute Health Board area.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6941.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">

  <p>It is for Highland Health Board, Argyll and Clyde Health Board and their respective Trusts to provide health services appropriate to the needs of the local population.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6954.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">Health</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6954.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80237" speakername="Tommy Sheridan (Glasgow) (SSP)" spid="S1W-6954" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the current waiting lists are, broken down by health board, for wheelchairs.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6954.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">

  <p>There is currently no national data available regarding waiting times for the provision of wheelchairs.</p>

  <p>The Rehabilitation Technology Information Service (ReTIS) has been established to collect and analyse benchmarking information on wheelchairs, prosthetics, orthotics and electronic assistive technology throughout the NHS in Scotland. The information collected will include waiting times for wheelchairs and will be used as an evidence base for future service provision, thus providing a framework against which best practice delivery of rehabilitation technology services can be measured.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6955.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">Health</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6955.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80237" speakername="Tommy Sheridan (Glasgow) (SSP)" spid="S1W-6955" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the current waiting list is for wheelchairs in the Greater Glasgow Health Board area; whether this is higher or lower than the national average; if it is higher, by how much, and what detailed plans it has to reduce the list and within what timescale.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6955.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6932">

  <p>There are currently no patients in the Greater Glasgow Health Board area waiting to have manual wheelchairs prescribed. However there is a time period between prescription and delivery and presently 105 patients are awaiting delivery of manual wheelchairs. To put this figure in context, during the 1999-2000 period 3,611 manual wheelchairs were prescribed and delivered to patients in the Greater Glasgow Health Board area, and that figure is expected to rise during this year.</p>

  <p>There are currently 70 patients awaiting delivery of electrically powered wheelchairs which are only prescribed after a patient has been assessed by a multi-disciplinary team. This ensures that the exact type of wheelchair and accessories are prescribed to meet their needs, and that their living environment is suitably adapted for its use.</p>

  <p>There is currently no national data available regarding waiting times for the provision of wheelchairs. The answer to question S1W-6954 details the NHS in Scotland's initiative to address this.</p>

  <p>Discussions are currently taking place between the West of Scotland Mobility and Rehabilitation Centre (WESTMARC) and the West of Scotland Consortium of six health boards regarding appropriate funding levels for the service.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7071.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7071">Higher Education</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7071.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80151" speakername="Mrs Margaret Ewing (Moray) (SNP)" spid="S1W-7071" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7071">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive when the Scottish Higher Education Funding Council report into Moray College was completed and when it will be in the public domain.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7071.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7071">

  <p>Professor Sizer, Chief Executive and Accounting Officer of the Scottish Further Education Funding Council issued his report to the Board of Management at Moray College on 24 February 2000. The board has responded to the report and an agreed Action Plan is being implemented. Any decision on whether the report is to be placed in the public domain is a matter not for the Scottish Executive, but for either the Funding Council or Audit Scotland.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7024.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7024">Highlands and Islands</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7024.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80236" speakername="Tavish Scott (Shetland) (LD)" spid="S1W-7024" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7024">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what areas of the Highlands and Islands are currently included in the &quot;Initiative of the Edge&quot; designation; whether there are any plans to add to these areas, and what assessment of the initiative has been done or is due to take place.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7024.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80214" speakername="Mr Alasdair Morrison" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7024">

  <p>Iomairt aig an Oir (Initiative at the Edge) was introduced as a means of assisting a number of areas in the Highlands &amp; Islands which have endured particularly severe, long-term economic and social decline. The eight areas covered by the Iomairt are: Uig &amp; Bernera, Bays of Harris, Eriskay and Lochboisdale in the Western Isles as well as North Sutherland, Colonsay, Ardnamurchan and the Orkney Islands of Westray &amp; Papa Westray. The success of the initiative is being assessed against an evaluation framework and a strategy agreed by the partners in the Iomairt.</p>

  <p>The National Steering Group of Iomairt aig an Oir will consider the circumstances of any request to broaden Iomairt Oir.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6903.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6903">Hospitals</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6903.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80262" speakername="Dorothy-Grace Elder (Glasgow) (SNP)" spid="S1W-6903" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6903">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will make representations to Greater Glasgow Health Board to extend the consultation period on the new plans for Glasgow hospitals from three months to six months.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6903.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80262" speakername="Dorothy-Grace Elder (Glasgow) (SNP)" spid="S1W-6904" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6903">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it has made any response to the submission by UNISON and others that the public consultation period over the review of Glasgow hospitals be extended from three months to six months.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6903.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6903">

  <p>It is for Greater Glasgow Health Board to determine the length of time over which its public consultation exercise on the modernisation of acute hospital services across the city will be carried out.</p>

  <p>I understand, however, that the health board has recently extended the consultation period, which began on 27 March, to 9 September. A further consultation period between the end of September and 1 December to give consultees the opportunity to respond to the health board&#8217;s Position Paper is also proposed.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6849.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6849">Housing</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6849.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80196" speakername="Tricia Marwick (Mid Scotland and Fife) (SNP)" spid="S1W-6849" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6849">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will provide a breakdown for the &pound;36.5 million budget for New Housing partnerships current expenditure in 2000-01 of provision for (a) stock condition surveys, (b) tenant consultation or capacity building, (c) financial planning and (d) other expenditure.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6849.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80131" speakername="Ms Wendy Alexander" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6849">

  <p>The figure of &pound;36.5 million was prepared on the basis of an estimated &pound;15.5 million earmarked for those councils which are undertaking feasibility and other work related to possible stock transfers. The final breakdown of these earmarked funds has still to be agreed with councils. A further &pound;21 million was set aside for assistance with debt.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7065.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6849">Housing</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7065.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80210" speakername="Pauline McNeill (Glasgow Kelvin) (Lab)" spid="S1W-7065" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6849">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether, under the proposals for housing stock transfer, the right to buy and the current discount will be retained.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7065.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80131" speakername="Ms Wendy Alexander" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6849">

  <p>Current arrangements allow for tenants to transfer with a preserved right to buy. Detailed proposals for a modernised right to buy will be announced in early summer as part of the forthcoming Housing Bill.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6770.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6770">Information Technology</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6770.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80150" speakername="Fergus Ewing (Inverness East, Nairn and Lochaber) (SNP)" spid="S1W-6770" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6770">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what action it is taking to ensure protection for public bodies and businesses against problems resulting from possible computer viruses similar to the recent &quot;love-bug&quot; computer virus.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6770.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6770">

  <p>The Scottish Executive&#8217;s virus protection system has been enhanced to cope with the &quot;Iloveyou&quot; virus and all its known variants and clones.</p>

  <p>The Executive continue to liaise with other Government agencies regarding all IT security issues including viruses but is not directly responsible for the physical protection of their IT systems.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6772.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6770">Information Technology</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6772.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80150" speakername="Fergus Ewing (Inverness East, Nairn and Lochaber) (SNP)" spid="S1W-6772" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6770">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the estimated financial loss to public bodies and businesses was as a result of the &quot;love-bug&quot; computer virus.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6772.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6770">

  <p>The love-bug virus did not penetrate the Scottish Executive virus protection system and therefore no financial loss was incurred.</p>

  <p>We have no ready means of making an estimate of any financial loss to businesses.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-3551.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#3551">Justice</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-3551.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80229" speakername="Shona Robison (North-East Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S1W-3551" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#3551">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive why it has taken over five months to establish the steering group to implement the recommendations of <i>The Stephen Lawrence Inquiry: An Action Plan for Scotland</i> as announced by Mr Jim Wallace on 20 July 1999.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-3551.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80252" speakername="Mr Jim Wallace" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#3551">

  <p>The time taken reflects extensive consultation with the Commission for Racial Equality on the membership of the group and the careful consideration given to the matter within the Executive.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5430.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#3551">Justice</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5430.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80196" speakername="Tricia Marwick (Mid Scotland and Fife) (SNP)" spid="S1W-5430" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#3551">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many freeing orders were applied for and how many were granted in 1995, 1996, 1997, 1998 and 1999.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5430.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80252" speakername="Mr Jim Wallace" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#3551">

  <p>Information is not available in the form requested. The following table sets out the information which is recorded on the number of freeing orders which were granted in the years 1995 to 1999.</p>

  <p><table border="BORDER" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="2" width="100%">
<tr>
<td width="32%" valign="TOP">
<p>Year 
                </p></td>
<td width="12%" valign="TOP">
<p align="CENTER">1995 
                </p></td>
<td width="12%" valign="TOP">
<p align="CENTER">1996 
                </p></td>
<td width="14%" valign="TOP">
<p align="CENTER">1997 
                </p></td>
<td width="14%" valign="TOP">
<p align="CENTER">1998 
                </p></td>
<td width="16%" valign="TOP">
<p align="CENTER">1999 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="32%" valign="TOP">
<p>Freeing Orders granted 
                </p></td>
<td width="12%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">45 
                </p></td>
<td width="12%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">93 
                </p></td>
<td width="14%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">96 
                </p></td>
<td width="14%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">103 
                </p></td>
<td width="16%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">137 
                </p></td>
</tr>
</table></p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-4783.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#4783">Legislation</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-4783.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80150" speakername="Fergus Ewing (Inverness East, Nairn and Lochaber) (SNP)" spid="S1W-4783" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#4783">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, further to the answer to question S1W-4008 by Mr Jim Wallace on 28 January 2000, whether it will widen the remit of the Scottish Law Commission&#8217;s (SLC) review of the law of the foreshore and seabed and, in particular, whether it will instruct the SLC to consider the interests of (a) local communities, (b) individual residents and (c) local businesses who may be affected by the law of the foreshore and seabed.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-4783.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80252" speakername="Mr Jim Wallace" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#4783">

  <p>No change in the remit is necessary. Under the existing remit, the commission will take account of such issues in its review of what the existing law actually is, and in its recommendations for improving its clarity and consistency.</p>

  <p>And, as is usual, the commission will prepare and issue a discussion paper before drawing up its recommendations. Local communities, individuals and businesses will therefore have the opportunity to make their views known as part of the process.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-3098.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#3098">Lifelong Learning</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-3098.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80171" speakername="Hugh Henry (Paisley South) (Lab)" spid="S1W-3098" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#3098">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will consider the establishment of a Trade Union Learning Fund.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-3098.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#3098">

  <p>I should like to apologise for the delay in responding. Trade unions have long made a valuable contribution to workplace learning in Scotland, and that experience has been valuable in the development of key lifelong learning initiatives such as the Scottish University for Industry. I have therefore agreed that we will establish a Trade Union Learning Fund for Scotland. I have invited the STUC to explore with officials how trade unions in Scotland can best provide further support for workplace learning.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7011.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7011">Local Government</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7011.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80164" speakername="Donald Gorrie (Central Scotland) (LD)" spid="S1W-7011" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7011">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how much was paid by each local authority to consultants in each year from 1995-96 to 1999-2000.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7011.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80201" speakername="Mr Jack McConnell" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7011">

  <p>This information is not collected centrally.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6579.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6579">Nutrition</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6579.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80211" speakername="Des McNulty (Clydebank and Milngavie) (Lab)" spid="S1W-6579" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6579">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether any of the money generated by the &quot;tobacco tax&quot; will be targeted at the promotion of healthy eating, including nutritional education within schools.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6579.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6579">

  <p>It is my intention that a proportion of the &pound;26 million from the additional tobacco taxation announced in this year&#8217;s budget statement should fund initiatives aimed at improving Scotland&#8217;s diet; and that these initiatives should have a particular focus on encouraging children and young people to adopt a healthy diet.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6898.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6898">Occupational Health</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6898.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80209" speakername="Mr Duncan McNeil (Greenock and Inverclyde) (Lab)" spid="S1W-6898" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6898">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how the level and standard of the occupational health services provided by the NHSiS compares to those provided in England and Wales and elsewhere in the European Union and what plans it has to improve the level and standard of occupational health services provided by the NHSiS.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6898.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6898">

  <p>Information on the level and standard of occupational health service provision outwith Scotland is not available. The Scottish Executive&#8217;s aim is clearly set out in the Occupational Health and Safety Services Strategy <i>Towards a Safer Healthier Workplace</i> published in November 1999, which promoted an exemplar role for the NHSiS. The strategy also set out the minimum standard of service provision expected for staff of the NHSiS and advocated the development of clinical and audit networks to allow benchmarking and to ensure uniformly high standard occupational health throughout Scotland. An Occupational Health and Safety Service Strategy Implementation Group is currently being set up which will be responsible for ensuring the strategy action points are achieved; that includes a system of peer audit review and benchmarking.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6899.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6898">Occupational Health</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6899.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80209" speakername="Mr Duncan McNeil (Greenock and Inverclyde) (Lab)" spid="S1W-6899" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6898">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what plans it has to encourage greater use of the occupational health services provided by the NHSiS.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6899.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6898">

  <p>The Occupational Health and Safety Services Strategy <i>Towards a Safer Healthier Workplace</i> made clear that, as a source of trusted specialist advice on occupational health, the NHSiS should promote and facilitate the development of high quality occupational health with employers throughout Scotland.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6843.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6843">Organ Transplants</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6843.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80226" speakername="Nora Radcliffe (Gordon) (LD)" spid="S1W-6843" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6843">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many heart transplant operations have been carried out at the Scottish Cardio-Pulmonary Transplant Unit at Glasgow Royal Infirmary since it opened and how many patients survived for a period of (a) six months, (b) one year and (c) one to five years after their operation.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6843.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6843">

  <p>215 heart transplants have been carried out at the Scottish Heart Transplant Unit since it opened in 1992. Information on survival times is set out in the table below:</p>

  <p><table border="BORDER" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="2" width="100%">
<tr>
<td width="23%" valign="TOP">
<p>Survival period 
                </p></td>
<td width="21%" valign="TOP">
<p align="CENTER">Six months 
                </p></td>
<td width="25%" valign="TOP">
<p align="CENTER">One year 
                </p></td>
<td width="31%" valign="TOP">
<p align="CENTER">Five years 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="23%" valign="TOP"> </td>
<td width="21%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">159 
                </p></td>
<td width="25%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">132 
                </p></td>
<td width="31%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">43 
                </p></td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Statistics prepared by the UK Transplant Support Service Authority from the National Transplant Database maintained on behalf of the UK transplant community.</p>

  <p>As the answer to question S1W-6845 shows, the results are in line with outcomes in the UK generally.</p>

  <p>Analyses of survival in the context of transplantation relate to one of three events: graft survival, patient survival or transplant survival, which covers either graft failure or patient death. The analysis above is based on transplant survival.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6844.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6843">Organ Transplants</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6844.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80226" speakername="Nora Radcliffe (Gordon) (LD)" spid="S1W-6844" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6843">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many heart transplant operations have been carried out at the Scottish Cardio-Pulmonary Transplant Unit at Glasgow Royal Infirmary since it opened after being refused by other units in the UK and how many patients survived for a period of (a) six months, (b) one year and (c) one to five years after their operation.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6844.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6843">

  <p>Of the 215 heart transplant operations carried out in Glasgow since the Scottish Heart Transplant Unit opened in 1992, 49 involved hearts which had been retrieved from elsewhere in the UK, which meant they had been refused at least by the retrieval centre.</p>

  <p>The information on survival is set out in the table below:</p>

  <p><table border="BORDER" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="2" width="100%">
<tr>
<td width="23%" valign="TOP">
<p>Survival Period 
                </p></td>
<td width="19%" valign="TOP">
<p align="CENTER">Six months 
                </p></td>
<td width="28%" valign="TOP">
<p align="CENTER">One year 
                </p></td>
<td width="30%" valign="TOP">
<p align="CENTER">Five years 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="23%" valign="TOP"> </td>
<td width="19%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">31 
                </p></td>
<td width="28%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">25 
                </p></td>
<td width="30%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">6 
                </p></td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Statistics prepared by the UK Transplant Support Service Authority from the National Transplant Database maintained on behalf of the UK transplant community.</p>

  <p>The answer to question S1W-6843 explains the basis on which analyses of survival are calculated in the transplantation context. The above analysis is based on transplant survival.</p>

  <p>A heart would be refused by a unit because it did not have on its waiting list a patient for whom it would be a good match.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6845.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6843">Organ Transplants</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6845.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80226" speakername="Nora Radcliffe (Gordon) (LD)" spid="S1W-6845" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6843">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how the success ratio the Scottish Cardio-Pulmonary Transplant Unit at Glasgow Royal Infirmary compares with other units in the UK in terms of survival rates of (a) six months, (b) one year and (c) one to five years or (d) over five years.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6845.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6843">

  <p>The information is set out in the table below:</p>

  <p><table border="BORDER" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="2" width="100%">
<tr>
<td width="25%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p>Survival Period 
                </p></td>
<td width="36%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p align="CENTER">% Survival (Glasgow) 
                    
                </p></td>
<td width="39%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p align="CENTER">% Survival (Rest 
                    of UK) 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="25%" valign="TOP" height="10">
<p>6 months 
                </p></td>
<td width="36%" valign="TOP" height="10">
<p align="RIGHT">85.6% 
                </p></td>
<td width="39%" valign="TOP" height="10">
<p align="RIGHT">80.4% 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="25%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p>1 year 
                </p></td>
<td width="36%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p align="RIGHT">83.2% 
                </p></td>
<td width="39%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p align="RIGHT">77.4% 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="25%" valign="TOP">
<p>5 years 
                </p></td>
<td width="36%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">61.6% 
                </p></td>
<td width="39%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">64.6% 
                </p></td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Statistics prepared by UK Transplant Support Service Authority from the National Transplant Database maintained on behalf of the UK transplant community.</p>

  <p>The answer to question S1W-6843 explains the basis on which analyses of survival are calculated in the context of transplantation. The analysis above is based on transplant survival.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6847.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6843">Organ Transplants</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6847.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80226" speakername="Nora Radcliffe (Gordon) (LD)" spid="S1W-6847" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6843">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how it plans to manage the transfer of resources between Scottish health boards and English health authorities in cases where Scottish patients travel to England for heart transplant operations.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6847.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80146" speakername="Susan Deacon" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6843">

  <p>Heart transplantation is funded nationally, not by individual health boards. The money is channelled through the National Services Division (NSD) of the Common Services Agency, which has Service Agreements with each of the transplant units in England to cover any access required by Scottish residents.</p>

  <p>The Service Agreement with the Freeman Hospital in Newcastle will be adjusted to take account of the funding needed to cover the heart transplant operations performed there during the suspension of the Scottish service.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6964.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6964">Police</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6964.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80159" speakername="Phil Gallie (South of Scotland) (Con)" spid="S1W-6964" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6964">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive when the report on the pilot project on equipping the police with CS gas sprays will be available.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-6964.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80252" speakername="Mr Jim Wallace" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#6964">

  <p>The police report on the Scottish trial of CS incapacitant spray was published in November 1998. I am arranging for a copy of the report to be placed in the Scottish Parliament Information Centre.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-4592.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#4592">Prison Service</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-4592.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80220" speakername="Alex Neil (Central Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S1W-4592" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#4592">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many offences have been committed by prisoners in the past twelve months which have led to (a) internal disciplinary action, (b) a criminal charge being laid and (c) a criminal conviction, in Bowhouse Prison, Kilmarnock, Perth Prison, Peterhead Prison and Barlinnie Prison.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-4592.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80252" speakername="Mr Jim Wallace" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#4592">

  <p>The numbers of cases where disciplinary action has been taken against a prisoner in the above prisons are set out in the table. The Scottish Prison Service is not always informed, and has no records of, criminal charges being laid and convictions resulting from offences committed within prisons.</p>

  <p><table border="BORDER" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="2" width="100%">
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="TOP"> </td>
<td width="51%" valign="TOP">
<p align="CENTER">Disciplinary Action 
                    
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p>Kilmarnock 
                </p></td>
<td width="51%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p align="RIGHT">2,187 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="TOP">
<p>Perth 
                </p></td>
<td width="51%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">1,550 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="TOP">
<p>Peterhead 
                </p></td>
<td width="51%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">358 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="49%" valign="TOP">
<p>Barlinnie 
                </p></td>
<td width="51%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">1,186 
                </p></td>
</tr>
</table></p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-4594.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#4592">Prison Service</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-4594.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80220" speakername="Alex Neil (Central Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S1W-4594" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#4592">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will provide details of the capacity of and average number of prisoners detained in each prison during the last twelve months for which figures are available.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-4594.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80252" speakername="Mr Jim Wallace" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#4592">

  <p>The details requested are in the table below.</p>

  <p><table border="BORDER" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="2" width="100%">
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="26">
<p>Prisons 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="26">
<p align="CENTER">Design Capacity 
                    at 26 March 1999 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="26">
<p align="CENTER">Average Daily Prisoner 
                    Population 1998-99<sup>1</sup>
</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="8">
<p>Aberdeen 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="8">
<p align="RIGHT">163 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="8">
<p align="RIGHT">181 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="11">
<p>Barlinnie 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="11">
<p align="RIGHT">943 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="11">
<p align="RIGHT">1,124 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="14">
<p>Castle Huntly 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="14">
<p align="RIGHT">150 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="14">
<p align="RIGHT">106 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="7">
<p>Cornton Vale 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="7">
<p align="RIGHT">217 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="7">
<p align="RIGHT">180 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p>Dumfries 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p align="RIGHT">150 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p align="RIGHT">137 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="14">
<p>Dungavel 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="14">
<p align="RIGHT">135 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="14">
<p align="RIGHT">113 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="6">
<p>Edinburgh 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="6">
<p align="RIGHT">637 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="6">
<p align="RIGHT">731 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="9">
<p>Friarton 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="9">
<p align="RIGHT">90 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="9">
<p align="RIGHT">77 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="12">
<p>Glenochil 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="12">
<p align="RIGHT">670 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="12">
<p align="RIGHT">573 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="15">
<p>Greenock 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="15">
<p align="RIGHT">233 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="15">
<p align="RIGHT">236 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="8">
<p>Inverness 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="8">
<p align="RIGHT">107 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="8">
<p align="RIGHT">122 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p>Kilmarnock 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p align="RIGHT">500 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p align="RIGHT">*1 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="14">
<p>Longriggend 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="14">
<p align="RIGHT">176 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="14">
<p align="RIGHT">158 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="8">
<p>Low Moss 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="8">
<p align="RIGHT">396 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="8">
<p align="RIGHT">362 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="11">
<p>Noranside 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="11">
<p align="RIGHT">135 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="11">
<p align="RIGHT">102 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="13">
<p>Penninghame 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="13">
<p align="RIGHT">98 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="13">
<p align="RIGHT">89 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="7">
<p>Perth 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="7">
<p align="RIGHT">436 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="7">
<p align="RIGHT">477 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="10">
<p>Peterhead (inc. Unit) 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="10">
<p align="RIGHT">305 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="10">
<p align="RIGHT">297 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="13">
<p>Polmont 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="13">
<p align="RIGHT">422 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="13">
<p align="RIGHT">443 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p>Shotts (inc. Unit) 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p align="RIGHT">474 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p align="RIGHT">467 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="9">
<p>Shotts NIC 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="9">
<p align="RIGHT">54 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="9">
<p align="RIGHT">48 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p>Legalised Police Cells 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p></p>
</td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p align="RIGHT">1 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="34%" valign="TOP" height="5">
<p>TOTAL 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="5">
<p align="RIGHT">6,491 
                </p></td>
<td width="33%" valign="TOP" height="5">
<p align="RIGHT">6,029 
                </p></td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>* HMP Kilmarnock opened in March 1999, the first intake of prisoners was on 25 March.</p>

  <p>Notes:</p>

  <p>1. These figures are published in the <i>Scottish Prison Service Annual Report and Accounts</i> for 1998-99 which was laid before the Scottish Parliament by the Scottish Ministers in July 1999.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5802.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#4592">Prison Service</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5802.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80262" speakername="Dorothy-Grace Elder (Glasgow) (SNP)" spid="S1W-5802" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#4592">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether any discussions are being held on the future of Barlinnie Prison in Glasgow and the possible sale of the site of the prison.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5802.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80252" speakername="Mr Jim Wallace" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#4592">

  <p>The Scottish Prison Service are conducting a fundamental review of their estate to identify likely future pressures and needs over the long term and to generate options for meeting these. This process involves detailed consideration of the role and condition of every SPS establishment, including Barlinnie.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5545.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#5545">Protection of Wild Mammals (Scotland) Bill</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5545.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80217" speakername="David Mundell (South of Scotland) (Con)" spid="S1W-5545" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#5545">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it has carried out or intends to carry out any evaluation of the likely impact on police resources of the passing of the Protection of Wild Mammals (Scotland) Bill.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5545.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80252" speakername="Mr Jim Wallace" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#5545">

  <p>We have no plans to carry out such an evaluation.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7019.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7019">Renewable Energy</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7019.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80236" speakername="Tavish Scott (Shetland) (LD)" spid="S1W-7019" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7019">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what targets are in place for the generation of solar energy in Scotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7019.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80134" speakername="Sarah Boyack" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7019">

  <p>The consultation exercise currently under way on the Scottish Climate Change Programme prepossess that between 2003 and 2010 the share of Scotland&#8217;s energy consumption met from renewable sources will increase by 5%. This will take the form of an obligation on all electricity suppliers to meet that target and, under the Utilities Bill, once enacted there will be no statutory powers to enable targets to be set for any specific renewable technology.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7021.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7019">Renewable Energy</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7021.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80236" speakername="Tavish Scott (Shetland) (LD)" spid="S1W-7021" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7019">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it monitors the use of active solar heating systems in Scotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7021.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80134" speakername="Sarah Boyack" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7019">

  <p>The Scottish Executive is committed to the promotion of renewable sources of energy. There is, however, no monitoring of the use of active solar heating systems in Scotland, but we are keen to see solar energy play a part in contributing to the use of renewable energy.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7031.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7031">Roads</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7031.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80261" speakername="Lord James Douglas-Hamilton (Lothians) (Con)" spid="S1W-7031" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7031">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it has been made aware in the information provided by Midlothian Council of any possible geological or instability problems on the proposed route of the A701 upgrade.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7031.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80134" speakername="Sarah Boyack" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7031">

  <p>The Environmental Statement (ES) which accompanied the Notice of Intention to Develop came to the conclusion that the proposals were unlikely to have any significant effect on the geology and geomorphology of the area. There was also no suggestion in the ES of any likely instability problems.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7035.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7031">Roads</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7035.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80261" speakername="Lord James Douglas-Hamilton (Lothians) (Con)" spid="S1W-7035" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7031">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what details relating to the geological state of the Clippens landfill site and substances contained within it were supplied to it in the notice of intention to develop the A701 received from Midlothian Council.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7035.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80134" speakername="Sarah Boyack" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7031">

  <p>The statement from Midlothian Council which accompanied the Notice of Intention to Develop indicates that the site investigation into the former Clippens landfill site broadly confirmed that landfill gases are absent, or present only at low levels. The statement also indicates that the design of the new route minimises excavation works in the vicinity of Clippens and notes that, if any contaminated material is excavated, it will be removed to a suitable licensed disposal site and disposed of in accordance with waste management regulations.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7036.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7031">Roads</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7036.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80261" speakername="Lord James Douglas-Hamilton (Lothians) (Con)" spid="S1W-7036" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7031">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it received and gave consideration to any objections detailing geological problems or contamination of the Clippens landfill site on the route of the A701.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7036.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80134" speakername="Sarah Boyack" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7031">

  <p>No. The Scottish Executive did not receive any objections detailing geological problems or contamination of the Clippens landfill site in relation to the Notice of Intention to Develop in respect of proposed improvements to the A701.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7037.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7031">Roads</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7037.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80261" speakername="Lord James Douglas-Hamilton (Lothians) (Con)" spid="S1W-7037" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7031">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what guidance it has given or intends to give Midlothian Council on issues relating to safety on the proposed A701 route following the emergence of a crater.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7037.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80134" speakername="Sarah Boyack" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7031">

  <p>National guidance sets out rigorous procedures in respect of the geotechnical aspects of the construction of new roads and it is entirely for Midlothian Council to take account of this guidance in respect of the construction of the proposed A701.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7029.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7029">Rural Affairs</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7029.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80236" speakername="Tavish Scott (Shetland) (LD)" spid="S1W-7029" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7029">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what progress is being made in developing an area-based scheme of Hill Livestock Compensation Allowances to be implemented on 1 January 2001.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7029.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80155" speakername="Ross Finnie" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7029">

  <p>Proposals for a new Less-Favoured Area based scheme were put to the European Commission in late December as part of the Scottish Executive&#8217;s Rural Development Plan. A response is now being prepared to points of principle and detail raised by the Commission.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7095.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7029">Rural Affairs</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7095.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80203" speakername="Irene McGugan (North-East Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S1W-7095" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7029">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, further to the answer to S1O-1596 by Mr Ross Finnie on 4 May 2000, what other avenues of support are being explored in respect of the Scottish Berry Project.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7095.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80203" speakername="Irene McGugan (North-East Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S1W-7096" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7029">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, further to the answer to question S1O-1596 by Ross Finnie on 4 May 2000, when it anticipates that the Scottish Berry Project might be actioned.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7095.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80155" speakername="Ross Finnie" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7029">

  <p>My officials discussed the project with the Scottish Soft Fruit Growers on 23 May. As a result of these discussions SSFG have been invited to reconsider their original proposals and to put forward revised proposals for a pilot study.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5343.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#5343">Sign Language</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5343.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80149" speakername="Dr Winnie Ewing (Highlands and Islands) (SNP)" spid="S1W-5343" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#5343">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what legal or other status British sign language has in Scottish courts.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5343.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80252" speakername="Mr Jim Wallace" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#5343">

  <p>A person with hearing difficulties who understands the nature of an oath is treated as an ordinary witness, except that he/she is sworn and their evidence is taken through an interpreter using the deaf and dumb alphabet, or by other signs which can be understood. The court has a duty to ensure that persons appearing before it either as accused persons or as witnesses are able to understand the proceedings. In criminal cases the Procurator Fiscal arranges the attendance of an appropriate interpreter/signer and in civil cases this responsibility falls to the party requiring the service.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7118.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7118">Student Finance</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7118.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80236" speakername="Tavish Scott (Shetland) (LD)" spid="S1W-7118" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7118">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what discussions it has had with the Student Awards Agency on its policy for the payment of travel costs faced by students from the Scottish Islands.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7118.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7118">

  <p>The Scottish Executive has had no recent discussions with the Student Awards Agency for Scotland about the arrangements for reimbursing excess travel costs to students in higher education, which have been in place for many years and in our view work well.</p>

  <p>However, I am always keen to learn of particular areas of concern about the way in which the student support system impacts on students. The Executive is currently consulting on its plans for changes to the system from academic year 2001-02 in the light of the publication of <i>Scotland: The Learning Nation - Helping Students</i>. I am happy to receive any views on the issue of reimbursing travel costs as part of that process.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7044.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7044">Task Forces</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7044.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80150" speakername="Fergus Ewing (Inverness East, Nairn and Lochaber) (SNP)" spid="S1W-7044" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7044">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what its estimate is of the number of jobs created or preserved by each of its task forces since July 1999.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7044.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80205" speakername="Henry McLeish" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7044">

  <p>Of the eight task forces set up or continued by the Scottish Executive, only the Knowledge Economy and the Digital Scotland Task Forces have aims which include encouraging economic development. However in neither case would it be appropriate to link the activities of the task forces directly with particular numbers of jobs created or safeguarded.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7137.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7137">Transport</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7137.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80262" speakername="Dorothy-Grace Elder (Glasgow) (SNP)" spid="S1W-7137" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7137">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what effect existing bus/taxi/cycle lanes and gates have had on small businesses and private hire cars in Glasgow since their introduction.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7137.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80134" speakername="Sarah Boyack" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7137">

  <p>The operation of bus/taxi/cycle lanes and gates in Glasgow is a matter for Glasgow City Council. No studies have been carried out by the Scottish Executive on the effect of these traffic management measures on small businesses and private hire cars.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5696.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#5696">Victim Support</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5696.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80133" speakername="Scott Barrie (Dunfermline West) (Lab)" spid="S1W-5696" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#5696">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether there are any plans to fund local victim support schemes from a central budget.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-5696.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80252" speakername="Mr Jim Wallace" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#5696">

  <p>The Scottish Executive is the major source of funding for Victim Support Scotland local schemes. For 2000-01, the Executive has made available grant of &pound;1.213 million for local victim support services from central funds under the provisions of section 10(1) of the Social Work (Scotland) Act 1968. This represents an increase of 8.6% over the previous year's figure.</p>

</reply>


<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.3.mh" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#5696">Scottish Parliamentary Corporate Body</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7008.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7008">Holyrood Project</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7008.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80164" speakername="Donald Gorrie (Central Scotland) (LD)" spid="S1W-7008" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7008">

  <p>To ask the Presiding Officer (a) when the plans for the Holyrood site were, or will be, signed off; (b) when and how these plans will be available for inspection by MSPs and the public; (c) when the Holyrood progress group will meet, and (d) whether the Holyrood progress group will consist of professionals in the construction field or of MSPs or both.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7008.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80277" speakername="Sir David Steel" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7008">

  <p>It is intended that the Stage &quot;D&quot; plans will be signed off this month. The plans are available for public inspection now at the City of Edinburgh Council Planning Department, 1 Cockburn Street, Edinburgh. The SPCB will make another report to members very shortly. The Progress Group is in the process of being appointed. The exact make-up in terms of political and professional representation has not yet been finalised though it will, of course, reflect the terms of the resolution passed by the Parliament on 5 April. The group will meet together with the SPCB next week.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7009.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7008">Holyrood Project</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7009.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80164" speakername="Donald Gorrie (Central Scotland) (LD)" spid="S1W-7009" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7008">

  <p>To ask the Presiding Officer what categories of expenditure are included in the &pound;195 million cost limit approved by the Parliament for the new Parliament buildings at Holyrood.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7009.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80277" speakername="Sir David Steel" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#7008">

  <p>The information is provided in the following table:</p>

  <p><table border="BORDER" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="2" width="100%">
<tr>
<td width="75%" valign="TOP">
<p>Category 
                </p></td>
<td width="25%" valign="TOP">
<p align="CENTER">&pound; million 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="75%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p>Site acquisition, demolition 
                    and archaeology 
                </p></td>
<td width="25%" valign="TOP" height="4">
<p align="RIGHT">5.0 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="75%" valign="TOP">
<p>Construction estimate 
                </p></td>
<td width="25%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">108.0 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="75%" valign="TOP">
<p>Contingencies on construction, 
                    fees, site organisation costs &amp; VAT 
                </p></td>
<td width="25%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">62.5 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="75%" valign="TOP">
<p>Total site and construction costs 
                    
                </p></td>
<td width="25%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">175.5 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="75%" valign="TOP">
<p>Fit out (including VAT &amp; 
                    Fees) 
                </p></td>
<td width="25%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">19.5 
                </p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="75%" valign="TOP">
<p>Total 
                </p></td>
<td width="25%" valign="TOP">
<p align="RIGHT">195.0 
                </p></td>
</tr>
</table></p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7010.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#QuestionText">Holyrood Project</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7010.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80164" speakername="Donald Gorrie (Central Scotland) (LD)" spid="S1W-7010" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#QuestionText">

  <p>To ask the Presiding Officer <a name="QuestionText">(a) which elements of expenditure relevant to the new parliamentary buildings at Holyrood are not included in the &pound;195 million cost limit agreed by the Parliament; (b) what the current cost estimate for these elements is, and (c) which organisation is expected to pay for each of these costs.</a></p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2000-06-02.S1W-7010.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80277" speakername="Sir David Steel" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-00/wa0602.htm#QuestionText">

  <p>The running costs of the Holyrood Project Team are just under &pound;480,000 for 2000-01. The current cost estimate for the Project Team&#8217;s &quot;on site&quot; accommodation, which is provided on a rental basis, is around &pound;590,000 to the end of December 2002. The Holyrood Project also has a budget for 2000-01 of &pound;240,000 to fund non-capital items related to the project such as newsletters, upgrading models etc. All of these items are met from the Parliaments annual &quot;running cost&quot; budget.</p>

  <p>Consideration is also being given to various options available for the fit out of a public exhibition and the provision of a viewing gallery at the Holyrood site, although no firm estimates are yet available. The cost of landscaping external to the site is a matter for the Scottish Executive. None of the above costs are included in the &pound;195 million<br /></p>

</reply>
</publicwhip>