<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE publicwhip [

<!ENTITY pound   "&#163;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">

<!ENTITY agrave  "&#224;">
<!ENTITY aacute  "&#225;">
<!ENTITY egrave  "&#232;">
<!ENTITY eacute  "&#233;">
<!ENTITY ecirc   "&#234;">
<!ENTITY iacute  "&#237;">
<!ENTITY ograve  "&#242;">
<!ENTITY oacute  "&#243;">
<!ENTITY uacute  "&#250;">
<!ENTITY Aacute  "&#193;">
<!ENTITY Eacute  "&#201;">
<!ENTITY Iacute  "&#205;">
<!ENTITY Oacute  "&#211;">
<!ENTITY Uacute  "&#218;">
<!ENTITY Uuml    "&#220;">
<!ENTITY auml    "&#228;">
<!ENTITY euml    "&#235;">
<!ENTITY iuml    "&#239;">
<!ENTITY ouml    "&#246;">
<!ENTITY uuml    "&#252;">
<!ENTITY fnof    "&#402;">
<!ENTITY aelig   "&#230;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">
<!ENTITY reg     "&#174;">
<!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
<!ENTITY shy     "&#173;">
<!ENTITY deg     "&#176;">
<!ENTITY middot  "&#183;">
<!ENTITY ordm    "&#186;">
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY hellip  "&#8230;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">

<!ENTITY acirc   "&#226;">
<!ENTITY Agrave  "&#192;">
<!ENTITY Aring   "&#197;">
<!ENTITY aring   "&#229;">
<!ENTITY atilde  "&#227;">
<!ENTITY Ccedil  "&#199;">
<!ENTITY ccedil  "&#231;">
<!ENTITY Egrave  "&#200;">
<!ENTITY Icirc   "&#206;">
<!ENTITY icirc   "&#238;">
<!ENTITY Igrave  "&#204;">
<!ENTITY igrave  "&#236;">
<!ENTITY ntilde  "&#241;">
<!ENTITY ocirc   "&#244;">
<!ENTITY oelig   "&#339;">
<!ENTITY Ograve  "&#210;">
<!ENTITY Oslash  "&#216;">
<!ENTITY oslash  "&#248;">
<!ENTITY Scaron  "&#352;">
<!ENTITY scaron  "&#353;">
<!ENTITY sup1    "&#185;">
<!ENTITY sup2    "&#178;">
<!ENTITY sup3    "&#179;">
<!ENTITY ugrave  "&#249;">
<!ENTITY Ugrave  "&#217;">
<!ENTITY yacute  "&#253;">
<!ENTITY frac12  "&#189;">
<!ENTITY micro   "&#181;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8225;">
]>

<publicwhip>

<source url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm"/>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.0.mh" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm">Scottish Executive</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.1.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#1">Agriculture</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.1.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80037" speakername="Karen Gillon (Clydesdale) (Lab)" spid="S2W-3029" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#1">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what measures it is taking to encourage organic farming.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.1.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80032" speakername="Ross Finnie" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#1">

  <p>The Organic Action Plan published in February 2003 sets out the Scottish Executive&#8217;s intentions for future action to support the development of the organic sector in Scotland. It commits the Executive to a series of actions, which will deliver the Forward Strategy for Scottish Agriculture&#8217;s priorities for the organic sector.</p>

  <p>In consultation with key stakeholders, I announced in August of this year proposed improvements to the way we support organic farming, including increased payment rates for the conversion of good-quality land to organic status and continuing financial support after the conversion period. Subject to European Commission and Scottish Parliament approval, I intend to introduce these improvements from 1 April 2004.</p>

  <p>The Scottish Executive gives priority to organic projects under its processing and marketing grants scheme and marketing development scheme. As an example, out of the &#163;11.9 million of funding for the lowland agricultural processing and marketing grant scheme, 44% of this funding has gone to projects with an organic processing and marketing element.</p>

  <p>The Scottish Executive has recently commissioned a study to identify areas of research need for the organic farming market to function effectively in Scotland.</p>

  <p>The Scottish Executive also funds the Scottish Agricultural College to operate an &quot;Organic Helpline&quot; providing free advice to farmers wishing to convert to organic farming.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.2.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#2">Children and Young People</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.2.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80043" speakername="Christine Grahame (South of Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S2W-3002" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#2">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what steps it will take, with schools and colleges, to educate pupils and students in foster care issues in order to reduce ignorance of the circumstances of fostered children.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.2.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80105" speakername="Euan Robson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#2">

  <p>Schools have designated teachers whose role is to champion the interests of looked after children in their school and act as an information point within the school for others to aid their understanding of what it means to be looked after. Seminars for designated teachers will be held in December to share best practice and start a network of such teachers to provide support and information.</p>

  <p>The Fostering Network also undertake training in individual schools to educate young people and teachers on fostering issues.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.3.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#3">Conservation</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.3.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80016" speakername="Ms Rosemary Byrne (South of Scotland) (SSP)" spid="S2W-3079" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#3">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what its policy is with regard to protection of raised bogs.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.3.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80128" speakername="Allan Wilson" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#3">

  <p>Raised bogs are listed in Annex I of the EC Habitats Directive as a habitat for which Special Areas of Conservation (SACs) must be designated. The Scottish Executive is committed to meeting its obligations under the Habitats Directive and has designated 27 raised bog SACs. A further 38 raised bogs are afforded domestic UK protection through designation as Sites of Special Scientific Interest in Scotland.</p>

  <p>The UK Biodiversity Action Plan identifies raised bog as a priority habitat and a specific Lowland Raised Bog Action Plan has been developed. As lead partner for the Lowland Bog Action Plan, Scottish National Heritage is also engaged in promoting raised bog conservation through the relevant Local Biodiversity Action Partnerships.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.4.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#4">Drug Misuse</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.4.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80118" speakername="Nicola Sturgeon (Glasgow) (SNP)" spid="S2W-2991" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#4">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how much funding drug action teams (DATs) will be awarded in (a) 2003-04 and (b) future financial years for which figures are available.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.4.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80046" speakername="Hugh Henry" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#4">

  <p>The operation of drug action teams (DATs) is supported by &#163;1.5 million of funding in this financial year, allocated via NHS boards. Resources for future years have not yet been confirmed.</p>

  <p>Resources to tackle drug misuse are allocated through a number of different funding streams, much of which cannot be separately identified as it is spent through generic expenditure programmes e.g. social work services; enforcement and criminal justice activities, including prisons; prevention and education programmes; employability initiatives and funding to support communities.</p>

  <p>However, the following table shows the main drug-specific allocations to NHS boards and local authorities in 2003-04. Decisions on funding for 2004-05 have not yet been finalised.</p>

  <p><table width="100%" border="border" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0">
<tr>
<td valign="TOP"> <p>2003-04 Funding</p></td>
<td valign="TOP"> <p style="text-align: center">Drug Misuse 
                      Treatment</p></td>
<td valign="TOP"> <p style="text-align: center">Rehabilitation</p></td>
<td valign="TOP"> <p style="text-align: center">Changing Children&#8217;s 
                      Services Fund</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="TOP"> <p>Total (&#163; million)</p></td>
<td valign="TOP"> <p style="text-align: right">16.952*</p></td>
<td valign="TOP"> <p style="text-align: right">6.8</p></td>
<td valign="TOP"> <p style="text-align: right">8.0</p></td>
</tr>
</table></p>

  <p>Note:</p>

  <p>*Funding does not include additional resources of &#163;500,000 allocated to Greater Glasgow NHS Board to meet the treatment costs of the Glasgow Drug Court pilot.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.5.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#5">European Union</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.5.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80061" speakername="Richard Lochhead (North East Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S2W-3172" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#5">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive, further to the answer to question S1W-34840 by Mr Jim Wallace on 31 March 2003, what proportion of formal meetings of the Council of Ministers have been attended by its ministers this year.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.5.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80057" speakername="Mr Andy Kerr" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#5">

  <p>Scottish Executive ministers have attended six out of 39 formal meetings of EU Councils in the period January to September 2003.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.6.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#6">Fire Service</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.6.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80063" speakername="Mr Kenny MacAskill (Lothians) (SNP)" spid="S2W-3028" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#6">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what the fuel costs for each fire brigade have been in each year since 1997, broken down by local authority area.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.6.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80046" speakername="Hugh Henry" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#6">

  <p>This information is not held centrally.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.7.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#7">Fisheries</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.7.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80061" speakername="Richard Lochhead (North East Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S2W-2636" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#7" holdingdate="2003-09-29">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what progress has been made in persuading the European Commission to support a significant reduction in industrial fishing in the North sea.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.7.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80032" speakername="Ross Finnie" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#7">

  <p>The Scottish Executive remains concerned about the scale of industrial fishing and its potential impact on the marine ecosystem and has been active in discussing future management options.</p>

  <p>In the course of this year, we have sought progress on two fronts.</p>

  <p>As a result of bilateral discussions with Denmark, representations have been made to the Commission to extend the sandeel fishery closure in the &quot;Wee Bankie&quot; area for a further three years. The Commission is, we understand, minded to agree.</p>

  <p>More generally, the UK Fisheries Conservation Group (which brings together relevant administrations, and industry and other representatives) held a seminar in May on all issues relating to industrial fishing. Following this seminar a paper was produced for the European Commission.</p>

  <p>For the future, we now await the Commission&#8217;s specific proposals for the relevant Total Allowable Catches (TACs) for agreement at the December council. It is noteworthy that the International Council for the Exploration of the Sea appears to be implying that TACs in certain industrial fisheries (such as that for sandeels) should be reduced significantly.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.8.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#8">Health</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.8.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80088" speakername="Mr Brian Monteith (Mid Scotland and Fife) (Con)" spid="S2W-3012" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#8">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many deaths there have been due to clinical error, negligence, misdiagnosis or other causes that may be attributed to the actions of doctors and clinicians in each of the last three years.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.8.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80018" speakername="Malcolm Chisholm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#8">

  <p>This information is not held centrally.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.9.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#9">Justice</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.9.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80009" speakername="Scott Barrie (Dunfermline West) (Lab)" spid="S2W-3114" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#9">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether guidance issued to Procurators Fiscal encourages the prosecution of licensees charged with selling alcohol to minors.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.9.r0" speakerid="unknown" speakername="Mrs Elish Angiolini" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#9">

  <p>Procurators Fiscal consider all cases reported to them on their individual merits. To assist Procurators Fiscal in their consideration of cases, confidential, internal guidance is provided in relation to a range of issues. Proceedings will be commenced if there is sufficient reliable and credible evidence, and it is in the public interest to do so. As stated in our prosecution code, the assessment of the public interest necessarily includes consideration of public concern and local community interests.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.10.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#10">Mental Health</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.10.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80000" speakername="Brian Adam (Aberdeen North) (SNP)" spid="S2W-2190" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#10" holdingdate="2003-09-23">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether it will extend the range of illnesses that qualify for free prescriptions to include schizophrenia.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.10.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80018" speakername="Malcolm Chisholm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#10">

  <p>The Executive is committed to reviewing NHS prescription charges for people with chronic health conditions and young people in full-time education or training. The detailed remit of the review is still under consideration and the consultation process has yet to be determined. Whatever the exact shape of the review, it is our firm intention to consult widely with patient interest groups, NHS professionals and other key stakeholders. When the review process is completed, the Executive will consider whether changes should be made to the current prescription charge exemption and remission arrangements.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.11.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#11">Ministerial Correspondence</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.11.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80116" speakername="Stewart Stevenson (Banff and Buchan) (SNP)" spid="S2W-2979" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#11">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive when the Minister for Transport will respond to my letter dated 26 August 2003 regarding flooding problems at Stirling Village, Peterhead.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.11.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80115" speakername="Nicol Stephen" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#11">

  <p>I replied to your letter on 3 October 2003.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.12.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#12">Ministerial Visits</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.12.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80061" speakername="Richard Lochhead (North East Scotland) (SNP)" spid="S2W-3173" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#12">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many visits there have been by ministers to (a) Brussels, (b) London and (c) other locations outwith Scotland in each of the last four years and this year, expressed also as a percentage of ministerial visits outwith Scotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.12.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80057" speakername="Mr Andy Kerr" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#12">

  <p>I refer the member to the answers given to questions S1W-29052 on 9 September 2002 and S2W-2904 on 25 September 2003. These answers set out details of all overseas engagements carried out by Scottish Executive ministers from July 1999 to March 2003. All answers to written parliamentary questions are available on the Parliament&#8217;s website, the search facility for which can be found at <a title="Search Written Answers" href="wa0103.htm">http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/webapp/wa.search</a> "> <a href="/webapp/wa.search">http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/webapp/wa.search</a> .</p>

  <p>The Scottish Executive does not hold records of ministerial visits within the United Kingdom.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.13.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#13">NHS Staff</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.13.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80088" speakername="Mr Brian Monteith (Mid Scotland and Fife) (Con)" spid="S2W-3011" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#13">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many doctors and clinicians have been employed by the NHS in each year since 2000.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.13.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80018" speakername="Malcolm Chisholm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#13">

  <p>The information requested is published on the website of the Information and Statistics Division of NHSScotland. Scottish health statistics can be accessed via the following link: http://www.isdscotland.org/isd.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.14.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#14">Renewable Energy</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.14.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80036" speakername="Mr Rob Gibson (Highlands and Islands) (SNP)" spid="S2W-3023" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#14">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether its &#163;2.125 million investment in the Marine Energy Test Centre, off Orkney, will enable Ocean Power Delivery Ltd&#8217;s Pelamis wave energy project to be ready for commercial application on schedule.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.14.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80064" speakername="Lewis Macdonald" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#14">

  <p>The Marine Energy Test Centre will allow Scotland&#8217;s fledgling marine industry to test, accredit, and showcase its products for the burgeoning world market. Ocean Power Delivery Ltd&#8217;s Pelamis device will be the first device to be installed in the centre later this year. Issues relating to the commercial deployment of the device thereafter are a matter for the company.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.15.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#14">Renewable Energy</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.15.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80036" speakername="Mr Rob Gibson (Highlands and Islands) (SNP)" spid="S2W-3024" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#14">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what level of market incentives it is offering to renewable energy firms for projects such as Ocean Power Delivery Ltd&#8217;s Pelamis project to make commercial application of their research in Scotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.15.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80064" speakername="Lewis Macdonald" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#14">

  <p>The Scottish Executive introduced the Renewables Obligation Scotland (ROS) in April 2002. Under the ROS, all licensed electricity suppliers are obliged to source increasing amounts of their electricity from qualifying renewable sources.</p>

  <p>In order to comply with their obligation, suppliers can buy Renewable Obligation Certificates (ROCs) from renewable generators and provide these to the industry regulator, Ofgem, as proof that they have met their obligation. Alternatively, suppliers may choose to pay to Ofgem thirty pounds for each megawatt hour of electricity for which they do not produce a ROC. As a result, renewable generators such as Ocean Power Delivery can gain additional income by selling ROCs in addition to the electrical output which their plants generate.</p>

  <p>The additional costs imposed upon electricity suppliers under the ROS, estimated to reach around 4-5% by 2010, are met by all electricity consumers.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.16.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#15">Roads</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.16.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80087" speakername="Margaret Mitchell (Central Scotland) (Con)" spid="S2W-3013" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#15">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how long the temporary traffic arrangements at the Shawhead Interchange will be in place and what plans it has to alleviate any congestion and traffic flow problems that have arisen as a result of such arrangements.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.16.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80115" speakername="Nicol Stephen" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#15">

  <p>The temporary traffic arrangements will be necessary until the upgrading is completed in December. The design of these arrangements and regular on-going consultation with Strathclyde Police, Amey Highways and North Lanarkshire Council are intended to alleviate congestion and traffic flow problems arising from the works.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.17.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">Social Inclusion Partnerships</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.17.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80015" speakername="Bill Butler (Glasgow Anniesland) (Lab)" spid="S2W-3125" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether any social inclusion partnership (SIP) in Glasgow has ever been investigated for fraud.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.17.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80022" speakername="Ms Margaret Curran" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">

  <p>I have asked Angiolina Foster, Acting Chief Executive of Communities Scotland to respond. Her response is as follows:</p>

  <p>Glasgow City Council is the accountable body for the SIPs in Glasgow and handles all financial matters. While the city council has carried out investigations into individual SIP-funded projects in the city, no SIP in Glasgow has ever been investigated for fraud.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.18.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">Social Inclusion Partnerships</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.18.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80015" speakername="Bill Butler (Glasgow Anniesland) (Lab)" spid="S2W-3126" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive whether any social inclusion partnership (SIP) has ever been investigated for fraud.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.18.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80022" speakername="Ms Margaret Curran" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">

  <p>I have asked Angiolina Foster, Acting Chief Executive of Communities Scotland to respond. Her response is as follows:</p>

  <p>Councils are the accountable bodies for SIPs and handle all financial matters. While some councils have carried out investigations into individual SIP funded projects, no SIP has ever been investigated for fraud.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.19.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">Social Inclusion Partnerships</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.19.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80015" speakername="Bill Butler (Glasgow Anniesland) (Lab)" spid="S2W-3127" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many projects received social inclusion partnership (SIP) funding in Glasgow in 2002-03.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.19.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80022" speakername="Ms Margaret Curran" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">

  <p>I have asked Angiolina Foster, acting Chief Executive of Communities Scotland, to respond. Her response is as follows.</p>

  <p>Following a recent analysis of the final grant claim for the core SIP fund, I can confirm that 577 projects were funded during 2002-03.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.20.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">Social Inclusion Partnerships</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.20.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80015" speakername="Bill Butler (Glasgow Anniesland) (Lab)" spid="S2W-3128" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how many projects received social inclusion partnership (SIP) funding in 2002-03.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.20.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80022" speakername="Ms Margaret Curran" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">

  <p>I have asked Angiolina Foster, acting Chief Executive of Communities Scotland, to respond. Her response is as follows.</p>

  <p>Following a recent analysis of the final grant claims for the core SIP fund submitted by SIP fund grant recipients across the network of 48 SIPs in Scotland, I can confirm that over 1,300 projects were funded during 2002-03.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.21.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">Social Inclusion Partnerships</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.21.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80015" speakername="Bill Butler (Glasgow Anniesland) (Lab)" spid="S2W-3129" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what arrangements are in place in Glasgow to monitor the financial and administrative performance of social inclusion partnerships (SIPs) and the projects that they fund.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.21.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80022" speakername="Ms Margaret Curran" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">

  <p>I have asked Angiolina Foster, acting Chief Executive of Communities Scotland, to respond. Her response is as follows:</p>

  <p>A monitoring framework has been in place since 1999, which sets out the relevant administrative arrangements and responsibilities for all SIPs in Scotland. In addition, local authorities in their role as SIP fund grant recipients must adhere to the SIP fund terms and conditions. Additional financial guidance also sets out the financial roles and responsibilities. All three documents are available on the Communities Scotland website www.communitiesscotland.gov.uk.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.22.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">Social Inclusion Partnerships</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.22.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80015" speakername="Bill Butler (Glasgow Anniesland) (Lab)" spid="S2W-3130" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what arrangements are in place to monitor the financial and administrative performance of social inclusion partnerships and the projects that they fund.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.22.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80022" speakername="Ms Margaret Curran" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">

  <p>I have asked Angiolina Foster, acting Chief Executive of Communities Scotland, to respond. Her response is as follows:</p>

  <p>I refer the member to the answer given to S2W-1329 on 28 July 2003, which is available on the Parliament&#8217;s website the search facility for which can be found at:</p>

  <p><a title="Search Written Answers" href="wa0103.htm">http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/webapp/wa.search</a>"><a href="/webapp/wa.search">http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/webapp/wa.search</a>.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.23.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">Social Inclusion Partnerships</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.23.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80015" speakername="Bill Butler (Glasgow Anniesland) (Lab)" spid="S2W-3133" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how social inclusion partnership (SIP) boards in Glasgow are constituted and how these arrangements ensure that the community is represented.</p>

</ques>


<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.23.q1" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80015" speakername="Bill Butler (Glasgow Anniesland) (Lab)" spid="S2W-3134" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive how the social inclusion partnership boards are constituted and how the arrangements ensure that the community is represented.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.23.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80022" speakername="Ms Margaret Curran" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">

  <p>I have asked Angiolina Foster, acting Chief Executive of Communities Scotland, to respond. Her response is as follows:</p>

  <p>There is no one prescribed manner in which Social Inclusion Partnership Boards should be constituted. Broad guidance was, however, provided in the initial letter sent by the Scottish Office to local authorities on 28 July 1998 inviting expressions of interest for participation in the SIP Programme. This letter advised that SIPs would be expected to demonstrate:</p>

  <p>the commitment of all the relevant local partners, including representatives of the voluntary and private sector, and</p>

  <p>the involvement of the local community at the heart of the process.</p>

  <p>Regarding community representation on SIP Boards, the SIP Monitoring Framework requires SIPs to provide factual evidence of community involvement in the work of the SIP as part of the annual reports submitted to Communities Scotland in June each year. Communities Scotland uses these reports, along with other measures such as formal appraisals and visits to SIPs to ensure that communities are appropriately represented on SIP boards and fully engaged in all aspects of the work of partnerships.</p>

  <p>Those SIPs in Glasgow managed by the Glasgow Alliance are subject to specific provisions within the Alliance&#8217;s &quot;Rules of Procedure&quot; for SIP boards. These ensure that communities are both represented on SIP boards and that board meetings cannot proceed unless the community is represented.</p>

</reply>


<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.24.h" nospeaker="True" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">Telecommunications</minor-heading>

<ques id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.24.q0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80012" speakername="Mr Ted Brocklebank (Mid Scotland and Fife) (Con)" spid="S2W-3009" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">

  <p>To ask the Scottish Executive what plans it has to monitor emissions of existing terrestrial trunked radio masts throughout Scotland.</p>

</ques>


<reply id="uk.org.publicwhip/spwa/2003-10-28.24.r0" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/80018" speakername="Malcolm Chisholm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/pqa/wa-03/wa1028.htm#16">

  <p>The Radiocommunications Agency, an executive agency of the Department of Trade and Industry, is undertaking a programme of measurements of emissions from mobile phone base stations throughout the UK to assess compliance with relevant exposure guidelines. This programme has recently been extended to TETRA installations and will include TETRA base stations in Scotland. The Executive has no current plans to augment this process.</p>

</reply>
</publicwhip>