<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.153.0" colnum="153">Preamble</major-heading>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.153.1" colnum="153" time="">
<p><i>The House met at Eleven of the Clock,</i> MR. SPEAKER <i>in the Chair.</i></p>
</speech>
<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.153.2" colnum="153">PROROGATION.</major-heading>
<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.153.3" colnum="153">HIS MAJESTY'S MOST GRACIOUS SPEECH.</minor-heading>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.153.4" colnum="153" time="">
<p><i>Message to attend the Lords Commissioners.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.153.5" colnum="153" time="">
<p><i>The House went; and, having returned,</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.153.6" hansard_membership_id="4455" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/14943" speakername="Mr. SPEAKER" colnum="153" time="">
<p>(<i>standing in the Clerk's place at the Table</i>): I have to acquaint the House that the House has been to the House of Peers, where a Commission under the Great Seal was read. The EARL of ONSLOW, being one of the Lords Commissioners, delivered His Majesty's Most Gracious Speech to both Houses of Parliament, in pursuance of His Majesty's Command, as followeth:</p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.153.7" colnum="153" time="">
<p><b>My Lords and Members of the House of Commons,</b></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.153.8" colnum="153" time="">
<p><i>I AM addressing you for the first time as your Sovereign. I desire before all to express once more My deep appreciation of the sympathy which has been extended to Me and to My</i>

<i>dear Mother in every part of My dominions. I have been profoundly touched by the universal expression of the affection and respect with which My beloved Father was regarded. I am well assured that the memory of King George's life of devotion and unremitting service will long live in the hearts of His people.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.154.0" colnum="154" time="">
<p><i>My relations with foreign Powers continue to be friendly.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.154.1" colnum="154" time="">
<p><i>On the 26th August a Treaty of Alliance with the King of Egypt was signed in London by delegates representing My Government and the Egyptian Government. It is My earnest hope that this Treaty when ratified will be the beginning of a new era in which the friendly co-operation that has marked the relations between My country and Egypt in the past will be confirmed and strengthened.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.154.2" colnum="154" time="">
<p><i>A Conference was held at Montreux in the summer for the revision of the Straits Convention of Lausanne. The successful outcome of this Conference, to which I am pleased to think that My Government contributed, has set a happy example for the future.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.154.3" colnum="154" time="">
<p><i>The Assembly of the League of Nations have recently opened an inquiry into the working of the Covenant, and My Government, which remain firmly attached to the principles of the Covenant of the League, have made known their views upon the manner in which its application might be improved.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.154.4" colnum="154" time="">
<p><i>My Ministers have been engaged in negotiations for a meeting between the Five Powers signatory to the Treaty of Locarno on the basis of the agreement reached by My Government and the Governments of France and Belgium in London on the</i> 23rd <i>July. These negotiations are continuing.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.154.5" colnum="154" time="">
<p><i>I have viewed with concern and anxiety the events in Spain during the last three months. My Government have spared no pains to promote and encourage humanitarian efforts to mitigate the suffering of the people of Spain. My Navy has acted in accordance with its high traditions in re-</i>


<i>lieving the distress caused by these disturbances. It has been the consistent policy of My Government to attempt to localise this unhappy struggle, and with this end in view they seconded the initiative of the French Government for a non-intervention agreement and have energetically co-operated in its negotiation and application.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.155.0" colnum="155" time="">
<p><i>My Ministers were glad to be able, in conjunction with the Government of the United States of America, to lend their co-operation to the scheme for the re-adjustment of the value of the French currency. I trust that the measures taken recently by the French and several other Governments will pave the way for a further improvement in international trade.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.155.1" colnum="155" time="">
<p><b>Members of the House of Commons,</b></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.155.2" colnum="155" time="">
<p><i>I thank you for the provision you have made for the public service.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.155.3" colnum="155" time="">
<p><i>I thank you for the arrangements you have made for the maintenance of the honour and dignity of the Crown.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.155.4" colnum="155" time="">
<p><b>My Lords and Members of the House of Commons:</b></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.155.5" colnum="155" time="">
<p><i>The measures essential for improving and strengthening all three of My defence forces, which were laid before you this year, have been steadily pursued.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.155.6" colnum="155" time="">
<p><i>I rejoice at the further marked increase in trade and employment during the year. I note, with much gratification, that unemployment generally is still diminishing and that employment has reached the highest level ever recorded. Schemes for the amelioration of the conditions in those districts where the problem of unemployment still presents special difficulties have continued to engage the close attention of My Ministers and of the Commissioners appointed for those areas.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.155.7" colnum="155" time="">
<p><i>Steps have been taken to reduce the rate of contributions under the general unemployment insurance scheme.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.155.8" colnum="155" time="">
<p><i>Regulations relating to unemployment assistance and measures for bringing to an end the period of standstill which has existed since February, 1935,</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.156.0" colnum="156" time="">
<p><i>received your approval in July, and will come into effect in November.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.156.1" colnum="156" time="">
<p><i>The development of the national health services has received the close attention of My Ministers. Good progress has been made in the clearance and replacement of slums, the surveys of overcrowding required under the Housing Acts,</i> 1935, <i>have been completed by local authorities, and the work of providing new accommodation under those Acts has been begun. The high rate of house production in general has been well maintained.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.156.2" colnum="156" time="">
<p><i>Acts have been passed for the improvement of the maternity services by the provision of an organised service of salaried midwives, and for the consolidation and amendment of the law relating to public health.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.156.3" colnum="156" time="">
<p><i>I have given My assent to a Bill to amend the law in England and Wales relating to compulsory school attendance and to assistance from public funds towards expenditure on voluntary school buildings; and also to a Bill providing for the raising of the school-leaving age in Scotland and for certain improvements in the educational system, in particular as regards children suffering from physical and mental defects.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.156.4" colnum="156" time="">
<p><i>Action has been taken, in co-operation with Local Authorities, to improve and extend the provision of physical education in the schools.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.156.5" colnum="156" time="">
<p><i>Measures have been enacted providing for a solution of the problem of tithe rentcharge upon a permanent footing, and for the maintenance of the beet sugar industry as part of the general agricultural policy of this country. Assistance to the cattle and dairying sections of the agricultural industry has been continued.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.156.6" colnum="156" time="">
<p><i>An Act has been passed for insuring agricultural workers against unemployment, which will enable such workers, if unemployed during the coming winter, to receive benefit.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.156.7" colnum="156" time="">
<p><i>I have given My assent to Bills to facilitate the elimination of surplus productive capacity in the spinning section of the cotton industry, and to</i>


<i>continue for a further year the temporary subsidy granted to tramp shipping in</i> 1935. <i>Steps have been taken to enable the selling arrangements of the coal industry to be co-ordinated.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.157.0" colnum="157" time="">
<p><i>A number of other measures of public utility have been added to the Statute Book.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.157.1" colnum="157" time="">
<p><i>In bidding you farewell, I pray that the blessing of Almighty 'God may rest upon your labours.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.157.2" colnum="157" time="">
<p><i>Then a Commission for Proroguing the Parliament was read in the House of Lords.</i></p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.157.3" colnum="157" time="">
<p>After which the EARL OF ONSLOW said:</p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.157.4" colnum="157" time="">
<p>My Lords and Members of the House of Commons: By virtue of His Majesty's

Commission, under the Great Seal, to us and other Lords directed, and now read, we do, in His Majesty's Name and in obedience to His Majesty's Commands, prorogue this Parliament to Tuesday, the third day of November, one thousand nine hundred and thirty-six, to be then here holden; and this Parliament is accordingly prorogued until Tuesday, the third day of November, one thousand nine hundred and thirty-six.</p>
</speech>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/1936-10-30a.158.0" colnum="158" time="">
<p><i>End of the First Session (opened Tuesday, 3rd December,</i> 1935) <i>of the Thirty-seventh Parliament of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, in the First year of the Reign of His Majesty King Edward the Eighth.</i></p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>